<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>caffeineletter</title>
    <description>From choosing your coffee to how minute modifications change your taste notes - learn it all here.</description>
    
    <link>https://archive.letter.coffee/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://rss.beehiiv.com/feeds/arqSjkRars.xml" rel="self"/>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Sep 2025 02:03:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <pubDate>Sun, 21 Sep 2025 02:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    <atom:published>2025-09-21T02:00:00Z</atom:published>
    <atom:updated>2025-09-21T02:03:32Z</atom:updated>
    
      <category>Culture</category>
      <category>Food And Drink</category>
      <category>Lifestyle</category>
    <copyright>Copyright 2025, caffeineletter</copyright>
    
    <image>
      <url>https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/publication/logo/a76da1ea-6fcc-4776-a7aa-6bc95fed4c92/logo.png</url>
      <title>caffeineletter</title>
      <link>https://archive.letter.coffee/</link>
    </image>
    
    <docs>https://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>beehiiv</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <webMaster>support@beehiiv.com (Beehiiv Support)</webMaster>

      <item>
  <title>Daily Coffee Workflow 2025</title>
  <description>Story of how I brew pour over daily and the important variables I consider</description>
  <link>https://archive.letter.coffee/p/daily-coffee-workflow-2025</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://archive.letter.coffee/p/daily-coffee-workflow-2025</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 21 Sep 2025 02:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  <atom:published>2025-09-21T02:00:00Z</atom:published>
    <dc:creator>Aravind Balla</dc:creator>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[
    <div class='beehiiv'><style>
  .bh__table, .bh__table_header, .bh__table_cell { border: 1px solid #C0C0C0; }
  .bh__table_cell { padding: 5px; background-color: #FFFFFF; }
  .bh__table_cell p { color: #2D2D2D; font-family: 'Lora',Palatino,'Book Antiqua',Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
  .bh__table_header { padding: 5px; background-color:#F1F1F1; }
  .bh__table_header p { color: #2A2A2A; font-family:'Libre Baskerville','DejaVu Serif',Garamond,Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
</style><div class='beehiiv__body'><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Every morning starts the same way for me – with the ritual of making a pour over.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">But here&#39;s the thing: while the ritual stays consistent, the actual brew changes every single day.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I&#39;m a pour over fan through and through. There&#39;s something about the control, the variables, and the endless possibilities that keeps me coming back. My setup isn&#39;t fancy, <i>okay it is a bit</i>, but the main thing is it works perfectly for what I need.</p><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/ccaf7c63-7b3d-462a-a4c3-a202120ef928/IMG_7091_2.jpeg?t=1758292629"/><div class="image__source"><span class="image__source_text"><p>The Coffee Station</p></span></div></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The routine begins with heating water in my stovetop gooseneck kettle. Nothing electric here – just the good old flame and a kitchen thermometer to check the temperature. Depending on the beans and my mood, I&#39;m anywhere between 85°C for darker roasts to 96°C for those stubborn light roasts that need extra convincing.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">While the water heats up, I grab my Timemore C2 grinder. This little hand grinder has been with me for years now. The clicking sounds as I adjust the grind setting have become part of the morning soundtrack. Some days it&#39;s 16 clicks for a light roast, other days 24 for something darker.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">My daily driver these days is the Hario Switch. I talked about this beauty in a <a class="link" href="https://letter.coffee/p/this-brewer-replaced-my-daily-driver/?utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=daily-coffee-workflow-2025" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">previous post</a>, but it&#39;s worth mentioning again how much this brewer changed my pour over game. The ability to switch between immersion and percolation – sometimes even mid-brew – opens up so many possibilities.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I don&#39;t have a daily recipe. Most people find their perfect recipe and stick to it. <i>But where&#39;s the fun in that?</i></p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">My coffee dose stays fairly consistent at 15g – that&#39;s my constant. Some mornings I&#39;ll do an extended immersion bloom for 2 minutes. Other days, I&#39;m doing quick 30-second pours. Water ratio might be 1:15 today, 1:17 tomorrow. It all depends on how the previous cup turned out and what I&#39;m feeling that morning.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This is where my notebook comes in. While sipping my coffee, I jot down all the parameters – water temperature, grind clicks, pour timing, total brew time. More importantly, I write how the coffee tastes. Too sour? Maybe I&#39;ll grind finer tomorrow. Bit bitter? Let&#39;s try a coarser grind or lower temperature.</p><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/43854784-98ab-4dfe-b055-3cd21a167610/CleanShot_2025-09-21_at_07.10.26_2x.png?t=1758418858"/></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">These notes have become invaluable. When I nail a particularly good cup, I can recreate it. When something goes wrong, I know exactly what to adjust. It&#39;s like having a conversation with yesterday&#39;s me about today&#39;s coffee.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Sometimes I&#39;ll look back at notes from weeks ago and realize I&#39;ve been gradually shifting my preferences. Maybe I&#39;m grinding progressively finer as the beans age, or unconsciously gravitating toward higher temperatures as the weather gets colder.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This might sound like a lot of work for a morning cup of coffee. But honestly? This experimentation, this daily dance with variables – it&#39;s what makes every morning interesting. No two cups are exactly the same, and that&#39;s exactly how I like it.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The whole process, from heating water to that first sip, takes about 10 minutes. Add another minute or two for note-taking. Those 11 minutes have become my morning meditation, my way of easing into the day.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">So {{ first name | friend }}, what&#39;s your morning coffee workflow like? Are you a recipe repeater or a daily experimenter like me? I&#39;d love to know if anyone else keeps coffee notes – sometimes I wonder if I&#39;m the only one geeking out this much over morning brew parameters.</p><hr class="content_break"><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">That’s all I have. Have a caffeinated weekend.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">See you.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Keep on brewing!</p></div><div class='beehiiv__footer'><br class='beehiiv__footer__break'><hr class='beehiiv__footer__line'><a target="_blank" class="beehiiv__footer_link" style="text-align: center;" href="https://www.beehiiv.com/?utm_campaign=2b43d9d4-f815-474d-9417-0a3e28541add&utm_medium=post_rss&utm_source=caffeineletter">Powered by beehiiv</a></div></div>
  ]]></content:encoded>
</item>

      <item>
  <title>Does freshly roasted coffee taste best? </title>
  <description>We explore why fresh coffee is not always ready and the science behind resting your coffee well.</description>
      <enclosure url="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/2c1efecb-41d1-48c9-a5a7-d38983b706ed/aravindballa_watercolor_kitten_taking_a_nap_on_packets_of_cof_8aff66ad-3d50-4a6a-880b-49fc5259912d_1.png" length="765249" type="image/png"/>
  <link>https://archive.letter.coffee/p/does-freshly-roasted-coffee-taste-best</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://archive.letter.coffee/p/does-freshly-roasted-coffee-taste-best</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2025 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
  <atom:published>2025-09-06T13:30:00Z</atom:published>
    <dc:creator>Aravind Balla</dc:creator>
    <category><![CDATA[Science]]></category>
    <category><![CDATA[Teenage Cat]]></category>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[
    <div class='beehiiv'><style>
  .bh__table, .bh__table_header, .bh__table_cell { border: 1px solid #C0C0C0; }
  .bh__table_cell { padding: 5px; background-color: #FFFFFF; }
  .bh__table_cell p { color: #2D2D2D; font-family: 'Lora',Palatino,'Book Antiqua',Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
  .bh__table_header { padding: 5px; background-color:#F1F1F1; }
  .bh__table_header p { color: #2A2A2A; font-family:'Libre Baskerville','DejaVu Serif',Garamond,Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
</style><div class='beehiiv__body'><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/70600454-ef96-4285-8d00-417115cddf30/aravindballa_watercolor_kitten_taking_a_nap_on_packets_of_cof_8aff66ad-3d50-4a6a-880b-49fc5259912d_1.png?t=1757144166"/></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Couple of months ago, I ordered a bag of coffee beans from the roasters site. The package said the coffee was roasted 3 days back. I was excited thinking that the coffee would be so beautiful as it is very fresh.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Soon, I made a cup with that and I was surprised. In a bad way. It tasted flat, as if I made the coffee with room temperature water.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Before calling this a bad coffee, I wanted to validate myself and I looked if people had any reviews online. There were a few praises on reddit. And then, after some more research, I discovered that the coffee should be rested.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Let&#39;s see why.</p><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="degassing-is-crucial">Degassing is crucial</h2><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">As soon as the coffee is roasted, the coffee is fresh, but not ready. It has a lot of CO<sub>2</sub> trapped in it, based on how dense the coffee is.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The CO<sub>2</sub> trapped inside the beans actively repels water. When you pour hot water over grounds that haven&#39;t fully degassed, the CO<sub>2</sub> bubbles interfere with the water&#39;s ability to uniformly saturate all the coffee particles. This leads to an uneven extraction, where some grounds are over-extracted and others are under-extracted.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Because degassing prevents an uneven extraction, it allows for a more balanced and refined flavor profile. Coffee brewed too early can taste overly bright, acidic, or sour due to excess CO<sub>2</sub>. Resting allows the more subtle, complex, and sweet notes to emerge and balance the flavors.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This is why I had a bad experience with fresh coffee.</p><h3 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="pour-over-vs-espresso">Pour over vs Espresso</h3><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">In manual brewing methods like pour-over, the &quot;bloom&quot;, where the first pour of hot water is done and the coffee bed swells up, is a result of CO<sub>2</sub> escaping. While a good bloom indicates fresh coffee, an <b>overly aggressive</b> one from beans that have not rested can disrupt the brewing process and prevent proper saturation.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">And in espresso, uncontrolled gas release can lead to <b>channeling</b>, where water forges uneven pathways through the coffee bed or puck. This results in a poor extraction that lacks sweetness and can cause a watery mouthfeel and a less-than-ideal texture.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Coffee being used for espresso might need more resting compared to the manual brewing methods.</p><h3 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="light-vs-dark-roasts">Light vs Dark Roasts</h3><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Light roasts are more dense than Dark roasts. Which means, light roasts need more time to degass than the dark ones.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Typically, light roasts can take from 7 to 14 days to properly degass and achieve peak flavour. Where as, dark roasts are quick and can be brewed with in 4 days.</p><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="best-practices">Best practices</h2><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">So, how do we let the coffee rest, properly?</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The best way is to keep it as is.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Almost all coffee bags have a one way valve, where the gases from inside are let out and no gas from outside is let in. This is crucial.</p><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/e7fc9441-0e2d-4fa6-adb0-067d950c4bf2/98165.png?t=1757143831"/></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">If we let oxygen in, coffee starts becoming stale. So the one way valve just lets the degassed CO<sub>2</sub> come out.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The environment should be not too hot or not too cold, leaving it in your room should be okay. It&#39;s best if the place is dark, so maybe in a drawer. Fridge is a no-go as coffee is hygroscopic, meaning it readily absorbs moisture and odors from its surroundings, meaning, bad coffee.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Roasters typically tell you how long should the coffee be rested, either on the packaging or on their website. If not, we can follow the above days based on the coffee.</p><hr class="content_break"><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Knowing this fundamentally changed when I order my next bag of coffee at home. It used to be after I finish the current stash, but now it&#39;s a week in advance.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">When I am left with ~120g of coffee, I start <a class="link" href="https://letter.coffee/baazar/?utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=does-freshly-roasted-coffee-taste-best" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">searching for my next beans</a>. By the time I finish the current ones, new coffee is both fresh and ready.</p><hr class="content_break"><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">That’s all I have. Have a caffeinated weekend.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">See you.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Keep on brewing!</p></div><div class='beehiiv__footer'><br class='beehiiv__footer__break'><hr class='beehiiv__footer__line'><a target="_blank" class="beehiiv__footer_link" style="text-align: center;" href="https://www.beehiiv.com/?utm_campaign=6a75db6b-191d-4421-8687-ba86c63fcd3a&utm_medium=post_rss&utm_source=caffeineletter">Powered by beehiiv</a></div></div>
  ]]></content:encoded>
</item>

      <item>
  <title>How is Yerba Mate different from Coffee?</title>
  <description>Let&#39;s talk yet another caffeinated beverage, see how it compares to coffee and how you can try it.</description>
      <enclosure url="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/8b81c45a-c580-4c7e-b61e-f9eeb775b438/Gemini_Generated_Image_jkav4ajkav4ajkav.png" length="1630452" type="image/png"/>
  <link>https://archive.letter.coffee/p/yebra-vs-coffee</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://archive.letter.coffee/p/yebra-vs-coffee</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 30 Aug 2025 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
  <atom:published>2025-08-30T13:30:00Z</atom:published>
    <dc:creator>Aravind Balla</dc:creator>
    <category><![CDATA[Science]]></category>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[
    <div class='beehiiv'><style>
  .bh__table, .bh__table_header, .bh__table_cell { border: 1px solid #C0C0C0; }
  .bh__table_cell { padding: 5px; background-color: #FFFFFF; }
  .bh__table_cell p { color: #2D2D2D; font-family: 'Lora',Palatino,'Book Antiqua',Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
  .bh__table_header { padding: 5px; background-color:#F1F1F1; }
  .bh__table_header p { color: #2A2A2A; font-family:'Libre Baskerville','DejaVu Serif',Garamond,Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
</style><div class='beehiiv__body'><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/8b81c45a-c580-4c7e-b61e-f9eeb775b438/Gemini_Generated_Image_jkav4ajkav4ajkav.png?t=1756559489"/></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This week, I want to talk about another caffeinated drink I enjoy - Yerba Mate.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I first heard about yerba mate on a Huberman Lab episode where he mentioned drinking it for sustained focus. Naturally, I had to try it.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Finding yerba mate in India turned out to be a treasure hunt. After scouring Amazon, I discovered Matero – apparently the only company selling yerba mate here back then. I tried and thought, &quot;Okay, this is interesting.&quot;</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">A couple of months later, my coworker from Argentina sent some authentic yerba mate with a traditional gourd and bombilla. That&#39;s when I realized I&#39;d been missing something special.</p><blockquote align="center" class="twitter-tweet"><p dir="ltr" lang="en"><p>Switching the gears a bit for the caffeine dose</p></p><a href="https://twitter.com/aravindballa/status/1805846854103712184?utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=how-is-yerba-mate-different-from-coffee"><p> &mdash; Aravind Balla (@aravindballa) <br/> 6:13 AM • Jun 26, 2024 </p></a></blockquote><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">It was actually better and the difference felt similar to how speciality coffee and instant coffee were.</p><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="what-is-yerba-mate">What is Yerba Mate?</h2><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Unlike coffee (from coffee beans) or tea (from tea leaves), yerba mate comes from a South American holly tree. Yes, a holly tree. The leaves are dried, crushed, and traditionally drunk from a hollow gourd through a metal straw called a bombilla.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The traditional way involves sharing – one person prepares the mate, takes the first sip (it&#39;s the most bitter), then passes it around. Everyone drinks from the same bombilla, refilling the gourd with hot water. It&#39;s a social ritual that brings people together, kind of like how we share coffee conversations, but more intimate.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">In fact, a lot of famous people drink yerba.</p><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/a6a229d8-6d8c-472f-a345-46c87fbc4ce0/79187.png?t=1756552336"/><div class="image__source"><span class="image__source_text"><p><a class="link" href="https://matexperience.com/insights/culture/celebrities-who-enjoy-yerba-mate/?utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=how-is-yerba-mate-different-from-coffee" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">https://matexperience.com/insights/culture/celebrities-who-enjoy-yerba-mate/</a></p></span></div></div><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="coffee-vs-yerba-mate-the-real-diffe">Coffee vs Yerba Mate: The Real Difference</h2><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Your regular cup of coffee packs about 95mg of caffeine. That&#39;s its main weapon.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Yerba mate brings ~80mg of caffeine, but here&#39;s the kicker – it also contains theobromine (the stuff in chocolate that makes you feel good) and theophylline.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Coffee hits you like that friend who shows up loud and leaves suddenly. You get that immediate kick, your heart rate jumps, and 30 minutes later you&#39;re flying. Then comes the crash.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Yerba mate, much like <a class="link" href="https://letter.coffee/p/matcha-science/?utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=how-is-yerba-mate-different-from-coffee" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">matcha</a>, plays the long game. The energy builds slowly and stays for 2-3 hours. No dramatic peaks, no sudden crashes. My stomach, which sometimes protests against coffee&#39;s acidity, actually handles yerba mate pretty well.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><i>Mostly</i> no jitters, I should say. Drink too much and you&#39;ll still feel wired. I keep drinking it the whole day, refilling it with hot water in the same gourd.</p><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="my-honest-take">My Honest Take</h2><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Yerba mate tastes grassy, earthy, and bitter. If someone told you it tastes like drinking liquid hay, they wouldn&#39;t be entirely wrong.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">But remember your first black coffee? That wasn&#39;t love at first sip either. Yerba mate is an acquired taste that grows on you.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I reach for yerba mate when I need sustained energy for the entire day – like during long coding sessions or back-to-back meetings. It&#39;s also my go-to when coffee&#39;s acidity acts up, or when it&#39;s late afternoon and I need caffeine that won&#39;t destroy my sleep.</p><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="how-can-you-try">How can you try?</h2><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">There are less, but good options in India.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><a class="link" href="https://chadotea.in/products/yerba-mate?utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=how-is-yerba-mate-different-from-coffee" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">https://chadotea.in/products/yerba-mate</a></p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><a class="link" href="https://matero.in/?utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=how-is-yerba-mate-different-from-coffee" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">https://matero.in/</a> (they also sell gourds)</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><a class="link" href="https://www.sol-mate.in/?utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=how-is-yerba-mate-different-from-coffee" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">https://www.sol-mate.in/</a></p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">So {{ first_name | friend }}, would you try yerba mate? If you have, let me know how it compares to your coffee experience.</p><hr class="content_break"><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">That’s all I have. Have a caffeinated weekend.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">See you.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Keep on brewing!</p></div><div class='beehiiv__footer'><br class='beehiiv__footer__break'><hr class='beehiiv__footer__line'><a target="_blank" class="beehiiv__footer_link" style="text-align: center;" href="https://www.beehiiv.com/?utm_campaign=1760053f-13e1-4e03-a0a5-3b3d94c97c55&utm_medium=post_rss&utm_source=caffeineletter">Powered by beehiiv</a></div></div>
  ]]></content:encoded>
</item>

      <item>
  <title>Brewing Light Roasts on Pour Over</title>
  <description>This is how I make my favourite cup of coffee every morning.</description>
      <enclosure url="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/6a923f8f-a19a-4153-85e5-3ebd3fcf62ff/aravindballa_watercolor_kitten_looking_at_coffee_cup_in_a_gar_486b8827-6461-4577-81cc-03901945a78c_1.png" length="2122431" type="image/png"/>
  <link>https://archive.letter.coffee/p/brewing-light-roasts-on-pour-over</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://archive.letter.coffee/p/brewing-light-roasts-on-pour-over</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 23 Aug 2025 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
  <atom:published>2025-08-23T13:30:00Z</atom:published>
    <dc:creator>Aravind Balla</dc:creator>
    <category><![CDATA[Recipes]]></category>
    <category><![CDATA[Og Tom]]></category>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[
    <div class='beehiiv'><style>
  .bh__table, .bh__table_header, .bh__table_cell { border: 1px solid #C0C0C0; }
  .bh__table_cell { padding: 5px; background-color: #FFFFFF; }
  .bh__table_cell p { color: #2D2D2D; font-family: 'Lora',Palatino,'Book Antiqua',Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
  .bh__table_header { padding: 5px; background-color:#F1F1F1; }
  .bh__table_header p { color: #2A2A2A; font-family:'Libre Baskerville','DejaVu Serif',Garamond,Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
</style><div class='beehiiv__body'><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/93a992a1-5984-4ca9-94c1-099aa86d8ef0/aravindballa_watercolor_kitten_looking_at_coffee_cup_in_a_gar_486b8827-6461-4577-81cc-03901945a78c_1.png?t=1755949706"/></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I generally reach for light to medium roasts when I make my morning pour over. Those bright, complex flavours dancing through the V60 - that&#39;s what got me hooked on speciality coffee in the first place.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Let&#39;s look at the nuances while extracting the best out of coffee in this post.</p><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="anatomy-of-light-roasts">Anatomy of Light Roasts</h2><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Light roasted beans are dense little things. They haven&#39;t been pushed to their breaking point by heat, so their cellular structure is still tight and compact.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This is what makes them special. You get bright acidity, floral notes that remind you of jasmine or black tea, fruit flavors that can range from citrus to stone fruits to berries. Sometimes you even get this wine-like complexity that makes you stop mid-sip and think &quot;wait, this is coffee?&quot;</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Most importantly, this is what specialty coffee is all about - you can taste where the coffee came from. That Coorg estate&#39;s monsoon-kissed sweetness, that Araku Valley organic earthiness, that Chikmagalur chocolate note. It&#39;s all there, waiting to be extracted.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The challenge? These dense beans don&#39;t give up their goods easily. They need convincing.</p><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="convincing-brewing-light-roasts"><span style="text-decoration:line-through;">Convincing</span> Brewing Light Roasts</h2><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Let&#39;s get to the pour over terms now.</p><h3 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="temperature-is-your-friend">Temperature is Your Friend</h3><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">With light roasts, I push the temperature high - 94-96°C. Sometimes I even go to 98°C (which is just off boiling) for particularly stubborn beans.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">These dense beans need that extra heat to open up and release their solubles. Think of it like trying to dissolve sugar in cold water versus hot water. The heat speeds everything up and helps break down those tight cellular walls.</p><h3 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="grind-finer-but-not-too-fine">Grind Finer, But Not Too Fine</h3><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">On my Timemore C2, I&#39;m usually around 16-19 clicks for light roasts. That&#39;s definitely finer than the 20-21 I use for mediums.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The finer grind increases surface area, giving the water more coffee to work with. But here&#39;s the catch - go too fine and you&#39;ll clog the filter, leading to an over-extracted mess that tastes bitter and astringent.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I have been there too.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I know I&#39;ve gone too fine when the water takes forever to drain and leaves a muddy bed at the bottom. Back off a click or two if this happens.</p><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="recipe-1-the-extended-bloom">Recipe 1: The Extended Bloom</h2><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This one changed my light roast game completely.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Start with 15g of coffee ground at 18 clicks (or your grinder&#39;s equivalent of medium-fine).</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Pour 45g of 96°C water for the bloom. But here&#39;s the key - grab a spoon and give it a good stir. Really get in there. Make sure every ground is saturated. I do figure-8 motions for about 5 seconds.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Wait 45 seconds to a minute. <i>Yes, a minute.</i> Lance Hendrik, a popular coffee youtuber, even likes to wait the bloom for 2 minutes. <i>Linking the whole video below as it’s a great reciepe for light roasts as well.</i></p><iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube_embed" frameborder="0" height="100%" src="https://youtube.com/embed/rAdgJNK0csc" width="100%"></iframe><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Now pour to 120g in slow circles, keeping that water level consistent. Wait for it to drain until the coffee bed is just exposed.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Final pour to 250g, same slow circles. Total brew time should be around 2:45-3:00.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The extended, agitated bloom ensures even extraction from the start. No dry pockets, no channeling.</p><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="recipe-2-fantastic-five">Recipe 2: Fantastic Five</h2><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Sometimes I want to maintain maximum heat throughout the brew and have a good body. That&#39;s where this method shines.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Same dose - 15g of coffee, 250g total water at 96°C.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">But instead of 3 pours, we&#39;re doing 5 smaller ones of 50g each. When I am teaching someone to brew for the first time, I go with this recipe as it&#39;s easy to remember. 50x5.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Each pour keeps the slurry temperature high. The water never gets a chance to cool down. It&#39;s like keeping constant pressure on those dense beans.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The multiple pours also create more agitation, which helps with extraction. Total time ends up around 3:15-3:30.</p><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="some-hacks-i-picked-up-along-the-wa">Some Hacks I picked up along the way</h2><table width="100%" class="bh__column_wrapper"><tr><td width="50%" class="bh__column"><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/b662c7bb-3a32-4ddc-af5e-bc9089d85c56/IMG_6650.jpeg?t=1755949754"/></div></td><td width="50%" class="bh__column"><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/de816337-a3b2-4b3f-be46-ea64a25deacf/IMG_6722.jpeg?t=1755949849"/></div></td></tr></table><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><b>The Bypass Method</b> If your cup is too acidic even after trying everything, brew a concentrated 1:13 ratio coffee, then add 40g of hot water directly to the cup. This &quot;bypasses&quot; the coffee bed and dilutes the acidity while maintaining body. <i>On another note, I also enjoy a mokapot with light roasts along with this bypass.</i></p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><b>Temperature Compensation</b> Can&#39;t grind fine enough? Bump your water temperature by 2-3 degrees. If your grinder only goes so fine, let temperature do the extra extraction work.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><b>Reading the Bloom</b> A good bloom on light roasts should dome up like a mushroom. If it craters immediately, your water might be too hot or your coffee might be older than you think. If it barely moves, grind finer or increase agitation.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><b>The Two-Temperature Trick</b> Start with 96°C water for the bloom to really open things up, then drop to ~80°C for the second half of the pours. You get aggressive extraction at the start when you need it most, then gentle extraction to avoid bitterness. I guess Tetsu talks about this in some recipe video.</p><hr class="content_break"><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">These are all the things I wanted to share on my favourite way to drink coffee.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">What do think? Do you have any inputs or feedback?</p><hr class="content_break"><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">That’s all I have. Have a caffeinated weekend.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">See you.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Keep on brewing!</p></div><div class='beehiiv__footer'><br class='beehiiv__footer__break'><hr class='beehiiv__footer__line'><a target="_blank" class="beehiiv__footer_link" style="text-align: center;" href="https://www.beehiiv.com/?utm_campaign=24e1c329-3e7a-4504-bb7e-84f8cdf49dc5&utm_medium=post_rss&utm_source=caffeineletter">Powered by beehiiv</a></div></div>
  ]]></content:encoded>
</item>

      <item>
  <title>What&#39;s up (with) Matcha?</title>
  <description>Let&#39;s see who wins the coffee vs matcha debate</description>
      <enclosure url="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/efd6adc1-5efc-447a-9a5e-7af1dd75e385/aravindballa_watercolor_kitten_looking_at_green_matcha_in_a_b_907691b0-d98c-4cd2-b350-087a45f9159a_0.png" length="878429" type="image/png"/>
  <link>https://archive.letter.coffee/p/matcha-science</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://archive.letter.coffee/p/matcha-science</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 16 Aug 2025 14:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
  <atom:published>2025-08-16T14:30:00Z</atom:published>
    <dc:creator>Aravind Balla</dc:creator>
    <category><![CDATA[Science]]></category>
    <category><![CDATA[Baby Kitten]]></category>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[
    <div class='beehiiv'><style>
  .bh__table, .bh__table_header, .bh__table_cell { border: 1px solid #C0C0C0; }
  .bh__table_cell { padding: 5px; background-color: #FFFFFF; }
  .bh__table_cell p { color: #2D2D2D; font-family: 'Lora',Palatino,'Book Antiqua',Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
  .bh__table_header { padding: 5px; background-color:#F1F1F1; }
  .bh__table_header p { color: #2A2A2A; font-family:'Libre Baskerville','DejaVu Serif',Garamond,Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
</style><div class='beehiiv__body'><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/efd6adc1-5efc-447a-9a5e-7af1dd75e385/aravindballa_watercolor_kitten_looking_at_green_matcha_in_a_b_907691b0-d98c-4cd2-b350-087a45f9159a_0.png?t=1755350918"/></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I had my fair share of laughs looking at matcha memes, coffee lovers hating matcha and vice versa. But know what, I don’t hate matcha. I didn’t like it initially, but recently developed a taste for it.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Never liked it in cafes. Let’s discuss why, what made me build a taste and all the fun (science).</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Let me be clear - if you love coffee, which is one of the reasons you are here, you don’t have to hate matcha.</p><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="how-is-it-made">How is it made?</h2><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Unlike regular tea where you steep leaves and throw them away, matcha is <i>the whole leaf</i>.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Matcha Tea plants are put in shade for about 3-4 weeks before harvest. This stresses the plant (in a good way) and makes it produce more chlorophyll and amino acids. That’s why matcha has that vibrant green colour that looks almost unnatural.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">After harvesting, the leaves are steamed, dried, and have their stems and veins removed. What’s left is called <i>“tencha”</i>. These leaves are then ground into a super fine powder using stone mills. Traditional stone grinding can take up to an hour to produce just 30 grams of matcha!</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The grind is so fine that when you whisk it with water, you’re essentially drinking the entire leaf.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">That’s also why ceremonial grade matcha costs a bomb. All that careful processing adds up.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">And this “ceremonial grade” is the culprit that led me to like matcha in the first place.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Because it costs a lot, most cafes use regular matcha - tastes okayish. But ceremonial grade is next level. I ordered ceremonial grade from Amazon and tried it with just hot water, normal milk, and even oat milk. Every drink was top-notch.</p><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="how-are-the-effects-different-from-">How are the effects different from Coffee?</h2><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Here’s where things get interesting for us coffee lovers.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Coffee hits you like a freight train. You drink it, and within 15-20 minutes, you’re buzzing. Your heart rate goes up, you feel alert, maybe a bit jittery if you overdo it. And then comes the crash - that 2 PM slump where you’re reaching for another cup.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Matcha has the slow-push.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The caffeine content is lower - about 70mg per serving compared to coffee’s 95-200mg. But the game-changer molecule is L-theanine, an amino acid that basically puts the brakes on caffeine absorption. Instead of that spike and crash, you get a sustained release over 4-6 hours.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">L-theanine also promotes alpha brain waves - the same ones you get during meditation. So while coffee makes you alert but potentially anxious, matcha gives you “calm alertness”. You’re focused but not wired.</p><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/f6e330ed-13dd-47fa-937e-0659e05fea28/image.png?t=1755350618"/><div class="image__source"><span class="image__source_text"><p>Matcha vs Coffee</p></span></div></div><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="when-do-i-actually-reach-for-matcha">When do I actually reach for matcha?</h2><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Practically speaking, I go for matcha when:</p><ul><li><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I have a long focus session ahead</p></li><li><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">It’s past noon, and I still need caffeine (won’t mess with sleep as much)</p></li><li><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">My stomach is acting up from too much coffee. You would know if you have coffee on an empty stomach for long enough.</p></li></ul><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">And here’s a <b>fun hack I love </b>- you can get matcha’s L-theanine effects without actually drinking matcha. L-theanine supplements are available, and you can take them with coffee to smooth out the caffeine hit. Best of both worlds? Maybe.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I would love for you to try.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The taste? Honestly, it’s an acquired one. Grassy, vegetal, slightly sweet if you get good quality. Nothing like coffee’s roasted, caramelized notes. But that’s okay - they’re different drinks for different moods.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Let me leave you with links to the ones I bought so that you can get a bit closer to what I experienced.</p><hr class="content_break"><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">That’s all I have. Have a caffeinated <i>(well yes, matcha is caffeine too)</i> weekend.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">See you.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Keep on brewing!</p></div><div class='beehiiv__footer'><br class='beehiiv__footer__break'><hr class='beehiiv__footer__line'><a target="_blank" class="beehiiv__footer_link" style="text-align: center;" href="https://www.beehiiv.com/?utm_campaign=b6ee10b0-828d-47f9-b256-c2d7b70615da&utm_medium=post_rss&utm_source=caffeineletter">Powered by beehiiv</a></div></div>
  ]]></content:encoded>
</item>

      <item>
  <title>How to develop taste for coffee</title>
  <description>Identifying coffee flavour notes is a skill. Like any skill, it can be learned and mastered.</description>
      <enclosure url="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/8d42751e-ebd6-448a-9c32-9c7c1b9601bc/aravindballa_watercolor_kitten_holding_a_coffee_cup_creating__4052c5f8-0d65-4519-bd49-6b6bc9c525df_2.png" length="1598476" type="image/png"/>
  <link>https://archive.letter.coffee/p/developing-taste-for-coffee</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://archive.letter.coffee/p/developing-taste-for-coffee</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 09 Aug 2025 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
  <atom:published>2025-08-09T13:30:00Z</atom:published>
    <dc:creator>Aravind Balla</dc:creator>
    <category><![CDATA[Og Tom]]></category>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[
    <div class='beehiiv'><style>
  .bh__table, .bh__table_header, .bh__table_cell { border: 1px solid #C0C0C0; }
  .bh__table_cell { padding: 5px; background-color: #FFFFFF; }
  .bh__table_cell p { color: #2D2D2D; font-family: 'Lora',Palatino,'Book Antiqua',Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
  .bh__table_header { padding: 5px; background-color:#F1F1F1; }
  .bh__table_header p { color: #2A2A2A; font-family:'Libre Baskerville','DejaVu Serif',Garamond,Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
</style><div class='beehiiv__body'><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/05a46242-661b-4af6-93f9-0add94b6c78f/aravindballa_watercolor_kitten_holding_a_coffee_cup_creating__4052c5f8-0d65-4519-bd49-6b6bc9c525df_2.png?t=1732269972"/></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Few months ago, I attended a coffee workshop in Hyderabad. We learned about a few brewing methods. There was also a V60 brewing competition at the end of the workshop. Why am I telling you about the competition? Because <a class="link" href="https://x.com/aravindballa/status/1858095754893836602?utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=how-to-develop-taste-for-coffee" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">we won</a> as our cup was the most <i>tasteful</i>.</p><blockquote align="center" class="twitter-tweet"><p dir="ltr" lang="en"><p>Attended a brewing and tasting workshop.</p><p>Ended up winning the v60 pour over competition. Our cup was the most liked among the 4 teams</p></p><a href="https://twitter.com/aravindballa/status/1858095754893836602?s=46&utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=how-to-develop-taste-for-coffee"><p> &mdash; Aravind Balla (@aravindballa) <br/> 10:32 AM • Nov 17, 2024 </p></a></blockquote><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Let’s talk about tasting coffee today.</p><hr class="content_break"><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="developing-a-taste-for-your-coffee">Developing a taste for your coffee </h2><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">We all know coffee isn’t just bitter water and that certain coffees taste a certain way. If not, you wouldn’t be here reading this email.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">What happens most of the time is we lack the skill to describe what we like. Saying things like “This is a great cup” will not do. When a barista asks how you like your coffee, can you describe it?</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I was in the same boat until recently. I couldn’t make out the tasting notes of the coffee until I attended a cupping and tasting workshop. I am still not a pro at this, but I am actively learning.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I want you to know the direction I am taking so you can enjoy your cups better.</p><div class="blockquote"><blockquote class="blockquote__quote"></blockquote></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Here is what I have learned so far.</p><hr class="content_break"><h3 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="how-does-it-work">How does it work?</h3><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Coffee gets its flavour from a lot of things, but mostly it’s the environment, where it’s grown, what’s growing around it and how it’s processed. There are different types of processing, washed and natural to name a few which have a good amount of influence on the taste of it.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><b>We will discuss in detail another day, but coming to the tasting of brewed coffee...</b></p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">A simple thing you can do every time you sip the coffee, think of what it reminds you. Maybe it’s some fruit. Maybe it’s a green forest. Maybe evenings in your childhood, which in turn can be traced back to snacks you enjoyed then. Or maybe some packaged food. It can be anything; just look for what comes up.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">For example, when I was in the tasting workshop, one of the coffees reminded me of a peanut chikki, which was indeed some notes of caramel.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">You have to actively put this into practice.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">When a coffee nerd says a certain coffee has the acidity of a pineapple, it doesn’t mean it tastes like a pineapple. <i>The sourness in the coffee reminds them of the sourness of a pineapple.</i></p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">As you can see, this becomes highly subjective and differs from person to person. But that mostly doesn’t matter. There is no right answer. What matters is to communicate about the tastes.</p><hr class="content_break"><h3 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="build-your-flavour-bank">Build your Flavour Bank</h3><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">To identify the notes well, it’s important to taste and smell a wide range of flavours. Being in India, it’s an advantage because just the staple food has a wide range of flavours and aromas.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Although, that’s not enough. We should train our palates enough to be able to recognize them. The next time you eat or drink something, identify what all went in. Put this into practice consciously. Try smelling fruits, leaves, flowers, vegetables, etc. While you do this, observe what emotions and memories it evokes. We make connections like these in our brains better.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Expand your taste bank.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This skill actually improves your quality of life by giving you the vocabulary to describe what you like. It will help you enjoy and appreciate food and drinks better.</p><hr class="content_break"><h3 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="starting-your-adventure">Starting your adventure</h3><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Before you can identify the specifics, here are some broader terms you can try describing the coffee with:</p><ul><li><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><b>Acidity</b>: This is generally the sourness but sour is referred to as something that’s overly sour. Like squeezing a lemon on your tongue. It’s considered bad. But then, what’s desired is bright acidity, something you find in orange or pineapple.</p></li><li><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><b>Body</b>: How heavy or light the coffee feels on your tongue. Like is it as heavy as full cream milk, or is it light like water?</p></li><li><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><b>After taste</b>: Does any taste linger in your mouth after you’ve gulped? Heavy-bodied coffees generally do this.</p></li><li><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><b>Balance</b>: How does the mouth feel holding together? Is something like acidity or bitterness standing out?</p></li><li><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><b>Flavour</b>: These are finally what flavours you can sense.</p></li></ul><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Look at the coffee flavour wheel, going from broad to specific. I like to pull this up often. It’s also interactive, so you can click through and see notes on identifying a specific flavour.</p><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/45a66b09-40b9-47c9-9692-51c79df559ff/Screenshot_2024-11-22_at_12.16.20_2x.png?t=1732258020"/><div class="image__source"><span class="image__source_text"><p><a class="link" href="https://notbadcoffee.com/flavor-wheel-en/?utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=how-to-develop-taste-for-coffee" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">https://notbadcoffee.com/flavor-wheel-en/</a></p></span></div></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">As I have said, there is no right way. We are just learning how to describe what we like. You might like bitter coffee and I might like acidic ones, neither of us is wrong.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The simplest thing you can do is get a pour over the next time you go to a coffee shop, befriend the barista, and discuss the taste notes of it. I also highly recommend attending a tasting workshop. Every city seems to host workshops for good.</p><hr class="content_break"><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">See you.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Keep on brewing!</p></div><div class='beehiiv__footer'><br class='beehiiv__footer__break'><hr class='beehiiv__footer__line'><a target="_blank" class="beehiiv__footer_link" style="text-align: center;" href="https://www.beehiiv.com/?utm_campaign=6e57a908-ea19-4782-9424-e1accd78d9de&utm_medium=post_rss&utm_source=caffeineletter">Powered by beehiiv</a></div></div>
  ]]></content:encoded>
</item>

      <item>
  <title>Brewing Dark Roasts on Pour Over</title>
  <description>Let&#39;s look at how the recipes and techniques can be tweaked to make dark roasts on a pour over more enjoyable.</description>
      <enclosure url="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/bcc75d98-aaf6-4754-8e8b-8964ebf9f7c3/aravindballa_watercolor_kitten_looking_at_dark_roasted_coffee_d5178c58-2f1b-4a11-88ef-8856f4873aa0_1.png" length="2242330" type="image/png"/>
  <link>https://archive.letter.coffee/p/dark-roasts-on-pour-over</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://archive.letter.coffee/p/dark-roasts-on-pour-over</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 02 Aug 2025 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
  <atom:published>2025-08-02T13:30:00Z</atom:published>
    <dc:creator>Aravind Balla</dc:creator>
    <category><![CDATA[Recipes]]></category>
    <category><![CDATA[Og Tom]]></category>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[
    <div class='beehiiv'><style>
  .bh__table, .bh__table_header, .bh__table_cell { border: 1px solid #C0C0C0; }
  .bh__table_cell { padding: 5px; background-color: #FFFFFF; }
  .bh__table_cell p { color: #2D2D2D; font-family: 'Lora',Palatino,'Book Antiqua',Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
  .bh__table_header { padding: 5px; background-color:#F1F1F1; }
  .bh__table_header p { color: #2A2A2A; font-family:'Libre Baskerville','DejaVu Serif',Garamond,Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
</style><div class='beehiiv__body'><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/bcc75d98-aaf6-4754-8e8b-8964ebf9f7c3/aravindballa_watercolor_kitten_looking_at_dark_roasted_coffee_d5178c58-2f1b-4a11-88ef-8856f4873aa0_1.png?t=1754142166"/></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I generally prefer light to medium roast with a pour over. The whole complex flavour profile of the coffee opens up with the magic of a pour over.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">But sometimes, you don&#39;t get to choose.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Maybe you ordered the wrong coffee and can&#39;t throw it away now. Or maybe it was a gift. Now, you are left with dark roasts.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Mind you, they stale faster.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">What do we do now?</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Honestly, I would pickup a moka pot and make some nice bold espresso like shots and use them as the base for coffee mocktails. We covered a few in the previous posts.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">My next choice, however, would be a pour over. And that is because I get to control things here. Let&#39;s go through how I would brew this.</p><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="anatomy-of-dark-roasts">Anatomy of Dark Roasts</h2><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Beans are darkly roasted, meaning they are already put through a lot of heat and are roasted till they just give up.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">You can expect one or more of nutty, woody, dark chocolate, roasted nuts, popcorn flavours. This depends on the coffee, of course.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Most cafes use this for their espressos. Mainly because when a bean is darkly roasted, the origin flavours (fruity, floral or acidic) are lost. So it doesn&#39;t matter where your coffee is from. Also cafes operate on speed. The bitterness that dark roasts tend to give are cut out with milk and sweeteners anyways.</p><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="brewing-dark-roasts">Brewing Dark Roasts</h2><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Let&#39;s talk pour over terms now.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">We don&#39;t need much temperature to start brewing with. I typically go below 85C, sometimes even 80C, with the water. We should be careful not to over-extract it. And for the same reason, I keep my coffee ground coarse, like French Press coarse.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I still go with 1:15 for the coffee to water ratio. I find increasing this makes it too weak.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I don&#39;t like to make the body heavier as it increases the not so desirable compounds like bitterness.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">With those things in mind, let&#39;s discuss 2 recipes and see how they fit. For reference, I use 15g of coffee and 225g of water. You can scale this up as needed.</p><h3 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="tetsus-46-method">Tetsu&#39;s 4:6 method</h3><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Actual recipe for reference.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Starting with 85C water, I go the first half in two parts normally. 2 pours of 45g each, totaling to 90g. We don&#39;t need much bloom, around 30 seconds is enough, as it&#39;s a dark roast anyways.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">For the second half, I go all in with one single pour, slowly with agitating the coffee bed much. This is to keep a light body and not over extracting things. We can even go with cooler water, around 70C, for this last pour.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Almost always, I get a good cup with this technique.</p><h3 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="osmotic-flow">Osmotic Flow</h3><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This recipe feels like it has been developed specially for dark roasts.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This too uses slightly coarse coffee but a tighter coffee to water ratio, around 1:13, which amounts to 15g of coffee and 195g of water.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">We pour the water only in the center, making small circles, and not the a whole big circle like a regular pour over.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The science behind this is osmosis, which in terms of this, means that coffee will move from high concentration areas to low concentration areas. The column which we create with the water flow will be less concentrated as we keep pouring the water.</p><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/73db8a56-5218-4d4c-b0fc-2af66ef28378/Screenshot_2025-08-02_at_15.41.41_2x.png?t=1754130042"/></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This recipe changed how I look at dark roasts.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This video explains this well.</p><iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube_embed" frameborder="0" height="100%" src="https://youtube.com/embed/kqQDYf8BmIA" width="100%"></iframe><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">These things let me enjoy pour overs with dark roast coffee.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I hope these techniques and changes to recipes help you enjoy your pour overs more.</p><hr class="content_break"><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><i>That’s all I...</i></p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Wait, I have an ask today. What is one song (or a playlist) you like to listen while making your coffee? I need some ideas and thanks in advance.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">That’s all I have. Have a caffeinated weekend.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">See you.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Keep on brewing!</p></div><div class='beehiiv__footer'><br class='beehiiv__footer__break'><hr class='beehiiv__footer__line'><a target="_blank" class="beehiiv__footer_link" style="text-align: center;" href="https://www.beehiiv.com/?utm_campaign=4ef0033d-d0d1-4131-8654-209f8a28efa9&utm_medium=post_rss&utm_source=caffeineletter">Powered by beehiiv</a></div></div>
  ]]></content:encoded>
</item>

      <item>
  <title>Pour Over tastes off? Here&#39;s how to fix it</title>
  <description>Summing up all the mistakes made and lessons learnt, this is your guide to diagnose your brew.</description>
      <enclosure url="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/52a5cda1-e353-4a2f-82c7-475e248fd5c5/aravindballa_watercolor_kitten_looking_at_coffee_in_V60_dripp_d58b2ba5-3316-404d-a542-f99ab7382735_3.png" length="2107512" type="image/png"/>
  <link>https://archive.letter.coffee/p/fixing-pour-overs</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://archive.letter.coffee/p/fixing-pour-overs</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jul 2025 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
  <atom:published>2025-07-26T13:30:00Z</atom:published>
    <dc:creator>Aravind Balla</dc:creator>
    <category><![CDATA[Og Tom]]></category>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[
    <div class='beehiiv'><style>
  .bh__table, .bh__table_header, .bh__table_cell { border: 1px solid #C0C0C0; }
  .bh__table_cell { padding: 5px; background-color: #FFFFFF; }
  .bh__table_cell p { color: #2D2D2D; font-family: 'Lora',Palatino,'Book Antiqua',Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
  .bh__table_header { padding: 5px; background-color:#F1F1F1; }
  .bh__table_header p { color: #2A2A2A; font-family:'Libre Baskerville','DejaVu Serif',Garamond,Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
</style><div class='beehiiv__body'><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/52a5cda1-e353-4a2f-82c7-475e248fd5c5/aravindballa_watercolor_kitten_looking_at_coffee_in_V60_dripp_d58b2ba5-3316-404d-a542-f99ab7382735_3.png?t=1753513918"/></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I was at a friend&#39;s place last week, and he was struggling with his pour over. The coffee was not tasting how he likes it. He asked, &quot;Why does my coffee taste so sour?&quot;</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">That&#39;s when I realized - I&#39;ve been writing about recipes and methods, but never really talked about the work that goes into fixing a bad cup.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">So today is about diagnosis - How to fix your pour over when it doesn&#39;t taste right.</p><hr class="content_break"><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="core-issues">Core Issues</h2><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">In my years of making pour overs, I&#39;ve noticed most issues fall into three categories:</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><b>Sour</b> - Coffee tastes acidic, sharp, maybe even lemony. This usually means under-extraction - you haven&#39;t pulled enough good stuff out of the beans.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><b>Bitter</b> - It&#39;s harsh, ashy, or leaves a dry feeling in your mouth. Classic over-extraction - you&#39;ve pulled out too much, including the unpleasant compounds.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><b>Weak</b> - Watery, lacking body, forgettable. This one&#39;s tricky because it could be under-extraction or just wrong ratios.</p><hr class="content_break"><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="and-the-fixes">And the fixes</h2><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Now for the fun part - how to fix these issues. I like to think of it as having a toolkit where each tool serves a specific purpose.</p><h4 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="grind-size"><b>Grind Size</b></h4><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This is usually where I start because it&#39;s the easiest to adjust. When you grind your own coffee, you get control.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Going finer increases extraction. The water has more surface area to work with, pulling more flavors out. So if your coffee tastes sour, try clicking your grinder a notch or two finer.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Going coarser does the opposite. Less surface area means less extraction. Perfect for when things are getting too bitter.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">On my Timemore C2, I usually work between 18-22 clicks. Light roasts sit around 18-19, mediums at 20, and darks at 21-24. But these are just starting points.</p><h4 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="temperature"><b>Temperature</b></h4><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Heat speeds up extraction. It&#39;s like the difference between making cold brew and hot coffee - same beans, drastically different extraction rates.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">For light roasts, I push it to 94-96°C. They&#39;re dense and need that extra heat to open up. Dark roasts? They&#39;re already broken down from roasting, so 85-88°C works great.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Here&#39;s a neat trick I learned - if your grinder can&#39;t go fine enough for a light roast, bump up your water temperature by 2-3 degrees. It achieves a similar effect.</p><h4 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="pouring-pattern"><b>Pouring pattern</b></h4><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This one&#39;s subtle but powerful. How you pour affects which compounds get extracted when.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Your first 40% of water (in a 250g brew, that&#39;s 100g) controls the sweet-acid balance. When we divide this 40% into two: a bigger first pour emphasizes brightness and acidity. And a bigger second pour brings out more sweetness.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The remaining 60% controls body. More pours = heavier body. Fewer pours = lighter, tea-like cup.</p><iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube_embed" frameborder="0" height="100%" src="https://youtube.com/embed/nxmrSgwW25g" width="100%"></iframe><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="few-hacks">Few Hacks</h2><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Over the years, I&#39;ve collected some unconventional solutions that actually work.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><b>Salt:</b> A tiny pinch of salt can neutralize bitterness. I&#39;m talking barely visible amounts - like three grains. It sounds bizarre but the science checks out. Salt blocks bitter receptors on your tongue.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><b>Stirring Blooms:</b> Some people swear by stirring the bloom. Others say never touch it. I&#39;ve found that a gentle stir can help with channeling issues, especially with darker roasts that tend to dome up.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><b>Lower Temperature in the last half:</b> If you&#39;re getting both sour AND bitter notes (yes, it happens), try starting with hot water for the bloom, then dropping 5-10 degrees for the remaining pours. You extract acids first, then ease off before the bitter compounds come out.</p><hr class="content_break"><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="my-diagnostic-process">My Diagnostic Process</h2><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">When I&#39;m dialing in a new coffee, here&#39;s my approach:</p><ul><li><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Start with the base recipe (15g coffee, 250g water, medium grind)</p></li><li><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Taste and identify the main issue</p></li><li><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Make ONE adjustment at a time</p></li><li><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Taste again</p></li><li><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Repeat until happy</p></li></ul><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The key is changing only one variable. Otherwise, you&#39;re shooting in the dark.</p><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/f1e146bc-d129-4826-afdc-a3cfac4b2a1e/IMG_2312.jpeg?t=1730459576"/></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I keep notes, vigorously. You can start with &quot;Salawara Estate Washed, 19 clicks, 94°C, still sour&quot; or &quot;Salawara Estate Washed, 21 clicks, 88°C, perfect.&quot; These notes become gold when you buy the same coffee again, or even if you want to repeat a perfect brew few days later.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Look, not every cup will be perfect. I&#39;ve been doing this for years and I still mess up.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">But that&#39;s part of the journey. Each &quot;failed&quot; cup teaches you something. And honestly? Even my worst pour over beats instant coffee any day.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Next time your pour over doesn&#39;t taste right, don&#39;t just suffer through it or throw it away. See what can be fixed.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">So {{ first name | friend }}, what&#39;s your most common pour over problem? And have you tried any weird fixes that actually worked? I&#39;m always looking for new tricks to add to the toolkit.</p><hr class="content_break"><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">That’s all I have. Have a caffeinated weekend.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">See you.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Keep on brewing!</p></div><div class='beehiiv__footer'><br class='beehiiv__footer__break'><hr class='beehiiv__footer__line'><a target="_blank" class="beehiiv__footer_link" style="text-align: center;" href="https://www.beehiiv.com/?utm_campaign=56ffdb3f-ae2d-4713-af7d-521dffd4e33a&utm_medium=post_rss&utm_source=caffeineletter">Powered by beehiiv</a></div></div>
  ]]></content:encoded>
</item>

      <item>
  <title>The Right Temperature to Brew Coffee</title>
  <description>We look at how water temperature varies the flavours and how to &#39;guess&#39;timate what works for you.</description>
      <enclosure url="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/e044ad08-680c-4998-8f99-a47a8db3e1d3/aravindballa_watercolor_The_kitten_heating_water_in_a_kettle__65260115-a6bf-4e87-afd7-02d59951b5b6_3.png" length="1604865" type="image/png"/>
  <link>https://archive.letter.coffee/p/the-right-temperature-to-brew-coffee</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://archive.letter.coffee/p/the-right-temperature-to-brew-coffee</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jul 2025 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
  <atom:published>2025-07-19T13:30:00Z</atom:published>
    <dc:creator>Aravind Balla</dc:creator>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[
    <div class='beehiiv'><style>
  .bh__table, .bh__table_header, .bh__table_cell { border: 1px solid #C0C0C0; }
  .bh__table_cell { padding: 5px; background-color: #FFFFFF; }
  .bh__table_cell p { color: #2D2D2D; font-family: 'Lora',Palatino,'Book Antiqua',Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
  .bh__table_header { padding: 5px; background-color:#F1F1F1; }
  .bh__table_header p { color: #2A2A2A; font-family:'Libre Baskerville','DejaVu Serif',Garamond,Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
</style><div class='beehiiv__body'><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/96cad8f2-a590-4b3f-bd6a-a1211f4edf36/aravindballa_watercolor_The_kitten_heating_water_in_a_kettle__65260115-a6bf-4e87-afd7-02d59951b5b6_3.png?t=1730460417"/></div><h1 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="the-right-water-temperature">The Right Water Temperature</h1><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><i>“What are you talking about? Can you just not put boiling water in ground coffee?”</i></p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Definitely not. Treat the poor coffee grounds carefully.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">We have seen chai and coffee made at our homes on the stovetops since childhood. It’s easy to think boiling water is necessary to extract the coffee. That is not completely wrong. But it’s easy to extract the unwanted flavours, like bitterness, at higher temperatures.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The coffee beans, or the pre-ground coffee, we generally get for brewing now is carefully studied and roasted. Boiling water just destroys everything. Or at least not to the full potential of what it can truly be.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The taste of coffee depends on a lot of factors like the roast level, temperature, coffee to water ratio and brewing technique. Let’s see how temperature can affect your brew.</p><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="whats-the-right-temperature-then">What’s the right temperature then?</h2><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">It’s quite tricky. Plus varies from palette (your taste) to palette. But we can follow guidelines.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Brewing coffee is as much science as it is an art.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">We know there are different types or levels of roasts: light, medium and dark. Each of them has different characteristics that extend to different ideal brewing temperatures.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Light roasts are known for their vibrant acidity (like the sourness in a fruit) and are generally more dense. Hotter water helps extract them better.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">On the other hand, medium and darker roasts are not as hard to extract, so we can drop the temperature down and not over-extract them. These dark roasts are already roasted at high temperatures.</p><div class="blockquote"><blockquote class="blockquote__quote"></blockquote></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Ideal temperatures help extract a balanced cup with the coffee&#39;s full aromatic profile. The recommended temperature is from 85C to upto 96C. I cannot give you a ball park figure as it depends on a lot of factors.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">We will talk about how to reach those temperatures without any measuring equipment in some time.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">But don&#39;t take my word for it. Experiment. Note down the temperature and how the coffee felt. Make changes accordingly. This newsletter is only a starting point for your exploration.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Every day is a new experiment. And when you are experimenting, it&#39;s generally advised to have only one variable and everything else consistent. For example, if you are figuring out the right temperature, keep the grind size and technique consistent.</p><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/f1e146bc-d129-4826-afdc-a3cfac4b2a1e/IMG_2312.jpeg?t=1730459576"/><div class="image__source"><span class="image__source_text"><p>For inspiration, this is how I log my brews.</p></span></div></div><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="how-to-eyeball-temperatures">How to eyeball temperatures</h2><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Knowing the temperature is a major factor in brewing your coffee. It is good to invest in a good temperature-controlled kettle.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">If you don&#39;t have it yet, here is what you can follow.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I do have a temperature-controlled kettle and did some experiments for you.</p><div class="blockquote"><blockquote class="blockquote__quote"></blockquote></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Keeping these ballpark figures in mind, you can adjust your brewing as you like.</p><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="one-last-tip">One last tip</h2><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">It’s equally important to keep the temperature consistent throughout the brew. And when you pour any hot liquid into a cold cup/brewer, it cools down significantly.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Preheat your equipment. This ensures your coffee doesn&#39;t get a thermal shock. It involves heating your brewer and cup before starting the brewing process.</p><div class="blockquote"><blockquote class="blockquote__quote"></blockquote></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Hope this makes your brews exciting and experimental. Keep brewing!</p></div><div class='beehiiv__footer'><br class='beehiiv__footer__break'><hr class='beehiiv__footer__line'><a target="_blank" class="beehiiv__footer_link" style="text-align: center;" href="https://www.beehiiv.com/?utm_campaign=bdfdce1e-fcd3-412c-af6b-e5723c3c3969&utm_medium=post_rss&utm_source=caffeineletter">Powered by beehiiv</a></div></div>
  ]]></content:encoded>
</item>

      <item>
  <title>This brewer quickly replaced my Daily Driver</title>
  <description>Let&#39;s talk about my current favourite coffee brewer - the Hario Switch.</description>
      <enclosure url="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/545e9388-06fe-44c5-8ad8-0d10d2843be8/aravindballa_watercolor_kitten_looking_at_coffee_in_V60_dripp_d58b2ba5-3316-404d-a542-f99ab7382735_2.png" length="1342613" type="image/png"/>
  <link>https://archive.letter.coffee/p/this-brewer-replaced-my-daily-driver</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://archive.letter.coffee/p/this-brewer-replaced-my-daily-driver</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jul 2025 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
  <atom:published>2025-07-13T13:30:00Z</atom:published>
    <dc:creator>Aravind Balla</dc:creator>
    <category><![CDATA[Equipment]]></category>
    <category><![CDATA[Recipes]]></category>
    <category><![CDATA[Baby Kitten]]></category>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[
    <div class='beehiiv'><style>
  .bh__table, .bh__table_header, .bh__table_cell { border: 1px solid #C0C0C0; }
  .bh__table_cell { padding: 5px; background-color: #FFFFFF; }
  .bh__table_cell p { color: #2D2D2D; font-family: 'Lora',Palatino,'Book Antiqua',Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
  .bh__table_header { padding: 5px; background-color:#F1F1F1; }
  .bh__table_header p { color: #2A2A2A; font-family:'Libre Baskerville','DejaVu Serif',Garamond,Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
</style><div class='beehiiv__body'><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/545e9388-06fe-44c5-8ad8-0d10d2843be8/aravindballa_watercolor_kitten_looking_at_coffee_in_V60_dripp_d58b2ba5-3316-404d-a542-f99ab7382735_2.png?t=1752411264"/></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Continuing to talk on the pour over coffee brewing, I recently got my hands on the Hario Switch, which is an upgraded version of V60. I have been eyeing this brewer from long enough, while trying to replicate what it does with some hacks, but brewing with this is game changing.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">If you don&#39;t have a pour over brewer like the V60 already, I can happily suggest you get this as your first pour over brewer for flexibility it has.</p><h3 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="so-how-is-this-brewer-different">So, how is this brewer different?</h3><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The Hario Switch looks almost identical to a regular V60, but there&#39;s a clever addition – a valve mechanism at the bottom. This valve is what makes all the difference.</p><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/a635ffa4-0a43-4c65-9d48-b3bed21d3c99/Screenshot_2025-07-13_at_18.27.19_2x.png?t=1752411478"/></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">With a regular V60, water flows through the coffee bed continuously. You have no control over the contact time except through your pouring technique and grind size. The Switch gives you a pause button. You can literally stop the flow whenever you want.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This might seem like a small change, but it opens up a whole new world of brewing possibilities.</p><h3 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="percolation-immersion-best-of-both-">Percolation + Immersion - best of both worlds</h3><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This is where the Switch really shines.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">In our previous posts, we talked about immersion brewing (like <a class="link" href="https://letter.coffee/p/understanding-french-press/?utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=this-brewer-quickly-replaced-my-daily-driver" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">French Press</a>, where coffee sits in water) and percolation (like regular <a class="link" href="https://letter.coffee/p/pour-over-coffee/?utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=this-brewer-quickly-replaced-my-daily-driver" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">V60</a>, where water flows through coffee). Each has its strengths:</p><ul><li><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><b>Immersion</b> gives you consistent extraction, fuller body, and is more forgiving with technique</p></li><li><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><b>Percolation</b> gives you clarity, brightness, and highlights the coffee&#39;s unique characteristics</p></li></ul><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I do feel percolation is superior at extracting coffee compounds, as fresh water flows through the coffee bed always and it has more ability to dissolve. But that could be not helpful all the times as we would want to cut down and not over extract.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The Switch lets you combine both the above methods in a single brew. You can start with immersion (closed valve) for the bloom – letting those CO2 gases escape while the coffee fully saturates. Then switch to percolation (open valve) for the main extraction. Or do the opposite. Or alternate between the two. The possibilities are endless!</p><h3 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="recipes-i-am-loving">Recipes I am loving</h3><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I am particularly enjoying an immersed first pour.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Recently, I discovered the technique of <i>adding water first</i> and then adding the coffee grounds on top. This let&#39;s the fines that come through cheap grinders not clog and stall the water flow.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Then I continue with the rest of the 4:6 method (we talked about this in <a class="link" href="https://letter.coffee/p/dissecting-a-versatile-pour-over-recipe/?utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=this-brewer-quickly-replaced-my-daily-driver" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">a previous post</a>) in percolation. But this isn&#39;t fixed. I experiment a lot and try to find what works best for the particular coffee that I am using.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">When I don&#39;t have time and I have to make something quick, I go with this <b>fool proof recipe</b> - 90deg water, 1:16 coffee to water ratio, put the coffee first and add 2/3rds of total water with the valve closed and wait for 2 minutes. Then open the valve add the rest of the water.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Let me leave you with recipes that I take inspiration from.</p><iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube_embed" frameborder="0" height="100%" src="https://youtube.com/embed/gC8K40kZ_6E" width="100%"></iframe><iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube_embed" frameborder="0" height="100%" src="https://youtube.com/embed/blQsogeBG7M" width="100%"></iframe><iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube_embed" frameborder="0" height="100%" src="https://youtube.com/embed/68ZOXrXbVHc" width="100%"></iframe><hr class="content_break"><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">That’s all I have. Have a caffeinated weekend.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">See you.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Keep on brewing!</p></div><div class='beehiiv__footer'><br class='beehiiv__footer__break'><hr class='beehiiv__footer__line'><a target="_blank" class="beehiiv__footer_link" style="text-align: center;" href="https://www.beehiiv.com/?utm_campaign=636cb7f5-20a7-4f50-ab92-76996149e56e&utm_medium=post_rss&utm_source=caffeineletter">Powered by beehiiv</a></div></div>
  ]]></content:encoded>
</item>

      <item>
  <title>Kenya&#39;s Coffee Scene</title>
  <description>From drinking good coffee in the middle of nowhere, to finding amazing espresso at gas stations, this the coffee experience during a short trip to Kenya.</description>
      <enclosure url="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/1e2bdf94-902c-4d5d-bf60-ba911de88c07/aravindballa_watercolor_baby_leapord_looking_at_coffee_in_cup_b75bd690-f1af-4bd0-a9aa-bd8a3d4def10_3.png" length="1404250" type="image/png"/>
  <link>https://archive.letter.coffee/p/coffee-scene-in-kenya</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://archive.letter.coffee/p/coffee-scene-in-kenya</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jul 2025 11:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
  <atom:published>2025-07-05T11:30:00Z</atom:published>
    <dc:creator>Aravind Balla</dc:creator>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[
    <div class='beehiiv'><style>
  .bh__table, .bh__table_header, .bh__table_cell { border: 1px solid #C0C0C0; }
  .bh__table_cell { padding: 5px; background-color: #FFFFFF; }
  .bh__table_cell p { color: #2D2D2D; font-family: 'Lora',Palatino,'Book Antiqua',Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
  .bh__table_header { padding: 5px; background-color:#F1F1F1; }
  .bh__table_header p { color: #2A2A2A; font-family:'Libre Baskerville','DejaVu Serif',Garamond,Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
</style><div class='beehiiv__body'><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/1e2bdf94-902c-4d5d-bf60-ba911de88c07/aravindballa_watercolor_baby_leapord_looking_at_coffee_in_cup_b75bd690-f1af-4bd0-a9aa-bd8a3d4def10_3.png?t=1751698024"/></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Last week I was in Kenya, loving all the animals around in Masai Mara. It was a wonderful trip. Keeping the topic of this newsletter in mind, let me give you all the coffee details.</p><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/ef895fbe-03fb-428f-aa9e-e2600e134c48/IMG_0113_2.jpeg?t=1751697390"/></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I didn&#39;t want to carry my coffee kit (Aeropress and a grinder) to this trip as Kenya, and the whole Africa, is known for producing and exporting a lot of coffee. But I didn&#39;t want to take any chances, so I did. Ended up using it twice, so that was good in the end.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">At the place we stayed, they had instant coffee, which was no different than the ones we get here. So skipped that and made my own.</p><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="brewed-coffee-in-a-forest">Brewed Coffee in a Forest</h2><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">After a couple of days of not finding good coffee and making my own, I was surprised to find at a place that I least expected.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">We finished a hot air balloon ride, landed in the middle of a forest where our jeeps picked us up and took for a place to have breakfast. As we walked to our tables, I saw one french press per table and I was happy.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I had a chat with the waiters there. I explained this term French Press to them. They said they would happily keep calling it &quot;coffee maker&quot;. 😂</p><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/7d201d3f-ab7a-4417-83bc-fd0abd3d1044/IMG_5745.jpeg?t=1751697556"/><div class="image__source"><span class="image__source_text"><p>In that forest…</p></span></div></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Drinking that freshly brewed coffee, even if it was a espresso ground dark roast, was reviving.</p><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="coffee-scene">Coffee Scene</h2><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I haven&#39;t spent time in Kenya for long. All the days were at the forest in Masai Mara. But while going there from Airport and coming back, we stopped at cafes and gas stations (which surprising had good coffee shops).</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">There were very few places with manual brews like pour over and Aeropress. But they did use speciality coffee at some places. The espressos were fantastic. I haven&#39;t finished an espresso that fast. That too at a coffee shop in a gas station.</p><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/518fded4-446a-470b-a81f-486b7276f4ef/IMG_5302.jpeg?t=1751697674"/><div class="image__source"><span class="image__source_text"><p>Gas Station Coffee</p></span></div></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I later learnt that all the good, high-grade coffee is exported out of Kenya. Only the average coffee is the one that remains. Kenya, known for its high-grade Arabica, is one of the biggest exporters of coffee. Obviously, after Ethiopia.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Ethiopia is where coffee was first discovered. Even though it&#39;s near Kenya, coffee didn&#39;t arrive directly. It took centuries. French missionaries brought coffee seeds into Kenya, later British colonists controlled the whole coffee production until the 1930s when Kenyans were allowed to grow coffee on their lands.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Today, Kenya produces and trades a lot of coffee.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Our guide told us about Nairobi Coffee Exchange, the hub of coffee trading. It seems all coffee offered at the exchange must meet specific quality standards, ensuring that only the finest beans reach the market. This even influences the price of the coffee globally.</p><hr class="content_break"><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">That’s my excerpt from Kenya.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Have a caffeinated weekend.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">See you. Keep brewing! ☕️ </p></div><div class='beehiiv__footer'><br class='beehiiv__footer__break'><hr class='beehiiv__footer__line'><a target="_blank" class="beehiiv__footer_link" style="text-align: center;" href="https://www.beehiiv.com/?utm_campaign=cae8b3e4-77ba-4603-8ad3-05a7704bfa45&utm_medium=post_rss&utm_source=caffeineletter">Powered by beehiiv</a></div></div>
  ]]></content:encoded>
</item>

      <item>
  <title>Dissecting a versatile Pour Over Recipe</title>
  <description>Let&#39;s see how one recipe let&#39;s you tweak and make different tasting cups with the same set of coffee beans and equipment</description>
      <enclosure url="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/d5ec2d4b-b153-4692-b51f-f9d4a4077a7b/aravindballa_watercolor_kitten_looking_at_coffee_in_cup_from__086f753e-4085-43c9-a4c1-a4aee588472a_3.png" length="1251722" type="image/png"/>
  <link>https://archive.letter.coffee/p/dissecting-a-versatile-pour-over-recipe</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://archive.letter.coffee/p/dissecting-a-versatile-pour-over-recipe</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 11:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
  <atom:published>2025-06-21T11:30:00Z</atom:published>
    <dc:creator>Aravind Balla</dc:creator>
    <category><![CDATA[Teenage Cat]]></category>
    <category><![CDATA[Recipes]]></category>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[
    <div class='beehiiv'><style>
  .bh__table, .bh__table_header, .bh__table_cell { border: 1px solid #C0C0C0; }
  .bh__table_cell { padding: 5px; background-color: #FFFFFF; }
  .bh__table_cell p { color: #2D2D2D; font-family: 'Lora',Palatino,'Book Antiqua',Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
  .bh__table_header { padding: 5px; background-color:#F1F1F1; }
  .bh__table_header p { color: #2A2A2A; font-family:'Libre Baskerville','DejaVu Serif',Garamond,Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
</style><div class='beehiiv__body'><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/4e06a7ce-bcad-43a0-8e4e-f0077d8037fb/aravindballa_watercolor_kitten_looking_at_coffee_in_cup_from__086f753e-4085-43c9-a4c1-a4aee588472a_3.png?t=1750435326"/></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Last we looked at how coffee can be brewed in its purest form, respecting the whole complex flavour profile of the coffee beans using <a class="link" href="https://letter.coffee/p/pour-over-coffee/?utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=dissecting-a-versatile-pour-over-recipe" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">the pour over method</a>.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Today, I want to talk about a versatile recipe that lets you tweak and make differently tasting cups of coffee with the same set of coffee beans and equipment.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">But first let us understand what goes behind the scenes while brewing coffee by jumping into a bit of science.</p><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="magic-happens-in-stages">Magic Happens in Stages</h2><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><a class="link" href="https://letter.coffee/p/pour-over-coffee/?utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=dissecting-a-versatile-pour-over-recipe" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">We talked that to make a pour over, we add water to the filter with ground coffee in different pours, or different stages</a>. At these different stages different flavours or compounds are extracted.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">First come the <b>acids</b> – those bright, citrusy notes that make your taste buds dance. These little compounds (citric and malic acids) are eager to jump out in the first 30 seconds, especially if when the water is the hottest.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Then comes the sweet stuff. Between 30 seconds and 2 minutes, <b>sugars and caramelized compounds</b> start flowing in. These are what give your coffee that lovely sweetness.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Lastly <b>tannins and bitter compounds</b> start getting extracted. These make up the body of the coffee.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">When everything is balanced, including the bitterness, a great cup of coffee takes shape.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This can easily be tested by changing the cup you are extracting into midway through the brew. Drinking from both the cups individually, beginning and the ending ones, wont be enjoyable but when mixed it becomes beautiful.</p><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="enter-tetsu-kasuyas-46-method">Enter Tetsu Kasuya&#39;s 4:6 Method</h2><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This Japanese champion figured out something brilliant. His method splits your brewing into two acts:</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><b>Act 1 (First 40% of water in 2 pours):</b> This is where you control the sweet-acid balance. Want more tang? Make your first pour bigger. Craving sweetness like a good filter coffee? Make the second pour larger. You&#39;re literally controlling which compounds extract more!</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><b>Act 2 (Remaining 60% in 3 pours):</b> This determines your coffee&#39;s strength and body. More pours = heavy body, fewer pours = lighter cup. Think of body as density. Full cream milk has heavy body and green tea has light body.</p><iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube_embed" frameborder="0" height="100%" src="https://youtube.com/embed/wmCW8xSWGZY" width="100%"></iframe><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><i>What about the other variables?</i></p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I like to set the <b>temperature</b> based on the roast level. Light roasts the hottest upto 96 deg and dark roast go as low as 85deg.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">For the <b>grind size</b>, my standard grind is around <a class="link" href="https://letter.coffee/tools/grind-size/?sourceBrand=Timemore&sourceModel=C2&sourceClicks=20&utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=dissecting-a-versatile-pour-over-recipe" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">20 clicks on the Timemore C2</a>. If it&#39;s too sour, I decrease. If it&#39;s too bitter, I increase.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">With just this one recipe, I keep playing and experimenting for weeks.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I hope this helps in understanding the what happens when you make a pour over and helps your brewing.</p><hr class="content_break"><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">That’s all I have. Have a caffeinated weekend.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">See you.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Keep on brewing!</p></div><div class='beehiiv__footer'><br class='beehiiv__footer__break'><hr class='beehiiv__footer__line'><a target="_blank" class="beehiiv__footer_link" style="text-align: center;" href="https://www.beehiiv.com/?utm_campaign=8d0f8671-4e3d-4dd3-8b21-bd9c08fde382&utm_medium=post_rss&utm_source=caffeineletter">Powered by beehiiv</a></div></div>
  ]]></content:encoded>
</item>

      <item>
  <title>Let&#39;s make a cup of Pour Over Coffee</title>
  <description>We talk about the basics, equipment needed and the recipe for an amazing cup of coffee, in its purest form, that you can make at home.</description>
      <enclosure url="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/bb89604d-110c-4241-9576-f8cba587b8d6/aravindballa_watercolor_kitten_looking_at_coffee_in_V60_dripp_35917822-5434-40c9-bb24-5e5b02b64747_2.png" length="1340669" type="image/png"/>
  <link>https://archive.letter.coffee/p/pour-over-coffee</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://archive.letter.coffee/p/pour-over-coffee</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jun 2025 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  <atom:published>2025-06-14T14:00:00Z</atom:published>
    <dc:creator>Aravind Balla</dc:creator>
    <category><![CDATA[Equipment]]></category>
    <category><![CDATA[Teenage Cat]]></category>
    <category><![CDATA[Recipes]]></category>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[
    <div class='beehiiv'><style>
  .bh__table, .bh__table_header, .bh__table_cell { border: 1px solid #C0C0C0; }
  .bh__table_cell { padding: 5px; background-color: #FFFFFF; }
  .bh__table_cell p { color: #2D2D2D; font-family: 'Lora',Palatino,'Book Antiqua',Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
  .bh__table_header { padding: 5px; background-color:#F1F1F1; }
  .bh__table_header p { color: #2A2A2A; font-family:'Libre Baskerville','DejaVu Serif',Garamond,Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
</style><div class='beehiiv__body'><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/bb89604d-110c-4241-9576-f8cba587b8d6/aravindballa_watercolor_kitten_looking_at_coffee_in_V60_dripp_35917822-5434-40c9-bb24-5e5b02b64747_2.png?t=1749889428"/></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Today, let us talk about my go-to and favourite way of making coffee: <b>pour over</b>.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The reason it&#39;s my favourite is because it&#39;s fun. It does take time (around 10 mins from setup to cleanup) and some skill (which is not that complicated), but the variables you can play with and tweak make the whole thing <i>worth it</i>. The resulting cup you get is full of flavour and I enjoy drinking from hot till it comes to the room temperature.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">In this post, I will write about the equipment you will need, and a basic recipe, which is the one I use when I start to brew a new bag of coffee beans. And then based on how it tastes I tend to alter the variables until I get a perfect one.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">There is a lot I can talk about and for you to know. But thankfully, you don&#39;t have to everything before you start brewing with it.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">And to keep the posts short and value packed, I plan to write multiple posts that accompany this one.</p><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="essentials">Essentials</h2><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">For the equipment, I want talk about the must-have tools first and then good to have ones, in the decreasing order of importance. So that this acts like a nice upgrade path for you as you step up your game.</p><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/c8780c06-3e04-400b-a5fa-ed77d080b0b4/IMG_5164.jpg?t=1749890091"/><div class="image__source"><span class="image__source_text"><p>Aravind’s current V60 brewing setup</p></span></div></div><h3 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="brewing-device-v-60-dripper">Brewing device - V60 dripper</h3><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><i>Obvio!</i></p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">There is absolutely no need to go fancy here. You can get a basic Hario V60 dripper for around ₹500. This was my first pour over dripper from 4 years ago and I still have it today. This is the one I use for by base recipes.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">In this dripper, we put in a filter, most commonly a paper filter. We get a few filters with the dripper when we buy, and we should restock them after we run out.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">We talked about <a class="link" href="https://letter.coffee/p/one-of-a-kind-coffee-filter/?utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=let-s-make-a-cup-of-pour-over-coffee" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">filters</a> in an earlier post.</p><h3 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="kettle">Kettle</h3><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">You need a way to heat the water, and also pour it on the coffee.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The later, pouring on the coffee, is equally important because that determines how much the of coffee bed is getting disturbed and how evenly the coffee is getting extracted. When you just directly pour hot water from a utensil, it&#39;s hard to make sure all that things happen and it is hard to exactly repeat the process.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">A gooseneck kettle gives you that precise control. You can start with a normal kettle and then upgrade to this gooseneck one. Trust me, it&#39;s a game changer.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">To measure the temperature, you can get a kitchen thermometer, or buy an electric coffee kettle which can be set to a certain temperature.</p><h3 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="scale">Scale</h3><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Eyeballing things will only take you so far.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Look, I get it. Measuring seems like too much work for your morning coffee. But the thing is - making a cup coffee is basically chemistry, and chemistry needs precision. A small digital scale that can measure in grams will cost you around ₹800-1,000.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Once you start weighing your coffee and water, you&#39;ll notice how much more consistent your cups become.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I used to start a stopwatch on my phone earlier, but the scale I have now also has a timer built in. I start it and see how slow or how fast I am pouring.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Making a cup of V60 pour over involves multiple rounds of pouring water and waiting. One tool that measures weight and time makes sense.</p><h3 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="coffee-grinder">Coffee Grinder</h3><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">You can directly buy ground coffee, but I would not advise you to.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">For me, fresh ground coffee is non-negotiable. Pre-ground coffee loses its flavour faster than you can say &quot;filter kaapi&quot;.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">A hand grinder is your best friend here. Grinders are the costliest part of the coffee setups. Because that definitely makes a lot of difference.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Manual grinders like the Hario Mini Mill (around ₹3,000) or TimeMore C2 (around ₹5,000) will serve you well. Yes, it&#39;s a bit of arm workout, but honestly, I find the grinding process quite meditative.</p><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="how-the-brewing-works">How the brewing works</h2><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Fresh hot water goes through the bed of coffee in the filter, extracts the coffee from the ground beans and gets collected in the cup. This process is called percolation.</p><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="the-base-recipe">The Base Recipe</h2><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This is the recipe I use to judge the coffee beans when get a new fresh bag.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I have the Timemore C2, and on it, I grind 15g of coffee at <a class="link" href="https://letter.coffee/tools/grind-size/?sourceBrand=Timemore&sourceModel=C2&sourceClicks=20&utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=let-s-make-a-cup-of-pour-over-coffee" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">20 clicks</a>. Based on the roast level, I heat the water up to a certain temperature. Light roasts need more heat, around 94-96deg, and dark roast can be done well with 85deg too. Total water I use will be 250g which makes the coffee to water ratio around 1:16.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">With the V60 put on a cup, and a paper filter in it, I get ready to brew by rinsing the filter and making it stick to the dripper. Then I put the coffee grounds in and start adding hot water from the gooseneck kettle.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The first phase is called bloom, where I use water that measures 3x the weight of coffee, pour it slowly in circles and wait for up to 45 seconds. I split the remaining water, which is 250 - 45 = 205, into two parts and pour one after the other. So the next stop would be around 147g on the scale, and after the water drains out, final pour comes in making the total weight 250g. I aim to finish this brew around 3:00 minutes.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Now, based on how it tastes, I alter the recipe. If I want to make it more lighter and tea like, I reduce the number of pours. If the acidity is high and I want to balance it with some bitterness, I either crank up the temperature a bit, or reduce the grind size. If it&#39;s too bitter, then the opposite.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This is the fun.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">While making these cups, I also note down all the things so that I remember what I followed last time and a rating of how it turned out. It is really helpful.</p><hr class="content_break"><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This is all what you need to get started. In the next post, let&#39;s take one famous recipe for V60 from the internet and try to understand how it works.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">See you.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Keep on brewing!</p></div><div class='beehiiv__footer'><br class='beehiiv__footer__break'><hr class='beehiiv__footer__line'><a target="_blank" class="beehiiv__footer_link" style="text-align: center;" href="https://www.beehiiv.com/?utm_campaign=a49d57fc-0971-4ced-9004-761dd7b233ee&utm_medium=post_rss&utm_source=caffeineletter">Powered by beehiiv</a></div></div>
  ]]></content:encoded>
</item>

      <item>
  <title>One-of-a-kind Coffee Filter</title>
  <description>In the recent 2025 World Brewers Cup, a finalist used a special kind of filter for his pour over which caught attention</description>
      <enclosure url="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/4fb6b764-ae46-46f4-aa47-b8d0ad2a0b98/aravindballa_watercolor_beige_color_kitten_watching_tv_on_a_t_caac8cf3-eabf-444c-92f9-fd3f20eb2964_0.png" length="1329827" type="image/png"/>
  <link>https://archive.letter.coffee/p/one-of-a-kind-coffee-filter</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://archive.letter.coffee/p/one-of-a-kind-coffee-filter</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2025 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
  <atom:published>2025-05-24T13:30:00Z</atom:published>
    <dc:creator>Aravind Balla</dc:creator>
    <category><![CDATA[Equipment]]></category>
    <category><![CDATA[Og Tom]]></category>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[
    <div class='beehiiv'><style>
  .bh__table, .bh__table_header, .bh__table_cell { border: 1px solid #C0C0C0; }
  .bh__table_cell { padding: 5px; background-color: #FFFFFF; }
  .bh__table_cell p { color: #2D2D2D; font-family: 'Lora',Palatino,'Book Antiqua',Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
  .bh__table_header { padding: 5px; background-color:#F1F1F1; }
  .bh__table_header p { color: #2A2A2A; font-family:'Libre Baskerville','DejaVu Serif',Garamond,Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
</style><div class='beehiiv__body'><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/4fb6b764-ae46-46f4-aa47-b8d0ad2a0b98/aravindballa_watercolor_beige_color_kitten_watching_tv_on_a_t_caac8cf3-eabf-444c-92f9-fd3f20eb2964_0.png?t=1748067747"/></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Do you randomly watch Coffee Championship videos? I do.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I was recently watching <a class="link" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tzgXKvxbyPg&list=PLzI16LSYAwDb0DjMUHUo5ILnMFPcZGazo&utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=one-of-a-kind-coffee-filter" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">2025 World Brewers Cup videos</a> and came across something very interesting.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">It is a filter, used in making a pour over coffee, that doesn&#39;t let plain water pass through initially, until the first parts of the coffee is extracted.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I know this is cool but before we look into why and how that is possible, let&#39;s talk about why filters in coffee brewing.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Filters are what separate coffee from water. So they do seem to play a crucial role.</p><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="types-of-filters">Types of filters</h2><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Broadly, there are 3 types of filters - <b>paper, metal and cloth</b>.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><b>Paper filters</b> are the most used. For all types of major types of coffee brewing like pour overs, Aeropress, chemex etc. They tend to filter very well, effectively trapping oils and fine particles resulting in clean cup with enhanced brightness and acidity. The best part about these is that there is no sediments in the cup.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><b>Metal filters</b> have larger pores than the paper ones, allowing oils and fines to pass to the cup. It results in much fuller body and a good mouth feel.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This is not always not desirable. There were a lot of Aeropress Championships which were won with a metal filter.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><b>Cloth ones</b>, although I haven&#39;t used them yet, seem to be a middle ground between paper and metal. It has a faster flow rate than paper which means higher extraction.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Flow rate is the speed with which water passes through the coffee bed and falls into the cup. Matters only in percolation type brews like pour overs, or the unverted aeropress.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Now, in paper filters, there are <i>yet a few types</i>. Not all paper filters are the same. You can choose ones based on the flow rate or their ability catch the micro-fines from going into our cups. For example, if brewing with dark roasts, Cafec T-90 helps you not over extract with a faster flow rate.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This difference is achieved based on how thick and porous the papers are made. They can choose to have different textures inside and outside.</p><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="coming-to-the-oneofakind-one">Coming to the one-of-a-kind one</h2><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/eb09f06c-1b35-43a1-905d-f7ac4e0bcb21/Screenshot_2025-05-24_at_11.35.27_2x.png?t=1748067021"/><div class="image__source"><span class="image__source_text"><p>Water is in the filter but doesn&#39;t drip. <a class="link" href="https://youtu.be/OnUGoLwp1cI?t=214&utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=one-of-a-kind-coffee-filter" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">Source</a></p></span></div></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This one is so new I could not find any material online.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">It is essentially a hydrophobic filter. Meaning that it repells water. So initial till it is only water and nothing else, nothing passes. This results in an immersion style bloom for some time. My guess is that it improves the acidity and sweetness.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Slowly when the coffee starts to extract, chemicals in coffee react with the filter and let it pass and it becomes a normal filer.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">All of this is fascinating to me. I hope I passed on some of it to you now as well.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">As usual, let me leave you with some links so that you can explore further.</p><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="more-links-to-explore">More Links to explore</h2><iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube_embed" frameborder="0" height="100%" src="https://youtube.com/embed/HfVjGx1x7Ds" width="100%"></iframe><iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube_embed" frameborder="0" height="100%" src="https://youtube.com/embed/Ca2BMotyyAc" width="100%"></iframe><h2 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="the-competition-video">The competition video 👇🏼</h2><iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube_embed" frameborder="0" height="100%" src="https://youtube.com/embed/OnUGoLwp1cI" width="100%"></iframe><hr class="content_break"><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">That’s all I have. Have a caffeinated weekend.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">See you.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Keep on brewing!</p></div><div class='beehiiv__footer'><br class='beehiiv__footer__break'><hr class='beehiiv__footer__line'><a target="_blank" class="beehiiv__footer_link" style="text-align: center;" href="https://www.beehiiv.com/?utm_campaign=cc9cc183-5326-458d-a40f-b505379ac371&utm_medium=post_rss&utm_source=caffeineletter">Powered by beehiiv</a></div></div>
  ]]></content:encoded>
</item>

      <item>
  <title>Understanding the Moka Pot</title>
  <description>Let us look how to brew with this amazing no-extra-equipment-needed brewer that sits on a stovetop.</description>
      <enclosure url="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/38833eae-69ef-4573-b8be-a885b4001a21/aravindballa_watercolor_kitten_looking_at_coffee_in_moka_pot__653ff03b-3bb9-456d-b20d-5cbde731ef19_0.png" length="1553904" type="image/png"/>
  <link>https://archive.letter.coffee/p/understanding-the-moka-pot</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://archive.letter.coffee/p/understanding-the-moka-pot</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 18 May 2025 05:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
  <atom:published>2025-05-18T05:00:00Z</atom:published>
    <dc:creator>Aravind Balla</dc:creator>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[
    <div class='beehiiv'><style>
  .bh__table, .bh__table_header, .bh__table_cell { border: 1px solid #C0C0C0; }
  .bh__table_cell { padding: 5px; background-color: #FFFFFF; }
  .bh__table_cell p { color: #2D2D2D; font-family: 'Lora',Palatino,'Book Antiqua',Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
  .bh__table_header { padding: 5px; background-color:#F1F1F1; }
  .bh__table_header p { color: #2A2A2A; font-family:'Libre Baskerville','DejaVu Serif',Garamond,Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
</style><div class='beehiiv__body'><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/38833eae-69ef-4573-b8be-a885b4001a21/aravindballa_watercolor_kitten_looking_at_coffee_in_moka_pot__653ff03b-3bb9-456d-b20d-5cbde731ef19_0.png?t=1747540505"/></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Moka pot is probably the best brewer to impress your parents and justify your coffee equipment purchase. Most Indians are into milk based coffees and Moka is just perfectly positioned to enhance a milk coffee.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">With this ~1000 INR priced brewer which operates on a stovetop, you can make multiple types of coffee – a near espresso style drink, a americano style drink and a regular milk based coffee like cortado or a cappuccino.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">For time to time, I enjoy a strong bold jolt of coffee that I can brew from the Moka.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">A lot of people call it a stove top Espresso Maker. But it is technically not an espresso. It might have the same strength of the coffee but it is extracted at a way low, under 2 bars of pressure, compared to espresso which is 9 bars.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">While brewing with this is easy enough, I used to make a mess and didn&#39;t like what it was producing. I definitely knew it was skill issue and researched a bit about it, leading me to enjoy this drink.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I will leave you with the tricks and tips so you can build on top of my mistakes when you start.</p><h3 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="how-it-works-brews">How it <span style="text-decoration:line-through;">works</span> brews</h3><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Like espresso, a mokapot uses pressure to drive water through coffee and extract. It&#39;s quite fascinating actually.</p><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/3c39f262-192b-4b65-9cb3-55d69e71b6b6/28233.png?t=1747539767"/><div class="image__source"><span class="image__source_text"><p>Parts of the Moka pot</p></span></div></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">We put water in the below chamber, coffee in the funnel which is ground fairly fine but not espresso grind, screw the whole thing together and put it on a stove top.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The heat makes the water boil and slowly it starts to turn into vapour. Because the system is completely locked, there is nowhere for the vapour to go. So it pushes this water which is getting hot and makes spaces for itself. Where would the water go? Only way it has is to raise up through the coffee, in the funnel.</p><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/2fca279c-2aac-4ba6-899c-c9981c6774f7/Untitled_Artwork.jpg?t=1747539795"/><div class="image__source"><span class="image__source_text"><p>How water flows.</p></span></div></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">And that&#39;s how, my friend, you get a beautiful cup of coffee brewed with the Mokapot.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">You can treat this as the base coffee for a lot of drinks you can make. Hot water makes it Americano. Adding milk is a great option. You can even drink it straight if you enjoy a bitter jolt.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Best part is that you can mixers, like sparkling water or orange juice or tonic water or ginger ale. It becomes a beautiful refreshing summer drink. This coffee has the right concentration to be mixed with these things.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">If you remember, I told you I wasn’t getting satisfactory cups in the beginning.</p><h3 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="things-that-have-fixed-the-taste-fo">Things that have fixed the taste for me</h3><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">First is to not let it sputter. After the coffee is almost done extracting, it starts sputtering. We should immediately remove from the stove top and maybe run it through cold water to let it cool. Whatever comes after this phase is not tasty.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The goal should be to get most of the water through the coffee grounds before it starts to sputter.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This gets me to my second point which is to start with boiling water. The main advantage of this is that it takes less time to brew. And the brewing starts at a good temperature (around 90C). If you take room temperature water, water that gets pushed through the coffee is not yet at optimal temperature, and you get an under extracted feel. This alone got a substantial improvement in the taste.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Below are a few optional ones that you don&#39;t really have to do but if done, the taste and feel is slightly improved.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">If your grind has many fines, there is a possibility that they end up in your cup. The last sip with coffee grounds is not a good experience. What helps here is an Aeropress paper filter. Yes, you heard it right.</p><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/2cac50ba-43c3-483e-9209-95a6ba182603/Screenshot_2025-05-18_at_09.15.43_2x.png?t=1747539984"/><div class="image__source"><span class="image__source_text"><p>Aeropress filter on the moka pot upper chamber</p></span></div></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">You put an Aeropress filter on the upper chamber and wet it a little bit so that it sticks there until you screw this to the lower chamber.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This not only helps in filtering out the fines but also improves the taste by preserving some acidity of the coffee.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I hope these tips and tricks help you as well in your Moka journey.</p><hr class="content_break"><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">That’s all I have. Have a caffeinated weekend.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">See you.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Keep on brewing!</p></div><div class='beehiiv__footer'><br class='beehiiv__footer__break'><hr class='beehiiv__footer__line'><a target="_blank" class="beehiiv__footer_link" style="text-align: center;" href="https://www.beehiiv.com/?utm_campaign=72f4aef2-cc09-4e6e-b21a-ec802e725be3&utm_medium=post_rss&utm_source=caffeineletter">Powered by beehiiv</a></div></div>
  ]]></content:encoded>
</item>

      <item>
  <title>Brewing with the Aeropress</title>
  <description>Here is all you need to know.</description>
      <enclosure url="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/10a4d5fa-320b-4155-bb58-cd5b7312787f/IMG_0992.jpeg" length="358732" type="image/jpeg"/>
  <link>https://archive.letter.coffee/p/brewing-with-the-aeropress</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://archive.letter.coffee/p/brewing-with-the-aeropress</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2025 13:01:05 +0000</pubDate>
  <atom:published>2025-05-10T13:01:05Z</atom:published>
    <dc:creator>Aravind Balla</dc:creator>
    <category><![CDATA[Equipment]]></category>
    <category><![CDATA[Og Tom]]></category>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[
    <div class='beehiiv'><style>
  .bh__table, .bh__table_header, .bh__table_cell { border: 1px solid #C0C0C0; }
  .bh__table_cell { padding: 5px; background-color: #FFFFFF; }
  .bh__table_cell p { color: #2D2D2D; font-family: 'Lora',Palatino,'Book Antiqua',Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
  .bh__table_header { padding: 5px; background-color:#F1F1F1; }
  .bh__table_header p { color: #2A2A2A; font-family:'Libre Baskerville','DejaVu Serif',Garamond,Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
</style><div class='beehiiv__body'><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/10a4d5fa-320b-4155-bb58-cd5b7312787f/IMG_0992.jpeg?t=1746881874"/></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">We talked about the Aeropress Championship last week which was mostly about the competition and not much about the actual craft–brewing with the Aeropress.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Let’s talk about it in this post.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Aeropress is my second favourite brewer (V60 stands in the first place) and my constant travel companion.</p><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/171e642c-c4e0-4946-9ebe-4cd3327a2fa2/IMG_1474.jpeg?t=1743162770"/><div class="image__source"><span class="image__source_text"><p>Repurposing a pic I took while travelling in the Himalayas</p></span></div></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This is a versatile brewer that costs around 4k INR. Lot of people make a strong cup and use it like an espresso for milk based drinks. Or make it with a pour over consistency and drink it straight.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">It is also very forgiving in my opinion. You don&#39;t need your grinds to be perfect, or need any extra equipment like gooseneck kettle or a scale. You can start with just the brewer and that makes it a beginner friendly brewer.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">It became so popular a couple of years after it was invented. Soon people started having competition all over the world.</p><h3 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="why-was-it-invented">Why was it invented?</h3><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Alan Adler, an Aerodynamics Engineer, invented Aeropress to have a quick way to get a nice cup of coffee. Time and a single cup were the priorities back then.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Single cup used to be one of the cons back then. But now we have an XL version of the cup. And also a smaller more compact GO version aimed at travel. I use the original version though.</p><h3 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="lets-get-to-brewing-now">Let’s get to brewing now</h3><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">There are essentially two ways one can brew with an Aeropress. Normal way where the chamber, with the filter attached or an inverted way where the piston and chamber are in an upside down position.</p><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/4e40b0ae-8efa-4bcc-a734-592d8eee25bc/IMG_0988.jpeg?t=1746880877"/><div class="image__source"><span class="image__source_text"><p>The two ways: Normal and Inverted</p></span></div></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Let me tell you how I like to brew it.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I like to do it in the inverted fashion. I get more control like this. 12g of ground coffee to start with in the chamber, I put some hot water to fully make the coffee wet. I swirl it and wait for the coffee to bloom for about 30 seconds. Pour the rest of the water to almost fill the chamber. Wait for 2 minutes, put the filter cap and flip the whole Aeropress over a cup and plunge.</p><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/e40e07c7-7e7b-4ac1-85f1-0e7c13a3bf0c/IMG_0990.jpeg?t=1746881001"/><div class="image__source"><span class="image__source_text"><p>Parts of an Aeropress</p></span></div></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The whole process takes about 3 minutes. I end up with a nice and consistent cup all times.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">If you observe, there are no specific calculations involved here. For the coffee as well, you can use one particular spoon all the time and measure it like one spoon or two spoons.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This is what makes it travel friendly as well. I carry the spoon with which I measure the coffee. I get a kettle at almost all the places I stay.</p><h3 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="what-about-the-normal-method">What about the normal method?</h3><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The non inverted, or the unverted method like the reddit folks call it also has it’s own advantage.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Immersion and Percolation are two major categories of coffee brewing. What we saw above with the inverted method is immersion, where the coffee is in contact with the water all the time. In percolation, coffee extracted by flowing through water.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">In the normal method, we can use a mix of percolation and immersion.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">When you put the chamber with the filter on a cup and pour water over the coffee in it, water flows through and falls into the cup. Then you can keep pouring until desired level and then attach the plunger on top. If you don’t press the plunger, the water stays in the chamber without dripping in the cup, which is immersion mode.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Lots to experiment here right?</p><h3 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="some-cons">Some cons</h3><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">One majorly discussed con is that you can’t brew more than a cup with this Aeropress. Even though there is Aeropress XL, there are a few hacks to brew a bigger cup two cups with a standard Aeropress as well.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The idea is that you brew a much stronger cup with more coffee, and then you add hot water and dilute the brew to a better intensity. This is called bypassing.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">One more con is that the Aeropress is made with plastic. They tell you the plastic is BPA-free though. And it is always better to buy an original one than the knock offs available. There is also one Premium version that comes in glass and metal but that is pricey again.</p><hr class="content_break"><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Let me leave you with some links to dive deep, some recipes, some science etc instead of going on and rambling here. <i>Didn’t realised I wrote these many words.</i></p><iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube_embed" frameborder="0" height="100%" src="https://youtube.com/embed/bl0mV6Nb0GQ" width="100%"></iframe><iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube_embed" frameborder="0" height="100%" src="https://youtube.com/embed/CafyJ2p0Bgs" width="100%"></iframe><iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube_embed" frameborder="0" height="100%" src="https://youtube.com/embed/jBXm8fCWdo8" width="100%"></iframe><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">So, what do you think about the Aeropress? Do you use one already or planning to get one? I am curious to know!</p><hr class="content_break"><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">That’s all I have. Have a caffeinated weekend.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">See you.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Keep on brewing!</p></div><div class='beehiiv__footer'><br class='beehiiv__footer__break'><hr class='beehiiv__footer__line'><a target="_blank" class="beehiiv__footer_link" style="text-align: center;" href="https://www.beehiiv.com/?utm_campaign=9495ca28-9961-4017-a471-7f01a02c6bcc&utm_medium=post_rss&utm_source=caffeineletter">Powered by beehiiv</a></div></div>
  ]]></content:encoded>
</item>

      <item>
  <title>Aeropress Championship 2025 Lessons</title>
  <description>Preparation, brewing coffee and learnings from regional Indian Aeropress Championship</description>
      <enclosure url="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/1310bded-a52f-4357-8b16-ad0a04eb0ef2/aravindballa_watercolor_3_kittens_on_table_beside_aeropress_c_f04a0734-9f35-45b8-98d6-1192517c904a_2.jpg" length="129655" type="image/jpeg"/>
  <link>https://archive.letter.coffee/p/aeropress-championship-2025-lessons</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://archive.letter.coffee/p/aeropress-championship-2025-lessons</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 03 May 2025 03:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
  <atom:published>2025-05-03T03:30:00Z</atom:published>
    <dc:creator>Aravind Balla</dc:creator>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[
    <div class='beehiiv'><style>
  .bh__table, .bh__table_header, .bh__table_cell { border: 1px solid #C0C0C0; }
  .bh__table_cell { padding: 5px; background-color: #FFFFFF; }
  .bh__table_cell p { color: #2D2D2D; font-family: 'Lora',Palatino,'Book Antiqua',Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
  .bh__table_header { padding: 5px; background-color:#F1F1F1; }
  .bh__table_header p { color: #2A2A2A; font-family:'Libre Baskerville','DejaVu Serif',Garamond,Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
</style><div class='beehiiv__body'><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/32745056-6523-4f3b-bbd5-2c80a296f604/aravindballa_watercolor_3_kittens_on_table_beside_aeropress_c_f04a0734-9f35-45b8-98d6-1192517c904a_2.jpg?t=1746180110"/></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">A couple of days ago, the Indian Aeropress Championship Regionals took place in Hyderabad.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><i>Of course, I had to participate.</i></p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This post is a distillation of all my learnings, how I prepared and why should anyone participate.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Did I win? No, I got eliminated too soon.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">You&#39;d probably stop reading. But don&#39;t you learn a lot from mistakes compared to wins?</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Let&#39;s talk about the championship itself and not the Aeropress much as that deserves a post in itself.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The format of the competition is elimination. You brew the coffee along with 2 others. The judges will blind taste the coffee and pick one cup they like. If your cup is picked, you go to the next round.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">First the regionals take place. Top 3 winners go compete at Nationals. One winner then competes Internationally.</p><h3 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="preparation">Preparation</h3><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Around 10 days before the event, you receive a bag of competition coffee beans. These are the same ones you will get during the competition.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">During this time, we experiment with the beans trying out different recipes and tweaking the controllables with Aeropress coffee brewing.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The parameters you can tweak are - temperature, grind size, coffee to water ratio and the time to brew.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">You can search on YouTube for recipes or even championship recipes. There are tonnes of them. If you already brew with an Aeropess, it&#39;s best to stick to what you already do and tweak things. One thing to remember with the recipes you find online is that the beans are not the same - so the result cup will differ.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">And when you burry yourself with a lot of recipes, it quickly gets overwhelming and returns diminish. Bloom or not, preheat the paper or not etc confuse you and they don&#39;t even affect the resulting cup.</p><iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="true" class="youtube_embed" frameborder="0" height="100%" src="https://youtube.com/embed/jBXm8fCWdo8" width="100%"></iframe><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This is a good video to go through where James Hoffmann talks about what would affect the cup and what would not. Prioritize more brews with one recipe and parameter tweaks that many different recipes.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Take a note of the taste notes and the mouthfeel of the coffee, the recipe, and the parameters you used.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I suggest doing this experiments over 10 days you have. I could not do this properly as I was traveling. Just before the competition, I brew around 12 cups in 2 days. And by the end of if, I guess my tongue got fatigue, I couldn&#39;t tell the difference between cups.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The outcome from this should ideally be one recipe and a good understanding of tweaking which parameter changes what. This is crucial because at the competition you have to brew a cup which is different from the other 2 brewing alongside you and a good cup.</p><h3 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="at-the-competition">At the competition</h3><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I arrived at the cafe, where the competition was taking place, with all my equipment - Aeropress, grinder, kettle, filters etc. only to discover they provide all the equipment.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Any which ways, I practiced on my equipment so I used only those in the competition. They had a world class Mahklong automatic grinder, but I used my Timemore C2 for the experiments. I didn&#39;t want to make last minute changes.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I was surprised to see more than 50 members participating in the championship. Most of them were baristas from cafés. There were a handful home brewers like me.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Coming to brewing coffee, one of the mistakes I did was to not take into account how cool the room was. I practice in my kitchen at home. Here, there was an AC set at 18deg blasting cool air from my back when I was brewing. My recipe had water at 80deg which is already cool than regular ones. AC cooled it more. What I had was a weak under-extracted cup.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This cannot be the only reason, obviously. I could have prepared well with a nicer recipe if I had all the 10 days to understand the beans.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">A few more tips that I picked from look at others brewing and talking to the participants there:</p><ul><li><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">It is good to check if the equipment you use is allowed or not. In my case, I had a metal filter for Aeropress which was from a 3rd party and not from original Aeropress company. This wasn&#39;t allowed. Thankfully, a co participant had the original one and they let me borrow it. <i>Neither of us made it to the next round, that&#39;s irrelavant.</i></p></li><li><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The equipment can give up in the middle of your brew. So it&#39;s good to carry yours and making sure it has fresh batteries etc. It happened to a participant that the scale stopped functioning midway. In situations like this, you have to eyeball stuff and that can only be done if you have practiced a lot.</p></li><li><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Remember to keep an eye on how you co brewers are brewing.</p></li></ul><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">There is a lot to take away from the competition. Just being in a room full for coffee enthusiasts boosts you. Everyone is friendly.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Would I participate again next year? Hell yeah.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Should you participate? Yes. Even if you are just a beginner. People are supportive. You will discover and learn a lot.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I hope this helps you in your preparation and motivates you to participate.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I want to leave you with a few links that helped in my preparation:</p><ul><li><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><a class="link" href="https://www.youtube.com/@roasting_hands/search?query=aeropress&utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=aeropress-championship-2025-lessons" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">https://www.youtube.com/@roasting_hands/search?query=aeropress</a></p></li><li><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><a class="link" href="https://coffeeadastra.com/2021/09/07/reaching-fuller-flavor-profiles-with-the-aeropress/?utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=aeropress-championship-2025-lessons" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">https://coffeeadastra.com/2021/09/07/reaching-fuller-flavor-profiles-with-the-aeropress/</a></p></li><li><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><a class="link" href="https://coffeeadastra.com/2022/08/01/the-mechanism-behind-astringency-in-coffee/?utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=aeropress-championship-2025-lessons" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">https://coffeeadastra.com/2022/08/01/the-mechanism-behind-astringency-in-coffee/</a></p></li><li><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><a class="link" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CafyJ2p0Bgs&utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=aeropress-championship-2025-lessons" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CafyJ2p0Bgs</a></p></li></ul><hr class="content_break"><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">That’s all I have. Have a caffeinated weekend.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">See you.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Keep on brewing!</p></div><div class='beehiiv__footer'><br class='beehiiv__footer__break'><hr class='beehiiv__footer__line'><a target="_blank" class="beehiiv__footer_link" style="text-align: center;" href="https://www.beehiiv.com/?utm_campaign=e0ff54f8-8e3a-4385-a4ea-dd0c8a89da1d&utm_medium=post_rss&utm_source=caffeineletter">Powered by beehiiv</a></div></div>
  ]]></content:encoded>
</item>

      <item>
  <title>Can Steel Ball make Coffee better?</title>
  <description>I stumbled upon a coffee brewer that makes better coffee and is backed by science.</description>
      <enclosure url="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/464c3769-d1e0-4534-a2cc-7c7a8b543ce7/aravindballa_watercolor_kitten_looking_at_a_small_steel_ball__7cca8db4-a1d8-44ef-9395-99e05e1bd2c9_3.png" length="1458602" type="image/png"/>
  <link>https://archive.letter.coffee/p/can-steel-ball-make-coffee-better</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://archive.letter.coffee/p/can-steel-ball-make-coffee-better</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 19 Apr 2025 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
  <atom:published>2025-04-19T13:30:00Z</atom:published>
    <dc:creator>Aravind Balla</dc:creator>
    <category><![CDATA[Teenage Cat]]></category>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[
    <div class='beehiiv'><style>
  .bh__table, .bh__table_header, .bh__table_cell { border: 1px solid #C0C0C0; }
  .bh__table_cell { padding: 5px; background-color: #FFFFFF; }
  .bh__table_cell p { color: #2D2D2D; font-family: 'Lora',Palatino,'Book Antiqua',Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
  .bh__table_header { padding: 5px; background-color:#F1F1F1; }
  .bh__table_header p { color: #2A2A2A; font-family:'Libre Baskerville','DejaVu Serif',Garamond,Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
</style><div class='beehiiv__body'><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/464c3769-d1e0-4534-a2cc-7c7a8b543ce7/aravindballa_watercolor_kitten_looking_at_a_small_steel_ball__7cca8db4-a1d8-44ef-9395-99e05e1bd2c9_3.png?t=1745070688"/></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">How are you doing, {{first_name | coffee lover}}? Hope you had a nice caffeinated week. </p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I recently saw an interesting pour-over setup at a cafe. Between the pour-over brewer and the coffee server, there was a holder. I was intrigued.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I asked the barista about it; he told me a cold steel ball goes in that holder while brewing, and it makes the coffee taste better.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The coffee we get isn&#39;t cold, but the cold ball is used in the first half of the brewing process to improve its taste.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I had to try it. But was it better?</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Before telling you how it tasted or felt, let me talk about the research this interesting brewer sparked.</p><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/02d6d8a6-23ce-4125-9671-bcb18d2c7c53/Pasted_image_20250419161243.png?t=1745061565"/></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This brewer is called Paragon from the company named Nucleus coffee tools. They came up with a science technique called &quot;Extract Chilling.&quot;</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Let me boil down how it works.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Any experience, either food or a drink, involves not just the taste but also the smell or the aroma of that item.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">To test this, you can sip coffee with your nose pinched. It doesn&#39;t feel the same. Remember when you had a cold and your nose was all stuffed up? You probably noticed how bland the food tasted.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">And in coffee, there are a lot of volatile compounds that make up the aroma. If you take a cup of coffee, you can taste different notes at different temperatures because of this.</p><hr class="content_break"><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Coming back to the brewer, the chilling rock plays a crucial role of locking in the volatile aroma compounds while brewing.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">First let&#39;s look at the brewing process without the chilling rock, and then go to how it makes the taste better.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This technique is primarily a pour-over.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Coffee extracts differently at different temperatures. Especially in a pour-over. When you pour hot water from above onto the coffee, first the acids and fats get extracted. Then the sweetness. By this time, the whole coffee reaches higher temperatures. And now the body and bitterness get extracted. When all of these are balanced well, the cup tastes good.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Now, when the coffee is beginning to extract, we let it drip over the chilling rock and lock in the aroma. This chilling rock is used in the zone when the acids and sweetness are extracted.</p><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/8c1db280-291d-4287-9352-53d2084207be/24748.png?t=1745061653"/></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This is known to lock in up to 40% more volatiles which otherwise are lost in the air. The aroma that fills the room while making coffee is captured with this.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Back to the question of whether the coffee tasted good – it was a great cup of coffee in general. What I should have done is taste the coffee normally with out this chill ball and then with, to make out the difference.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Let me leave you with a few links where you can learn more about this.</p><ol start="1"><li><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><a class="link" href="https://nucleuscoffeetools.com/news/understanding-the-paragon-and-its-scientific-approach/?utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=can-steel-ball-make-coffee-better" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">Understanding the Paragon and its Scientific approach</a></p></li><li><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><a class="link" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zFw2OjnB43c&utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=can-steel-ball-make-coffee-better" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">Chill Extract Theory and Paragon Brewer</a></p></li></ol><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">It&#39;s fascinating how things in coffee are developed and invented.</p><hr class="content_break"><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">That’s all I have. Have a caffeinated weekend.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">See you.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Keep on brewing!</p></div><div class='beehiiv__footer'><br class='beehiiv__footer__break'><hr class='beehiiv__footer__line'><a target="_blank" class="beehiiv__footer_link" style="text-align: center;" href="https://www.beehiiv.com/?utm_campaign=782decdb-c0a8-4122-9d5f-7f553ca3050f&utm_medium=post_rss&utm_source=caffeineletter">Powered by beehiiv</a></div></div>
  ]]></content:encoded>
</item>

      <item>
  <title>A Cheeky little Coffee Dripper</title>
  <description>Tasting coffee brewed with V60&#39;s younger brother and bit of pour over science.</description>
      <enclosure url="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/3fd63e93-dc98-425d-8964-b445d15b7933/aravindballa_watercolor_kitten_making_staring_at_a_coffee_cup_00a0d8d3-cb0a-4265-91cd-38a40e40e812_1__1_.png" length="1357462" type="image/png"/>
  <link>https://archive.letter.coffee/p/cheeky-little-coffee-dripper</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://archive.letter.coffee/p/cheeky-little-coffee-dripper</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 13:33:31 +0000</pubDate>
  <atom:published>2025-04-05T13:33:31Z</atom:published>
    <dc:creator>Aravind Balla</dc:creator>
    <category><![CDATA[Equipment]]></category>
    <category><![CDATA[Og Tom]]></category>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[
    <div class='beehiiv'><style>
  .bh__table, .bh__table_header, .bh__table_cell { border: 1px solid #C0C0C0; }
  .bh__table_cell { padding: 5px; background-color: #FFFFFF; }
  .bh__table_cell p { color: #2D2D2D; font-family: 'Lora',Palatino,'Book Antiqua',Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
  .bh__table_header { padding: 5px; background-color:#F1F1F1; }
  .bh__table_header p { color: #2A2A2A; font-family:'Libre Baskerville','DejaVu Serif',Garamond,Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
</style><div class='beehiiv__body'><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/3fd63e93-dc98-425d-8964-b445d15b7933/aravindballa_watercolor_kitten_making_staring_at_a_coffee_cup_00a0d8d3-cb0a-4265-91cd-38a40e40e812_1__1_.png?t=1743853335"/></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Last week I was at one of the cozy coffee shops in Hyderabad named <a class="link" href="https://www.instagram.com/kohe.hyderabad/?hl=en&utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=a-cheeky-little-coffee-dripper" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">Kohe</a>. They were expanding the space and they now have a manual coffee station.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">As usual, I ordered hot pour over.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This was 8 am or else I would have definitely opted for an iced one to combat the Summer’s heat. I am also drafting a post on my favourite iced coffee drinks (black) I make at home, for the hot summers. Let me know if you are interested.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Coming back, I order this drink and walk my way to this newly setup manual brewing station and I see some an array of different drippers.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This cute V60 looking one caught my eye. A little conversation with the barista made me want to try it.</p><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/4fd93df2-7552-4a6f-b7c0-34ae199128fb/IMG_4431.jpeg?t=1743850898"/><div class="image__source"><span class="image__source_text"><p>Deep 27 Coffee Dripper</p></span></div></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This one is called Flower Dripper Deep 27, from the Japanese coffee geniuses - Cafec.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">27, as you might have guessed, is the bottom angle. Similar to how V60 is named.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Their <a class="link" href="https://cafec-jp.com/products/deep27/?utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=a-cheeky-little-coffee-dripper" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">site</a> talks a lot on what went behind the scenes why coming up with this dripper. Before this they came up with Deep 45, which they was best for 3-7 cups. And now they wanted to come up with one that can do single cups perfectly. After, one and half years, they finalised 27.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">You should <a class="link" href="https://cafec-jp.com/products/deep27/?utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=a-cheeky-little-coffee-dripper" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">check it out</a> as they talk about rib heights and hole diameters. Fascinating.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><i>I asked the Barista, &quot;How is this different from the regular V60?&quot;.</i> He said that this one has a faster run down rate.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">That means water doesn&#39;t stay with the coffee grounds for long.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">So he was making changes, like increasing agitation with more number of pours, to counter this run down rate. Or else we would have been left with an under extracted cup tasting weak and sour.</p><hr class="content_break"><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Let us take a small detour to understand why.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;"><b>Different stages of the brewing extracts different components from the coffee.</b> First, when the coffee is getting wet with hot water, it&#39;s the acidic and the fatty components come out. Then the sweeter ones. And at last come the bitterness and boldness.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">When all of these are perfectly balanced, you get a good tasting cup. And depending on the coffee, you can tweak, balance and get a cup of your choice.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This is the reason I like experimenting with pour overs, all the different brewers and the parameters. Same coffee but different tastes.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">With this gyaan, I hope you see and analyze coffee with a different lens.</p><hr class="content_break"><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The cup ended up tasting sweet, well balanced and bodied.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Because it&#39;s in a cafe, they used 15g of coffee which is their standard dose. But one of the great advantages you get with this dripper is that you can brew coffee with as low as 6g as it&#39;s narrow and bed height wouldn&#39;t be so low.</p><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/946524f8-4fae-4a77-82e3-2b871aea141e/28179.png?t=1743850988"/><div class="image__source"><span class="image__source_text"><p><a class="link" href="https://cafec-jp.com/products/deep27/?utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=a-cheeky-little-coffee-dripper" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">https://cafec-jp.com/products/deep27/</a></p></span></div></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This only means you can micro dose caffeine through out the day. ;)</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">One more thing to keep in mind is that you would need a get filter papers that are designed specifically for this dripper. Cafec strongly suggests we don&#39;t use regular V60 papers with extra folds as it makes the base uneven and raising the angle to 30deg.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">So yes, this is what I have learnt after stumbling upon this coffee dripper at a cafe.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Would I buy it? Yes, it wouldn&#39;t hurt.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Would you get one? If you have tried it, I would love to know how your experience was.</p><hr class="content_break"><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">That’s all I have. Have a caffeinated weekend.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">See you.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Keep on brewing!</p></div><div class='beehiiv__footer'><br class='beehiiv__footer__break'><hr class='beehiiv__footer__line'><a target="_blank" class="beehiiv__footer_link" style="text-align: center;" href="https://www.beehiiv.com/?utm_campaign=4242a510-4cd3-433b-847a-a2487e5dc382&utm_medium=post_rss&utm_source=caffeineletter">Powered by beehiiv</a></div></div>
  ]]></content:encoded>
</item>

      <item>
  <title>Travel Coffee Setups</title>
  <description>Practical and mobile setups to enjoy freshly brewed coffee while travelling.</description>
      <enclosure url="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/3660e25c-10eb-4be4-81d8-686a62363bbf/aravindballa_watercolor_kitten_making_coffee_mountains_in_the_ba8ee0bb-dd45-4319-ba7e-cf93c1a71138_2.png" length="1540811" type="image/png"/>
  <link>https://archive.letter.coffee/p/travel-coffee-setups</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">https://archive.letter.coffee/p/travel-coffee-setups</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 29 Mar 2025 03:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
  <atom:published>2025-03-29T03:40:00Z</atom:published>
    <dc:creator>Aravind Balla</dc:creator>
    <category><![CDATA[Teenage Cat]]></category>
  <content:encoded><![CDATA[
    <div class='beehiiv'><style>
  .bh__table, .bh__table_header, .bh__table_cell { border: 1px solid #C0C0C0; }
  .bh__table_cell { padding: 5px; background-color: #FFFFFF; }
  .bh__table_cell p { color: #2D2D2D; font-family: 'Lora',Palatino,'Book Antiqua',Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
  .bh__table_header { padding: 5px; background-color:#F1F1F1; }
  .bh__table_header p { color: #2A2A2A; font-family:'Libre Baskerville','DejaVu Serif',Garamond,Georgia,serif !important; overflow-wrap: break-word; }
</style><div class='beehiiv__body'><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/65c5bc76-de5f-43cb-95e9-76589a6bc3ba/aravindballa_watercolor_kitten_making_coffee_mountains_in_the_ba8ee0bb-dd45-4319-ba7e-cf93c1a71138_2.png?t=1743163291"/></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Good coffee is so addictive that you can&#39;t leave it behind when you travel. Once you start making it at home, it becomes very hard not to have it.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">You might have a great setup at home, but you can&#39;t travel around with all that. It becomes so cumbersome to pack everything.</p><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/0d6e3f09-9f56-448e-a028-45918df0ed57/IMG_4143.jpeg?t=1743162917"/><div class="image__source"><a class="image__source_link" href="https://www.altspaced.com/?utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=travel-coffee-setups" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><span class="image__source_text"><p>Alt Space, Dharamshala</p></span></a></div></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I am at Dharamshala now and I packed an Aeropress, hand grinder along with some coffee beans. And I love this setup.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I spoke with my fellow travellers who happen to love coffee as well. This post is a distillation of all the practical options for a mobile coffee setup.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">And while you book stay for your travel, it is good to confirm that they have a water heating kettle. Most areas have it.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">For the coffee beans, I like freshly ground, so I carry a hand grinder. But you can take ground coffee if this is not something you are obsessed about.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I mainly talk about the setups for black coffee here but you can fancy a milk one with one of the espresso techniques.</p><h3 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="aeropress">Aeropress</h3><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">This is hands down the best choice. I always carry this with me while travelling.</p><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/171e642c-c4e0-4946-9ebe-4cd3327a2fa2/IMG_1474.jpeg?t=1743162770"/><div class="image__source"><span class="image__source_text"><p>Aeropress-ing morning coffee from the hostel in Himalayas</p></span></div></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Aeropress is good mainly because the setup is small to carry. The Aeropress itself, paper filters/metal filter, and coffee beans.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">I recently learnt that you can also get an attachment to the Aeropress called <a class="link" href="https://youtu.be/daHVyiUoRYw?utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=travel-coffee-setups" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">Prismo</a> which opens up possibilities for an espresso.</p><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/7d5b9354-75d6-4abf-a293-cbbb4b46e056/11818.png?t=1743162996"/><div class="image__source"><span class="image__source_text"><p><a class="link" href="https://www.benkibrewingtools.com/products/fellow-aeropress-prismo?utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=travel-coffee-setups" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">https://www.benkibrewingtools.com/products/fellow-aeropress-prismo</a></p></span></div></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">With this, you can have an espresso, Americano, or any milk based drinks.</p><h3 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="nanopress">Nanopress</h3><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">On the slightly expensive side, we have Nanopress for around 6k INR. This works well for an espresso again.</p><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/d1638db1-228c-48e4-84c8-650faf7f0cc2/68896.png?t=1743163031"/><div class="image__source"><span class="image__source_text"><p><a class="link" href="https://www.benkibrewingtools.com/collections/wacaco/products/wacaco-nanopresso-espresso-coffeemaker?utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=travel-coffee-setups" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">https://www.benkibrewingtools.com/collections/wacaco/products/wacaco-nanopresso-espresso-coffeemaker</a></p></span></div></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The way this works is you put in the ground coffee, hot water and pump the nob with you hand. The maximum pressure you can generate is 18 bars which is more than enough for an espresso.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Again, the possibilities are unlimited when you have an espresso at hand.</p><h3 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="easy-pour-bags">Easy Pour bags</h3><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">If you are into pour overs, this is a great option. You get these easy pour bags which put over a cup, pour hot water and enjoy the coffee.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">We talked about them in a <a class="link" href="https://letter.coffee/p/easiest-way-to-brew-speciality-coffee-at-home/?utm_source=caffeineletter&utm_medium=newsletter&utm_campaign=travel-coffee-setups" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">post</a> earlier and I have also mentioned a few options where you can buy from.</p><div class="image"><img alt="" class="image__image" style="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/18844bc0-1558-4f1f-8a4d-d04a3e2e6341/Lifestyle_4_bcc19eef-90f6-43ba-8ca2-c5571d31a385.jpeg?t=1743163075"/></div><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">A lot of the people here prefer this method. Especially as there is no major investment over any equipment.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">If you are feeling fancy and experimental, you can get only the bags on amazon and fill it with your favourite coffee ground to perfection by you. Then you can carry them in any airtight container and you are good to go.</p><h3 class="heading" style="text-align:left;" id="last-resort">Last resort</h3><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">The last option is instant coffee, like Davidoff, Sleepy Owl, etc. I hate to mention it because I don&#39;t like it. But people do carry or buy instant coffee while travelling. So it gets to be here on this post.</p><hr class="content_break"><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">So, what will be your travel companion. Let me know.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">That’s all I have. Have a caffeinated weekend.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">See you.</p><p class="paragraph" style="text-align:left;">Keep on brewing!</p></div><div class='beehiiv__footer'><br class='beehiiv__footer__break'><hr class='beehiiv__footer__line'><a target="_blank" class="beehiiv__footer_link" style="text-align: center;" href="https://www.beehiiv.com/?utm_campaign=20442556-86f1-404b-ac94-b84e84bd95cc&utm_medium=post_rss&utm_source=caffeineletter">Powered by beehiiv</a></div></div>
  ]]></content:encoded>
</item>

  </channel>
</rss>
