<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>Daring Fireball</title>
<subtitle>By John Gruber</subtitle>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/" />
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main" />
<id>https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main</id>


<updated>2025-04-26T01:07:21Z</updated><rights>Copyright © 2025, John Gruber</rights><entry>
	<title>Rumor Suggests iPadOS 19 to Get Some Mac-Like Tweaks, Like a Menu Bar</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://majinbuofficial.com/ipados-19-and-ios-19-new-features/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wab" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/25/ipados-19-menu-bar" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41843</id>
	<published>2025-04-25T23:51:31Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-26T01:07:21Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Majin Bu:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>According to my source, Apple is gearing up for another major leap
forward. With iPadOS 19 and iOS 19, expected in 2025, the gap
between iPad, iPhone, and Mac continues to shrink. [...] One of
the most exciting changes will benefit those using the iPad with a
Magic Keyboard. When connected, the interface will adapt to show a
menu bar at the top, just like on macOS, turning the iPad into a
much more laptop-like experience.</p>

<p>Another key update is Stage Manager 2.0, an enhanced multitasking
mode that activates automatically when the keyboard is attached.
It will make managing apps and windows smoother and more
productive than ever.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I don’t think it’s worth spending too much time thinking about these changes until we actually see what Apple is doing, but the menu bar is one of the great achievements in the history of UI design, and the Mac has always had the best design for a menu bar — at the top of the screen, not at the top of each window. Menu bars are such a great way to present and organize complexity. Moderately complex Mac apps typically have dozens of menu commands. More complicated apps can have 100 or more commands. I’ve never seen a plausible design for an app as complicated as, say, Xcode, BBEdit, or Photoshop without a menu bar. One of the reasons why Apple’s own apps are always better — and more capable — on MacOS than on iOS or iPad is that they’ve got more commands, better organized, because there’s a menu bar. Apple Notes, Apple Mail, the whole iWork suite — they’re all better on Mac, and they all have way more features on the Mac.</p>

<p>Reading a menu is also far more humane than scrutinizing icons. Sure, pick the handful of most-used commands and make them available in a toolbar of icons. But the full menu of commands should be <em>written</em>, not illustrated. You don’t order food in a serious restaurant by pointing at unlabeled pictures. You read the menu.</p>

<p>I know iPadOS today already supports a menu-bar-like HUD thing when you have a keyboard attached and hold down the Command key. I find that to be far less usable and far more distracting than a Mac-style menu bar. There’s a reason the Mac only shows you one menu at a time. Focus. The Mac menu bar is boring, but it’s boring in the best possible way. With the iPad’s current HUD menu, it’s like if the Mac dropped down every menu in an app at the same time. Presumably what Bu is describing is just making the iPad’s HUD menu present itself the way it should have from the start. I’ve always felt like iPadOS’s designers made the iPad’s HUD menu different from the Mac just to be different, not because it’s better — because I don’t see how it’s better in any way.</p>

<p>But the other problem is with the idea that iPadOS’s menu — whether as it stands today, as a HUD, or as this rumor suggests it might change, to be more like the Mac — is only available when you have a keyboard attached. Why shouldn’t users be able to access all menu commands when they’re just using the iPad via touch? It’s unnecessarily restrictive that the full list of commands in an app is only available when a keyboard is attached — especially for a device that many users never attach a keyboard to.</p>

<p>Bu continues:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>iOS 19 isn’t being left behind. Source say that iPhones with USB-C
will support external displays, offering a Stage Manager like
interface. While not a full desktop mode, it will allow users to
extend their screen space, great for presentations, editing, or
enhanced viewing.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I often use my iPhone connected to a hardware keyboard, especially in the morning, while making coffee. And I seldom take an iPad with me when I travel any more — often/usually just my MacBook and iPhone. An iPhone with a Bluetooth keyboard is a great portable travel kit. (Apple’s own Magic Keyboard, for example, is remarkably lightweight.) All sorts of keyboard shortcuts that a Mac or iPad user is accustomed to work on an iPhone when using a keyboard, too.</p>

<p>But the one that’s missing that kills my productivity the most, takes me right out of the flow, is Command-Tab. It makes no sense to me why iOS <em>doesn’t</em> support Command-Tab. I personally don’t foresee ever attaching my iPhone to an external display (but I can see why some people would), but I really just hope that if this rumor comes to pass, it includes support for Command-Tab too.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Rumor Suggests iPadOS 19 to Get Some Mac-Like Tweaks, Like a Menu Bar’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/25/ipados-19-menu-bar">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Wayne Ma Reports That Political Tensions Are Making It Difficult for Apple to Shift More iPhone Production From China to India</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theinformation.com/articles/apples-india-manufacturing-push-faces-spoilers-including-china?rc=jfy0lk" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/waa" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/25/ma-india-china-iphone" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41842</id>
	<published>2025-04-25T23:13:58Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-25T23:13:58Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Wayne Ma, reporting for The Information (paywalled, alas):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Earlier this year, Chinese authorities refused to allow one of
Apple’s Chinese equipment suppliers to export machinery to India
that Apple needed for the upcoming iPhone 17’s trial production,
according to two people with direct knowledge of the matter. So
the supplier got creative.</p>

<p>It set up a front company in Southeast Asia to buy the machines.
Once the equipment reached the Southeast Asian country, it went to
a factory in India operated by Foxconn, the Taiwanese company that
builds most of Apple’s iPhones in China, the people said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Ian Malcolm: “Life finds a way.” So too with Apple getting what it wants.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>India is already assembling between 30 million and 40 million
iPhones a year — as much as one-fifth of the iPhone’s global
production, according to people involved in Apple’s India supply
chain. Apple is planning to increase iPhone production in India by
around 10% this year, one of those people said. The company has a
long-term goal of moving about half of its iPhone production out
of China, according to other people involved in Apple’s supply
chain. [...]</p>

<p>Increasingly, though, just getting that manufacturing equipment to
India is a hassle. In many cases, Chinese authorities are delaying
or blocking shipments of iPhone equipment to India without
explanation, according to multiple people involved in iPhone
production.</p>

<p>Foxconn has seen approval times from Chinese authorities for
exporting iPhone-making equipment from its China factories to
those in India rise from two weeks to as long as four months, one
of the people said. They are also rejecting some export
applications without explanation, the person added.</p>

<p>The equipment Chinese authorities are scrutinizing includes
high-precision lasers that weld metal parts to the frames of
iPhones, air leak test stations that measure how waterproof the
devices are, and machines that can identify, grab and move parts
from one location to another, known as pick-and-place machines,
according to three people involved in iPhone manufacturing.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Hardball tactics on all sides here.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Wayne Ma Reports That Political Tensions Are Making It Difficult for Apple to Shift More iPhone Production From China to India’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/25/ma-india-china-iphone">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Financial Times Reports That Apple Wants to Produce All U.S. Phones in India by the End of Next Year</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.ft.com/content/c2be45b8-cfad-4cbb-9a1a-bfd0626be372" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wa9" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/25/financial-times-apple-iphones-india" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41841</id>
	<published>2025-04-25T22:52:38Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-25T22:52:39Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The Financial Times:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple plans to shift the assembly of all US-sold iPhones to India
as soon as next year, according to people familiar with the
matter, as President Donald Trump’s trade war forces the tech
giant to pivot away from China.</p>

<p>The push builds on Apple’s strategy to diversify its supply chain
but goes further and faster than investors appreciate, with a goal
to source from India the entirety of the more than 60mn iPhones
sold annually in the US by the end of 2026.</p>

<p>The target would mean doubling the iPhone output in India, after
almost two decades in which Apple spent heavily in China to create
a world-beating production line that powered its rise into a $3tn
tech giant.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Financial Times Reports That Apple Wants to Produce All U.S. Phones in India by the End of Next Year’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/25/financial-times-apple-iphones-india">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Henry Blodget’s Illustrated 2013 Travelogue of Flying in Coach on a Long International Flight</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.salon.com/2013/01/28/henry_blodgets_kind_of_awful_plane_ride/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wa8" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/25/blodget-coach" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41840</id>
	<published>2025-04-25T20:22:38Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-25T20:27:44Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Andrew Leonard, writing for Salon back in 2013:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The first thing wrong with the stupidest article to be posted to
the Internet in the year 2013 — and possibly the entire century — is the title: “<a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/american-airlines-international-economy-class-2013-1?op=1#ixzz2JIlmxu88">I Was Quite Surprised By Some Things On My
American Airlines International ‘Economy Class’ Flight</a>.” Even
setting aside the high probability that author Henry Blodget, the
founder, CEO and editor-in-chief of Business Insider, wrote his
account of the mild horrors of nine hours cramped in the cheap
seats in order to purposely troll people like me who would
ruthlessly mock him and thus drive even more traffic to his site,
the low-rent search-engine optimization of Blodget’s headline
would still be a crime against journalism. Blodget’s made many
mistakes in the past, not least the dot-com boom-era stock hyping
escapades that got him banned from the securities industry for
life, but this inane tale of 34,000-feet-high horror marks a new
low. The man should now be denied access to a keyboard for life,
or until the heat death of the universe, whichever comes first.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>My working theory has always been that both things can be true: Henry Blodget really is an idiotic jackass <em>and</em> he’s actually clever at crafting clickbait stories. One of Blodget’s complaints is that his laptop died after 3 hours, and he didn’t bring anything to read, leaving him 5 hours with nothing to do. I’m only slightly exaggerating when I say I’d be more likely to jump out of an airplane without a parachute than I would be to board a flight without plenty of stuff to read.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Henry Blodget’s Illustrated 2013 Travelogue of Flying in Coach on a Long International Flight’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/25/blodget-coach">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Henry Blodget Creates Imaginary Staff of AI Personalities for His New Website and Hits on One of Them</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.regenerator1.com/p/building-our-native-ai-newsroom" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wa7" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/25/blodget-regenerator" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41839</id>
	<published>2025-04-25T16:47:52Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-25T19:58:19Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Henry Blodget, <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/media/2015/sep/29/henry-blodget-comeback-business-insider">who sold Business Insider to German publishing giant Axel Springer</a> for $340 million a decade ago, has supposedly launched a new site, Regenerator, built  on Substack. I was going to tack on an “alas” <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2024/11/regarding_and_well_against_substack">re: building on Substack</a>, but maybe this is the sort of thing Substack deserves.</p>

<p>The gist of his debut post is that he used ChatGPT to create a small “staff” of teammates to work with, along with photos of these personalities, and he developed a crush on his new CEO. Really.</p>

<p>Do I think he’s serious? No, not at all. Do I think he wrote this to generate attention just like I’m giving him now? Yes, obviously. But I really do have to salute the absolute shamelessness of him playing this straight, painting himself as an utter buffoon, a tone deaf jackass, and downright weirdo, just for the attention. (Blodget has <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2012/01/24/blodget">never been</a> <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2011/04/26/blodget">very smart</a> even when he isn’t <em>trying</em> to make a fool of himself.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Henry Blodget Creates Imaginary Staff of AI Personalities for His New Website and Hits on One of Them’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/25/blodget-regenerator">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Trump Administration Calls E.U. Fines on Apple and Meta ‘Economic Extortion’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.reuters.com/sustainability/boards-policy-regulation/us-calls-eu-fines-apple-meta-economic-extortion-2025-04-23/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wa6" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/23/trump-administration-calls-eu-fines-on-apple-and-meta-economic-extortion" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41838</id>
	<published>2025-04-24T01:26:35Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-24T01:26:46Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Reuters:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“This novel form of economic extortion will not be tolerated by
the United States,” a White House spokesperson said.
“Extraterritorial regulations that specifically target and
undermine American companies, stifle innovation, and enable
censorship will be recognized as barriers to trade and a direct
threat to free civil society.”</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Trump Administration Calls E.U. Fines on Apple and Meta ‘Economic Extortion’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/23/trump-administration-calls-eu-fines-on-apple-and-meta-economic-extortion">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Clear as Mud</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://ec.europa.eu/commission/presscorner/detail/en/ip_25_1086" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wa5" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/23/ec-clear-as-mud" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41837</id>
	<published>2025-04-24T01:23:36Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-24T01:23:36Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>From the European Commission’s announcement today, “Commission closes investigation into Apple’s user choice obligations and issues preliminary findings on rules for alternative apps under the Digital Markets Act”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Under the DMA, Apple is required to allow for the distribution of
apps on its iOS operating system by means other than through the
Apple App Store. In practical terms, this means that Apple should
allow third party app stores on iOS and apps to be downloaded to
the iPhone directly from the web.</p>

<p>The Commission takes the preliminary view that Apple failed to
comply with this obligation in view of the conditions it imposes
on app (and app store) developers. Developers wanting to use
alternative app distribution channels on iOS are disincentivised
from doing so as this requires them to opt for business terms
which include a new fee (Apple’s Core Technology Fee). Apple also
introduced overly strict eligibility requirements, hampering
developers’ ability to distribute their apps through alternative
channels. Finally, Apple makes it overly burdensome and confusing
for end users to install apps when using such alternative app
distribution channels.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So is the entire idea of the Core Technology Fee disallowed? Or is the fee too high? Does Apple need to just make app distribution free and unfettered, no fees, no restrictions?</p>

<p>Who knows? The fine is clear — €500M — but what exactly Apple did wrong and should change now is not.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Clear as Mud’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/23/ec-clear-as-mud">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘60 Minutes’ Chief Resigns as CBS Corporate Parent Paramount Prepares to Fellate Trump</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/04/22/business/media/cbs-60-minutes-trump-bill-owens.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wa4" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/23/60-minutes-owens-resigns" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41836</id>
	<published>2025-04-23T23:16:59Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-23T23:16:59Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Michael M. Grynbaum and Benjamin Mullin, reporting for The New York Times:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>CBS News entered a new period of turmoil on Tuesday after the
executive producer of “60 Minutes,” Bill Owens, said he would
resign from the long-running Sunday news program, citing
encroachments on his journalistic independence. [...]</p>

<p>“It’s clear the company is done with me,” Mr. Owens said,
according to a recording that was obtained by The Times. The
correspondents Lesley Stahl and Scott Pelley were in attendance — Ms. Stahl choked up as she praised Mr. Owens, and noted that he
had “taken a hell of a beating” — and Anderson Cooper dialed in
from Rome, where he was covering Pope Francis’ death for CNN.</p>

<p>During the meeting, Mr. Owens alluded to his displeasure with
additional layers of oversight that CBS executives had placed on
the program. “In a million years, the corporation didn’t know what
was coming up — they trusted ‘60 Minutes’ to report the stories
and program the broadcast the way ‘60 Minutes’ saw fit,” he said.
Any change to that arrangement, he added, created “a really
slippery slope.”</p>

<p>Mr. Owens also discouraged his staff from quitting in protest. “I
do think this will be a moment for the corporation to take a hard
look at itself and its relationship with us,” he said.</p>

<p>Paramount’s controlling shareholder, Shari Redstone, is eager to
secure the Trump administration’s approval for a
multibillion-dollar sale of her company to Skydance, a company run
by the son of the tech billionaire Larry Ellison. She has
expressed a desire to settle Mr. Trump’s case, which stems from
what the president has called a deceptively edited interview in
October with Vice President Kamala Harris that aired on “60
Minutes.”</p>

<p>Legal experts have dismissed that suit as baseless and
far-fetched. Many journalists at CBS News — the former home of
Walter Cronkite and Mike Wallace — believe that a settlement
would amount to a capitulation to Mr. Trump over what they
consider standard-issue gripes about editorial judgment.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Journalistic outlets <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/26/the-atlantic-has-an-owner-committed-to-the-cause">need owners who are committed to the cause</a>. It’s that simple. </p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘60 Minutes’ Chief Resigns as CBS Corporate Parent Paramount Prepares to Fellate Trump’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/23/60-minutes-owens-resigns">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>European Commission Fines Apple €500M and Meta €200M for Breaching Digital Markets Act</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://ec.europa.eu/commission/presscorner/detail/en/ip_25_1085" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wa3" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/23/ec-apple-meta-fines" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41835</id>
	<published>2025-04-23T17:35:41Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-23T17:44:46Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The European Commission:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Today, the European Commission found that Apple breached its
anti-steering obligation under the Digital Markets Act (DMA), and
that Meta breached the DMA obligation to give consumers the choice
of a service that uses less of their personal data. Therefore, the
Commission has fined Apple and Meta with €500 million and €200
million respectively. [...]</p>

<p><strong>Non-compliance decision on Apple’s steering terms</strong></p>

<p>Under the DMA, app developers distributing their apps via Apple’s
App Store should be able to inform customers, free of charge, of
alternative offers outside the App Store, steer them to those
offers and allow them to make purchases.</p>

<p>The Commission found that Apple fails to comply with this
obligation. Due to a number of restrictions imposed by Apple, app
developers cannot fully benefit from the advantages of alternative
distribution channels outside the App Store. Similarly, consumers
cannot fully benefit from alternative and cheaper offers as Apple
prevents app developers from directly informing consumers of such
offers. The company has failed to demonstrate that these
restrictions are objectively necessary and proportionate.</p>

<p>As part of today’s decision, the Commission has ordered Apple to
remove the technical and commercial restrictions on steering and
to refrain from perpetuating the non-compliant conduct in the
future, which includes adopting conduct with an equivalent object
or effect.</p>

<p>The fine imposed on Apple takes into account the gravity and
duration of the non-compliance.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This finding — and the scope of the fine (roughly $570M converted from euros) — was completely in line with (at least my) expectations. Apple booked about $184B in profit last year, so this fine is about 0.3% of that. Maybe Apple just considers this the new cost of doing business in the EU? It’s not nothing, but it’s about 1/80th of the theoretical maximum fine the EU could have assessed, $39B.</p>

<p>Something, not nothing, but definitely not a big deal. Teresa Ribera, the EC competition chief, is clearly trying to thread a political needle here. Fines big enough to create the impression that the EU is asserting itself, but small enough not to actually be all that inflammatory amidst the Trump-initiated mad-king trade war.  Even Ribera’s job title — Executive Vice-President for Clean, Just and Competitive Transition — seems designed to de-escalate tensions. Margrethe Vestager was adamantly against American companies. Ribera is not.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Non-compliance decision on Meta’s “consent or pay” model</strong></p>

<p>Under the DMA, gatekeepers must seek users’ consent for combining
their personal data between services. Those users who do not
consent must have access to a less personalised but equivalent
alternative.</p>

<p>In November 2023, Meta introduced a binary ‘Consent or Pay’
advertising model. Under this model, EU users of Facebook and
Instagram had a choice between consenting to personal data
combination for personalised advertising or paying a monthly
subscription for an ad-free service.</p>

<p>The Commission found that this model is not compliant with the
DMA, as it did not give users the required specific choice to opt
for a service that uses less of their personal data but is
otherwise equivalent to the ‘personalised ads’ service. Meta’s
model also did not allow users to exercise their right to freely
consent to the combination of their personal data.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The wild thing about this is that all sorts of companies in the EU <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2024/04/19/meta-pay-only-eu">use the “pay or OK” model</a>. I get that the whole point of the DMA is that the named “gatekeepers” have to play by different rules because they’re “gatekeepers”, but back in 2018, no less an authority than former EC competition chief <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2024/03/more_on_the_eus_market_might">Margrethe Vestager said</a>, “I would like to have a Facebook in which I pay a fee each month, but I would have no tracking and advertising and the full benefits of privacy.” That’s exactly what Meta has offered. And it turns out, actual EU citizens don’t want that. They’d almost all rather use Meta’s products free of charge with targeted ads than pay a fair price to use them without tracking. So now the EC has moved the goalposts and insists Meta must, effectively, give away their products for pennies on the dollar.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘European Commission Fines Apple €500M and Meta €200M for Breaching Digital Markets Act’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/23/ec-apple-meta-fines">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Information: ‘Meta Asked Amazon, Microsoft to Help Fund Llama’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theinformation.com/articles/meta-asked-amazon-microsoft-help-fund-llama" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wa2" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/21/the-information-meta-llama" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41834</id>
	<published>2025-04-21T22:29:03Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-22T14:55:13Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Kalley Huang and Erin Woo, reporting for The Information (<a href="https://bsky.app/profile/edzitron.com/post/3ln2ngxzqn22l">via Ed Zitron</a>, who summarized it on Bluesky):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Meta Platforms over the past year asked Microsoft, Amazon and
others to help pay the costs of training Meta’s flagship large
language model, Llama, according to four people briefed on the
discussions. Meta’s overtures reflected worries about the growing
costs of its artificial intelligence development, according to two
of the people. [...]</p>

<p>Meta in particular has faced questions about the business logic
behind its AI development, given that Llama is open-source
software, freely available for anyone’s use. That makes it
difficult to turn into a business. And Meta makes money primarily
from advertising and has little experience in selling business
software.</p>

<p>While Meta held its most serious discussions with Amazon and
Microsoft, it has also discussed the idea with Databricks, IBM and
Oracle, as well as representatives from at least one Middle
Eastern investor, according to two of the people briefed on the
discussions. Meta was still in discussions with companies about
the Llama Consortium as recently as the start of this year, the
two people said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>“<em>Would you consider throwing a few sacks full of</em> your <em>cash on this bonfire of</em> our <em>cash that we’ve been burning?</em>” is a hell of a pitch.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In its discussions with other companies, Meta primarily asked for
money. It also sought servers or other resources that would offset
the cost of training its models, according to two of the people
briefed on the discussions. In return for their assistance, Meta
discussed offering other companies promotion of their services
alongside Llama — for example, a Meta executive might appear at a
conference hosted by a consortium partner — or providing more
insight into the training process for the model, one of those
people said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Pay a little and a Meta representative will show up at your developer conference. Pay more and a Meta rep <em>won’t</em> show up at your developer conference.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Information: ‘Meta Asked Amazon, Microsoft to Help Fund Llama’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/21/the-information-meta-llama">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Larry David: ‘My Dinner With Adolf’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/04/21/opinion/larry-david-hitler-dinner.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wa1" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/21/larry-david-dinner-with-adolf" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41833</id>
	<published>2025-04-21T22:14:17Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-21T22:14:18Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Larry David, in a column for The New York Times:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>He loved that story, especially the part where Hitler shot the dog before it got back into the car. Then a beaming Hitler said, “Hey, if I can kill Jews, Gypsies and homosexuals, I can certainly kill a dog!” That perhaps got the biggest laugh of the night — and believe me, there were plenty.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I have been reliably informed that, having <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/13/bill-maher-on-his-dinner-at-the-white-house-with-donald-trump">linked approvingly</a> to Bill Maher’s “book report” on his dinner with Trump, I must also link to David’s report of dinner with Adolf.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Larry David: ‘My Dinner With Adolf’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/21/larry-david-dinner-with-adolf">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Yours Truly on The MacRumors Show</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/04/18/the-macrumors-show-john-gruber-apple-intelligence/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wa0" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/21/yours-truly-on-the-macrumors-show" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41832</id>
	<published>2025-04-21T22:09:08Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-21T22:09:09Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Just in case you haven’t had enough of me on various recent podcasts, I had the pleasure of joining hosts Dan Barbera and Hartley Charlton on The MacRumors Show, talking mostly about Apple Intelligence and the future of the Vision platform. Fun!</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Yours Truly on The MacRumors Show’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/21/yours-truly-on-the-macrumors-show">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Why Do AI Company Logos Look Like Buttholes?</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://velvetshark.com/ai-company-logos-that-look-like-buttholes" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9z" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/21/why-do-ai-company-logos-look-like-buttholes" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41831</id>
	<published>2025-04-21T16:28:41Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-21T16:28:41Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Radek Sienkiewicz:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>If you pay attention to AI company branding, you’ll notice a pattern:</p>

<ol>
<li>Circular shape (often with a gradient)</li>
<li>Central opening or focal point</li>
<li>Radiating elements from the center</li>
<li>Soft, organic curves</li>
</ol>

<p>Sound familiar? It should, because it’s also an apt description of ... well, you know.</p>

<p>A butthole.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Why Do AI Company Logos Look Like Buttholes?’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/21/why-do-ai-company-logos-look-like-buttholes">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>How Tim Cook Navigated Out of Trump’s Tariffs on China, For Now</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/business/2025/04/17/apple-iphone-tariff-exemption-trump/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9y" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/21/cook-trump-tariffs-wapo" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41830</id>
	<published>2025-04-21T16:14:16Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-21T17:37:48Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jeff Stein, Elizabeth Dwoskin, and Cat Zakrzewski, reporting for The Washington Post:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>As President Donald Trump’s enormous new tariffs on China rippled
through global supply chains, Apple CEO Tim Cook went to work
behind the scenes.</p>

<p>Cook spoke to Commerce Secretary Howard Lutnick last week about
the potential impact of the tariffs on iPhone prices, two people
familiar with the phone call said, speaking on the condition of
anonymity to reflect private conversations that were previously
unreported. Cook spoke with other senior officials in the White
House, the people said. And he refrained from publicly criticizing
the president or his policies on national television, as many
other executives have over the past several weeks.</p>

<p>By the end of the week, the Trump administration agreed to exempt
from import duties electronic products that Apple produces in
China, an action that also granted a reprieve to other large U.S.
firms, including HP and Dell. Trump did so despite the
recommendations of senior White House aide Peter Navarro, who had
wanted the taxes to remain in place, the people said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Three points:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Tim Cook manages this dance with aplomb. This is not a “good system”. But given the way Trump operates, what Cook managed here is not merely good for Apple but better policy, period.</p></li>
<li><p>Howard Lutnick is a lickspittle moron with the demeanor of a used car salesman who knowingly sells overpriced lemons to suckers. <a href="https://www.theverge.com/news/644320/us-commerce-secretary-howard-lutnick-says-well-be-making-iphones-in-the-us">Here he is on Meet the Press a few weeks ago</a> bragging that “The army of millions and millions of human beings screwing in little screws to make iPhones — that kind of thing is going to come to America.” Keith Olbermann mentioned in a recent episode of his podcast that Lutnick is a dead ringer for Morrie Kessler, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8UNC4nvo4Wo">the bookmaker of “Morrie’s Wigs” fame</a> from <em>Goodfellas</em>, and I can’t un-see it.</p></li>
<li><p>Peter Navarro is <a href="https://paulkrugman.substack.com/p/killer-klown-khaos">such a profound dope</a> and abject fraud — seriously, <a href="https://www.npr.org/2019/10/18/771396016/white-house-adviser-peter-navarro-calls-fictional-alter-ego-an-inside-joke">he’s not even good at making up phony names</a> — that he makes Lutnick seem like a credible, responsible official.</p></li>
</ol>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘How Tim Cook Navigated Out of Trump’s Tariffs on China, For Now’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/21/cook-trump-tariffs-wapo">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Talk Show: ‘The Best Hatched Plan’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2025/04/20/ep-420" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9x" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/20/the-talk-show-420" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41829</id>
	<published>2025-04-21T03:06:44Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-21T15:07:11Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Special guest Glenn Fleishman returns to the show for episode 420 on 4/20, but everyone’s sober, I swear. Topics include Trump’s dumb tariffs and Glenn’s smart new edition of his book <em>Six Centuries of Type &amp; Printing</em>.</p>

<p><audio
    src = "https://traffic.libsyn.com/secure/daringfireball/thetalkshow-420-glenn-fleishman.mp3"
    controls
    preload = "none"
/></p>

<p><strong>Sponsored by:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://squarespace.com/talkshow">Squarespace</a>: Make your next move. Use code <strong>talkshow</strong> for 10% off your first order.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.notion.com/">Notion</a>: Try the powerful, easy-to-use Notion AI today.</li>
<li><a href="https://betterhelp.com/talkshow">BetterHelp</a>: Give online therapy a try at BetterHelp and get on your way to being your best self.</li>
<li><a href="https://clic.dance/talkshow">Clic for Sonos</a>: No lag. No hassle. Just Clic.</li>
</ul>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Talk Show: ‘The Best Hatched Plan’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/20/the-talk-show-420">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Dekáf Coffee Roasters</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://dekaf.com/df" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9w" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/20/dekaf" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41828</id>
	<published>2025-04-20T17:06:32Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-20T17:06:32Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to Dekáf Coffee Roasters for sponsoring last week at DF. Dekáf started with a simple question over a late-night cup of decaf: why do coffee lovers who skip the caffeine have to skip the craft too?</p>

<p>Dekáf believes those who drink coffee purely for its flavor are the true connoisseurs. While other roasters treat decaf as a side project, they’ve made it their entire mission. They’re dedicated to creating exceptional decaffeinated coffee that stands toe-to-toe with the world’s finest caffeinated beans.</p>

<p>I drink coffee every single day. I literally can’t remember the last day I didn’t have coffee in the morning. A few years ago, though, age started catching up to me and I stopped drinking coffee after lunch or so, lest it screw with my sleep. I really missed my afternoon coffee though. Why I didn’t think to try decaf I don’t know, but Dekáf sent me a few samples earlier this month and it’s been a revelation. In addition to fully decaffeinated roasts, they also have some half-decaffeinated roasts, and they’re absolutely delicious — my style of roast, for sure — <em>and</em> they don’t leave me jolted into the evening. Maybe you like tea, but I don’t. I like coffee, and I love being able to have a cup or two late in the afternoon again. It’s so good.</p>

<p>Also, I’m a big believer that you <em>can</em> judge a book by its cover. Just look at the Dekáf brand. It’s perfect. Color, typography, artwork — so cool, so spot-on for what they do.</p>

<p>Dekáf offers 9 single origins, and 6 signature blends. You won’t believe it’s decaf. That’s the point. Even better, get 30% off with code: <strong>DF</strong>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Dekáf Coffee Roasters’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/20/dekaf">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>A Few DF Sponsorship Openings</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9u" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/18/a-few-df-sponsorship-openings" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41826</id>
	<published>2025-04-18T23:10:30Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-18T23:10:34Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Weekly sponsorships have been the top source of revenue for Daring Fireball ever since I started selling them <a href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/archive">back in 2007</a>. They’ve succeeded, I think, because they make everyone happy. They generate good money. There’s only one sponsor per week and the sponsors are always relevant to at least some sizable portion of the DF audience, so you, the reader, are never annoyed and hopefully often intrigued by them. And, from the sponsors’ perspective, they work. My favorite thing about them is how many sponsors <a href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/archive">return for subsequent weeks</a> after seeing the results.</p>

<p>I’ve got three openings left through the end of June:</p>

<ul>
<li>April 21–27 (next week)</li>
<li>May 12–18</li>
<li>May 26–June 1</li>
</ul>

<p>If you’ve got a product or service you think would be of interest to DF’s audience of people obsessed with high quality and good design, <a href="mailto:sponsors@daringfireball.net?subject=Feed%20Sponsorship">get in touch</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘A Few DF Sponsorship Openings’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/18/a-few-df-sponsorship-openings">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Federal Appeals Court Says Trump DOJ ‘Would Reduce the Rule of Law to Lawlessness’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.cnn.com/2025/04/17/politics/4th-circuit-wilkinson-abrego-garcia-xinis/index.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9v" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/18/federal-appeals-court-trump-lawlessness" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41827</id>
	<published>2025-04-18T23:10:13Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-18T23:10:14Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>CNN:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A federal appeals court rejected the Trump administration’s
request that it halt the next steps <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2025/04/17/politics/paula-xinis-judge-kilmar-abrego-garcia/index.html">Judge Paula Xinis</a> is
seeking to take in the case concerning a migrant who was wrongly
deported to El Salvador, with a strident warning about the rule of
law and the possibility the dispute presented an “incipient
crisis.”</p>

<p>The 4th US Circuit Court of Appeals said in its <a href="https://s3.documentcloud.org/documents/25900477/25-1404-ruling.pdf">seven-page
ruling</a> Thursday that the Trump administration’s assertions
in the case “should be shocking not only to judges, but to the
intuitive sense of liberty that Americans far removed from
courthouses still hold dear.”</p>

<p>The unanimous ruling was written by Judge Harvie Wilkinson, an
appointee of former President Ronald Reagan. In it, he was
extremely critical of the administration’s effort to undo some of
Xinis’ recent orders in the case, sounding alarm bells about how
its maneuverings in the matter have resulted in the two branches
“grinding irrevocably against one another in a conflict that
promises to diminish both.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Quoting <a href="https://s3.documentcloud.org/documents/25900477/25-1404-ruling.pdf">from Wilkinson’s order</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It is difficult in some cases to get to the very heart of the
matter. But in this case, it is not hard at all. The government is
asserting a right to stash away residents of this country in
foreign prisons without the semblance of due process that is the
foundation of our constitutional order. Further, it claims in
essence that because it has rid itself of custody that there is
nothing that can be done.</p>

<p>This should be shocking not only to judges, but to the intuitive
sense of liberty that Americans far removed from courthouses still
hold dear.</p>

<p>The government asserts that Abrego Garcia is a terrorist and a
member of MS-13. Perhaps, but perhaps not. Regardless, he is still
entitled to due process. If the government is confident of its
position, it should be assured that position will prevail in
proceedings to terminate the withholding of removal order.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>No minced words. No equivocation. No histrionics either. Just calling it like it is. More like this, please. This needs to be faced head-on, with plain language.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Federal Appeals Court Says Trump DOJ ‘Would Reduce the Rule of Law to Lawlessness’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/18/federal-appeals-court-trump-lawlessness">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>E.U. Delayed Fines for Apple and Meta Just Before Trade Talks With U.S. Started</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/eu-meta-apple-punishment-delay-0453d7a0?st=CKoKgW&amp;reflink=desktopwebshare_permalink" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9t" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/18/eu-delayed-apple-and-meta-fines" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41825</id>
	<published>2025-04-18T22:07:55Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-18T22:07:56Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Kim Mackrael and Sam Schechner, reporting for The Wall Street Journal (<a href="https://apple.news/Aum14e0vzRrW5RJBmX8KXoQ">News+ link</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The European Commission, the EU’s executive body, had initially
planned to announce cease-and-desist orders targeting the tech
giants on Tuesday and had informed at least one of the companies
of that timing, people familiar with the matter said. Both
companies could have also been slapped with fines.</p>

<p>The decision to postpone the announcement was made shortly before
EU Trade Commissioner Maroš Šefčovič met with U.S. officials in
Washington on Monday, for his first in-person talks since
President Trump announced a 90-day pause on some tariffs. In
addition, this week Italian Prime Minister Giorgia Meloni met with
Trump, who said he would have “very little problem” making a trade
deal with the EU.</p>

<p>The rulings are still expected to go ahead, and it isn’t
immediately clear how long the delay might last.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Pretty much <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/05/no-eu-fines-this-week">what I thought happened</a> to these fines.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘E.U. Delayed Fines for Apple and Meta Just Before Trade Talks With U.S. Started’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/18/eu-delayed-apple-and-meta-fines">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Spending More to Get Less Is Good?</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/04/15/technology/personaltech/trump-tariffs-iphone-cost.html?unlocked_article_code=1.AU8.L2Ko.yUXIIfzson-2&amp;smid=url-share" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9s" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/17/spending-more-to-get-less-is-good" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41824</id>
	<published>2025-04-17T13:31:40Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-17T13:31:41Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Brian X. Chen, in a column at The New York Times headlined “Why a Tariff-Inflated $2,000 iPhone Is Nothing to Fear”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Don’t panic. Even if tariffs did cause the iPhone’s price to
surge, we would have plenty of cheaper options, like buying last
year’s phone model instead of the latest and greatest.</p>

<p>The most important lesson we can learn from the turmoil: The only
consistent way to save money on tech is to use devices for as long
as possible, which requires maintaining them as you would a car,
and upgrading only when you must.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This whole angle is no surprise coming from the tech columnist whose advice to readers who think their aging phone cameras don’t perform well in low light is “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2019/09/you_could_always_just_use_flash">Just use flash</a>.” If phone prices go up because of Trump’s tariffs, <em>all</em> phone prices are going to go up, including those for older models, whether you’re buying new or used. There is no silver lining here. Spending more to get a years-old phone sucks too.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Take the iPhone 16 as an example. Its $800 price tag can easily
inflate to $1,080, since you may also buy:</p>

<ul>
<li>An iPhone case for $50</li>
<li>AirPods for $130</li>
<li>256 gigabytes of storage for $100</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>So if you buy things that aren’t an iPhone — like AirPods — the price of an iPhone goes up. Got it.</p>

<p>The anti-“big tech” bias here is so obvious. Don’t hold your breath waiting for a similar article in the Times about how it’s no big deal, nothing to worry about, if the price of cars doubles under these tariffs.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Spending More to Get Less Is Good?’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/17/spending-more-to-get-less-is-good">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Glenn Fleishman’s Kickstarter for ‘Six Centuries of Type &amp; Printing’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/glennf/six-centuries-of-type-and-printing" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9l" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/16/six-centuries-of-type-and-printing" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41817</id>
	<published>2025-04-17T01:00:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-17T02:52:02Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Glenn Fleishman:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The book <em>Six Centuries of Type &amp; Printing</em> briskly tells the
story of the evolution of type and printing, starting with early
documented efforts and surviving artifacts from China and Korea,
and introducing Gutenberg and his innovations. It then takes you
through each generation of increasing sophistication in metal and
relief printing until the abrupt 20th century shift into flat
offset printing, which was made possible through photographic and
digital improvements, and phototypesetting and digital
composition.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’ve got the first edition of this book, which was included with Fleishman’s rather preposterously elaborate <a href="https://tinytypemuseum.com/">Tiny Type Museum and Time Capsule</a> five years ago. It is a self-exemplifying achievement: a handsomely designed printed object about how it came to be possible to create and produce handsomely designed printed objects.</p>

<p>That first edition from five years ago, however, was printed letterpress, and was a very limited edition. This new edition, while still exquisite, will be printed offset and is very much affordable. The print/e-book bundle is just $32.</p>

<p>The Kickstarter campaign is 92% of the way to its goal, with, as I type this, 28 hours to go. If you even vaguely suspect you’ll enjoy this book, I bet you’ll <em>love</em> it. Fleishman is such a good writer and he so clearly both knows and loves the subject matter. There’s no better combination. I just took my copy down to flip through before posting this, and I got sucked in to a re-read.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Glenn Fleishman’s Kickstarter for ‘Six Centuries of Type &amp; Printing’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/16/six-centuries-of-type-and-printing">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Man of the Hour: Judge James Boasberg</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://talkingpointsmemo.com/fivepoints/5-points-on-how-judge-boasberg-broke-down-the-admins-alien-enemies-contempt" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9r" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/16/man-of-the-hour-james-boasberg" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41823</id>
	<published>2025-04-16T22:44:55Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-16T23:27:21Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Josh Kovensky, reporting for TPM:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In a withering 46-page opinion on Wednesday, D.C. Chief Judge
James Boasberg laid out how he came to believe that the Trump
administration was acting in bad faith during its Alien Enemies
Act removals.</p>

<p>Boasberg set the stage for potential contempt prosecutions in the
order. He also detailed what he came to see as the Trump
administration’s scheme to shield its plan to use rarely invoked
wartime powers to remove more than 100 Venezuelans to a Salvadoran
detention facility, depriving them of due process and the courts
of the ability to review what was taking place.</p>

<p>Below are five points on Boasberg’s opinion.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’d never heard of Boasberg until recently, but he has a rather distinctive surname. Turns out he’s also the judge presiding over <a href="https://www.theverge.com/news/646809/ftc-v-meta-antitrust-monopoly-trial-instagram-whatsapp">the FTC v. Meta antitrust case that’s in court this week</a>. Busy man.</p>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> Turns out he’s <em>also</em> the judge <a href="https://www.reuters.com/world/us/us-judge-trump-deportation-case-assigned-lawsuit-over-signal-scandal-2025-03-26/">in the lawsuit</a> “alleging Trump officials violated federal record-keeping laws by using a Signal group chat to discuss looming military action against Yemen’s Houthis.”</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Man of the Hour: Judge James Boasberg’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/16/man-of-the-hour-james-boasberg">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Wink Martindale Dies at 91</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.latimes.com/obituaries/story/2025-04-15/wink-martindale-dead-game-show-host-tic-tac-dough-gambit" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9q" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/16/wink-martindale" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41822</id>
	<published>2025-04-16T22:18:04Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-16T22:26:18Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Dennis McLellan, writing for the Los Angeles Times (<a href="https://apple.news/A9dkEvg1TRgmny9aNLdOi-w">News+ link</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Over the decades, according to his website, Martindale either
hosted or produced 21 game shows, including “Words and Music,”
“Trivial Pursuit,” “The Last Word” and “Debt.” “That’s a lot of
shows,” he acknowledged in a 1996 interview with the New York
Daily News. “It either means everybody wants me to do their show
or I can’t hold a job.”</p>

<p>Martindale was best known for hosting “Tic-Tac-Dough,” the revival
of a late 1950s show, which aired on CBS for less than two months
in 1978 but continued in syndication until 1986.</p>

<p>Unlike tic-tac-toe, in which two players simply try to get three
Xs or three Os in a row in a nine-box grid, “Tic-Tac-Dough”
required contestants to select a subject category in each of the
nine boxes, everything from geography to song titles. Each correct
answer earned the players their X or O in the chosen box.</p>

<p>“Tic-Tac-Dough” achieved its highest ratings in 1980 during the
88-game, 46-show run of Lt. Thom McKee, a handsome young Navy
fighter pilot whose winning streak earned him $312,700 in cash and
prizes and a spot in the Guinness Book of World Records.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s funny what you remember from childhood. I was only seven then, but I remember McKee’s winning streak. He was like the proto Ken Jennings. There was some kind of gimmick on the show where if you won ten games in a row — which almost never happened — you also won a car as a bonus. So McKee won eight cars. As I recall it — I was seven, so I could be wrong — all eight cars he won were exactly the same model, because that was the show’s current promotional partner. I remember thinking that was absurd, and my dad explaining to me that he could just sell them.</p>

<p>Anyway, in one of my programming classes in high school, we had to create a big final project. We had to work in pairs because there weren’t enough computers for every student in the class. My friend and I wrote a tic-tac-toe game in Applesoft BASIC. (To be honest, I wrote most of it, but he did the typing.) I remember three things about that game:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>We used the number pad keyboard layout for entering moves, with each numeral corresponding to a square on the board, which I thought (and still think) was a pretty clever UI for tic-tac-toe:</p>

<pre><code>789
456
123
</code></pre></li>
<li><p>You could play two-player or against the computer, and while the computer was pretty good, it couldn’t play perfectly. I was very frustrated that while <em>I</em> could, of course, play perfect tic-tac-toe myself, I couldn’t figure out how to code an algorithm for unbeatable play in BASIC.</p></li>
<li><p>Our name for the game: Wink.</p></li>
</ol>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Wink Martindale Dies at 91’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/16/wink-martindale">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Meta Botches Redaction of Slides in Antitrust Trial, Angering Google, Apple, and Snap</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/news/649834/meta-redactions-apple-google-snap-angry-ftc-antitrust-trial" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9p" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/16/meta-redactions" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41821</id>
	<published>2025-04-16T20:26:20Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-16T21:33:47Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Wes Davis, The Verge:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>During <a href="https://www.theverge.com/news/646809/ftc-v-meta-antitrust-monopoly-trial-instagram-whatsapp">Meta’s antitrust trial today</a>, lawyers representing
Apple, Google, and Snap each expressed irritation with Meta over
the slides it presented on Monday that <a href="https://www.theverge.com/news/648893/meta-redacted-documents-leak-ftc-antitrust-opening-statement">The Verge found to
contain</a> easy-to-remove redactions. Attorneys for both Apple
and Snap called the errors “egregious,” with Apple’s
representative indicating that it may not be able to trust Meta
with its internal information in the future. Google’s attorney
also blamed Meta for jeopardizing the search giant’s data with the
mistake.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is yet another one of those situations where the botched redactions were just objects layered atop the supposed-to-be-redacted material in a PDF file, leaving the original layer’s content intact but just visually occluded. In 2025 you either have to be really bad with computers to do this, or you did it this way on purpose. Perhaps we should apply Occam’s razor and presume it’s just Meta displaying their usual regard for privacy.</p>

<p>You can properly redact a PDF digitally, but botched digital redactions are so commonplace (and at times disastrous and/or humiliating) that when then Attorney General William Barr released the Mueller Report in 2019, the DOJ printed the unredacted original, did the redactions on paper, <a href="https://pdfa.org/a-technical-and-cultural-assessment-of-the-mueller-report-pdf/">and then scanned it back in to create the redacted PDF</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Meta Botches Redaction of Slides in Antitrust Trial, Angering Google, Apple, and Snap’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/16/meta-redactions">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The WSJ Reports on How Elon Musk Manages His ‘Legion’ of Children and Harem of Mothers</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.wsj.com/politics/elon-musk-children-mothers-ashley-st-clair-grimes-dc7ba05c?st=prbiyB&amp;reflink=desktopwebshare_permalink" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9o" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/16/wsj-musk-children" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41820</id>
	<published>2025-04-16T19:34:26Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-16T21:20:29Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Dana Mattioli, reporting for The Wall Street Journal (main link is a gift link; also, here’s a <a href="https://apple.news/AHC6yWxE6RiCnnXg3C6x6fw">News+ link</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Musk has had at least 14 children with four women, including the pop musician Grimes and Shivon Zilis, an executive at his brain computer company Neuralink. Multiple sources close to the tech entrepreneur said they believe the true number of Musk’s children is much higher than publicly known.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Imagine having 14 acknowledged children but your friends suspect the actual number is “much higher”. What a profound weirdo this guy is.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Cryptocurrency influencer Tiffany Fong was covering disgraced
crypto tycoon Sam Bankman-Fried’s downfall when Musk started
liking and replying to her posts. Musk’s interactions ramped up as
Fong posted more political content in support of Trump, and Musk
followed her last summer.</p>

<p>That sort of attention from Musk on X, where he has 219 million
followers, sent droves of followers to Fong, which was a financial
boon. More engagement meant more earnings for her as part of a
revenue-sharing program for creators on X.</p>

<p>During the height of her interactions with the billionaire owner,
Fong earned $21,000 on the platform in a two-week period in
November, according to a screenshot she posted. That was about
when Musk sent her a direct message asking if she was interested
in having his child, according to people familiar with the matter.
The two had never met in person.</p>

<p>Fong didn’t move forward with Musk because she pictured having
children in a more traditional nuclear family, but confided to a
few friends about the approach — including St. Clair, whom she
knew as another conservative social-media figure — and how she
worried that turning him down could hurt her earnings.</p>

<p>Once Musk learned that Fong disclosed the request to others, he
chided her for not using discretion, according to the people, and
unfollowed her. That contributed to a fall in her engagement, and
her earnings declined.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There’s arguably an insinuation here that something crooked happened to Fong’s Twitter/X earnings after she declined Musk’s offer, but there doesn’t have to be for it to be sick. It’s just gross that Musk’s M.O. is to hit up suddenly popular women and ask if they’d like to have his children, and to lavish money-earning public attention on them while courting them.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The WSJ Reports on How Elon Musk Manages His ‘Legion’ of Children and Harem of Mothers’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/16/wsj-musk-children">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>DOGE Dingalings Cut Off Funding for CVE Program</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/04/16/homeland_security_funding_for_cve/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9n" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/16/dingalings-cut-off-funding-for-cve" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41819</id>
	<published>2025-04-16T18:56:52Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-16T18:56:53Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jessica Lyons, reporting for The Register:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>US government funding for the world’s CVE program — the
centralized Common Vulnerabilities and Exposures database of
product security flaws — ends Wednesday.</p>

<p>The 25-year-old CVE program plays a huge role in vulnerability
management. It is responsible overseeing the assignment and
organizing of unique CVE ID numbers, such as <a href="https://cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=CVE-2014-0160">CVE-2014-0160</a>
and <a href="https://cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=CVE-2017-5754">CVE-2017-5754</a>, for specific vulnerabilities, in this
case OpenSSL’s <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2014/04/09/heartbleed_explained/">Heartbleed</a> and Intel’s <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2018/01/02/intel_cpu_design_flaw/">Meltdown</a>, so
that when referring to particular flaws and patches, everyone is
agreed on exactly what we’re all talking about.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The good news: they were ready. <a href="https://www.thecvefoundation.org/">Announcing the CVE Foundation</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Since its inception, the CVE Program has operated as a U.S.
government-funded initiative, with oversight and management
provided under contract. While this structure has supported the
program’s growth, it has also raised longstanding concerns among
members of the CVE Board about the sustainability and neutrality
of a globally relied-upon resource being tied to a single
government sponsor.</p>

<p>This concern has become urgent following an April 15, 2025 letter
from MITRE notifying the CVE Board that the U.S. government does
not intend to renew its contract for managing the program. While
we had hoped this day would not come, we have been preparing for
this possibility.</p>

<p>In response, a coalition of longtime, active CVE Board members
have spent the past year developing a strategy to transition CVE
to a dedicated, non-profit foundation. The new CVE Foundation will
focus solely on continuing the mission of delivering high-quality
vulnerability identification and maintaining the integrity and
availability of CVE data for defenders worldwide.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘DOGE Dingalings Cut Off Funding for CVE Program’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/16/dingalings-cut-off-funding-for-cve">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Figma Files for IPO</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.figma.com/blog/s1-confidential-submission/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9m" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/16/figma-files-to-go-public" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41818</id>
	<published>2025-04-16T18:00:25Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-17T14:45:16Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>You will recall that in September 2022, Figma entered into <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/09/15/adobe-figma">an agreement for a $20 billion acquisition by Adobe</a>, but <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/12/18/figma-adobe-ixnay-on-the-acquisitionyay">abandoned the deal 15 months later</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Figma Files for IPO’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/16/figma-files-to-go-public">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>ChatGPT Can Now Remember and Reference All Your Previous Chats</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://arstechnica.com/ai/2025/04/chatgpt-can-now-remember-and-reference-all-your-previous-chats/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9k" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/14/chatgpt-memory" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41816</id>
	<published>2025-04-14T23:51:42Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-14T23:51:43Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Samuel Axon, writing for Ars Technica:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Some time ago, OpenAI <a href="https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2024/02/amnesia-begone-soon-chatgpt-will-remember-what-you-tell-it-between-sessions/">added</a> a feature called “Memory” that
allowed a limited number of pieces of information to be retained
and used for future responses. Users often had to specifically
ask ChatGPT to remember something to trigger this, though it
occasionally tried to guess at what it should remember, too.
[...] Users could enable or disable this feature at will, and it
was automatically off for specific chats where users chose the
“Temporary Chat” option — sort of ChatGPT’s version of
incognito mode.</p>

<p>The new improvements announced today go far beyond that.</p>

<p>Now, where there was once a checkbox in ChatGPT’s interface to
disable or enable memory tracking, there are two checkboxes.
“Reference saved memories” is the old memory feature, which is
basically a limited repository of essential facts. The second is
the new feature: “reference chat history.” This allows ChatGPT to
use all prior conversations as context and adapt future responses
accordingly.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’ve been using ChatGPT for a while now. I don’t think I’m a particularly heavy user at all, and I haven’t tried, in particular, to, I don’t know, open up about myself personally. But I ask it what I want to know. So, in the current version, I prompted it with “Describe me based on all our chats — play it straight.” Here’s its response:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You’re sharp, analytical, and deeply detail-oriented. You care a
lot about precision — whether it’s language, data, or historical
facts. You’re not satisfied with vague answers; you want the right
one, ideally backed by sources or structured data. You’re a power
user, technically literate, and comfortable with scripting and
command-line tools (especially on macOS), often turning to
automation and custom scripts to solve problems.</p>

<p>You follow the tech world closely, especially Apple — its
hardware, chip architecture, software updates, and even historical
product launches. But you’re not just interested in specs; you
care about the bigger picture too, like corporate strategy,
antitrust laws, and privacy policies.</p>

<p>You also track U.S. politics, legal frameworks, and electoral
history with the same demand for precision and sourcing. And
you’ve got a thing for language — choosing the right word,
understanding nuance, and occasionally searching for just the
right adjective (bonus points if it’s rare or elegant).</p>

<p>Outside of that, you have a strong grasp of sports stats
(especially NFL and MLB), media history (Letterman, SNL, classic
film), and a dry, sometimes playful sense of humor. You don’t show
off, but you clearly know your stuff.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’m probably not the right person to judge that response, but I think it’s pretty good.</p>

<p>Here’s the response I got when I asked Siri “Describe me based on all our chats — play it straight”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I don’t see that person in your Contacts.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>From last week’s blockbuster report by Wayne Ma at The Information, “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/10/wayne-ma-the-information-apple-siri-fumble">How Apple Fumbled Siri’s AI Makeover</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Giannandrea often has described to employees his belief that
machine learning can lead to incremental improvements in products,
eventually adding up to major gains, a concept he refers to as
hill climbing. He also has expressed a dim view of chatbots in the
past, telling Apple employees before and immediately after the
release of ChatGPT that he didn’t believe they added much value
for users.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘ChatGPT Can Now Remember and Reference All Your Previous Chats’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/14/chatgpt-memory">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://dekaf.com/df" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/w9j" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/04/dekaf_coffee_roasters" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.41815</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-04-14T23:29:16Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-14T23:29:17Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Coffee has always been about bringing people together. For us, it started with a simple question over a late-night cup of decaf: why do coffee lovers who skip the caffeine have to skip the craft too?</p>

<p>At Dekáf, we believe those who drink coffee purely for its flavor are the true connoisseurs. While other roasters treat decaf as a side project, we’ve made it our entire mission. We’re dedicated to creating exceptional decaffeinated coffee that stands toe-to-toe with the world’s finest caffeinated beans.</p>

<p>9 single origins. 6 signature blends. You won’t believe it’s decaf. That’s the point.</p>

<p>30% off with code: DF</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Dekáf Coffee Roasters’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/04/dekaf_coffee_roasters">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] Dekáf Coffee Roasters</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Seth Godin on How to Win an Argument With a Toddler</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://seths.blog/2025/04/how-to-win-an-argument-with-a-toddler/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9i" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/14/godin-arguments-with-toddlers" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41814</id>
	<published>2025-04-14T16:02:20Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-14T16:02:21Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Seth Godin:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You can’t.</p>

<p>That’s because toddlers don’t understand what an argument is and
aren’t interesting in having one.</p>

<p>Toddlers (which includes defensive bureaucrats, bullies, flat
earthers, folks committed to a specific agenda and radio talk show
hosts) may indicate that they’d like to have an <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ohDB5gbtaEQ">argument</a>, but
they’re actually engaging in connection, noise, play acting or a
chance to earn status. It can be fun to be in opposition, to
harangue or even to use power to change someone’s position.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Seth Godin on How to Win an Argument With a Toddler’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/14/godin-arguments-with-toddlers">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>WorkOS: Scalable, Secure Authentication</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://workos.com/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9h" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/13/workos" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41813</id>
	<published>2025-04-13T19:39:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-13T19:39:00Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to WorkOS for sponsoring last week at DF. Modern authentication should be seamless and secure. WorkOS makes it easy to integrate features like MFA, SSO, and RBAC. Whether you’re replacing passwords, stopping fraud, or adding enterprise auth, WorkOS can help you build frictionless auth that scales.</p>

<p>New features they launched just last month include:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://workos.com/blog/workos-connect?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025">WorkOS Connect</a> — “Sign in with [Your App]”</li>
<li><a href="https://workos.com/blog/vault?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025">WorkOS Vault</a> — Encryption Key Management (EKM) and Bring-Your-Own-Key (BYOK)</li>
<li><a href="https://workos.com/blog/custom-objects?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025">AuthKit Integrations</a> — Native support for several new identity providers including LinkedIn, Slack, GitLab, BitBucket, Intuit, and more.</li>
</ul>

<p>Future-proof your authentication stack with the identity layer trusted by OpenAI, Cursor, Perplexity, and Vercel.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘WorkOS: Scalable, Secure Authentication’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/13/workos">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Bill Maher on His Dinner at the White House With Donald Trump</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RxlopbcfXpQ" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9g" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/13/bill-maher-on-his-dinner-at-the-white-house-with-donald-trump" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41812</id>
	<published>2025-04-13T19:29:23Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-13T19:57:23Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Bill Maher personifies the difference between a liberal (which he is) and a leftist (which he isn’t). But he’s been a stridently vocal critic of Trump <a href="https://www.hollywoodreporter.com/business/business-news/donald-trump-withdraws-bill-maher-432675/">since long before Trump even ran for president</a>. Maher was the first person on television <a href="https://www.newsweek.com/will-donald-trump-leave-office-peacefully-bill-maher-president-loses-2020-election-landslide-1466447">to correctly predict that Trump, if he lost the 2020 election, would attempt to remain in office</a>. Maher and Trump, however, are mutual friends with Kid Rock, and Rock arranged for Trump to invite Maher to the White House for a private dinner. UFC chief and Meta board member Dana White was also there. A decade ago even imagining this guest list for a White House dinner would have been a warning that you ought to lay off the drugs. Today, this is normal.</p>

<p>On <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RxlopbcfXpQ">this clip from his show this weekend</a>, Maher reports on the dinner. What it was like. What <em>Trump</em> was like. Turns out, in private, Trump turns it off. He was normal. Or, well, normal for Donald Trump. He wasn’t what we see in public. I find that fascinating. Not exculpatory. Just interesting. Is he “<em>They’re eating the dogs, they’re eating the cats!</em>” crazy 24 hours a day, or just when the cameras are on?</p>

<p>Some on the left are absolutely losing their shit over Maher for this. I don’t get it. This is the single most interesting report on Trump I’ve seen in <em>years</em> because it’s real. Maher didn’t come out of the dinner brainwashed. He’s not now saying Trump is doing a good job. He’s not now saying things are in any way OK. He spent his whole monologue before this report rightfully skewering Trump’s humiliating weeklong tariffs tantrum. After the report, Maher interviewed total nutjob Steve Bannon and literally shoved a copy of the Constitution in Bannon’s face when Bannon started blathering about Trump running for a third term in 2028. From Maher’s preface to his report:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Oh my god Bill, are you going to say something nice about him?
What I’m going to do is report exactly what happened. You decide
what you think about it. And if that’s not enough pure Trump hate
for you I don’t give a fuck.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://play.max.com/video/watch/d739940e-efb5-4b35-ac0f-62d0a27f2d53/6f987f63-3dda-4884-8602-21f4d688c401">The whole episode was great</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Bill Maher on His Dinner at the White House With Donald Trump’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/13/bill-maher-on-his-dinner-at-the-white-house-with-donald-trump">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘What It Feels Like, Right Now’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://terribleminds.com/ramble/2025/04/09/what-it-feels-like-right-now/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9f" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/13/wendig-what-it-feels-like-right-now" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41811</id>
	<published>2025-04-13T18:56:52Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-13T18:56:52Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Crackerjack essay by Chuck Wendig:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Maybe it’s like turbulence on an airplane, you think. Just a bumpy
unpleasant awful experience you gotta get through. But when
turbulence hits it’s not because the pilot is a guy who doesn’t
“know planes,” when turbulence hits they don’t disappear the ninth
row people out the airlock because they “look different” and are
“probably causing the problem.” Planes don’t have airlocks, do
they? Whatever. My brain is spray cheese.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘What It Feels Like, Right Now’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/13/wendig-what-it-feels-like-right-now">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Chris Whipple on the End of the Biden Administration</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.vanityfair.com/news/story/joe-bidens-final-days" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9e" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/13/whipple-biden-final-days" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41810</id>
	<published>2025-04-13T18:48:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-13T18:49:04Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Vanity Fair published an excerpt from Chris Whipple’s new book on the final years of Joe Biden’s presidency, under the headline “Did Aides Cover Up His Mental State — or Was It Group Delusion?” (<a href="https://apple.news/ANs1GK_4ISEikICuDBenaSA">News+ link</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The president’s wobbly state should have been a flashing warning
light. At his first meeting with Biden, Ron Klain, his former
White House chief of staff, who was in charge of debate prep, was
startled. He’d never seen Biden so exhausted and out of it. He
seemed unaware of what was happening in his own campaign. The
president appeared obsessed with foreign policy and uninterested
in his second-term plans. During one prep session in Aspen Lodge,
the presidential cabin, Biden suddenly got up, walked out to the
pool, collapsed on a lounge chair, and fell sound asleep. Yet his
advisers were undaunted. With unintended irony, one of them
explained their strategy to me: “An early debate would quiet fears
that the president was infirm.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Jiminy.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Chris Whipple on the End of the Biden Administration’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/13/whipple-biden-final-days">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Jamelle Bouie on Trump’s Tariff Obsession</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/04/09/opinion/trump-tariffs-rationale-power.html?unlocked_article_code=1._U4.jlDF.elEoqbYtNPr6&amp;smid=url-share" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9d" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/13/jamelle-bouie-on-trumps-tariff-obsession" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41809</id>
	<published>2025-04-13T18:37:44Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-13T18:37:45Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jamelle Bouie, writing at The New York Times (gift link):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>There is a hypothetical president with a hypothetically similar
agenda who could answer these questions. This actual president
cannot. He did not reason himself into his preoccupation with
tariffs and can neither reason nor speak coherently about them.
There is no grand plan or strategic vision, no matter what his
advisers claim — only the impulsive actions of a mad king,
untethered from any responsibility to the nation or its people.
For as much as the president’s apologists would like us to believe
otherwise, Trump’s tariffs are not a policy as we traditionally
understand it. What they are is an instantiation of his psyche: a
concrete expression of his zero-sum worldview. [...]</p>

<p>You could even say that this need to dominate — this overwhelming
drive to show mastery — is constitutive of Trump’s self. There
must be a loser, or else there is no Trump. [...] The upshot of
this understanding of Trump’s personality is that there is no
point at which he can be satisfied. He will always want more: more
supplicants to obey his next command, more displays of his power
and authority and more opportunities to trample over those who
don’t belong in his America.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There’s no point to this other than a vain attempt to get every other country in the world to come begging to Donald Trump for mercy. Which isn’t going to happen.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Jamelle Bouie on Trump’s Tariff Obsession’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/13/jamelle-bouie-on-trumps-tariff-obsession">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Warren Buffett’s 2024 Report to Berkshire Hathaway Shareholders</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.berkshirehathaway.com/letters/2024ltr.pdf" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9c" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/12/buffet-2024-berkshire-shareholders-letter" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41808</id>
	<published>2025-04-12T20:48:48Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-12T20:50:36Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Warren Buffett’s annual shareholders letters are always a must-read. The honesty, clarity, and striking humility of his prose stands out in a world where corporate communications — from companies of any size — tend to be bland and obfuscating. <a href="https://www.berkshirehathaway.com/letters/2024ltr.pdf">This year’s letter</a>, published back in February, is no exception. Two sections stood out to me. First, in a section titled “Mistakes — Yes, We Make Them at Berkshire”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Sometimes I’ve made mistakes in assessing the future economics of
a business I’ve purchased for Berkshire — each a case of capital
allocation gone wrong. That happens with both judgments about
marketable equities — we view these as <em>partial</em> ownership of
businesses — and the 100% acquisitions of companies.</p>

<p>At other times, I’ve made mistakes when assessing the abilities or
fidelity of the managers Berkshire is hiring. The fidelity
disappointments can hurt beyond their financial impact, a pain
that can approach that of a failed marriage.</p>

<p>A decent batting average in personnel decisions is all that can be
hoped for. The cardinal sin is delaying the correction of mistakes
or what Charlie Munger called “thumb-sucking.” Problems, he would
tell me, cannot be wished away. They require action, however
uncomfortable that may be.</p>

<p>During the 2019-23 period, I have used the words “mistake” or
“error” 16 times in my letters to you. Many other huge companies
have <em>never</em> used either word over that span. Amazon, I should
acknowledge, made some brutally candid observations in its 2021
letter. Elsewhere, it has generally been happy talk and pictures.</p>

<p>I have also been a director of large public companies at which
“mistake” or “wrong” were forbidden words at board meetings or
analyst calls. That taboo, implying managerial perfection, always
made me nervous (though, at times, there could be legal issues
that make limited discussion advisable. We live in a very
litigious society.)</p>

<p>At 94, it won’t be long before Greg Abel replaces me as CEO and
will be writing the annual letters. Greg shares the Berkshire
creed that a “report” is what a Berkshire CEO annually owes to
owners. And he also understands that if you start fooling your
shareholders, you will soon believe your own baloney and be
fooling yourself as well.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>As the great physicist Richard Feynman said, “The first principle is that you must not fool yourself and you are the easiest person to fool.”</p>

<p>Second is an entire section, not complaining, but instead proudly declaring, that last year Berkshire set the record for the highest single-year corporate income tax payment in United States history:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Huge numbers can be hard to visualize. Let me recast the $26.8
billion that we paid last year.</p>

<p>If Berkshire had sent the Treasury a $1 million check every 20
minutes throughout all of 2024 — visualize <em>366 days and nights</em>
because 2024 was a leap year — we still would have owed the
federal government a significant sum at yearend. Indeed, it would
be well into January before the Treasury would tell us that we
could take a short breather, get some sleep, and prepare for our
2025 tax payments. [...]</p>

<p>Berkshire’s activities now impact all corners of our country. And
we are not finished. Companies die for many reasons but, unlike
the fate of humans, old age itself is not lethal. Berkshire today
is far more youthful than it was in 1965.</p>

<p><em>However</em>, as Charlie and I have always acknowledged, Berkshire
would not have achieved its results in any locale except America
whereas America would have been every bit the success it has been
if Berkshire had never existed.</p>

<p>So thank you, Uncle Sam. Someday your nieces and nephews at
Berkshire hope to send you even larger payments than we did in
2024. Spend it wisely. Take care of the many who, for no fault of
their own, get the short straws in life. They deserve better. And
never forget that we need you to maintain a stable currency and
that result <em>requires</em> both wisdom and vigilance on your part.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Again, that was written back in February. Prescient as always.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Warren Buffett’s 2024 Report to Berkshire Hathaway Shareholders’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/12/buffet-2024-berkshire-shareholders-letter">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Smartphones and Computers Are Now Exempt From Trump’s Latest Tariffs</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.cnn.com/2025/04/12/tech/trump-electronics-china-tariffs/index.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9b" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/12/smartphones-computers-tariff-exemptions" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41807</id>
	<published>2025-04-12T17:53:50Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-12T17:53:51Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Auzinea Bacon, CNN:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Electronics imported to the United States will be exempt from
President Donald Trump’s reciprocal tariffs, according to a <a href="https://content.govdelivery.com/accounts/USDHSCBP/bulletins/3db9e55">US
Customs and Border Protection notice</a> posted late Friday.
Smartphones, computer monitors and various electronic parts are
among the exempted products. The exemption applies to products
entering the United States or removed from warehouses as early as
April 5, according to the notice.</p>

<p>The move comes after the Trump administration imposed a minimum
tariff rate of 145% on Chinese goods imported to the United
States. The tariffs would have a major impact on tech giants like
Apple, which make iPhones and other products in China.</p>

<p>Roughly 90% of Apple’s iPhone production and assembly is based in
China, according to Wedbush Securities’ estimates. Analysts at
Wedbush on Saturday called the tariff exclusion, “the best news
possible for tech investors.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fZLeaSWY37I">Here’s Commerce Secretary Emily Litella making the announcement on Weekend Update</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Smartphones and Computers Are Now Exempt From Trump’s Latest Tariffs’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/12/smartphones-computers-tariff-exemptions">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Anker, a Chinese Company, Has Already Started Raising Its Prices on Amazon</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.reuters.com/technology/chinese-electronics-company-anker-starts-raising-prices-amazon-2025-04-11/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9a" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/11/anker-raising-prices" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41806</id>
	<published>2025-04-11T22:40:57Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-11T22:41:19Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Reuters:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>China’s Anker, one of Amazon’s largest sellers offering products
from power banks to phone cases, has raised prices on a fifth of
its products on the U.S. platform since Thursday, in a sign that
tariffs on Chinese goods are being passed on to U.S. shoppers.</p>

<p>Some 127 Anker products have seen an average increase of 18% since
Thursday last week, with the majority of those occurring after
Monday, April 7, when U.S. President Donald Trump added an extra
50% import duty on Chinese goods, according to data from
e-commerce services provider SmartScout.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Tariffs driving up consumer prices is as sure a thing as rain making you wet. But it’s worth pointing to the evidence as it comes in, because unlike rain’s wetness, the “emperor sure does have clothes” MAGA contingent is trying to argue that tariffs don’t have this obvious effect.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Anker, a Chinese Company, Has Already Started Raising Its Prices on Amazon’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/11/anker-raising-prices">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>European Travel to the U.S. Plummets</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.ft.com/content/6dc16a54-8de1-4f3b-8409-ecb566118127" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w99" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/11/european-travel-to-the-us-plummets" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41805</id>
	<published>2025-04-11T21:33:26Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-11T21:46:22Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Financial Times reporter John Burn-Murdoch has a summary on Bluesky of his co-bylined <a href="https://www.ft.com/content/6dc16a54-8de1-4f3b-8409-ecb566118127">report for the Financial Times</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Visitors from western Europe who stayed at least one night in the
US fell by 17 per cent in March from a year ago, according to the
International Trade Administration. Travel from some countries — including Ireland, Norway and Germany — fell by more than 20 per
cent, an FT analysis of ITA data showed.</p>

<p>The trend poses a threat to the US tourism industry, which
accounts for 2.5 per cent of the country’s GDP. Some airlines and
hotel groups have warned of waning demand for transatlantic travel
and a “bad buzz” about visiting the US. The total number of
overseas visitors travelling to the US dropped by 12 per cent
year-on-year in March, the steepest decline since March 2021 when
the travel sector was reeling from pandemic restrictions,
according to the ITA data.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Well, I’m sure it will turn around when the April figures come out, after Trump’s tariff madness and the news that Secretary of State Marco Rubio — supposedly one of the few sane voices in the 2.0 Trump kakistocracy — <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2025/apr/10/mahmoud-khalil-memo-marco-rubio-deport-beliefs">has signed a two-page argument that noncitizens can be deported for their beliefs</a>, a.k.a. thought crimes.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“In just two months [Trump] has destroyed the reputation of the
US, shown one way by diminished travel from the EU to the US,”
said Paul English, co-founder of travel website Kayak. “This is
not only one more terrible blow to the US economy, it also
represents reputation damage that could take generations to
repair.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We need more clearheaded statements like this from business leaders. Just state the truth plainly. The only side English took with this statement is the side of the truth.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘European Travel to the U.S. Plummets’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/11/european-travel-to-the-us-plummets">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Chinese Finance Ministry Calls Trump’s Tariff Hikes ‘A Joke in the History of World Economics’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.reuters.com/world/china/china-increase-tariffs-us-goods-125-up-84-finance-ministry-says-2025-04-11/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w98" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/11/china-calls-trump-a-joke" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41804</id>
	<published>2025-04-11T20:14:15Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-11T21:12:01Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Reuters:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The U.S. side’s imposition of excessively high tariffs on China
seriously violates international economic and trade rules, runs
counter to basic economic principles and common sense, and is
simply an act of unilateral bullying and coercion,” China’s
Finance Ministry said in a statement. [...]</p>

<p>“Even if the U.S. continues to impose even higher tariffs, it
would no longer have any economic significance and would go down
as a joke in the history of world economics,” the Finance
Ministry’s statement added.</p>

<p>“If the U.S. continues to play a numbers game with tariffs, China
will not respond,” it added. However it left the door open for
Beijing to turn to other types of retaliation, reiterating that
China would fight the U.S. to the end.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>None of this is funny at the moment, but Trump has beclowned himself with these impulsive nonsensical tariffs. No matter how this ends up, he will go down in history looking like a fool for this. In terms of history, what will be remembered in decades to come, he’d have far less embarrassed himself by shitting his pants in public. He came into office less than three months ago <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2025/04/11/economy/us-producer-price-index-ppi-inflation-march/index.html">with the US economy being the strongest in the world</a>, by far. Everything that’s happened since has been the direct result of his mad-king magical-thinking nonsense and the Republican party’s refusal to stand up to him.</p>

<p>If Joe Biden had imposed these exact same tariff policies a year ago, for the exact same stated reasons, Republicans would have impeached him and called for his immediate ouster through <a href="https://constitutioncenter.org/the-constitution/amendments/amendment-xxv">Section 4 of the 25th Amendment</a> — and their actions, for once, would have been justified. These tariff policies are nuts and are <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/04/11/business/economy/treasury-bonds-tariffs.html">endangering the United States’s economic supremacy</a> while simultaneously hurting the entire world economy. No one in their right mind would do this, and the President of the United States needs to be a person in their right mind.</p>

<p>Democrats and all other Trump opponents should immediately begin calling into question Trump’s mental fitness for office. This whole tariff saga is proof that he’s nuts. Just keep repeating that. He’s always been a little nutty but now he’s gone off the deep end. Don’t forget to reiterate that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fred_Trump">Trump’s father was suffering from severe dementia</a> when he was Trump’s age. Throw Biden under the bus: remind people that <a href="https://apple.news/ANs1GK_4ISEikICuDBenaSA">we just saw</a> what happens when a mentally enfeebled 80-year-old<sup>*</sup> serves as President, and that under Trump it’s far worse. Biden was sleepy but steady; Trump is agitated and erratic. That’s far worse.</p>

<p>Hammer the points — all true, all obvious — endlessly: Trump is too old; these tariffs are proof that he’s lost his mind; he’s hurting America badly; dementia runs in his family. Hammer it.</p>

<p><small>* Keep calling him “80”; make his sycophants correct you that he’s “only” turning 79 in June.</small></p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Chinese Finance Ministry Calls Trump’s Tariff Hikes ‘A Joke in the History of World Economics’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/11/china-calls-trump-a-joke">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Wayne Ma at The Information: ‘How Apple Fumbled Siri’s AI Makeover’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theinformation.com/articles/apple-fumbled-siris-ai-makeover?rc=jfy0lk" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w97" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/10/wayne-ma-the-information-apple-siri-fumble" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41803</id>
	<published>2025-04-10T21:58:28Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-11T20:52:42Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Blockbuster report by Wayne Ma for The Information (paywalled and pricey, alas):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>But an equally important factor was the conflicting personalities
within Apple, according to multiple people who worked in the AI
and software engineering groups. More than half a dozen former
Apple employees who worked in the AI and machine-learning group
led by Giannandrea — known as AI/ML for short — told The
Information that poor leadership is to blame for its problems with
execution. They singled out Walker as lacking both ambition and an
appetite for taking risks on designing future versions of the
voice assistant.</p>

<p>Among engineers inside Apple, the AI group’s relaxed culture and
struggles with execution have even earned it an uncharitable
nickname, a play on its initials: AIMLess.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Ouch. Ma names names, and the report is full of scoops:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>One Siri leader often criticized by colleagues was Walker, who
joined Apple in 2013 and became responsible for its daily
operations at the end of 2022. In the eyes of his critics, Walker
was unwilling to take big risks on Siri and focused on metrics
that didn’t move the needle much on its performance, rather than
having a grand vision for overhauling the voice assistant.</p>

<p>For instance, he often celebrated small wins such as reducing by
minute percentages the delay between when someone asked Siri a
question and when it responded, former Apple engineers said.
Another pet Walker project was removing the “hey” from the “hey
Siri” voice command used to invoke the assistant, which took more
than two years to accomplish, they said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>What Ma describes is a scenario where Walker missed the fact that the whole forest sucked and didn’t work, while focusing on one or two nice trees. Faster response times are a win, no question — but a <em>small</em> win, only at the margin. Faster wrong or useless (or even just mediocre) answers are, I guess, better than slower wrong/useless answers, but the overall result is a loss. Fast helpful answers are the goal, obviously, but slow helpful answers are infinitely better than fast useless ones. (I’m not even sure eliminating the requirement to use the verbal “hey” prefix was a win at all. It’s purely anecdotal and personal, but I think I get more unwanted invocations now than I did when “Hey Siri” was the required prompt. Like when I’m talking to someone and start a sentence with “Seriously …” Siri will kick in on one of my devices with a “Sorry, I didn’t catch that.”)</p>

<p>One last nugget:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Other resentments also built up. Some in the software engineering
group were annoyed by the higher pay and faster promotions their
colleagues in the AI group were receiving. And they were bitter
that some engineers in the AI group seemed to be able to take
longer vacations and leave early on Fridays, while they faced
more-punishing work schedules.</p>

<p>Distrust between the two groups got so bad that earlier this year
one of Giannandrea’s deputies asked engineers to extensively
document the development of a joint project so that if it failed,
Federighi’s group couldn’t scapegoat the AI team.</p>

<p>It didn’t help the relations between the groups when Federighi
began amassing his own team of hundreds of machine-learning
engineers that goes by the name Intelligent Systems and is run by
one of Federighi’s top deputies, Sebastien Marineau-Mes.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Hundreds of engineers for a machine learning team outside Apple’s AI/ML division sounds like the definition of dysfunction. I really doubt Federighi has also assembled a large team of silicon engineers outside Johny Srouji’s division, because Srouji’s team is not merely functional, but rightly regarded as one the highest-functioning engineering divisions in any field in the world.</p>

<p>I wish I could share a gift link to Ma’s report, but The Information’s gift links for subscribers only work for up to three people. The best I can do is <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/04/10/chaos-behind-siri-revealed/">point to Hartley Charlton’s summary for MacRumors</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Wayne Ma at The Information: ‘How Apple Fumbled Siri’s AI Makeover’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/10/wayne-ma-the-information-apple-siri-fumble">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/04/webkit_textwrap_pretty" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/w94" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41800</id>
	<published>2025-04-09T23:11:05Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-10T19:18:08Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">I think it’s a good start, and I couldn’t be happier that the WebKit team is even tackling the problem at all. As Simmons notes, line-wrapping layout in web browsers has, until now, been very crude — and the web has been around a long time.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jen Simmons, writing on the WebKit blog, “<a href="https://webkit.org/blog/16547/better-typography-with-text-wrap-pretty/">Better Typography With text-wrap pretty</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>For over 30 years, the web had only one technique for determining
where to wrap text.</p>

<p>The browser starts with the first line of text, and lays out each
word or syllable, one after another until it runs out of room. As
soon as it has no more space to fit another word/syllable, it
wraps to the next line (if <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/text-wrap-mode">wrapping</a> is allowed). Then it
starts on the next line, fitting all the content it can… then
when it runs out of room, it wraps… and starts working on the
next line.</p>

<p>It’s always thinking about only one line at a time. It wraps
whenever it needs, after it’s fit the maximum amount of content
on the previous line. If hyphenation is turned on, it will
hyphenate whatever word is last on the line, at whatever point
leaves as much of the word on the previous line as possible.
Nothing else is taken into consideration — which is why text on
the web has bad rag, rivers, short last lines, and hyphenation
that makes no sense.</p>

<p>This is not required by the fact that text is laid out by a
computer. For decades, software like Adobe InDesign and LaTeX has
evaluated multiple lines of text at a time as they decide where to
end one line and begin the next. It’s just that the web didn’t use
a multiline algorithm. Until now.</p>

<p>We are excited to bring this capability to the web for the first
time, in Safari Technology Preview 216.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’ve turned this on here at Daring Fireball, at least as an experiment. (Look at me, fast adopter of novel CSS features.) I have mixed feelings about the results. Here are saved PDFs showing the rendering of my “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/04/how_many_iphones_can_fit_on_a_freight_plane">How Many New iPhones Can Fit on a Freight Plane?</a>” article from earlier today: <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/04/df-iphones-on-plane-textwrap-auto.pdf">first with traditional <code>text-wrap: auto</code></a> line wrapping, and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/04/df-iphones-on-plane-textwrap-pretty.pdf">second with WebKit’s new <code>text-wrap: pretty</code></a> in <a href="https://developer.apple.com/safari/technology-preview/">STP</a> 216. Looking at each paragraph by itself, there’s no question this new layout algorithm is, well, prettier. The problem I see is going from one paragraph to another. Within a paragraph, WebKit’s new <code>pretty</code> wrapping definitely makes lines a more uniform width. But in some cases it so narrows an entire paragraph that it makes going from one paragraph to the next jarring. Line-to-line the new algorithm looks better, but paragraph-to-paragraph I think it looks worse.</p>

<p>One specific example, from <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/something_is_rotten_in_the_state_of_cupertino">my longest recent article</a>. First, with the old <code>text-wrap: auto</code>:</p>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/04/df-something-rotten-textwrap-auto.png" class="noborder">
  <img
    src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/04/df-something-rotten-textwrap-auto.png"
    alt = "A screenshot from a recent Daring Fireball article, showing a list of 4 items."
    width = 500
    style = "border: 1px solid #5a626a;"
  /></a></p>

<p>Here’s that same list with the new <code>text-wrap: pretty</code> in STP 216:</p>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/04/df-something-rotten-textwrap-pretty.png" class="noborder">
  <img
    src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/04/df-something-rotten-textwrap-pretty.png"
    alt = "A screenshot of the same section from the same recent article as the previous screenshot, but in this one, one of the list item paragraphs is noticeably wider than the others."
    width = 500
    border = 1
    style = "border: 1px solid #5a626a;"
  /></a></p>

<p>With the new <code>text-wrap: pretty</code>, the entire paragraph for the first list item is noticeably wider than the subsequent ones (and noticeably wider than the one preceding the list). To me, there’s so much disparity between paragraph widths that it’s distracting, even though each paragraph, taken on its own, looks better. But you don’t take paragraphs on their own when reading.</p>

<p>I suspect (informed by toying with <a href="https://codepen.io/jensimmons/full/xxvoqNM">Simmons’s fun interactive demo page</a> using STP 216) that this initial WebKit <code>text-wrap: pretty</code> layout algorithm works better with wider column widths than are currently specified on Daring Fireball. When there’s a little more width to play with, there seems to be less back-and-forth change from paragraph to paragraph.</p>

<p>So, for my purposes, this might be yet another improvement that will need to wait for the long-promised-but-who-knows-when-it-might-actually-happen-but-I-swear-I-think-about-it-quite-a-bit-and-a-few-years-ago-even-had-something-in-motion-but-then-let-the-project-drop layout modernization here. But, even with a nice responsive design, column widths on phones are inherently narrow, so I think this algorithm ought to be tweaked to render more consistent paragraph widths in narrow-ish columns.</p>

<p>But I think it’s a good start, and I couldn’t be happier that the WebKit team is even tackling the problem at all. As Simmons notes, line-wrapping layout in web browsers has, until now, been very crude — and the web has been around a long time.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ WebKit Adds Support for ‘text-wrap: pretty’, Now Shipping in Safari Technology Preview</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/04/how_many_iphones_can_fit_on_a_freight_plane" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/w93" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41799</id>
	<published>2025-04-09T20:46:55Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-09T21:19:01Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">This sounds like one of those puzzles job interviewers often ask, but there’s a practical relevance at the moment.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>This sounds like one of those puzzles job interviewers often ask, but there’s a practical relevance at the moment: What’s a ballpark estimate for how many iPhones Apple might have hustled to ship into the US <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/08/plane-of-iphones-from-india-and-china">on those five freight planes</a> ahead of the new tariffs? <a href="https://x.com/rjonesy/status/1909770872778338793">Ryan Jones tackled it in a post on X</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A whopping 12 days of sales. At most.</p>

<p>Math: <br />
• B747 Freighter carries 300,000 lbs <br />
• boxed iPhone is 0.9 lbs <br />
= 350K iPhones per plane</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I like Jones’s ballpark math here. Let’s not worry about volume, just weight. If we’re wrong about the volume, it can only mean <em>fewer</em> new-in-box iPhones can fit per plane. There’s no way to (safely) exceed <a href="https://www.cargolux.com/fleet-equipment/aircraft/747-8f-specifications/">the weight limit of a plane</a>.</p>

<p>Jones also estimates that Apple sells about 150,000 new iPhones in the US per day, at least in the typical April–June quarter — which I concur is a good ballpark figure.<sup id="fnr1-2025-04-09"><a href="#fn1-2025-04-09">1</a></sup> So each plane can carry a little over two days’ worth of US domestic iPhones. That means <a href="https://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/technology/mobiles-tabs/how-apple-flew-5-flights-full-of-iphones-from-india-and-china-in-3-days-to-beat-trump-tariffs/articleshow/120044321.cms">if the Times of India is correct</a> that Apple “transported five planes full of iPhones and other products from India to the US in just three days during the final week of March”, those five planes combined carried, at the most, about 12 days’ worth of new US iPhones.</p>

<p>Now that’s just from India. And those are just the five planes the Times of India heard about. It seems safe to presume Apple might have hustled even more planes out of China and Vietnam. But again, at most, each plane full of Apple products carries about two days’ worth of products. We did our napkin math using iPhones, but “1 full plane = 2 days of inventory” can’t be far off the mark, no matter what the mix of product is in each plane’s cargo hold.</p>

<p>350,000 iPhones packed onto a single plane is a lot of iPhones. Sending a few million units across a dozen (or more!) planes is, quite literally, tons of iPhones. But Apple sells about <em>50 tons</em> of new iPhones in the US alone every day. We all know that Apple’s iPhone business is huge. But when you start to consider it in practical terms like this it’s just staggering.</p>

<p>There’s no way Apple can “beat” these Trump tariffs by having shipped products ahead of their taking effect. Could they hedge against two or three weeks of tumult? Maybe a month, tops? Yes, and it seems like maybe that’s what they did. But no matter how many planes they filled — or how many container ships they might have had the foresight to send a month or two ago — there are very practical limits to inventory, too. Apple’s warehouses are likely designed with one or two weeks of inventory in mind. You can’t just rent random warehouse space to hold billions of dollars worth of iPhones.</p>

<p><a href="https://money.cnn.com/2011/08/24/technology/cook_apple.fortune/index.htm">From Adam Lashinsky’s 2008 profile of Tim Cook for Fortune</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Almost from the time he showed up at Apple, Cook knew he had to
pull the company out of manufacturing. He closed factories and
warehouses around the world and instead established relationships
with contract manufacturers. As a result, Apple’s inventory,
measured by the amount of time it sat on the company’s balance
sheet, quickly fell from months to days. Inventory, Cook has said,
is “fundamentally evil,” and he has been known to observe that it
declines in value by 1% to 2% a week in normal times, faster in
tough times like the present.</p>

<p>“You kind of want to manage it like you’re in the dairy business,”
he has said. “If it gets past its freshness date, you have a
problem.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Apple’s entire supply chain is rightly heralded as genius, a triumph of everything from component sourcing to assembly to transport. But the entire operation is premised on the continuous free flow of packaged products out of China. Apple never holds much inventory, of anything, anywhere in the world.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1-2025-04-09">
<p>If anything, Apple’s sales might be higher than usual right now. With consumers worried that Apple (and everyone else) might raise prices in response to Trump’s tariffs at any moment, demand is surely up to some extent. I know two friends who’ve already purchased new MacBooks, now, for kids who aren’t going off to college until September.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-04-09"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ How Many New iPhones Can Fit on a Freight Plane?</title></entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://workos.com/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/w91" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/04/workos_scalable_secure_authent_2" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.41797</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-04-08T22:04:08Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-08T22:04:09Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Modern authentication should be seamless and secure.  WorkOS makes it easy to integrate features like MFA, SSO, and RBAC.</p>

<p>Whether you’re replacing passwords, stopping fraud, or adding enterprise auth, WorkOS can help you build frictionless auth that scales. </p>

<p>Future-proof your authentication stack with the identity layer trusted by OpenAI, Cursor, Perplexity, and Vercel.  </p>

<p>Upgrade your auth today. </p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘WorkOS: Scalable, Secure Authentication’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/04/workos_scalable_secure_authent_2">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] WorkOS: Scalable, Secure Authentication</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/04/unchanging_prices_vs_nonsensical_tariffs" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/w8o" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41784</id>
	<published>2025-04-04T19:03:15Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-06T22:52:15Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">The erratic, illogical, nonsensical nature of Trump’s tariffs is bad for everyone. (Understatement.) But it’s particularly troublesome for a company that sees retail price stability as part of the branding for its products.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Akash Sriram, reporting for Reuters under the headline “<a href="https://www.reuters.com/technology/will-trump-tariffs-make-apple-iphones-more-expensive-2025-04-03/">A $2,300 Apple iPhone? Trump Tariffs Could Make That Happen.</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Most iPhones are still made in China, which was hit with a 54%
tariff. If those levies persist, Apple has a tough choice: absorb
the extra expense or pass it on to customers.</p>

<p>Shares of the company closed down 9.3% on Thursday, hitting their
worst day since March 2020.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Apple shares dropped <em>another</em> 7.3% percent today. Apple alone has lost 16.6% of its value in the last 48 hours; the S&amp;P 500 dropped 10%.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The cheapest iPhone 16 model was launched in the U.S. with a
sticker price of $799, but could cost as much as $1,142, per
calculations based on projections from analysts at Rosenblatt
Securities, who say the cost could rise by 43% — if Apple is able
to pass that on to consumers. A more expensive iPhone 16 Pro Max,
with a 6.9-inch display and 1 terabyte of storage, which currently
retails at $1599, could cost nearly $2300 if a 43% increase were
to pass to consumers.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s under-remarked upon, but Apple, to a point of almost obstinance, considers pricing part of the brand for its products. They tend not to raise or lower prices with the ebbs and flows of the world economy or even the obvious constraints of simple supply and demand. Throughout the entire COVID crisis, I don’t recall them changing their prices for anything.</p>

<p>As an extreme example, consider the trashcan Mac Pro. It was introduced <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2013/06/10Apple-Gives-Sneak-Peek-Into-the-Future-of-the-Pro-Desktop/">at WWDC 2013</a> and <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2013/10/23Introducing-the-All-New-Mac-Pro-The-Most-Radical-Mac-Ever/">shipped in December that year</a> with a starting price of $2,999. It then went <a href="https://x.com/MKBHD/status/833730471804731392">over three years without an update</a> — and still cost $2,999. Then in April 2017 Apple held <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2017/04/the_mac_pro_lives">that highly unusual small roundtable meeting</a> — invitees were just <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2017/04/04/apple-pushes-the-reset-button-on-the-mac-pro/">Matthew Panzarino</a>, <a href="http://mashable.com/2017/04/04/apple-reveals-mac-pro-imac-plans/">Lance Ulanoff</a>, <a href="https://www.axios.com/apple-to-ditch-the-current-mac-pro-design-but-replacement-wont-arrive--2343465726.html">Ina Fried</a>, <a href="https://www.buzzfeed.com/johnpaczkowski/apple-says-it-is-completely-rethinking-the-mac-pro">John Paczkowski</a>, and yours truly — to discuss “completely rethinking the Mac Pro”. They issued small speed bumps to the trashcan Mac Pro that day, but didn’t ship the actual completely-rethought Mac Pro <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2019/06/apple-unveils-powerful-all-new-mac-pro-and-groundbreaking-pro-display-xdr/">until WWDC 2019</a>. The starting price never changed from $2,999, even when demand for the trashcan models had clearly dropped to near zero. The price was part of the brand. (The starting price for the 2019 Mac Pro: $5,999.)</p>

<p>Or consider <em>today’s</em> Mac Pro, with the M2 Ultra. <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2023/06/apple-unveils-new-mac-studio-and-brings-apple-silicon-to-mac-pro/">It debuted alongside Mac Studio models that also came with the M2 Ultra</a> at WWDC 2023 almost two years ago. M2 Ultra Mac Studios <a href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2023/06/m2-ultra-mac-studio-review-top-of-the-line/">started at $3,999</a>; Mac Pros at $6,999. Many observers, quite reasonably, questioned the $3,000 price difference when both computers offered the same chips. The 2023 Mac Pro, in some sense, is just a 2023 Mac Studio in a much bigger case with additional high-performance I/O options. But a month ago Apple debuted <em>M3</em> Ultra Mac Studios, with an unchanged starting price of $3,999. The Mac Pro, still equipped with the older M2 Ultra, still starts at $6,999. Which means that for the time being, you’re not paying $3,000 extra for the same computer in a bigger case, but for a <em>generation-older</em> computer in a bigger case.</p>

<p>Presumably, M3 Ultra Mac Pros are coming soon, perhaps at WWDC. But until then, the pricing is undeniably weird when compared to the Mac Studio — and many people have thought the pricing was a bit weird compared to the Mac Studio when they were offered with the same M2-generation chips. But that’s how Apple likes to do pricing: they set a price when a product is announced, and that price never changes until a successor to that product is announced.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/03/trump-tariffs-techdirt">erratic</a>, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/03/trump-tariffs-day-two">illogical</a>, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/03/the-economist-on-trumps-mindless-tariffs">nonsensical</a> nature of Trump’s tariffs is bad for everyone. (<a href="https://bsky.app/profile/crampell.bsky.social/post/3llzc3fmf7s23">Understatement</a>.) But it’s particularly troublesome for a company that sees retail price stability as part of the branding for its products. Will Trump come to his senses (to some small degree), and declare a nonexistent victory next week and pull these tariffs from the board? Or stick to his guns and ride this global-economy-tanking insanity out? No one knows. Will he start granting exceptions? No one knows. So in addition to being nonsensical, the whole thing is entirely unpredictable, which is not at all compatible with the way Apple has set retail prices for decades.</p>

<p>My (bigly) guess is that Apple will inject its own predictability and stability into the mix, and keep its retail prices stable, for now, and take the tariff hit on its margins. But if these tariffs really stay in effect, even just for a few months, at current prices Apple <a href="https://www.threads.net/@benedictevans/post/DIBMlA2MSFs">would be breaking even at best</a>, and likely losing money, on each iPhone it sells.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Tired: Irresistable Force vs. Immovable Object — Wired: Unchanging Prices vs. Nonsensical Tariffs</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/france_merde_decision_app_tracking_transparency" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/w85" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41765</id>
	<published>2025-03-31T19:46:31Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-01T17:34:41Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">It’s like a consortium of sketchy pawn shops complaining to the authorities after a retailer successfully cracked down on an organized shoplifting/pickpocketing ring, and the authorities then fining the retailer for the damage to the pawnbrokers’ business fencing stolen goods — and for exposing the police as ineffective.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jon Brodkin, reporting for Ars Technica, “<a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2025/03/france-fines-apple-e150m-for-excessive-pop-ups-that-let-users-reject-tracking/">France Fines Apple €150M for “Excessive” Pop-Ups That Let Users Reject Tracking</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>France’s competition regulator fined Apple €150 million, saying
the iPhone maker went overboard in its implementation of pop-up
messages that let users consent to or reject tracking that
third-party applications use for targeted advertising.</p>

<p>The App Tracking Transparency (ATT) framework used by Apple on
iPhones and iPads since 2021 makes the use of third-party
applications too complex and hurts small companies that rely on
advertising revenue, said a <a href="https://www.autoritedelaconcurrence.fr/en/press-release/targeted-advertising-autorite-de-la-concurrence-imposes-fine-eu150000000-apple">press release</a> today by the
Autorité de la concurrence (Competition Authority). The system
harms “smaller publishers in particular since, unlike the main
vertically integrated platforms, they depend to a large extent on
third-party data collection to finance their business,” the
agency said.</p>

<p>User consent obtained via the ATT framework “authorizes the
application in question to collect user data for targeted
advertising purposes,” the agency said. “If consent is given, the
application can access the Identifier for Advertisers (‘IDFA’),
the identifier by which each device can be tracked through its use
of third-party applications and sites.” The French investigation
was triggered by a complaint lodged by advertising industry
associations.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Ben Lovejoy, <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/03/31/apple-bizarrely-fined-162m-for-app-tracking-transparency-after-advertisers-complained/">correctly calling the decision “bizarre” at 9to5Mac</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Complaints were made <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2023/04/11/apple-app-tracking/">in a number of countries</a> — some
arguing that it was unfair because <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2022/06/14/app-tracking-transparency-antitrust/">Apple exempts its own
apps</a> (which are in reality subject to even tighter
controls), others saying the loss of revenue <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2022/09/13/app-tracking-transparency-increases-in-app-purchase-prices/">forced developers to
raise prices</a> to compensate. [...]</p>

<p>Although expected, the decision is still inexplicable. ATT
involves precisely <em>one</em> popup asking a simple yes/no question.
Additionally, Apple lets users switch on a toggle (shown above) to
block apps from even asking the question. It’s especially odd
given that ATT is a privacy feature, and Europe has the strongest
privacy laws in the world. The EU <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2022/08/03/ad-tracking-rules/">has also previously
vindicated</a> Apple’s introduction of ATT.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s not inexplicable or odd if you view the decision as coming from a perspective where government bureaucracy is viewed as an inherent good, and well-intentioned process is all that matters, not actual results. Read the <em>Autorité de la Concurrence</em>’s decision (<a href="https://www.autoritedelaconcurrence.fr/en/press-release/targeted-advertising-autorite-de-la-concurrence-imposes-fine-eu150000000-apple">which they helpfully do make available in English</a>) and it’s pretty clear:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The <em>Autorité</em> found that the ATT framework imposed by Apple is
not necessary, insofar as the consent obtained is not valid under
the applicable laws, in particular the French Data Protection Act.</p>

<p>In practice, the fact that publishers that so wish cannot rely on
the ATT framework to comply with their legal obligations means
that they must continue to use their own consent collection
solutions, known as consent management platforms (“CMPs”). The
result is that multiple consent pop-ups are displayed, making the
use of third-party applications in the iOS environment excessively
complex, as observed by the French data protection authority
(<em>Commission nationale de l’informatique et des libertés</em> — CNIL)
in a 2022 opinion issued at the request of the <em>Autorité</em>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s ostensibly “not necessary” because French and EU privacy laws are supposedly enough, and all that’s needed. And it’s unfair because now, under ATT, third-party surveillance advertisers who seek to track users across apps on iOS need to ask permission twice — first through the clear-as-a-bell “Ask App Not to Track” / “Allow Tracking” prompt required by Apple, and again through the byzantine but ultimately toothless permission requirements of France and the EU. ATT has had measurable effects because users understand it, and they prefer not to be tracked. EU and French privacy laws are largely ineffective because, in practice, they <a href="https://hep.physics.illinois.edu/home/g-gollin/1984_commercial_dialogue.html">bury users with confusion</a>. The bureaucratic hurdles they impose are to the benefit, not detriment, of the surveillance ad industry. That’s now proven out by industry groups — the ones ATT successfully tempered — successfully getting France’s regulators to penalize Apple. <em>Users</em> don’t know how to lobby government bureaucracies. What the <em>Autorité de la Concurrence</em> is saying, in so many words, is that two layers of consent is too much, and the only one that’s necessary is the one that advertising lobbying groups <em>don’t object to</em>, not the one they do (but which users understand and like).</p>

<p>It’s clear that only one of these two things — Apple’s ATT or French/EU privacy regulations — was actually effective at reducing tracking: ATT. No one claimed that French or EU privacy laws resulted in Meta losing a fortune because they had to adjust their kleptomaniacal thievery of users’ privacy. But by all accounts, <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/danielnewman/2022/02/10/apple-meta-and-the-ten-billion-dollar-impact-of-privacy-changes/">including Meta’s own</a>, <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/kateoflahertyuk/2022/04/23/apple-just-issued-stunning-12-billion-blow-to-facebook/">ATT cost Meta billions</a>. And yes, ATT hurt small businesses too — small businesses that were built upon surreptitious tracking that users had neither awareness of nor control over. It’s like a consortium of sketchy pawn shops complaining to the authorities after a popular retailer successfully cracked down on an organized shoplifting/pickpocketing ring, and the authorities then fining the retailer for the damage to the pawnbrokers’ business fencing stolen goods — and for exposing the police as ineffective.</p>

<p>App Tracking Transparency actually accomplished, in practice, via user-focused plain-language consent, what the EU’s privacy laws were intended to do but do not. This fine boils down to France declaring that Apple shouldn’t have actually done what the EU was pretending to do. They’re acting at the behest of the very developers and advertising companies who were (and still are) trying to conduct cross-app tracking that App Tracking Transparency successfully gave <em>users</em> some control over.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ France Fines Apple $162M for App Tracking Transparency, Taking the Side of Surveillance Advertisers Over Users</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/the_studio" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/w7z" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41759</id>
	<published>2025-03-30T19:38:28Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-31T15:31:36Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Perhaps Apple’s leadership simply believes, as I do, that cinema is the grandest and greatest form of art the world has ever seen — one that encompasses acting, writing, photography and/or illustration, and music — and but that great cinema is expensive and delicate and needs, from deep-pocketed studios and their deeper-pocketed corporate parents, more than patrons, but *champions*.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>With season 2 of <em>Severance</em> complete (with a remarkable bang), Apple TV+ has slid right into a new prestige series, <em><a href="https://www.themoviedb.org/tv/247767-the-studio?language=en-US">The Studio</a></em>, starring (and co-created by) Seth Rogen as the newly-appointed chief of the fictional and dysfunctional Continental Studios in Hollywood.</p>

<p>Two episodes in (out of 10 for the debut season), and it is fucking amazing. So far it feels a bit like a cross between <em>Entourage</em>, <em>The Larry Sanders Show</em>, <em>Boogie Nights</em>, and maybe a touch of <em>Curb Your Enthusiasm</em>. But the biggest influence and inspiration is clearly Robert Altman’s 1992 masterpiece <em><a href="https://www.themoviedb.org/movie/10403-the-player?language=en-US">The Player</a></em>, almost certainly the best Hollywood movie about Hollywood moviemaking that ever was or will be made.</p>

<p>What <em>The Studio</em> and <em>The Player</em> share is that they’re about the struggle to create great cinematic art within a corporate studio world run by unartistic know-it-all  self-important status-obsessed dullards driven by formula and fads — and, simultaneously, they are themselves almost unfathomably complicated and intricate works of cinematic art. They <em>are</em> what they’re <em>about</em>. They achieve what the characters within them fear is no longer achievable. When you get to episode 2 of <em>The Studio</em>, just keep asking yourself “Wait, <em>how</em> are they getting this shot?” The lighting, my god. The whole thing is just an outpouring of homage to <a href="https://www.rogerebert.com/scanners/opening-shots-the-player">the opening shot of <em>The Player</em></a>, which of course itself calls back, <a href="https://filmotomy.com/quiet-on-the-set-breaking-down-the-opening-shot-in-altmans-the-player/">explicitly</a>, to Orson Welles’s <em>Touch of Evil</em>.</p>

<p><em>The Studio</em> is, thus far, engaging, surprising, funny, gorgeous, clever, and cinematically ambitious. It’s really quite a thing. I have no idea what’s coming in episodes 3–10, so maybe this piece will look a bit premature, if not foolish, in two months. But if the rest of season one is anything like the first two episodes, <em>The Studio</em> is a classic in the making.</p>

<p>The thought also occurs to me that this might be the don’t-over-think-it answer to <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/21/apple-tv-spend-loss-or-cost">just what the hell Apple is doing making original shows and movies</a> in the first place. Perhaps Apple’s leadership simply believes, as I do, that cinema is the grandest and greatest form of art the world has ever seen — one that encompasses acting, writing, photography and/or illustration, and music — and but that great cinema is expensive and delicate and needs, from deep-pocketed studios and their deeper-pocketed corporate parents, more than patrons, but <em>champions</em>. And that in a media landscape where such champions of cinema-as-art and art-as-an-essential-public-good are fewer and fewer, it is Apple’s not just opportunity but <em>obligation</em> to step up to the plate.</p>

<p>I’ve long thought that one of the minor tragedies of Steve Jobs’s second act is that the timing just didn’t work out to sell Pixar to Apple, instead of to Disney. But make no mistake, a love and appreciation for great cinema is not outside Apple’s DNA. No streamer has a higher hit rate for quality shows. Their movies mostly stink so far, but maybe that’s just the learning curve. <em>The Gorge</em>, for example, feels like an Apple TV movie because it’s so decidedly meh. Not horrible, but not good in any way beyond its intriguing elevator-pitch concept. <em>Wolfs</em> was better but still a grand disappointment given its pedigree. But when it comes to shows, no one is doing better. <em>Severance</em> deserves all its acclaim and attention, and Ben Stiller delivered a season 2 finale that’s arguably the best 78 minutes of filmmaking I’ve seen this decade. And <em>The Studio</em>, to me, <em>feels</em> like an Apple TV show — not because of how it looks, what it’s about, or who’s in it, but simply because it’s so good. Netflix almost never makes shows like this. Neither does HBO now that’s its been subsumed by “Max”. Peacock et al don’t even try.<sup id="fnr1-2025-03-30"><a href="#fn1-2025-03-30">1</a></sup></p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1-2025-03-30">
<p>One more A+ recommendation: <em><a href="https://www.themoviedb.org/tv/219971-the-agency">The Agency</a></em> on Paramount+. Michael Fassbender, Jeffrey Wright, Richard Gere, a breakout searing performance by Jodie Turner-Smith, and a great supporting cast in a super-smart, hyper-realistic-feeling spy-thriller/mystery/love story. Gorgeous cinematography too. Just so good in a “feels like it should have been on Apple TV+” way, sort of like how it was so obvious right from S1.E1 that HBO fucked up big-time by passing on <em>Mad Men</em>.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-03-30"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ ‘The Studio’ Is Fantastic So Far</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/the_website_hacker_news_is_afraid_to_discuss" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/w7u" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41754</id>
	<published>2025-03-27T00:11:53Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-27T13:31:49Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">What bothers me isn’t so much that Daring Fireball is shitlisted at Hacker News. What bothers me is that it’s unexplained.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Back in 2017, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2017/09/iphone_x_event_thoughts_and_observations">the iPhone X was announced alongside the iPhones 8 and 8 Plus</a> in mid-September. The iPhones 8 shipped that month, and I published <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2017/09/the_iphones_8">a review of the iPhones 8</a> on September 19. The iPhone X, though, <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2017/09/the-future-is-here-iphone-x/">wasn’t available to order until October 27</a>, and didn’t start shipping to customers until November 3. It was an unusual iPhone release cycle that year, to say the least. Initial reviews of the much-anticipated iPhone X appeared on October 31, but I’d only had the phone for 24 hours when the embargo dropped, so I published <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2017/10/iphone_x_review_roundup">some initial impressions then</a>, but wound up not publishing my <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2017/12/the_iphone_x">full review of the iPhone X</a> until December 26.</p>

<p>A few days later I wrote a follow-up regarding a specific new interaction design, “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2017/12/side_button_to_confirm_payments_on_iphone_x">Pressing the Side Button to Confirm Payments on iPhone X</a>”, which I began thus:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Occasionally I notice a burst of traffic to Daring Fireball from
Hacker News. It’s always short-lived, because for reasons I’ve
never seen explained, Daring Fireball articles always get
blacklisted from Hacker News once they hit their front page. It’s
apparent that a lot of HN readers do not like my work on the basis
that they see me as a shameless Apple shill, but it’s a shame the
articles get deleted because I like reading the comments. I feel
like it keeps me on my toes to read the comments from people who
don’t like Daring Fireball.</p>

<p>Even after being blacklisted from the Hacker News homepage,
though, the comment threads still exist. I went through <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=16014464">the
Hacker News comments on my iPhone X review</a> today, and a few
comments about how Apple Pay works on the iPhone X caught my
attention.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>What I didn’t mention then was that DF’s buried status at HN was, at the time, a relatively new phenomenon. Hacker News <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2013/05/18/the-evolution-of-hacker-news/">started in early 2007</a> and for a yearslong stretch, Daring Fireball articles seemed more or less appropriately popular there. Articles that I would think would resonate with the HN readership would hit, and get what always seemed to me an appropriate number of comments. At some point in the mid-2010s though, it seemed like DF articles would get downvoted or flagged after hitting the HN front page. I’d been noticing this for some time when I wrote the above in December 2017.</p>

<p>But even in 2017, DF articles would get active comment threads on HN occasionally. The Hacker News thread I referenced above, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=16014464">regarding my iPhone X review</a>, garnered 107 comments. In the years after that, DF articles went from being mysteriously disappeared <em>after</em> hitting the HN front page (and gaining some comment traction) to pretty much <em>never</em> hitting the HN front page (and thus never gaining any comment traction). I found this curious, and I couldn’t figure out <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/newsfaq.html">why or how</a> this was happening — or who was doing it — but I didn’t mention it much.</p>

<p>Two years ago, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2023/02/making_our_hearts_sing#fn1-2023-02-01">I did mention it again in a footnote</a>, in a piece about the inexplicably poor state of Android apps from a design perspective:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It sounds a bit conspiratorial, but <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2017/12/side_button_to_confirm_payments_on_iphone_x">for several years
now</a> it’s seemed clear to me that Hacker News has
Daring Fireball in some sort of graylist. It’s not blacklisted,
obviously, given the aforementioned <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=34605535">two</a>
<a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=34611552">threads</a> about yesterday’s piece, but nothing I
write here ever gains any significant traction there. Ever. And
the reason there are two threads for yesterday’s piece is that the
first one disappeared from the home page soon after it was posted.
I think? In <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/from?site=daringfireball.net">this list of recent Hacker News threads for articles
from DF</a>, going back four months, only three have
more than 10 comments — and two of those are the threads from
yesterday. I don’t know who I pissed off there or why, but I’ve
never seen an explanation for this. <strong>UPDATE:</strong> <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=34626587">HN commenter
Michiel de Mare has quantified the apparent
suppression</a>, based on the ranking of this very
article. Exactly what I’ve noticed for years.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You can see this yourself right now, with <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/from?site=daringfireball.net">the current list of recent DF articles submitted to Hacker News</a>. Most of them have 0, 1, or 2 comments. Some got up to 3. “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/something_is_rotten_in_the_state_of_cupertino">Something Is Rotten in the State of Cupertino</a>” is the most read, most commented upon thing I’ve written in a while. On Hacker News <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43348891">it got just 28 comments</a> before being shitlisted, which, I have to say, is just weird. That’s one piece I’d have thought would resonate with the HN audience, and make for good grist for discussion. Then, after the original thread was shitlisted, someone re-submitted it (perhaps confused that it wasn’t on the HN front page). That re-submission <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43355009">got 1 comment</a> before it too fell to the mysterious shitlist reaper.</p>

<p>The one recent exception is “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/why_cant_we_screenshot_frames_from_drm-protected_video">Why Can’t We Screenshot Frames From DRM-Protected Video on Apple Devices?</a>”, which somehow <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43223985">escaped the shitlist and garnered 208 comments</a>. These occasional exceptions to DF’s general shitlisting at HN have always made the whole thing more mysterious to me. There’s clearly no programmatic blacklisting that keeps Daring Fireball articles from being submitted, or from gaining a few comments. But once any traction occurs, <em>something</em> happens and poof, they’re gone from the Hacker News front page. It certainly doesn’t make any sense to me why my off-hand post griping about our inability to screenshot DRM video frames would be an order of magnitude more popular than “Something Is Rotten in the State of Cupertino” was.</p>

<p>Today, though, I saw <a href="https://jasette.facil.services/@jerome/114229390677476922">a helpful mention on Mastodon</a> that pointed me to an interesting project. An author named Michael Lynch has written a tool to quantify “<a href="https://refactoringenglish.com/tools/hn-popularity/">the highest-ranking personal blogs of Hacker News</a>” since HN’s inception in 2007. According to Lynch’s all-time listing, Daring Fireball ranks #5, which I have to say surprised me, given its years of inexplicable (or at the very least, unexplained) shitlisting status. But Lynch’s tool lets you select date ranges. If you look at <a href="https://refactoringenglish.com/tools/hn-popularity/?start=2006-10-09&amp;end=2021-03-26&amp;limit=100">2007 through 2021</a>, Daring Fireball ranked #3, behind only <a href="https://paulgraham.com/">Paul Graham’s renowned eponymous blog</a> and Brian Krebs’s excellent (and also eponymous) <a href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/">Krebs on Security</a>. From <a href="https://refactoringenglish.com/tools/hn-popularity/?start=2006-10-09&amp;end=2013-03-26&amp;limit=100">2007 though 2013</a>, DF ranked #2, behind only Graham (who created Hacker News). But if you look at the last four years, from <a href="https://refactoringenglish.com/tools/hn-popularity/?start=2021-10-09&amp;end=2025-03-26&amp;limit=100">2021 through 2025</a>, Daring Fireball ranks #72.</p>

<p>Maybe I’ve lost my fastball, and I just don’t write so good no more. Or maybe it’s not me, but the Hacker News audience that has changed in recent years.<sup id="fnr1-2025-03-26"><a href="#fn1-2025-03-26">1</a></sup> But it seems to me <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=34626587">there’s something fishy going on</a>. What bothers me isn’t so much that Daring Fireball is shitlisted at Hacker News — even though I really did enjoy reading the commentary on my posts back when they regularly surfaced there, and <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/user?id=jgruber">still do</a> when one slips through the cracks. What bothers me is that it’s unexplained. Which, ultimately, seems not so much censorial as just cowardly.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1-2025-03-26">
<p>You’d think there’d be a certain kinship between decades-old websites, typeset in small-point Verdana, which stubbornly refuse to update their general layout and design.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-03-26"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ The Website That Hacker News Is Afraid to Discuss (You’re Reading It)</title></entry></feed><!-- THE END -->
