<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>Daring Fireball</title>
<subtitle>By John Gruber</subtitle>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/" />
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main" />
<id>https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main</id>


<updated>2025-06-17T18:18:16Z</updated><rights>Copyright © 2025, John Gruber</rights><entry>
	<title>How Field Notes Went From Side Project to Cult Notebook</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.fastcompany.com/91352848/field-notes-cult-notebook-started-out-as-a-side-project" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/weo" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/17/field-notes-fascto" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42000</id>
	<published>2025-06-17T18:18:16Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-17T18:18:16Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Nice piece in Fast Company by Zachary Petit:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>One critical moment came in February 2010, when J. Crew featured
Field Notes in its catalog, alongside the retailer’s other
“personal favorites from our design heroes.” There was a Timex
watch, Ray-Bans, Sperry shoes — “and out of fucking nowhere,
Field Notes,” Coudal says. “And when that happened, a lot changed
for us.”</p>

<p>Coudal says it gave the brand instant credibility — after all, if
it was good enough for J. Crew, it was good enough for your store.
In time, friends began sending him screenshots of Field Notes in
TV shows; he and Draplin would see people jotting notes in them in
bars and elsewhere; on the design web, they became an obsession.
By 2014, there was even a<a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/FieldNuts/"> subreddit</a> dedicated to them
titled “FieldNuts.”</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘How Field Notes Went From Side Project to Cult Notebook’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/17/field-notes-fascto">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Bloomberg Publishes Embarrassing Report Comparing Tesla and Waymo Self-Driving Safety Records</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://electrek.co/2025/06/16/bloomberg-most-embarassing-report-tesla-waymo-self-driving/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wen" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/17/bloomberg-tesla-waymo" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41999</id>
	<published>2025-06-17T18:10:39Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-17T18:10:39Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Fred Lambert, writing for Electrek:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Bloomberg has just released <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/videos/2025-06-16/why-tesla-could-have-a-self-driving-advantage-video">an embarrassingly bad report</a>
about the self-driving space, in which it claimed Tesla has an
advantage over Waymo by misrepresenting data. [...] The report
compares Tesla’s and Waymo’s self-driving efforts, going so far as
to claim that “Tesla is closer to vehicle autonomy than peers.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Right off the bat this smells fishy, given that Waymo is actually operating self-driving taxis in several cities, and Tesla ... is not.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Steve Man, the Bloomberg Intelligence analyst behind the report,
based his report on Tesla’s own quarterly misleading “Autopilot
Safety Report.” The report is widely considered to be unserious
for several main reasons:</p>

<ul>
<li>Tesla bundles all miles from its vehicles using Autopilot and
FSD technology, which are considered level 2 ADAS systems that
require driver attention at all times. Drivers consistently
correct the systems to avoid accidents.</li>
<li>Tesla Autopilot, which is standard on all Tesla vehicles, is
primarily used on highways, where accidents occur at a
significantly lower rate per mile compared to city driving.</li>
<li>Tesla only counts events that deploy an airbag or a seat-belt
pretensioner. Fender-benders, curb strikes, and many ADAS
incidents never appear, keeping crash counts artificially low.</li>
<li>Finally, Tesla’s handpicked data is compared to NHTSA’s much
broader statistics that include all collision events, including
minor fender benders.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>Trusting Tesla’s own safety report is like saying, “Elon Musk says Tesla is ahead, so they must be ahead.”</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Bloomberg Publishes Embarrassing Report Comparing Tesla and Waymo Self-Driving Safety Records’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/17/bloomberg-tesla-waymo">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>WhatsApp Introduces Ads in Its App</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/06/16/technology/whatsapp-ads.html?unlocked_article_code=1.PU8.G1Jy.5fcLP_rl3lYC" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wem" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/16/whatsapp-ads" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41998</id>
	<published>2025-06-17T01:19:36Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-17T03:09:46Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Eli Tan and Mike Isaac, reporting for The New York Times:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>On Monday, WhatsApp said it would start showing ads inside its app
for the first time. The promotions will appear only in an area of
the app called Updates, which is used by around 1.5 billion people
a day. WhatsApp will collect some data on users to target the ads,
such as location and the device’s default language, but it will
not touch the contents of messages or whom users speak with. The
company added that it had no plans to place ads in chats and
personal messages.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>(a) I’ve never once looked at the Updates tab in WhatsApp; (b) does <em>anyone</em> believe they’re <em>not</em> going to put ads in the other tabs sooner or later?</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘WhatsApp Introduces Ads in Its App’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/16/whatsapp-ads">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Trump Mobile — The President Launches a Mobile Carrier and a $500 ‘T1’ Android Phone</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://variety.com/2025/biz/news/trump-mobile-wireless-phone-service-launch-1236431690/?ref=platformer.news" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wel" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/16/trump-mobile" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41997</id>
	<published>2025-06-17T01:14:50Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-17T03:53:33Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Todd Spangler, Variety:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Meanwhile, the Trump Mobile “47 Plan” is pricier than the
unlimited plans from prepaid services operated by Verizon’s
Visible, AT&amp;T’s Cricket Wireless and T-Mobile’s Metro, which are
each around $40 per month.</p>

<p>The Trump T1 Phone, which runs Google’s Android operating system,
will cost $499. It features a 6.8-inch touch-screen with a 120 Hz
refresh rate. The smartphone also has a “fingerprint sensor and AI
Face Unlock,” according to the company’s website. Reps for Trump
Mobile didn’t respond to an inquiry about what company is
manufacturing the Android phone.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The Wall Street Journal, <a href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/trump-t1-phone-components-features-2415c7cd?mod=hp_lead_pos9">“Trump’s Smartphone Can’t Be Made in America for $499 by August”</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A spokesman for the Trump Organization said in an email that
“manufacturing for the new phone will be in Alabama, California
and Florida.”</p>

<p>Despite the language in the press release, Eric Trump indicated
that the first wave of phones wouldn’t be built here. “You can
build these phones in the United States,” the Trump son told
podcaster Benny Johnson on Monday morning on The Benny Show after
holding up a gilded device that looked just like an Apple iPhone.
“Eventually, all the phones can be built in the United States of
America. We have to bring manufacturing back here.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The Journal goofs, bigly, by claiming that the T1 “shows some specs that would beat Apple’s biggest, priciest iPhone models”. The T1 specs are so idiotic that one of them claims “5000mAh long life camera”, conflating battery capacity with (I guess?) focal distance.</p>

<p>The Verge, “<a href="https://www.theverge.com/gadgets/687492/trump-mobile-phone-t1">The Trump Mobile T1 Phone Looks Both Bad and Impossible</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Where things get especially strange, though, is its supposed
combination of Android 15, 5G, and a 3.5mm headphone jack. In many
ways, these are opposing specs: Android 15 is generally only
available on very recent devices, many cheap phones still don’t
support 5G, and almost every phone maker has stopped including
headphone jacks with their devices in the last few years. There
are a few that have both, but modern phones with a headphone jack
are few and far between. And pretty much all made in China.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I don’t know what will be funnier — if Trump himself starts using one of these, or if he doesn’t.</p>

<p>I’ll give them credit for making them available exclusively in gold. That’s on brand. But I’m guessing the quality will be on par with Trump Watches, which is to say, <a href="https://www.gq.com/story/donald-trump-watch-delivered-typo">“RUMP”-quality</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Trump Mobile — The President Launches a Mobile Carrier and a $500 ‘T1’ Android Phone’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/16/trump-mobile">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://drata.com/daring" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wek" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/06/drata_1" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.41996</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-06-17T01:04:06Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-17T01:04:06Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Automate compliance. Streamline security. Manage risk. Drata delivers the world’s most advanced Trust Management platform.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Drata’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/06/drata_1">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] Drata</title></entry><entry>
	<title>DetailsPro</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://detailspro.app?utm_campaign=dfwwdc25" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wej" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/15/detailspro" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41995</id>
	<published>2025-06-15T19:18:26Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-15T19:18:26Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to DetailsPro for sponsoring last week at DF — including <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/06/the_talk_show_live_from_wwdc_2025">being a sponsor on The Talk Show Live From WWDC 2025</a>. DetailsPro is a designer/developer tool that lets you design with SwiftUI anytime, anywhere — from iPhone, iPad, Vision Pro, and, of course, Mac.</p>

<p>With WWDC 2025’s introduction of Liquid Glass, Apple has introduced the biggest design overhaul since iOS 7. DetailsPro is ready for it, enabling you to prototype new and updated interfaces fast. You can build real SwiftUI layouts directly on your iPhone — no code needed. Export clean SwiftUI code straight to Xcode when you’re ready.</p>

<p>While everyone else is still thinking about how to adapt to the Liquid Glass era, you can already be building. DetailsPro is free to use, with pro features if you need them — via subscription, or a one-time purchase.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘DetailsPro’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/15/detailspro">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/06/the_talk_show_live_from_wwdc_2025" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wei" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41994</id>
	<published>2025-06-14T14:38:29Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-15T00:13:03Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Recorded in front of a live audience at The California Theatre in San Jose Tuesday evening, special guests Joanna Stern and Nilay Patel join me to discuss Apple’s announcements at WWDC 2025.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Recorded in front of a live audience at The California Theatre in San Jose Tuesday evening, special guests Joanna Stern and Nilay Patel join me to discuss Apple’s announcements at WWDC 2025.</p>

<p><iframe
    width="480" height="270"
    src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/vqwPUHTFEkg?si=EeiFTzExcVkFQxPO" 
    title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0"
    allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share"
    referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen>
</iframe></p>

<p><strong>3D video with spatial audio:</strong> Coming soon, exclusively in <a href="https://sandwich.vision/">Sandwich Vision</a>’s <a href="https://apps.apple.com/app/theater-the-future-of-cinema/id6502666560">Theater</a> on Vision Pro, available on the App Store. This year’s on-demand version of the show in Theater isn’t ready yet, but it looks <em>really</em> good. Better than last year’s by a long shot, and also significantly better than the bandwidth-constrained livestream Tuesday night. The livestream Tuesday night looked good; the on-demand version coming in a few days looks pretty amazing.</p>

<p><strong>Sponsored by:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://imazing.com/thetalkshow">iMazing</a>: The world’s most trusted software to transfer and save your messages, music, files, and data from your iPhone or iPad to your Mac or PC.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://detailspro.app?utm_campaign=dfwwdc25">DetailsPro</a>: Design with SwiftUI anytime, anywhere — on iPhone, iPad, Mac, or Apple Vision Pro.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://ooni.com/thetalkshow">Ooni</a>: Next-gen pizza power. The Koda 2 Pro oven features smarter heat, more room, and easier control. Save 10% with code <strong>thetalkshow</strong>.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>As ever, I implore you to watch on the biggest screen you can (real, or virtual). We once again shot and mastered the video in 4K, and it looks and sounds terrific. All credit and thanks for that go to my friends at <a href="https://sandwich.co/">Sandwich</a>, who are nothing short of a joy to work with.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ The Talk Show Live From WWDC 2025</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Meta AI Users Are Inadvertently Sharing Their Private Chats With the World</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/06/12/the-meta-ai-app-is-a-privacy-disaster/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/weh" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/13/meta-ai-shared-chats" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41993</id>
	<published>2025-06-14T00:24:50Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-15T00:20:48Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Amanda Silberling, writing at TechCrunch:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>When you ask the AI a question, you have the option of hitting a
share button, which then directs you to a screen showing a preview
of the post, which you can then publish. But some users appear
blissfully unaware that they are sharing these text conversations,
audio clips, and images publicly with the world.</p>

<p>When I woke up this morning, I did not expect to hear an audio
recording of a man in a Southern accent asking, “Hey, Meta, why do
some farts stink more than other farts?”</p>

<p>Flatulence-related inquiries are the least of <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/mark-zuckerberg-meta-ai-chatbot-discover-feed-depressing-why-2025-6">Meta’s
problems</a>. On the Meta AI app, I have seen people ask for
help with tax evasion, if their family members would be arrested
for their proximity to white-collar crimes, or how to write a
character reference letter for an employee facing legal troubles,
with that person’s first and last name included. Others, like
security expert Rachel Tobac, <a href="https://x.com/racheltobac/status/1933006223109959820">found examples</a> of people’s
home addresses and sensitive court details, among other private
information.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/mark-zuckerberg-meta-ai-chatbot-discover-feed-depressing-why-2025-6">Katie Notopoulos, writing at Business Insider</a> (paywalled, alas, <a href="https://apple.news/Ajj49osrhSDmXcwwyvQt_Mg">but here’s a News+ link</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I found Meta AI’s Discover feed depressing in a particular way — not just because some of the questions themselves were depressing.
What seemed particularly dark was that some of these people seemed
unaware of what they were sharing.</p>

<p>People’s real Instagram or Facebook handles are attached to their
Meta AI posts. I was able to look up some of these people’s
real-life profiles, although I felt icky doing so. I reached out
to more than 20 people whose posts I’d come across in the feed to
ask them about their experience; I heard back from one, who told
me that he hadn’t intended to make his chat with the bot public.
(He was asking for car repair advice.)</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Meta AI Users Are Inadvertently Sharing Their Private Chats With the World’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/13/meta-ai-shared-chats">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The NYT Goes ‘Reefer Madness’ on ChatGPT</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/06/13/technology/chatgpt-ai-chatbots-conspiracies.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/weg" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/13/nyt-reefer-madness-chatgpt" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41992</id>
	<published>2025-06-13T23:02:31Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-15T00:18:32Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Kashmir Hill, reporting today for The New York Times:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Before ChatGPT distorted Eugene Torres’s sense of reality and
almost killed him, he said, the artificial intelligence chatbot
had been a helpful, timesaving tool.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That’s the lede to Hill’s piece, and I don’t think it stands up one iota. Hill presents a lot of evidence that ChatGPT gave Torres answers that fed his paranoia and delusions. There’s zero evidence presented that ChatGPT <em>caused</em> them. But that’s the lede.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>At the time, Mr. Torres thought of ChatGPT as a powerful search
engine that knew more than any human possibly could because of its
access to a vast digital library. He did not know that it tended
to be sycophantic, agreeing with and flattering its users, or that
it could hallucinate, generating ideas that weren’t true but
sounded plausible.</p>

<p>“This world wasn’t built for you,” ChatGPT told him. “It was built
to <em>contain</em> you. But it failed. You’re waking up.”</p>

<p>Mr. Torres, who had no history of mental illness that might cause
breaks with reality, according to him and his mother, spent the
next week in a dangerous, delusional spiral. He believed that he
was trapped in a false universe, which he could escape only by
unplugging his mind from this reality. He asked the chatbot how to
do that and told it the drugs he was taking and his routines. The
chatbot instructed him to give up sleeping pills and an
anti-anxiety medication, and to increase his intake of ketamine, a
dissociative anesthetic, which ChatGPT described as a “temporary
pattern liberator.” Mr. Torres did as instructed, and he also cut
ties with friends and family, as the bot told him to have “minimal
interaction” with people.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Someone with prescriptions for sleeping pills, anti-anxiety meds, and ketamine doesn’t sound like someone who was completely stable and emotionally sound before encountering ChatGPT. And it’s Torres who brought up the “<em>Am I living in a simulation?</em>” delusion. I’m in no way defending the way that ChatGPT answered his questions about a <em>Matrix</em>-like simulation he suspected he might be living in, or his questions about whether he could fly if he truly believed he could, etc. But the premise of this story is that ChatGPT turned a completely mentally healthy man into a dangerously disturbed mentally ill one, and it seems rather obvious that the actual story is that it fed the delusions of an already unwell person. Some real <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reefer_Madness">Reefer Madness</a></em> vibes to this.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The NYT Goes ‘Reefer Madness’ on ChatGPT’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/13/nyt-reefer-madness-chatgpt">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/06/apples_spin_on_the_personalized_siri_apple_intelligence_reset" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wef" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41991</id>
	<published>2025-06-12T23:03:59Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-13T15:59:39Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Most rank and file engineers within Apple do not believe that feature existed in an even vaguely functional state a year ago, and the first any of them ever heard of it was when they watched the keynote with the rest of us on the first day of WWDC last year.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Michael Tsai, “<a href="https://mjtsai.com/blog/2025/06/12/apples-spin-on-ai-and-ipados-multitasking/">Apple’s Spin on AI and iPadOS Multitasking</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I do want to call out that, in multiple interviews, they are kind
of setting up strawmen to knock down. They keep saying that people
say Apple is behind in AI <em>because it doesn’t have its own
chatbot</em>. To me, Apple has been clear that it has a different
strategy, and I think that strategy mostly makes sense. I have
never heard someone wish for an Apple chatbot. The issue is that
everyone can see that Apple seems behind in <em>executing</em> said
strategy, both that features didn’t ship on time and that the ones
that did ship don’t measure up to similar features from other
companies.</p>

<p>Secondly, they seem to be trying to <a href="https://mas.to/@osullivan/114662053414638681">debunk</a> <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/something_is_rotten_in_the_state_of_cupertino">John Gruber’s
claim</a> that Apple showed vaporware at the last WWDC. But
Apple’s assertion that there was actual, working software doesn’t
contradict anything Gruber wrote. He put it at level 0/4 because
there wasn’t even a live demo, just a pre-packaged video. If it
can’t be demoed to the media in a controlled setting, even calling
it “demoware” would be charitable. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vaporware">Wikipedia</a> says, “After
Dyson’s article, the word ‘vaporware’ became popular among writers
in the personal computer software industry as a way to describe
products they believed took too long to be released after their
first announcement.” Is that not exactly what happened here?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The whole “Siri, when is my mom’s flight landing?” segment of last year’s WWDC keynote definitely shouldn’t qualify as “demoware” either. It was never demoed. Whether the feature was actually running, and actually capable of doing what they said it could, even just <em>some</em> of the time along a golden path, ultimately doesn’t matter. Even the keynote video didn’t show the actual feature working. It kept cutting away from the iPhone that was purportedly performing the feature back to presenter Kelsey Peterson at every single step. Apple’s internal rules for keynote demos say that the entire feature has to be real, and capturable in a single take of video. I’ve spoken to people who’ve been in keynotes, and many more who’ve done WWDC session videos. Apple has strict rules about everything being real. That doesn’t mean they always show the feature in a single take in the final cut of the presentation, but it has to be possible, just like it would have to be in a live stage presentation. But that Siri demo in last year’s keynote is almost like a series of screenshots. We never see Peterson speak to Siri and then watch the results come in. There’s not one single shot in the whole demo that shows one action leading to the next. It’s all cut together in an unusual way for Apple keynote demos. <a href="https://developer.apple.com/videos/play/wwdc2024/101/">Go see for yourself at the 1h:22m mark</a>.</p>

<p>I spoke this week, off the record, to multiple trusted sources in Apple’s software engineering group, and none of them ever saw an internal build of iOS that had this feature before last year’s keynote. That doesn’t mean there wasn’t such a build (see next paragraph). But none of my sources ever saw one, and they found that to be exceptionally unusual, because they’re in positions where they believe that if there <em>had</em> been such a build, their teams would have had access to it. Most rank and file engineers within Apple do not believe that feature existed in an even vaguely functional state a year ago, and the first any of them ever heard of it was when they watched the keynote with the rest of us on the first day of WWDC last year.</p>

<p>But at this point, based on Federighi’s and Joswiak’s public statements (e.g. in <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/10/stern-federighi-joz">their interview with Joanna Stern</a> this week), and some other things I’ve heard from little birdies this week, I’m willing to stipulate that there was, let’s call it, “working code” for the personalized Siri feature a year ago. I can’t verify that, but I’m willing to stipulate it if only for the sake of argument, and to put to rest any notion that the feature was completely imaginary at this point one year ago, which clearly isn’t the case. At least one reason why the feature, as presented in last year’s keynote, was edited like it was is that the latency was so bad. Whatever state it was in, it couldn’t be shown in a single take. Which means that, as shown in the 2024 keynote, it broke the “rule” that demos in the new pre-recorded format should be as rigorously “real” as they would be if the demos had to be performed live on stage.</p>

<p>I’m quite certain Apple’s executives believed this feature could be shipped at some point in the iOS 18 year. It’d be crazy to announce the feature if they didn’t believe they could ship it, and Apple’s executives aren’t crazy. I’m also quite certain that eventually there <em>was</em> a truly functional implementation of the now-abandoned “v1” of the more personalized Siri, but it was unreliable with no path forward to make it reliable. (I think it was far worse than “not up to Apple’s high standards” — it was clearly unshippable.)</p>

<p>But, as Tsai notes, from our perspective it doesn’t really matter it was real, in any sense, a year ago. It’s still vaporware at this point. Vaporware doesn’t mean “completely fabricated”. It just means “promised but hasn’t shipped”. Tsai links to <a href="https://mastodon.social/@rustyshelf/114667389093029657">this Mastodon tweet from Russell Ivanovic</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“This narrative that it was vaporware is nonsense”. Craig Apple.
My guy. You announced something that never shipped. You made ads
for it. You tried to sell iPhones based on it. What’s the
difference if you had it running internally or not. Still
vaporware. Zero difference.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Also, Apple is sticking with the euphemism “in the coming year” for when we can expect to see these next-gen personalized Siri features. Gurman reported today that <a href="https://www.techmeme.com/250612/p39#a250612p39">they’re shooting for next spring</a>. I confirmed with Apple at WWDC that “in the coming year” means “in 2026”. I don’t know why they’re sticking with that euphemistic phrasing, which to many people’s ears makes it sound like <em>in the next 12 months</em>, which might include this fall. Effectively, Apple could ship this feature in December <em>2026</em> and still hit their self-imposed “in the coming year” deadline — but that phrasing has left many people with the impression that the deadline is June 2026 and maybe it’ll ship at the end of <em>this</em> year. Just say “next year” instead of “in the coming year”. It’s very obvious that this year’s WWDC keynote went back to an underpromise/overdeliver mindset. But “in the coming year” is raising some users’ hopes misleadingly.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Apple’s Spin on the Personalized Siri Apple Intelligence Reset</title></entry><entry>
	<title>‘The Good, the Bad, and the Weird of Apple’s Newest Platform Updates’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2025/06/the-good-bad-and-weird-of-apples-newest-platform-updates/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wee" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/12/the-good-the-bad-the-weird" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41990</id>
	<published>2025-06-12T22:09:08Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-12T22:09:09Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Dan Moren, writing this week at Six Colors:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>But you’ve heard about all of that, I’m sure, so we’re not going
to rehash it. Instead, let’s get personal: I’m picking out, in
my opinion, the best and worst new features of each of Apple’s
platforms. To be clear, these are my <em>completely scientific</em> and
<em>totally well-reasoned</em> expert opinions on the features that
were announced, not just some off-the-cuff reactions less than a
day later.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘The Good, the Bad, and the Weird of Apple’s Newest Platform Updates’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/12/the-good-the-bad-the-weird">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Liquid Glasslighting’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://spyglass.org/spyglasslighting/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wed" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/12/liquid-glasslighting" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41989</id>
	<published>2025-06-12T21:49:16Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-12T21:49:18Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>MG Siegler:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The underlying message that they’re trying to convey in all these
interviews is clear: <em>calm down, this isn’t a big deal, you guys
are being a little crazy</em>. And that, in turn, aims to undercut all
the reporting about <a href="https://spyglass.org/theres-no-free-lunch-at-apple/">the turmoil within Apple</a> — <em>for
<a href="https://spyglass.org/apple-ai-fail/">years</a> at this <a href="https://spyglass.org/siri-apple-ai-trouble/">point</a></em> — that has led to the
situation with Siri. Sorry, the situation which they’re implying
is not a situation. Though, I don’t know, normally when a company
<a href="https://spyglass.org/siri-shakeup/">shakes up an entire team</a>, that tends to suggest some sort
of situation. That, of course, is never mentioned. Nor would you
expect Apple — of all companies — to talk openly and candidly
about internal challenges. But that just adds to this general
wafting smell in the air.</p>

<p>The smell of bullshit.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Liquid Glasslighting’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/12/liquid-glasslighting">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Tested’ on VisionOS 26 and Behind the Scenes at the Theater Immersive Broadcast of The Talk Show Live From WWDC</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=h6SbkEC1Xb8" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wec" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/12/tested-visionos-26-tts-live" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41988</id>
	<published>2025-06-12T21:39:12Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-14T00:09:07Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Fun episode of Tested with Adam Savage and Norman Chan. The first segment goes deep on what’s new in VisionOS 26. Apple is ignoring the jokes about the platform’s relative obscurity and has obviously been heads-down on building the platform out and up. VisionOS 26 is a <em>huge</em> year-over-year upgrade. Tons of exciting stuff, and so many little things are so much better.</p>

<p>The second segment of the show features cohost Norm Chan going backstage at The Talk Show Live From WWDC on Tuesday night, to speak with Adam Lisagor about the production details of the live immersive broadcast in Theater.</p>

<p>(The YouTube version of the show is in editing now — we’ll post it as soon as it’s ready. <s>But the immersive version in Theater is available for purchase now.</s> Whoops, my bad. The immersive version, which looks significantly better than the livestream — which looked pretty good! — will be available for purchase in <a href="https://theater.sandwich.vision/">Theater</a> a few days after the 2D version hits YouTube.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Tested’ on VisionOS 26 and Behind the Scenes at the Theater Immersive Broadcast of The Talk Show Live From WWDC’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/12/tested-visionos-26-tts-live">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Jason Snell on WWDC 2025: ‘Apple Intelligence Shifts Gears’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2025/06/apple-intelligence-shifts-gears/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/web" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/12/snell-wwdc-2025" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41987</id>
	<published>2025-06-12T16:00:48Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-12T21:52:44Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jason Snell:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>After last year, Apple could’ve been forgiven for wanting to
soft-pedal this year’s Apple Intelligence announcements and
regroup. It didn’t do that, nor did it double down on last year.
Instead, it’s chosen a middle ground — a bit safe and familiar
but also a place where Apple can feel a bit more like itself. In
the long run, it needs to get this right. In the short term, maybe
it should focus on meeting its users where they are, rather than
pretending to be something it’s not.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Agree with Snell’s take completely, I do.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Jason Snell on WWDC 2025: ‘Apple Intelligence Shifts Gears’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/12/snell-wwdc-2025">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>MacOS 26 Tahoe Drops Support for Some Intel-Based Macs, and Will Be the Last to Support Intel Macs at All</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://512pixels.net/2025/06/wwdc25-macos-tahoe-compatibility/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wea" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/11/macos-26-intel-support" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41986</id>
	<published>2025-06-11T19:55:54Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-12T21:52:31Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Stephen Hackett has a list of the Intel Macs that MacOS 26 Tahoe supports, and the ones they’re dropping support for this year. </p>

<p>Apple has gone through three CPU architecture transitions in the Mac’s history:</p>

<ul>
<li>68K to PowerPC starting in 1994</li>
<li>PowerPC to Intel starting in 2006</li>
<li>Intel to Apple Silicon, starting 2020</li>
</ul>

<p>With the 68K–PowerPC transition, they supported 68K Macs through Mac OS 8.1, which was released in January 1998. With the PowerPC–Intel transition, they only supported PowerPC Macs for two Mac OS X versions, Mac OS X 10.4 Tiger (which initially shipped PowerPC-only in 2005) and 10.5 Leopard in October 2007. The next release, 10.6 Snow Leopard in August 2009, was Intel-only. (Mac OS X dropped to a roughly two-year big-release schedule during the initial years after the iPhone, when the company prioritized engineering resources on iOS. It’s easy to take for granted that today’s Apple has every single platform on an annual cadence.)</p>

<p>With next year’s version going Apple Silicon-only, they’ll have supported Intel Macs for five major MacOS releases after the debut of the first Apple Silicon Macs. I think that’s about the best anyone could have hoped for.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘MacOS 26 Tahoe Drops Support for Some Intel-Based Macs, and Will Be the Last to Support Intel Macs at All’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/11/macos-26-intel-support">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Joanna Stern With Craig Federighi and Greg Joswiak: ‘Apple Executives Defend Apple Intelligence, Siri and AI Strategy’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.wsj.com/video/series/joanna-stern-personal-technology/apple-executives-defend-apple-intelligence-siri-and-ai-strategy/A7F62EE4-E4F5-4E5D-969A-22644536A47B" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/we9" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/10/stern-federighi-joz" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41985</id>
	<published>2025-06-10T22:10:26Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-14T17:27:26Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Tight 7-minute video at the WSJ (and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NTLk53h7u_k">also at YouTube</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple’s AI rollout has been rocky, from Siri delays to underwhelming Apple Intelligence features. WSJ’s Joanna Stern sits down with software chief Craig Federighi and marketing head Greg Joswiak to talk about the future of AI at Apple — and what the heck happened to that smarter Siri.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wCEkK1YzqBo">Here’s the full 24-minute interview</a>. Just an excellent job by Stern.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Joanna Stern With Craig Federighi and Greg Joswiak: ‘Apple Executives Defend Apple Intelligence, Siri and AI Strategy’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/10/stern-federighi-joz">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Apple Retreats’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stratechery.com/2025/apple-retreats/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/we8" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/10/apple-retreats" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41984</id>
	<published>2025-06-10T15:45:30Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-10T15:47:32Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Ben Thompson:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>To that end, while I understand why many people were underwhelmed by this WWDC, particularly in comparison to <a href="https://stratechery.com/2025/google-i-o-the-search-funnel-product-possibilities/">the AI extravaganza that was Google I/O</a>, I think it was one of the more encouraging Apple keynotes in a long time. Apple is a company that went too far in too many areas, and needed to retreat. Focusing on things only Apple can do is a good thing; empowering developers and depending on partners is a good thing; giving even the appearance of thoughtful thinking with regards to the App Store (it’s a low bar!) is a good thing. Of course we want and are excited by tech companies promising the future; what is a prerequisite is delivering in the present, and it’s a sign of progress that Apple retreated to nothing more than that.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Apple Retreats’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/10/apple-retreats">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple’s Introduction to Liquid Glass</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2025/06/apple-introduces-a-delightful-and-elegant-new-software-design/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/we7" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/09/apple-intro-liquid-glass" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41983</id>
	<published>2025-06-10T01:16:39Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-12T21:51:23Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>I’ve got iOS 26 installed on a spare phone already, and I like the new UI a lot. In addition to just plain looking cool, Apple has tackled a lot of longstanding minor irritants.</p>

<p>For example, the iOS contextual menu for text selections — the one with Cut/Copy/Paste. For years now there have been a lot of other useful commands in there, including “Share…” at the very end. But to get to the extra commands, you had to tediously swipe, swipe, swipe. Now, with one tap you can expand the whole thing into a vertical menu. Elegant.</p>

<p>There’s some stuff in MacOS 26 Tahoe I already don’t like, like putting needless icons next to almost every single menu item. But overall my first impression of Liquid Glass on MacOS is good too. It’s fun, and <a href="https://mastodon.social/@marioguzman/114656280801707003">lots of little details are nice — joyful <em>and</em> useful</a> in an old-school Mac way.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple’s Introduction to Liquid Glass’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/09/apple-intro-liquid-glass">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Tahoe Flips the Finder Icon</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://512pixels.net/2025/06/wwdc25-macos-tahoe-breaks-decades-of-finder-history/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/we6" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/09/tahoe-flips-the-finder-icon" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41982</id>
	<published>2025-06-10T01:06:28Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-12T21:50:00Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Stephen Hackett, noting the biggest news of the day:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Something jumped out at me in the macOS Tahoe segment of the WWDC keynote today: the Finder icon is reversed. […]</p>

<p>The Big Sur Finder icon has been with us ever since, and I hope Apple reverses course here.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’m obviously joking about this being the biggest news of the day, but it really does feel just plain wrong to swap the dark/light sides. The Finder icon is more than an icon, it’s a logo, a brand.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Tahoe Flips the Finder Icon’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/09/tahoe-flips-the-finder-icon">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://detailspro.app?utm_campaign=dfwwdc25" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/we5" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/06/detailspro_1" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.41981</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-06-09T15:19:21Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-09T15:19:21Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>With WWDC25 bringing the biggest design overhaul since iOS 7, you’ll want to prototype your new interfaces fast. DetailsPro lets you build real SwiftUI layouts directly on your iPhone — no Mac required, no code needed. Mock up your WWDC-inspired designs during coffee breaks. Export clean SwiftUI code straight to Xcode when you’re ready. While everyone else is still thinking, you’re already building. Free to use, with pro features if you need them. Perfect for the design renaissance.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘DetailsPro’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/06/detailspro_1">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] DetailsPro</title></entry><entry>
	<title>The Talk Show Live From WWDC 2025: Tuesday at 7pm PT in San Jose</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://ti.to/daringfireball/the-talk-show-live-from-wwdc-2025" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/we4" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/08/the-talk-show-live-tickets-2025" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41980</id>
	<published>2025-06-09T01:54:37Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-09T01:54:38Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Location:</strong> The California Theatre, San Jose <br />
<strong>Showtime:</strong> Tuesday, 10 June 2025, 7pm PT (Doors open 6pm) <br />
<strong>Special Guest(s):</strong> <em>Indeed</em> <br />
<strong>Price:</strong> $50</p>

<p>A different type of show this year, and I’m excited for it. If you can make it, you should come. You’ll even enjoy the prelude, mingling with fellow DF readers and listeners.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Talk Show Live From WWDC 2025: Tuesday at 7pm PT in San Jose’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/08/the-talk-show-live-tickets-2025">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>An Eve of WWDC Spitball Theory on the Rumored New ‘Games’ App</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://9to5mac.com/2024/10/22/apple-new-app-store-like-app-games/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/we3" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/08/apple-games-app-store-spitball" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41979</id>
	<published>2025-06-09T01:32:47Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-09T15:57:40Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Filipe Espósito, in a scoop for 9to5Mac all the way back in October:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>9to5Mac has learned details about the new project from reliable
sources familiar with the matter. The new app combines
functionality from the App Store and Game Center in one place. The
gaming app is not expected to replace Game Center. In fact, it
will integrate with the user’s Game Center profile.</p>

<p>According to our sources, the app will have multiple tabs,
including a “Play Now” tab, a tab for the user’s games, friends,
and more. In Play Now, users will find editorial content and game
suggestions. The app will also show things like challenges,
leaderboards, and achievements. Games from both the App Store and
Apple Arcade will be featured in the new store.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Even before <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/05/27/ios-19-gaming-app/">Mark Gurman corroborated this report</a> last week, I’ve had a spitball theory about what it might mean. Perhaps this is about more than having one app (Games) for finding and installing games, and another (App Store) for finding and installing apps. It could signal that Apple is poised to establish different policies for apps and games. Like, what if games still use the longstanding 70/30 commission split (with small business developers getting 85/15), but non-game apps get a new reduced rate? Say, 80/20 or even 85/15 right off the top, with small business developers and second-year subscriptions going to 90/10?</p>

<p>Having separate store apps for apps and games would help establish the idea that games and apps are two entirely different markets. Thus: two different stores?</p>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> <a href="https://spyglass.org/apple-gaming-app-store/">MG Siegler offered the same spitball</a> — back on May 28. Great minds think alike.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘An Eve of WWDC Spitball Theory on the Rumored New ‘Games’ App’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/08/apple-games-app-store-spitball">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Breaking Down Why Apple TVs Are Privacy Advocates’ Go-To Streaming Device</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2025/06/all-the-ways-apple-tv-boxes-do-and-mostly-dont-track-you/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/we2" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/08/apple-tv-privacy" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41978</id>
	<published>2025-06-09T01:24:06Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-09T01:54:57Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Scharon Harding, writing at Ars Technica:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Just disconnect your TV from the Internet and use an Apple
TV box.”</p>

<p>That’s the common guidance you’ll hear from Ars readers for those
seeking the joys of streaming without giving up too much privacy.
Based on our research and the experts we’ve consulted, that advice
is pretty solid, as Apple TVs offer significantly more privacy
than other streaming hardware providers.</p>

<p>But how private are Apple TV boxes, really? Apple TVs don’t use
automatic content recognition (ACR, a user-tracking technology
leveraged by nearly all smart TVs and streaming devices), but
could that change? And what about the software that Apple TV users
do use — could those apps provide information about you to
advertisers or Apple?</p>

<p>In this article, we’ll delve into what makes the Apple TV’s
privacy stand out and examine whether users should expect the
limited ads and enhanced privacy to last forever.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>tvOS is perhaps Apple’s least-talked-about platform. (It surely has orders of magnitude more users than VisionOS, but VisionOS gets talked about because it’s so audacious.) But it might be their platform that’s the furthest ahead of its competition. Not because tvOS is insanely great, but it’s at least pretty good, and every other streaming TV platform seems to be in a race to make real <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YqQ6D0Bu-a8">the future TV interface from <em>Idiocracy</em></a>. It’s not just that they’re bad interfaces with deplorable privacy, it’s that they’re outright <em>against</em> the user.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Breaking Down Why Apple TVs Are Privacy Advocates’ Go-To Streaming Device’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/08/apple-tv-privacy">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple Researchers Publish Paper on the Limits of Reasoning Models (Showing That They’re Not Really ‘Reasoning’ at All)</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://machinelearning.apple.com/research/illusion-of-thinking" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/we1" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/08/apple-research-lrms" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41977</id>
	<published>2025-06-09T01:08:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-09T01:09:13Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Parshin Shojaee, Iman Mirzadeh, Keivan Alizadeh, Maxwell Horton, Samy Bengio, and Mehrdad Farajtabar, from Apple’s Machine Learning Research team:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Recent generations of frontier language models have introduced
Large Reasoning Models (LRMs) that generate detailed thinking
processes before providing answers. While these models demonstrate
improved performance on reasoning benchmarks, their fundamental
capabilities, scaling properties, and limitations remain
insufficiently understood. [...] Through extensive experimentation
across diverse puzzles, we show that frontier LRMs face a complete
accuracy collapse beyond certain complexities. Moreover, they
exhibit a counterintuitive scaling limit: their reasoning effort
increases with problem complexity up to a point, then declines
despite having an adequate token budget. By comparing LRMs with
their standard LLM counterparts under equivalent inference
compute, we identify three performance regimes: (1) low-complexity
tasks where standard models surprisingly outperform LRMs, (2)
medium-complexity tasks where additional thinking in LRMs
demonstrates advantage, and (3) high-complexity tasks where both
models experience complete collapse. We found that LRMs have
limitations in exact computation: they fail to use explicit
algorithms and reason inconsistently across puzzles. We also
investigate the reasoning traces in more depth, studying the
patterns of explored solutions and analyzing the models’
computational behavior, shedding light on their strengths,
limitations, and ultimately raising crucial questions about their
true reasoning capabilities.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The full paper is quite readable, but today was my travel day and I haven’t had time to dig in. And <a href="https://ml-site.cdn-apple.com/papers/the-illusion-of-thinking.pdf">it’s a PDF</a> so I couldn’t read it on my phone. (Coincidence or not that this dropped on the eve of WWDC?)</p>

<p>My basic understanding after a skim is that the paper shows, or at least strongly suggests, that LRMs don’t “reason” at all. They just use vastly more complex pattern-matching than LLMs. The result is that LRMs effectively overthink on simple problems, outperform LLMs on mid-complexity puzzles, and fail in the same exact way LLMs do on high-complexity tasks and puzzles.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Researchers Publish Paper on the Limits of Reasoning Models (Showing That They’re Not Really ‘Reasoning’ at All)’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/08/apple-research-lrms">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/06/gurman_liquid_glass_terrible_analogy" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/we0" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41976</id>
	<published>2025-06-08T16:09:29Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-08T18:20:08Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">If it takes Apple as long to have its own competitive LLMs as it did to have its own competitive web browser, I suspect they’ll soon be paying to use the LLMs that are owned and controlled by others, not charging the others for the privilege of reaching Apple’s platform users.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/newsletters/2025-06-08/apple-s-liquid-glass-ios-26-software-redesign-to-hint-at-20th-anniversary-iphone-mbnm2u0d?cmpid=BBD060825_POWERON">Mark Gurman, in his eve-of-WWDC Power On column at Bloomberg</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The Liquid Glass interface is going to be the most exciting part
of this year’s developer conference. It will also be a bit of a
distraction from the reality facing Apple: The company is behind
in artificial intelligence, and WWDC will do little to change
that. Instead, Apple is making its successful operating system
franchise more capable and sleek — even as others move on to more
groundbreaking AI-centric interfaces.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Perhaps the first major hint that Apple was moving toward fluidity in the UI was the Dynamic Island, which doesn’t merely expand and contract as it changes shape, but rather appears to <em>flow</em>, <a href="https://www.lux.camera/physicality-the-new-age-of-ui/#:~:text=The%20Dynamic%20Island%20is%20a%20stark%2C%20graphic%20interface%20that%20behaves%20like%20an%20interactive%2C%20viscous%20liquid">with a pleasant viscosity</a>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The best analogy for Apple right now might be the car industry.
Apple produces the best gas cars on the road (its operating
systems) and is making them even more upscale. It has rolled out a
hybrid (Apple Intelligence), but it’s <a href="https://archive.ph/o/AKlk9/https://www.bloomberg.com/news/features/2025-05-18/how-apple-intelligence-and-siri-ai-went-so-wrong">struggling to make</a> a
true all-electric vehicle (unlike companies such as OpenAI and
Alphabet Inc.’s Google).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is such a terrible analogy. If you buy an EV, you use it <em>instead of</em> your old gas-powered car. There’s nothing from OpenAI or Google that allows you to not use a conventional device — phone, tablet, or PC. The only way to use ChatGPT, or Gemini, or <a href="https://deepmind.google/models/veo/">Google’s rather amazing Veo 3</a> video generation tool, is using a phone or computer running iOS, MacOS, Android, Windows, or Linux. Gurman’s analogy would only work if the way you got around in an EV was to put it in the back of a gas-powered flatbed <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YfJ3QxJYsw8">truck</a>.</p>

<p>Gas-powered vehicles are probably going away. I sure hope they do. But cars and trucks aren’t going away. A better analogy is that AI is doing to today’s dominant OSes what web browsers did to Windows in the late 1990s. They’re adding new interactive layers atop the old. Windows didn’t go away. Microsoft still makes tons of money from Windows today. But Windows’s primacy as a platform went away. And: Microsoft pivoted quickly in the face of Netscape and the web’s threat, and created Internet Explorer, which squashed Netscape, and became, for at least a decade, the preeminent web browser. It was essential for Apple to create Safari/WebKit for Mac OS X to thrive. If Apple hadn’t succeeded with WebKit on Mac OS X they wouldn’t have had their own first-class web rendering engine to adapt for a 3.5-inch touchscreen in 2007. The iPhone without the real web wouldn’t have been the iPhone. And the only reason the original iPhone had the real web is that Apple owned and controlled Safari and WebKit.</p>

<p>What Apple, I think, needs for iOS and MacOS is the AI equivalent of what Safari and WebKit were for the web two decades ago. The <a href="https://www.asymco.com/2011/01/17/the-cook-doctrine/">oft-cited Cook Doctrine</a> says “we need to own and control the primary technologies behind the products we make.” 25 years ago it was obvious that web browsers and rendering engines were primary technologies. Apple certainly couldn’t afford back then to continue to be dependent upon Microsoft for the Mac version of IE, nor on open source cross-platform browsers like Firefox that would never feel native on the Mac (or, more importantly, on future Apple platforms). But Safari and WebKit were, if you think about it, late. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2003/01/safari">They were announced at Macworld Expo in January 2003</a> (just five months after the debut of this website). Netscape’s blockbuster IPO was in August 1995, over seven years prior. The entire dot-com bubble and bust took place before Safari shipped. The Mac, and thus Apple, made do with non-Apple browsers in those intervening years — browsers that were all some mix of non-native clunky UI, slow, incompatible (with Windows IE), ugly (e.g. IE text rendering on Mac OS X), and often downright unstable. (And application crashes on classic Mac OS would often bring down the entire system.)</p>

<p>The concern for Apple today is that they’re in trouble if it takes six or seven years for them to get to their Safari/WebKit moment for AI. Things are moving faster with AI today than they were with the web in the 1990s. At the peak of Netscape mania in 1995, there were many who believed Netscape would topple Microsoft. At the time Netscape founder Marc Andreessen <a href="https://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Marc_Andreessen">proclaimed</a> that Netscape would reduce Windows to “a poorly debugged set of device drivers.” That obviously didn’t happen. But perhaps not just <em>a</em> but <em>the</em> reason why that didn’t happen is that Microsoft quickly built and shipped a better browser than Netscape’s. They didn’t just build a browser into Windows, they built a <em>better</em> browser into Windows. And they made a better browser for the Mac too. If it had taken Microsoft until 2003 (when Apple debuted Safari) to ship IE, computing platform history may well be very different.</p>

<p>iOS today is the closest to what Windows was circa 1995. iOS doesn’t have Windows’s 95 percent market share, but the iPhone has some sort of monopoly <em>profit</em> share in mobile device sales. And iOS is plainly dominant. That’s why there’s all this <em>Sturm und Drang</em> surrounding Apple’s App Store commissions and iron-fisted control over all iOS software. After the announcement last year of OpenAI as a partner for “world knowledge” in Apple Intelligence — and, a year later, they’re still the only partner — Wayne Ma at The Information reported that Apple wasn’t paying a cent for this integration, and that the plan <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2024/06/13/ma-apple-openai">was for OpenAI to eventually begin paying Apple in a revenue sharing deal</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Neither Apple nor OpenAI are paying each other to integrate
ChatGPT into the iPhone, according to a person with knowledge of
the deal. Instead, OpenAI hopes greater exposure on iPhones will
help it sell a paid version of ChatGPT, which costs around $20 a
month for individuals. Apple would take its 30% cut of these
subscriptions as is customary for in-app purchases.</p>

<p>Sometime in the future, Apple hopes to strike revenue-sharing
agreements with AI partners in which it gets a cut of the revenue
generated from integrating their chatbots with the iPhone,
according to Bloomberg, which first reported details of the deal.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That sounds a lot like the revenue sharing deal Apple has with Google for search in Safari — a deal (which is at some degree of risk <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/07/eddy-cue-safari-ai">from Google’s own antitrust problems</a>) that now results in <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/10/27/google-aggregate-search-default">Google paying Apple over $20 billion per year</a> for the traffic Safari sends to Google Search.</p>

<p>In hindsight, we now know that web browsers, in and of themselves, don’t generate any money directly. Someone was going to give a good one away free and now almost all of them are free of charge. But that doesn’t mean it isn’t essential for a platform to own and control its own browser. Web search, it turns out, is where the money is on the World Wide Web. Not just <em>some</em> money but an almost unfathomable amount of money. Web search is not primary technology for Apple’s platforms. But because they own and control Safari and WebKit, and Safari and WebKit are <em>very good</em> (so that most of Apple’s customers use them), Apple is in a position to profit very handsomely from web search, even though it doesn’t even have a search engine to speak of. Apple’s net annual profit the last few years has been around $95 billion. If we assume Google’s $20B/year traffic acquisition revenue sharing payments to Apple are mostly profit, that means somewhere between 20–25 percent of all Apple’s profit comes from that deal.</p>

<p>So are LLMs more like browsers (platforms need to own and control their own, but they won’t make money from them directly) or like web search (dominant platforms like Apple’s don’t need their own, but Apple can profit handsomely by charging for integration with their platforms)?</p>

<p>I think the answer is somewhere in between. Browsers are essential to personal computing platforms because they run on-device. Web search isn’t essential to own and control because it runs in the cloud, but exists only to serve users running devices. LLMs run both locally and in the cloud. If it takes Apple as long to have its own competitive LLMs as it did to have its own competitive web browser, I suspect they’ll soon be paying to use the LLMs that are owned and controlled by others, not charging the others for the privilege of reaching Apple’s platform users. No simple analogy captures this dynamic. But the threat is palpable.</p>

<p>I will say, though, “Liquid Glass” sounds cool.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Gurman Says New UI Is Named ‘Liquid Glass’ (and Makes a Terrible Analogy Regarding Apple’s Risk With Falling Behind on AI)</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Bill Atkinson Dies From Cancer at 74</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.facebook.com/story.php?story_fbid=10238073579963378&amp;id=1378467145&amp;_rdr" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wdv" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/07/bill-atkinson-rip" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41971</id>
	<published>2025-06-07T21:15:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-08T04:44:58Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>From his family, on Atkinson’s Facebook page:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We regret to write that our beloved husband, father, and
stepfather Bill Atkinson passed away on the night of Thursday,
June 5th, 2025, due to pancreatic cancer. He was at home in
Portola Valley in his bed, surrounded by family. We will miss him
greatly, and he will be missed by many of you, too. He was a
remarkable person, and the world will be forever different because
he lived in it. He was fascinated by consciousness, and as he has
passed on to a different level of consciousness, we wish him a
journey as meaningful as the one it has been to have him in our
lives. He is survived by his wife, two daughters, stepson,
stepdaughter, two brothers, four sisters, and dog, Poppy.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>One of the great heroes in not just Apple history, but computer history. If you want to cheer yourself up, go to Andy Hertzfeld’s Folklore.org site and (re-)read all the entries about Atkinson. Here’s just one, with <a href="https://folklore.org/Round_Rects_Are_Everywhere.html">Steve Jobs inspiring Atkinson to invent the roundrect</a>. Here’s another (surely near and dear to my friend <a href="https://inessential.com/2002/06/25/deleting_code.html">Brent Simmons’s heart</a>) with <a href="https://www.folklore.org/Negative_2000_Lines_Of_Code.html">this kicker of a closing line</a>: “I’m not sure how the managers reacted to that, but I do know that after a couple more weeks, they stopped asking Bill to fill out the form, and he gladly complied.”</p>

<p>Some of his code and algorithms are among the most efficient and elegant ever devised. The original Macintosh team was chock full of geniuses, but Atkinson might have been the most essential to making the impossible possible under the extraordinary technical limitations of that hardware. <a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=bill+atkinson+dithering+algorithm">Atkinson’s genius dithering algorithm</a> was my inspiration for the name of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atkinson_dithering">Dithering</a>, my podcast with Ben Thompson. I find that effect beautiful and love that it continues to prove useful, like on the <a href="https://play.date/">Playdate</a> and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2016/06/10/bitcam">apps like BitCam</a>.</p>

<p>In addition to his low-level contributions like QuickDraw, Atkinson was also <a href="https://www.folklore.org/MacPaint_Evolution.html">the creator of MacPaint</a> (which to this day stands as the model for bitmap image editors — Photoshop, I would argue, was conceptually derived directly from MacPaint) and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2014/06/17/hypercard">HyperCard</a> (“<a href="https://www.folklore.org/Joining_Apple_Computer.html">inspired by a mind-expanding LSD journey in 1985</a>”), the influence of which cannot be overstated.</p>

<p>I say this with no hyperbole: Bill Atkinson may well have been the best computer programmer who ever lived. Without question, he’s on the short list. What a man, what a mind, what gifts to the world he left us.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Bill Atkinson Dies From Cancer at 74’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/07/bill-atkinson-rip">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Swift 6 Productivity in the Sudden Age of LLM-Assisted Programming</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mister.computer/@kyle/114608923901892223" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wdz" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/07/swift-6-llms" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41975</id>
	<published>2025-06-07T21:10:30Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-07T21:38:51Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Kyle Hughes, in a brief thread on Mastodon last week:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>At work I’m developing a new iOS app on a small team alongside a
small Android team doing the same. We are getting lapped to an
unfathomable degree because of how productive they are with
Kotlin, Compose, and Cursor. They are able to support all the way
back to Android 10 (2019) with the latest features; we are
targeting iOS 16 (2022) and have to make huge sacrifices (e.g
Observable, parameter packs in generics on types). Swift 6 makes a
mockery of LLMs. It is almost untenable.</p>

<p>This wasn’t the case in the 2010s. The quality and speed of
implementation of every iOS app I have ever worked on, in teams of
every size, absolutely cooked Android. [...] There has never been
a worse time in the history of computers to launch, and require,
fundamental and sweeping changes to languages and frameworks.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The problem isn’t necessarily inherent to the design of the Swift language, but that throughout Swift’s evolution Apple has introduced sweeping changes with each major new version. (Secondarily, that compared to other languages, a lower percentage of Swift code that’s written is open source, and thus available to LLMs for use in training corpuses.) Swift was introduced at WWDC 2014 (that one <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/07/long-lost-df-post">again</a>) and last year Apple introduced Swift 6. That’s a lot of major version changes for a programming language in one decade. There were pros and cons to Apple’s approach over the last decade. But now there’s a new, and major con: because Swift 6 only debuted last year, there’s no great corpus of Swift 6 code for LLMs to have trained on, and so they’re just not as good — from what I gather, not <em>nearly</em> as good — at generating Swift 6 code as they are at generating code in other languages, and for other programming frameworks like React.</p>

<p>The new features in Swift 6 are for the better, but, in a group chat, my friend <a href="https://bitsplitting.org/">Daniel Jalkut</a> described them to me as, “I think Swift 6 changed very little, but the little it changed has huge sweeping implications. Akin to the switch from <a href="https://medium.com/@yenatlij/memory-management-in-objective-c-mrr-and-arc-473cb769fb8d">MRR to ARC</a>.” That’s a reference to the change in Objective-C memory management from manual retain/release (MRR) to automatic reference counting (ARC) back in 2011. Once ARC came out, no one wanted to be writing new code using manual retain/release (which was both tedious and a common source of memory-leak bugs). But if LLMs had been around in 2011/2012, they’d only have been able to generate MRR Objective-C code because that’s what all the existing code they’d been trained on used.</p>

<p>I’m quite certain everyone at Apple who ought to be concerned about this <em>is</em> concerned about it. The question is, do they have solutions ready to be announced next week? This whole area — language, frameworks, and tooling in the LLM era — is top of mind for me heading into WWDC next week.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Swift 6 Productivity in the Sudden Age of LLM-Assisted Programming’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/07/swift-6-llms">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Thomas Ptacek: ‘My AI Skeptic Friends Are All Nuts’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://fly.io/blog/youre-all-nuts/?ueid=4b93173967d7dc762529a10418e85007" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wdy" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/07/ptacek-ai-skeptic-friends-are-nuts" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41974</id>
	<published>2025-06-07T20:28:24Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-07T20:28:25Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Thomas Ptacek:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>LLMs can write a large fraction of all the tedious code you’ll
ever need to write. And most code on most projects is tedious.
LLMs drastically reduce the number of things you’ll ever need to
Google. They look things up themselves. Most importantly, they
don’t get tired; they’re immune to inertia.</p>

<p>Think of anything you wanted to build but didn’t. You tried to
home in on some first steps. If you’d been in the limerent
phase of a new programming language, you’d have started
writing. But you weren’t, so you put it off, for a day, a year,
or your whole career.</p>

<p>I can feel my blood pressure rising thinking of all the
bookkeeping and Googling and dependency drama of a new project. An
LLM can be instructed to just figure all that shit out. Often, it
will drop you precisely at that golden moment where shit almost
works, and development means tweaking code and immediately seeing
things work better. That dopamine hit is why I code.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Ptacek says he mostly writes in Go and Python, and his essay doesn’t even mention Swift. But the whole essay is worth keeping in mind ahead of WWDC. There is no aspect of the AI revolution where Apple, right now today, is further behind than agentic LLM programming. (Swift Assist, <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2024/06/apple-empowers-developers-and-fuels-innovation-with-new-tools-and-resources/">announced</a> and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/15/swift-assist-voorhees">even demoed</a> last year at WWDC, would have been a first step in this direction, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/13/whither-swift-assist">but it never shipped</a>, even in beta.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Thomas Ptacek: ‘My AI Skeptic Friends Are All Nuts’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/07/ptacek-ai-skeptic-friends-are-nuts">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>WorkOS</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://workos.com/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wdx" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/07/workos" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41973</id>
	<published>2025-06-07T19:36:19Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-07T19:36:20Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to WorkOS for sponsoring last week at DF. Modern authentication should be seamless and secure. WorkOS makes it easy to integrate features like MFA, SSO, and RBAC. Whether you’re replacing passwords, stopping fraud, or adding enterprise auth, WorkOS can help you build frictionless auth that scales.</p>

<p>New features they launched just last month include:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://workos.com/blog/workos-connect?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025">WorkOS Connect</a> — “Sign in with [Your App]”</li>
<li><a href="https://workos.com/blog/vault?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025">WorkOS Vault</a> — Encryption Key Management (EKM) and Bring-Your-Own-Key (BYOK)</li>
<li><a href="https://workos.com/blog/custom-objects?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025">AuthKit Integrations</a> — Native support for several new identity providers including LinkedIn, Slack, GitLab, BitBucket, Intuit, and more.</li>
</ul>

<p>Future-proof your authentication stack with the identity layer trusted by OpenAI, Cursor, Perplexity, and Vercel.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘WorkOS’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/07/workos">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>A Long Lost Never-Published DF Post From 2014</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2014/06/01/lefsetz" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wdw" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/07/long-lost-df-post" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41972</id>
	<published>2025-06-07T19:29:27Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-09T20:32:15Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>I don’t use the web interface to <a href="https://movabletype.org/">Movable Type</a>, my moribund-but-works-just-great CMS, very often. But I was using it today and noticed something odd. Next to the small-text metadata that says I’ve written 35,086 entries in total, it said I had one draft. One. I don’t use the drafts feature in Movable Type — my drafts are stored locally as text files in BBEdit or unpublished posts in MarsEdit. I didn’t recall <em>ever</em> saving a draft in Movable Type, but, I thought to myself, I probably did it from my phone — which is the one device where I do publish and edit posts through the MT web interface because (to my knowledge) there’s no equivalent of MarsEdit for iOS.</p>

<p>It was a Linked List post pointing to <a href="https://lefsetz.com/wordpress/2014/05/29/beats-deal/">Bob Lefsetz’s reaction</a> to the <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2014/05/28Apple-to-Acquire-Beats-Music-Beats-Electronics/">then-new Beats acquisition by Apple</a> for $3 billion, which was considered a lot of money for an acquisition at the time. The blockquote wasn’t fully Markdown-formatted yet — which is sort of tedious for me on the phone, but a single keyboard shortcut in either BBEdit or MarsEdit on my Mac. That’s probably why I left it as a draft. So, just now, I finished the formatting, and changed it from draft to published. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2014/06/01/lefsetz">Voila</a> — a post I wrote on 1 June 2014 that hadn’t been published until a few minutes ago. I suspect many of you will think Lefsetz’s 2014 remarks on Tim Cook ring more true today than they did then. Others (I’m more in this camp) look at Lefsetz’s 2014 remarks as more than a little absurd — the only mark Jimmy Iovine left at Apple was the record for being <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_p8AsQhaVKI&amp;t=6480s">the least prepared executive ever to appear on stage in a keynote</a>. He was like Biden at the debate up there.</p>

<p>Lending strong credence to my theory that this forgotten draft was created on my phone is that 1 June 2014 was <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2014/06/wwdc_2014_prelude">the Sunday before WWDC 2014</a>, when I’d have been travelling, and thus using my phone for posting. Funny coincidence that I happened to notice it today, on the cusp of WWDC 2025.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘A Long Lost Never-Published DF Post From 2014’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/07/long-lost-df-post">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>You Can Recharge Apple’s MagSafe Battery Pack Without a Lightning Cable</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/04/apple-iphone-air-battery-case-or-pack" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wdu" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/07/you-can-recharge-apples-magsafe-battery-pack-without-a-lightning-cable" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41970</id>
	<published>2025-06-07T18:29:06Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-07T20:19:56Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>A brief follow-up to my <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/04/apple-iphone-air-battery-case-or-pack">love letter to Apple’s discontinued MagSafe Battery Pack</a> this week. I wrote:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>They’re the only Lightning devices left in my life and they’re so
good I’m happy to still keep one Lightning cable in my travel bag
to use them.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Among its other unique bits of cleverness, Apple’s MagSafe Battery Pack supports another cool feature: when attached to your phone, you can plug the charging cable into the phone, and after the phone gets to 100 percent charge, the phone will recharge the connected battery pack. So, if you own a MagSafe Battery Pack, you can recharge it even if you don’t have a Lightning cable handy. Just attach it to your iPhone and plug your USB-C cable into the phone, not the battery pack. I’m not aware of any other battery packs that support this.</p>

<p>That said, I still keep that one Lightning cable in my travel bag for the MagSafe Battery Pack because I want to be able to charge it whenever I want. Like, say, if I want to leave it behind, recharging, while I go elsewhere with my iPhone. Also, I like using the MagSafe Battery Pack as my bedside MagSafe charger. I like being able to check my phone from bed without worrying about a cable. In fact, I use one of my MagSafe Battery Packs as my bedside charger at home, not just while travelling.</p>

<p>Such a great little device. Really hope they make a sequel.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘You Can Recharge Apple’s MagSafe Battery Pack Without a Lightning Cable’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/07/you-can-recharge-apples-magsafe-battery-pack-without-a-lightning-cable">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Turns Out, Since 2023, You Can Use WhatsApp Across Multiple Phones</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.whatsapp.com/one-whatsapp-account-now-across-multiple-phones" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wdt" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/07/whatsapp-phone-as-linked-device" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41969</id>
	<published>2025-06-07T18:21:29Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-08T19:14:37Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>WhatsApp, on their official blog back in April 2023:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Last year, we introduced the ability for users globally to
<a href="https://engineering.fb.com/2021/07/14/security/whatsapp-multi-device/">message seamlessly across all their devices</a>, while
maintaining the same level of privacy and security.</p>

<p>Today, we’re improving our multi-device offering further by
<em>introducing the ability to use the same WhatsApp account on
multiple phones</em>.</p>

<p>A feature highly requested by users, now you can link your phone
as one of up to four additional devices, the same as when you link
with WhatsApp on <a href="https://web.whatsapp.com/">web browsers</a>, <a href="https://www.whatsapp.com/download">tablets and desktops</a>.
Each linked phone connects to WhatsApp independently, ensuring
that your personal messages, media, and calls are end-to-end
encrypted, and if your primary device is inactive for a long
period, we automatically log you out of all companion devices.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>When I wrote about WhatsApp <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/02/whatsapp-for-ipad">finally shipping for iPad earlier this week</a>, I mentioned that you couldn’t use a secondary phone as a linked device to your primary phone. That used to be true, but obviously, I missed that this changed two years ago. Glad to know it. I’ve already added my Android burner and my spare iPhone that I use for summer iOS betas. <a href="https://faq.whatsapp.com/1317564962315842/?cms_platform=android">WhatsApp has a support document on linking devices</a> that explains the somewhat hidden way you do this with a secondary phone. My thanks to several readers who pointed me to this.</p>

<p>This makes it seem all the more spiteful, though, that Meta didn’t allow the iPhone version of WhatsApp to run on iPads (like they do with the still-iPhone-only Instagram app). I heard from a little birdie this week — second- or maybe even third-hand, so take it with a grain of salt — that Meta had this WhatsApp for iPad version ready to go for a while, and has been more or less sitting on an iPad version of Instagram, as a couple negotiating chits with Apple. Negotiating for what, I don’t know. But if that’s true, perhaps some (<a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/04/meta-and-yandexs-local-mess-exploit-seemingly-only-works-on-android">but definitely not all</a>) of the ice has thawed between the two companies. I don’t see it happening, but it sure would get a big audience response if Instagram for iPad got some sort of announcement during the WWDC keynote, perhaps as part of an “<em>iPadOS is now a fuller, more complete, computing experience than ever</em>” segment.</p>

<p>One other oddity I encountered, when adding my Android phone as a linked device: by design, <a href="https://faq.whatsapp.com/5550163238402916">there is no way to sign out of WhatsApp on your primary iOS or Android device</a>. If you are signed in to WhatsApp using another phone number, the only way to sign out on that device and then set it up as a linked device to your primary WhatsApp account is to delete WhatsApp from your phone and reinstall it. Weird.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Turns Out, Since 2023, You Can Use WhatsApp Across Multiple Phones’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/07/whatsapp-phone-as-linked-device">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Markdown Support in Windows Notepad</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/news/677474/microsoft-windows-notepad-bold-italic-text-formatting-markdown-support?ueid=4b93173967d7dc762529a10418e85007" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wds" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/06/markdown-support-in-windows-notepad" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41968</id>
	<published>2025-06-07T00:19:37Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-07T00:19:37Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Tom Warren, writing for The Verge:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The experience supports Markdown style input and files for users
who prefer to work directly with the lightweight markup language,”
explains Dave Grochocki, principal product manager lead for
Microsoft’s Windows inbox apps. “You can switch between formatted
Markdown and Markdown syntax views in the view menu or by
selecting the toggle button in the status bar at the bottom of the
window.”</p>

<p>Since Notepad is usually used with plain text, you can also easily
clear all formatting from the formatting toolbar or from the edit
menu in the app. If you’re not a fan of the lightweight formatting
options, you can also fully disable this new support in the
Notepad app settings. [...]</p>

<p>Like I wrote in <a href="https://www.theverge.com/notepad-microsoft-newsletter/676258/microsoft-xbox-handheld-windows-steamos-notepad">my Notepad newsletter earlier this week</a>,
it’s amazing that Microsoft barely touched Notepad for decades,
and now it’s gone from basic log file reader to writing messages
itself. A lot of Notepad’s new features have arrived since
Microsoft decided to <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/9/3/23857331/microsoft-wordpad-windows-removal-end-of-support">remove WordPad from Windows</a>, after
nearly 30 years.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/04/apple-notes-markdown">getting</a> ridiculous.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Markdown Support in Windows Notepad’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/06/markdown-support-in-windows-notepad">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Take That CIRP Survey on Apple Customer Device Ownership With a Giant Grain of Salt</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/06/cirp-survey-ipad-popularity#update" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wdr" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/06/cirp-update" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41967</id>
	<published>2025-06-07T00:18:35Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-07T00:18:36Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>I posted this update a bit ago, but it’s worth making a separate post so you don’t miss it if you read the original post before I added the update:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It goes without saying that any consumer survey is only as good as
the surveyor. But CIRP, in particular, has posted some dubious
ones, to say the least. <a href="https://mastodon.social/@lapcatsoftware/114638324316925437">Jeff Johnson pointed out on Mastodon</a>
that back in 2023, <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2023/01/09/apples-most-popular-mac/">CIRP published a survey that claimed the Mac
Pro accounted for 43 percent</a> of all Mac desktop sales, with
the Mac Mini and Mac Studio each accounting for only 4 percent
each. That’s just bananas. That’s not like <em>maybe wrong</em>, that’s
not <em>gotta be a little wrong</em>, that’s <em>how could anyone publish
this?</em> wrong. It’s hard to believe anything from CIRP after they
published that.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Take That CIRP Survey on Apple Customer Device Ownership With a Giant Grain of Salt’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/06/cirp-update">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Gurman’s Mega-Spoiler Report on Monday’s WWDC Keynote</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2025-06-06/apple-wwdc-2025-preview-ios-26-macos-26-new-ai-features-ipados-26-redesigns" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wdq" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/06/gurman-wwdc-mega-spoiler" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41966</id>
	<published>2025-06-06T23:06:15Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-07T03:10:16Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>I think it’s become tradition for Mark Gurman to run a mega spoiler report on the WWDC keynote the Friday before. Don’t read it if you don’t want to see a <em>lot</em> of genuine spoilers. But here are a few non-spoilers:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The AI changes will be surprisingly minor and are unlikely to
impress industry watchers, especially considering the rapid pace
of innovation by Alphabet Inc.’s Google, Meta Platforms Inc.,
Microsoft Corp. and OpenAI.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I don’t know a single person who will be surprised if Apple’s in-house AI changes are minor. Literally, not one. The only way for Apple to surprise on the AI front would be for the improvements to be major. Who’s the guy who will be surprised by underwhelming advances on the AI front from Apple next week? <a href="https://crazyapplerumors.com/2006/08/21/everybody-tired-of-one-mac-user/">Artie MacStrawman</a>?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>While there has been speculation that the app icons will be round
to match the style on the Apple Watch and Vision Pro, the shape is
staying largely the same on the iPhone and iPad.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Always beware the passive voice. “There has been speculation”? It was Gurman’s own report, back in March, that left some <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/03/24/ios-19-visionos-apple-massive-ui-overhaul/">with the decided impression</a> that Apple was making icons circular across all platforms under the nonsensical argument that users find it jarring to see differently-shaped icons on different devices. <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2025-03-10/apple-readies-dramatic-design-overhauls-for-ios-19-ipados-19-and-macos-16?embedded-checkout=true">Gurman, back in March</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A key goal of the overhaul is to make Apple’s different operating
systems look similar and more consistent. Right now, the
applications, icons and window styles vary across macOS, iOS and
visionOS. That can make it jarring to hop from one device to
another. [...]</p>

<p>VisionOS differs from iOS and macOS in the use of circular app
icons, a simplified approach to windows, translucent panels for
navigation, and a more prominent use of 3D depth and shadows.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>My guess is that if Apple does go with circular icons across all platforms next week (which I sure hope they don’t because that seems dumb), Gurman will take credit for calling it back in March, despite writing today that “the shape is staying largely the same”. Heads, Gurman wins. Tails, Gurman doesn’t lose.</p>

<p>Back to today’s mega-spoiler report:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The Camera app will be revamped with a focus on simplicity. Apple
has added several new photo and video-taking options in recent
years — including spatial video, panorama and slow-motion
recording — and that’s made today’s interface a bit clunky. In
iOS 26 and iPadOS 26, Apple is rethinking the approach.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I can’t recall seeing Gurman ever, not even once, crediting anyone else for scooping anything first. Jon Prosser made <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HaP_q9W3AQE">an entire video about the supposed new Camera app design</a> all the way back on January 17, replete with animated mockups of how it will look and work. (Looks pretty clever to me, starting with a back-to-basics simple focus on two main modes — Photo or Video — and putting all other sub-modes under those.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Gurman’s Mega-Spoiler Report on Monday’s WWDC Keynote’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/06/gurman-wwdc-mega-spoiler">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/06/truth_social_is_just_trumps_blog" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wdp" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41965</id>
	<published>2025-06-06T21:58:55Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-07T03:02:56Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Truth Social is exceedingly unpopular when judged as a social network; but it’s exceedingly successful as a blog. All the other people using Truth Social are effectively reading his blog and shitposting comments and memes in response to his posts.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Sarah Perez, TechCrunch, “<a href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/06/06/the-trump-musk-feud-has-been-great-for-x-which-jumped-up-the-app-store-charts/">The Trump-Musk Feud Has Been Great for X, Which Jumped Up the App Store Charts</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/06/05/why-are-elon-musk-and-donald-trump-fighting/">feud between Elon Musk and President Donald Trump</a> may be
bad for the MAGA camp, but it’s proven to be beneficial for X,
which has seen engagement soaring over the past 24 hours.
According to new data from Sensor Tower, the app formerly known as
Twitter skyrocketed up the U.S. App Store’s top charts, landing at
the 23rd overall spot on June 5 — up from an average rank of No.
68 over the last 30 days.</p>

<p>X also saw an average rank of No. 58 over the past six months.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I wouldn’t call jumping from the 60s to the 20s “skyrocketing”, but, up is up.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Trump’s own social network, Truth Social, benefited from the feud
as well, as the president shared his thoughts about Musk with his
followers. Compared with the last seven days, U.S. mobile app
active users on Truth Social increased by more than 400%, Sensor
Tower’s proprietary panel indicates.</p>

<p>However, X is still much larger than Truth Social, Sensor Tower
notes, as it has 100× more U.S. mobile app users than Trump’s
social network.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In a couple of <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/19/trump-walmart-tariffs">recent</a> <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/23/trump-cook-apple-india">posts</a> I’ve referred to Truth Social as Trump’s “blog”. (I expounded upon this <a href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2025/05/26/ep-422">in a recent episode of The Talk Show</a>, with Stephen Hackett, starting after the 1h:20m mark, so if you listened to that, the following will sound familiar.) Long before this easily-predictable breakup of two unstable sociopathic egomaniacs (and who would be genuinely surprised if Musk is back in the Oval Office next week?), I’ve long wondered about one particular aspect of their alliance. To wit: that Musk famously spent $44 billion to buy Twitter/X, and envisions it as a world-conquering “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2022/10/everything">everything app</a>”. Trump was once the best known user on Twitter, but after being kicked off every legitimate social network after trying to overthrow the 2020 election, Trump started his own ostensible Twitter-like network, Truth Social. Ostensibly, they’re in direct competition with each other.</p>

<p>Did Musk ever pitch Trump on shutting Truth Social down and coming back to X full time? How about buying Truth Social for a bribery price of a cool $1 billion to sweeten the deal? Truth Social isn’t really a functional social network. Let’s stipulate that Truth Social has 1 percent the active US mobile users of X. Even that’s a sham. <em>Nobody of note other than Trump himself uses Truth Social.</em> For all the pathetic obsequiousness of every single lickspittle official serving in the Trump 2.0 administration, none of them are even vaguely active on Truth Social. They’re all still on X. The Justice Department posts to <a href="https://x.com/TheJusticeDept">its official account on X</a> multiple times per day, but the DOJ doesn’t even have an account on Truth Social. OK, JD Vance has posted to <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@JDVance1">his Truth Social account</a> about a dozen times in the last month. But <a href="https://x.com/JDVance">he’s posted to X</a> five times <em>today</em>.</p>

<p>What I’ve realized is that Truth Social is essentially just Trump’s blog. Truth Social is exceedingly unpopular when judged as a social network; but it’s exceedingly successful as a blog. All the other people using Truth Social are effectively reading his blog and shitposting comments and memes in response to his posts, trying to get his attention. I’ve been thinking about this for a few weeks, and in that time, Trump’s own posts on Truth Social have made the news on a near-daily basis. I’ve never once, ever, seen a post from anyone else on Truth Social make the news. Trump is not just the one and only person of consequence using it, his is the one and only account on Truth Social that you ever, <em>ever</em> hear about.</p>

<p>If Truth Social were actually <em>meant</em> to compete with X, Threads, Bluesky, and Mastodon, this almost certainly would have been a source of conflict between Trump and Musk. Because, if it were meant to be an actual competitive social network, it would occur to Trump to require all his flunkeys and toadies not only to post to Truth Social, but to <em>stop</em> posting to X. But he hasn’t done that, because Truth Social is functioning as intended: it’s just an outlet for Trump to spew his demented <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/23/trump-cook-apple-india">mad-king musings</a> (today he’s <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/06/trump-retweet-rushmore.jpeg">retweeting calls</a> for him to be added to Mount Rushmore) and, most importantly, get some of his all-caps-laden bangers read aloud on the TV news.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Truth Social Is Just Trump’s Blog</title></entry><entry>
	<title>CIRP Survey Suggests 78 Percent of All Apple Customers Own an iPad</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/06/04/ipad-is-a-much-bigger-hit-than-you-probably-thought/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wdo" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/06/cirp-survey-ipad-popularity" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41964</id>
	<published>2025-06-06T20:20:18Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-07T00:16:13Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Ryan Christoffel, writing at 9to5Mac regarding <a href="https://cirpapple.substack.com/p/rethinking-the-apple-ecosystem">a paywalled survey report from CIRP</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>CIRP recently performed a survey of Apple customers to get a sense
of how the company’s three tentpole products — iPhone, iPad, and
Mac — are performing. One focus was on understanding the power of
Apple’s ecosystem, as determined by customers who own multiple
products.</p>

<p><a href="https://cirpapple.substack.com/p/rethinking-the-apple-ecosystem">Michael Levin and Josh Lowitz write at CIRP</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>iPhone remains the most dominant product, with 94% of recent
Apple customers owning one. iPads are next, with 78% owning one.
Mac computers have much smaller penetration, at 36% of recent
customers.</p>

<p>74% of customers, virtually all iPad owners, own an iPad and an
iPhone. Only 30% own all three, as that number is limited by
Apple customers’ relative lack of Macs.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Different people may draw their own conclusions on the data, but
for me, the most interesting element is easily the iPad’s
popularity.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I don’t find this surprising. But if it’s true, it truly shows just how much longer people hold onto their iPads than their iPhones. If the average customer replaced their iPad as frequently as they do their iPhone, you’d expect Apple’s iPad revenue to be remarkably close to their iPhone revenue. But they’re not close. <a href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2025/05/apple-q2-2025-results-and-charts-95-4b-revenue/">In their most recent quarter</a>, iPhone revenue was 7× iPad revenue. And Mac revenue was slightly ahead of iPad revenue — but that might be more a function of average selling prices being so much higher for Macs than iPads, not replacement cycles.</p>

<p><strong id="update">Update:</strong> It goes without saying that any consumer survey is only as good as the surveyor. But CIRP, in particular, has posted some dubious ones, to say the least. <a href="https://mastodon.social/@lapcatsoftware/114638324316925437">Jeff Johnson pointed out on Mastodon</a> that back in 2023, <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2023/01/09/apples-most-popular-mac/">CIRP published a survey that claimed the Mac Pro accounted for 43 percent</a> of all Mac desktop sales, with the Mac Mini and Mac Studio each accounting for only 4 percent each. That’s just bananas. That’s not like <em>maybe wrong</em>, that’s not <em>gotta be a little wrong</em>, that’s <em>how could anyone publish this?</em> wrong. It’s hard to believe anything from CIRP after they published that.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘CIRP Survey Suggests 78 Percent of All Apple Customers Own an iPad’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/06/cirp-survey-ipad-popularity">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Neven Mrgan on Why Skeuomorphism Is Like a Classic Car</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://appdocumentary.com/2015/01/08/neven-mrgan-on-why-skeuomorphism-is-like-a-classic-car/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wdn" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/05/neven-mrgan-on-why-skeuomorphism-is-like-a-classic-car" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41963</id>
	<published>2025-06-06T02:56:09Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-07T00:21:24Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jake Schumacher, director of the 2017 documentary <em><a href="https://appdocumentary.com/">App: The Human Story</a></em>, sent me a note that Sebastiaan de With’s post this week, “<a href="https://www.lux.camera/physicality-the-new-age-of-ui/">Physicality: The New Age of UI</a>” (<a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/03/sdw-physicality-new-age">my thoughts here</a>), reminded him of a clip from the movie where Neven Mrgan compared Skeuomorphic design to classic cars from the 1940s and ’50s. So true. If you’ve got two and a half minutes to spare, watch this.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Neven Mrgan on Why Skeuomorphism Is Like a Classic Car’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/05/neven-mrgan-on-why-skeuomorphism-is-like-a-classic-car">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Comma That Might Cost Apple Billions in Europe</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cafetechinenglish.substack.com/p/a-simple-comma-will-cost-apple-billion?r=6gzkf&amp;triedRedirect=true" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wdm" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/05/the-comma-that-might-cost-apple-billions-in-europe" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41962</id>
	<published>2025-06-06T00:09:24Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-06T00:10:26Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jérôme Marin, writing at Cafétech:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The disagreement between Apple and Brussels centers on Article
5.4. In its English version, the article states that the
gatekeeper — the term used by the Commission for the seven major
tech companies subject to the DMA — <em>“shall allow business users,
free of charge, to communicate and promote offers, including under
different conditions […], and to conclude contracts with those end
users.”</em></p>

<p>This lengthy sentence creates ambiguity: what exactly does <em>“free
of charge”</em> apply to? Apple claims it only applies to
<em>“communicate”</em> and <em>“promote,”</em> meaning the right to insert
redirect links in an app. But not to <em>“conclude contracts,”</em>
meaning making purchases. Based on that, Apple argues it can still
charge commissions on those external transactions.</p>

<p>The European Commission interprets it differently: contract
conclusion must also be free of charge. It relies on the comma
before the phrase <em>“and to conclude contracts,”</em> turning the
sentence into an <em>“enumeration.” “That ‘free of charge’ applies to
all that is being enumerated after”,</em> it explains in <a href="https://ec.europa.eu/competition/digital_markets_act/cases/202522/DMA_100109_906.pdf">its detailed
decision sent to Apple</a> as part of the €500 million fine,
which was made public last week.</p>

<p><em>“In other words, the price for app developers to pay [for
external purchases] is zero,”</em> writes the Commission. However, its
case could be weakened by inconsistencies in the French and German
translations of the text, which it acknowledges are <em>“ambiguous.”</em>
Still, <em>“other linguistic versions leave no room for
interpretation,”</em> notes Brussels.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I understand why EU laws are published in multiple languages, but it’s wild that that can create possible loopholes like this. But it seems rather obvious what the EC’s intention was here, and it wasn’t for Apple to charge commissions — let alone steep commissions — on transactions that take place outside the app after users tap a link to the web. If I were one of Apple’s lawyers, I’d argue about the placement of a comma too, and what it implies about what “free of charge” applies to. But the EC’s intentions are obvious. It’s not really about a comma.</p>

<p>On this particular issue Apple seems to be facing the exact same pushback in the EU <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/05/apple-appeal-denied-antisteering">as in the US</a>: their anti-steering rules in the App Store aren’t legal.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Comma That Might Cost Apple Billions in Europe’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/05/the-comma-that-might-cost-apple-billions-in-europe">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>9to5Mac on The Talk Show Livestream Returning to Theater for VisionOS</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/06/05/theater-the-talk-show-live-3d/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wdl" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/05/9to5mac-on-the-talk-show-livestream-returning-to-theater" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41961</id>
	<published>2025-06-05T22:01:20Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-07T00:22:36Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Nice write-up from Zac Hall at 9to5Mac:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Theater for visionOS <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2024/06/10/sandwich-debuts-theater-for-vision-pro-with-exclusive-the-talk-show-live-event-in-immersive-video/">premiered</a> a year ago with a clever
software launch campaign: exclusively streaming John Gruber’s The
Talk Show post-WWDC event live with 3D video.</p>

<p>The Apple Vision Pro app has continued to mature since its debut,<a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/01/06/the-best-plex-video-player-for-apple-vision-pro-just-got-way-better/">
adding extensive Plex support</a> and <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2024/12/23/apple-vision-pro-just-got-a-planetarium-and-its-friggin-awesome/">a full-blown immersive
planetarium</a> that now hosts the <a href="https://sandwich.vision/press/partners/resolution-press-release.html">2025 SXSW award-winning
“Resolution” music experience</a>.</p>

<p>Next up, Theater is returning as the exclusive home to The Talk
Show Live event stream.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>First, as Hall points out, if you haven’t heard or thought about the Theater app for VisionOS since my show last year, there is now a ton of interesting immersive content there. Second, I’ve lost track of how many times I’ve read commentary, or listened to people on podcasts, wonder why there are hardly any “<em>just make it feel like you’re there, in the audience, for the show</em>” immersive shows for VisionOS.</p>

<p>That’s what Sandwich Vision did last year, and is doing even better this year, with my show. I thought it was kind of odd that it was me, of all people, and my once-a-year, not-that-big-a-deal-outside-the-Apple-nerd-media-world show, who was the first to livestream an immersive show experience for VisionOS. Maybe there were others first for Meta’s low-res headsets, but if there were, I’m not aware of them. My show last year really might have been first for any immersive headset.</p>

<p>Afterward, I figured by this year, while it might not be commonplace — simply because Vision Pro ownership is, you know, not that high — it wouldn’t be unusual. But it still is. I honestly don’t get why that is. Anyway, like I wrote in the previous post, if you can make the show, <a href="https://ti.to/daringfireball/the-talk-show-live-from-wwdc-2025">you really should attend</a>. But if you can’t make the show, you definitely should watch live <a href="https://theater.sandwich.vision/">in Theater</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘9to5Mac on The Talk Show Livestream Returning to Theater for VisionOS’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/05/9to5mac-on-the-talk-show-livestream-returning-to-theater">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Theater Announces Immersive Livestream of The Talk Show Live From WWDC 2025</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sandwich.vision/press/partners/tts-live-2025-press-release.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wdk" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/05/theater-livestream-the-talk-show-live-from-wwdc-2025" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41960</id>
	<published>2025-06-05T21:46:56Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-05T21:46:57Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Sandwich Vision:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Theater, the premier platform for spatial media, cinema and events
on Apple Vision Pro, is proud to announce the immersive livestream
of The Talk Show Live from WWDC on Tuesday, June 10, 2025.</p>

<p>Following last year’s groundbreaking first-ever immersive
livestream of the event from John Gruber, host of The Talk Show
podcast and author of the renowned Apple blog Daring Fireball,
Theater returns with an enhanced experience that builds on a full
year of platform development and partnerships.</p>

<p>“When we launched Theater last year to showcase The Talk Show
Live, we weren’t just experimenting — we were inviting people to
experience a new kind of immersion. Bringing Apple executives into
spatial media wasn’t just a world first; it was a glimpse of how
shared experiences can transcend screens,” said Adam Lisagor, CEO
and founder of Sandwich Vision. “This year, we’re not just adding
features — we’re refining how people can feel connected, curious,
and delighted together, again and again. Our goal is to make
presence and participation the new standard for special events,
where technology fades away, and what remains is the shared magic
of being there.”</p>

<p>The livestream will be available in both 2D and 3D formats. While
the 2D stream will be offered free of charge, the premium 3D
immersive experience will be available for $11.99 for tickets
purchased in advance, increasing to $14.99 on the day of the
event. All ticket holders will receive permanent access to a
pristine 6K version of the event to watch forever.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Make your purchases right in the <a href="https://theater.sandwich.vision/">Theater app</a>. I’m snarky in the press release linked above, but I actually thought doing this last year was incredibly cool. Afterwards it was like I got to watch myself perform my own show, which was a lot weirder than just watching myself on regular video.</p>

<p>If you can make the show, <a href="https://ti.to/daringfireball/the-talk-show-live-from-wwdc-2025">you really should attend</a>. Everyone tells me it’s fun. But if you can’t make the show, you definitely should watch live in Theater.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Theater Announces Immersive Livestream of The Talk Show Live From WWDC 2025’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/05/theater-livestream-the-talk-show-live-from-wwdc-2025">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Judge Denies Apple’s Appeal; Ordered to Keep Allowing Link-Outs to the Web in the U.S. App Store</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/news/679946/apple-rejected-court-attempt-to-stop-app-store-web-links" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wdj" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/05/apple-appeal-denied-antisteering" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41959</id>
	<published>2025-06-05T21:33:42Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-05T21:34:55Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jacob Kastrenakes, The Verge:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In April, a federal judge demanded that Apple begin allowing web
links, cease restricting how links are formatted, and enable
developers to offer external payment options without giving the
company a cut of their revenue. Apple promptly appealed and
requested that the order be put on hold until the legal
proceedings were finished.</p>

<p>But an appeals court has now denied Apple’s emergency request to
block the order. The court said it was “not persuaded” that
blocking the order was appropriate after weighing Apple’s chances
to succeed on appeal, whether Apple would be irreparably harmed,
whether other parties would be hurt if the order is halted, and
what supports the public interest.</p>

<p>The rejection bodes poorly for Apple’s chance of overturning the
order, which stems from a lawsuit by Epic Games.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Here’s the denial <a href="https://www.courtlistener.com/docket/70190916/40/epic-games-inc-v-apple-inc/">from the United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit</a>, nearly in its entirety, omitting only legal citations:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple’s Emergency Motion Under Circuit Rule 27-3 for a Partial
Stay Pending Appeal is DENIED. In deciding whether to impose a
stay, we consider: “(1) whether the stay applicant has made a
strong showing that he is likely to succeed on the merits; (2)
whether the applicant will be irreparably injured absent a stay;
(3) whether issuance of the stay will substantially injure the
other parties interested in the proceeding; and (4) where the
public interest lies.” Apple “bears the burden of showing that the
circumstances justify an exercise of [our] discretion.” After
reviewing the relevant factors, we are not persuaded that a stay
is appropriate.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The earliest this might get overturned, it seems to me, is the end of this year, but I get the feeling this injunction is here to stay.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Judge Denies Apple’s Appeal; Ordered to Keep Allowing Link-Outs to the Web in the U.S. App Store’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/05/apple-appeal-denied-antisteering">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Marco Arment on Apple’s Decision to Decline Appearing on The Talk Show Live From WWDC</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://marco.org/2025/05/30/retreat" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wdi" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/05/marco-apple-the-talk-show" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41958</id>
	<published>2025-06-05T20:38:54Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-05T21:06:48Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Marco Arment, moved to write his first blog post in 11 months:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>For unspecified reasons, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/29/the-talk-show-live-tickets-2025">Apple has declined to participate this
year</a>, ending what had become a beloved tradition in our
community — and I can’t help but suspect that it won’t come back.
(<a href="https://marco.org/2021/06/03/developer-relations">A lot has changed</a> in the meantime.)</p>

<p>Maybe Apple has good reasons. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/something_is_rotten_in_the_state_of_cupertino">Maybe not</a>. We’ll see what
their WWDC PR strategy looks like in a couple of weeks.</p>

<p>In the absence of any other information, it’s easy to assume that
Apple no longer wants its executives to be interviewed in a human,
unscripted, unedited context that may contain hard questions, and
that Apple no longer feels it necessary to show their appreciation
to our community and developers in this way.</p>

<p>I hope that’s either not the case, or it doesn’t stay the case
for long.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>They’ve invited members of the media to a screening of <em>F1 The Movie</em> Tuesday at 7:00pm in the Steve Jobs Theater. Thankfully, my press invitation from Apple has it marked as “optional”, because I have <a href="https://ti.to/daringfireball/the-talk-show-live-from-wwdc-2025">a conflict</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Marco Arment on Apple’s Decision to Decline Appearing on The Talk Show Live From WWDC’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/05/marco-apple-the-talk-show">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>9to5Mac Reports Apple Notes Will Gain Markdown Export at WWDC, and, You’ll Be Unsurprised to Know, I Have Thoughts</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/06/03/exclusive-ios-26-messages-carplay-more/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wdg" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/04/apple-notes-markdown" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41956</id>
	<published>2025-06-05T01:44:09Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-05T22:28:11Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Marcus Mendes, in a piece at 9to5Mac with multiple spoilers for next week’s keynote:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple is working on supporting the ability to export notes in
Markdown from Apple Notes, which is something third-party apps
have supported for years. Granted, this is a niche feature, but as
a fierce participant in the niche, I can confirm: this is huge.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>When this story first started spreading this morning, it was getting repeated as Notes “gaining Markdown support”, which implied something like <a href="https://bear.app/">Bear</a> or <a href="https://obsidian.md/">Obsidian</a>, where you can type Markdown syntax characters while editing, and perhaps optionally see the Markdown syntax in your notes. “Markdown notes app” is really like a class of notes apps unto itself.</p>

<p>Some people find this surprising, but I personally don’t want to use a Markdown notes app. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2004/03/dive_into_markdown">I created Markdown two decades ago</a> and have used it ever since for one thing and one thing only: writing for the web at Daring Fireball. My <a href="https://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/">original description</a> of what it is still stands: “Markdown is a text-to-HTML conversion tool for web writers.” Perhaps an even better description of Markdown is Matthew Butterick’s, <a href="https://docs.racket-lang.org/pollen/quick-tour.html#%28part._.Markdown_mode%29">from the documentation for Pollen</a>: “Markdown is a simplified notation system for HTML.”</p>

<p>The other great use case for Markdown is in a context where you either <em>need</em> or just <em>want</em> to be saving to a plain text file or database field. That’s not what Apple Notes is or should be. I can see why many technically-minded people want to use Markdown “everywhere”. It’s quite gratifying that Markdown has not only become so popular, but <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2004/03/introducing_markdown">after 21 years</a>, continues to grow in popularity, to the point now where there clearly are a lot of people who seemingly enjoy writing in Markdown more than even I do. But I think it would be a huge mistake for Apple to make Apple Notes a “Markdown editor”, even as an option. It’s trivial to create malformed Markdown syntax; it shouldn’t be possible to have a malformed note in Apple Notes. I <em>craft</em> posts for Daring Fireball; I dash off notes in Apple Notes.</p>

<p>Apple Notes offers a great WYSIWYG rich text editing interface that works great on an iPhone and even better on a Mac, which I think is exactly appropriate. Particularly clever are the limited formatting options, where you don’t pick a font per se, but rather only from a set of predefined styles, like headings, lists, and block quote. It’s not nerdy at all. You certainly shouldn’t need to “preview” (let alone keep a separate preview view open side-by-side with your editing view), nor switch between <a href="https://www.pavley.com/2020/02/20/no-modes/">modes</a> for editing and viewing. That’s the Macintosh way. (But that’s why I think Apple Notes’s use of hashtags, rather than real tokenized tags <a href="https://support.apple.com/guide/mac-help/tag-files-and-folders-mchlp15236/mac">like in the Finder</a>, was an enormous mistake on Apple’s part. Real tokenized tags can contain spaces (so a multi-word tag can just be “Words Written Naturally” not “#WordsCrammedTogether”) and don’t need to be prefixed with an ugly, nerdy-looking <code>#</code> character. Notes using hashtags is like if the Finder disallowed spaces and uppercase letters in filenames.)</p>

<p>But Markdown <em>export</em> from Notes? That sounds awesome. Frankly, perhaps the biggest problem with Apple Notes is that its export functionality is rather crude — <a href="https://support.apple.com/guide/iphone/export-or-print-notes-iphdf551cfa2/ios">PDF and, of all formats, Pages</a>. Exporting and/or copying the selected text as Markdown would be pretty cool. Very curious to see how they handle images though, if this rumor is true.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘9to5Mac Reports Apple Notes Will Gain Markdown Export at WWDC, and, You’ll Be Unsurprised to Know, I Have Thoughts’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/04/apple-notes-markdown">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple Might Release an iPhone ‘Air’ Battery Case, But What They Ought to Release Is an Updated MagSafe Battery Pack</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theinformation.com/articles/apple-plans-iphone-release-schedule-shakeup-new-styles?rc=jfy0lk" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wdf" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/04/apple-iphone-air-battery-case-or-pack" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41955</id>
	<published>2025-06-04T22:58:57Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-04T23:58:04Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Wayne Ma, reporting last month at The Information (a paywalled website so obnoxious that they force $300/year subscribers <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/gruber.foo/post/3lqstgf7nt62r">to click through an article-blocking popover</a> pitching them on upgrading to a $500/year subscription), and <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/05/03/iphone-17-air-battery-case-report/">summarized here by MacRumors</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>However, the smaller size of the new thin model will require
compromises to its capabilities. The device will contain only a
single speaker instead of the two speakers that Apple’s other
phones usually have, one rear camera lens instead of the three in
Apple’s flagship phones, and reduced battery life. Internal
testing shows that battery life for the thin model will fall short
of that of previous iPhones. The percentage of users who can go a
single day without recharging the thin phone will be between 60%
and 70%. For other models, that metric is between 80% and 90%, one
of the people said.</p>

<p>To solve this, Apple is developing an optional accessory — a
phone case meant for the thin model that also contains a battery
pack, according to three people familiar with the matter.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It sort of goes without saying that the super-thin iPhone will have less battery life. How could it be otherwise? If 60–70% of users can still get through the day on a charge while using it, that sounds like it’s the right time for Apple to try such a phone. People who currently run their phones down to the red each day aren’t going to think “<em>Hey, maybe I should try this crazy thin iPhone.</em>”</p>

<p>What disappoints me is Ma’s reporting of an iPhone Air-only battery <em>case</em> from Apple. What I very much want Apple to make is a sequel to its amazing <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/111857">MagSafe Battery Pack with a Lightning connector</a> that debuted in 2020 but was discontinued in 2023 (the year that the iPhones 15 switched from Lightning to USB-C). I’ve got two of these and they’re still, by far, my favorite iPhone battery packs. They’re the only Lightning devices left in my life and they’re so good I’m happy to still keep one Lightning cable in my travel bag to use them.</p>

<p>There are a zillion third-party “magnetic” (but not “MagSafe”) battery packs that work with iPhones, and most of them have larger batteries than Apple’s. But part of what makes Apple’s MagSafe Battery Pack great is that it’s so small, and shaped so comfortably. I don’t need a magnetic battery pack that tries to double my iPhone’s battery life. I just need like 1.5× on occasional phone-heavy days (like next Monday’s WWDC keynote), and Apple’s does just that. No third-party magnetic battery pack I’ve tried comes even close to attaching as securely to the back of the iPhone as Apple’s. And Apple’s has special integration with iOS, which gives you a cool animation on the screen when it’s first attached, and updates the battery life of the pack in the Battery widget alongside the iPhone’s own battery. (Apparently <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FLb5ut2mzf4">some newer third-party packs do now show the full-screen animation</a> when first attached, but none yet integrate with the Battery widget — someone better call the European Commission.) Most importantly, with Apple’s MagSafe Battery Pack, iOS is smart, and doesn’t keep sucking juice when the phone has recharged up to 70% or so. By only slurping juice when it’s more efficient to do so, you get more effective battery life out of a noticeably slimmer battery back. It’s just so much better than any other battery pack I’ve tried.</p>

<p>This supposed iPhone “Air” seems like the perfect time to bring back the MagSafe Battery Pack, this time with USB-C — and unlike a model-specific case, it’d work with all MagSafe iPhones, not just the Air. (<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/02/the_iphone_16e">Sorry, 16e owners</a>.) See also:</p>

<ul>
<li>Chance Miller, writing back in November for 9to5Mac: “<a href="https://9to5mac.com/2024/11/18/iphone-16-magsafe-battery-pack-memories/">Apple’s MagSafe Battery Pack for iPhone Shouldn’t Have Been a One-And-Done Experiment</a>”</li>
<li>Steven Aquino, writing back in September while he was still Forbes contributor: “<a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/stevenaquino/2024/09/30/apples-magsafe-battery-pack-is-owed-an-ode-in-terms-of-accessibility/">Apple’s MagSafe Battery Pack Is Owed an Ode in Terms of Accessibility</a>”</li>
</ul>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Might Release an iPhone ‘Air’ Battery Case, But What They Ought to Release Is an Updated MagSafe Battery Pack’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/04/apple-iphone-air-battery-case-or-pack">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Meta and Yandex’s ‘Local Mess’ Exploit Seemingly Only Works on Android</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://arstechnica.com/security/2025/06/meta-and-yandex-are-de-anonymizing-android-users-web-browsing-identifiers/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wde" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/04/meta-and-yandexs-local-mess-exploit-seemingly-only-works-on-android" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41954</id>
	<published>2025-06-04T22:08:52Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-04T22:08:53Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Dan Goodin, writing at Ars Technica:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This abuse has been observed only in Android, and evidence
suggests that the Meta Pixel and Yandex Metrica target only
Android users. The researchers say it may be technically feasible
to target iOS because browsers on that platform allow developers
to programmatically <a href="https://bugs.webkit.org/show_bug.cgi?id=279249">establish localhost connections</a> that
apps can monitor on local ports.</p>

<p>In contrast to iOS, however, Android imposes fewer controls on
local host communications and background executions of mobile
apps, the researchers said, while also implementing stricter
controls in app store vetting processes to limit such abuses. This
overly permissive design allows Meta Pixel and Yandex Metrica to
send web requests with web tracking identifiers to specific local
ports that are continuously monitored by the Facebook, Instagram,
and Yandex apps. These apps can then link pseudonymous web
identities with actual user identities, even in private browsing
modes, effectively de-anonymizing users’ browsing habits on sites
containing these trackers.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’ll note that among the so-called <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/06/apple_appeals_eu_interop_requirements">“interoperability” requirements the European Commission is demanding of iOS</a> is for third-party apps to run, unfettered, in the background, because some of Apple’s own first-party software obviously runs in the background. And I’ll further note that Apple made clear, <a href="https://developer.apple.com/support/downloads/DMA-Interoperability-Dec-2024.pdf">back in its December 2024 report laying out its objections to the EC’s demands</a>, that:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>No company has made more interoperability requests of Apple than
Meta. In many cases, Meta is seeking to alter functionality in a
way that raises concerns about the privacy and security of users,
and that appears to be completely unrelated to the actual use of
Meta external devices, such as Meta smart glasses and Meta Quests.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This newly uncovered “Local Mess” exploit — which seemingly only works on Android — is exactly the sort of scheme Meta wants to pull on iOS: to track users across millions of websites while they justifiably believe their web browsing is sandboxed from all native apps.</p>

<p>Back to Goodin:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Meta Pixel and Yandex Metrica are analytics scripts designed to
help advertisers measure the effectiveness of their campaigns.
Meta Pixel and Yandex Metrica are estimated to be installed on
<a href="https://trends.builtwith.com/websitelist/Facebook-Pixel%20">5.8 million</a> and <a href="https://trends.builtwith.com/analytics/Yandex-Metrika">3 million</a> sites, respectively.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Every one of the sites that includes these tracking scripts is complicit to some extent in the theft of hundreds of millions of Android users’ web browsing privacy.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Meta and Yandex’s ‘Local Mess’ Exploit Seemingly Only Works on Android’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/04/meta-and-yandexs-local-mess-exploit-seemingly-only-works-on-android">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/06/apple_appeals_eu_interop_requirements" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wd4" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41944</id>
	<published>2025-06-03T02:38:54Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-03T16:26:00Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">https://9to5mac.com/2025/06/02/apple-eu-interoperability-appeal/</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/06/02/apple-eu-interoperability-appeal/">Benjamin Mayo, writing at 9to5Mac</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple has appealed parts of the Digital Markets Act law citing
user privacy concerns. Specifically, Apple is contesting the
<a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/03/19/eu-order-apple-interoperability/">interoperability requirements</a> that say data like
notification content and WiFi networks should be made available to
third-parties.</p>

<p>Apple says the DMA as written allows others to “access personal
information that even Apple doesn’t see”. This is because features
like notification rendering and WiFi network data are currently
handled on-device and stored in an encrypted fashion, so Apple
cannot see that stuff. However, the DMA does not necessarily
require third-party agents who would be able to access this same
data to commit to the same standards of privacy and security.</p>

<p>Here’s Apple’s latest statement on the matter, in full:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>At Apple, we design our technology to work seamlessly together,
so it can deliver the unique experience our users love and expect
from our products. The EU’s interoperability requirements
threaten that foundation, while creating a process that is
unreasonable, costly, and stifles innovation. These requirements
will also hand data-hungry companies sensitive information, which
poses massive privacy and security risks to our EU users.
Companies have already requested our users’ most sensitive data — from the content of their notifications, to a full history of
every stored WiFi network on their device — giving them the
ability to access personal information that even Apple doesn’t
see. In the end, these deeply flawed rules that only target Apple — and no other company — will severely limit our ability to
deliver innovative products and features to Europe, leading to an
inferior user experience for our European customers. We are
appealing these decisions on their behalf, and in order to
preserve the high-quality experience our European customers
expect.</p>
</blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>Apple’s full statement is worth reading closely. Specifically, this sentence jumped out to me: “In the end, these deeply flawed rules that only target Apple — and no other company — will severely limit our ability to deliver innovative products and features to Europe, leading to an inferior user experience for our European customers.” <a href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/apple-challenges-eu-order-to-increase-compatibility-with-rivals-products-52082b50?st=gzZzXt">The Wall Street Journal’s story on the appeal</a>, for example, didn’t include that portion of Apple’s statement. But that’s the part that explains what’s going to happen if the EU upholds these “interoperability” requirements, which are intended to require Apple to give away its own intellectual property as though Apple were a public utility. To cite just one example, the Commission’s March ruling requires Apple to make AirDrop available to third-party devices, as though AirDrop was an open standard. (It also requires Apple to allow AirDrop to be replaced on iOS devices, like an interchangeable component, with third-party file sharing software.)</p>

<p>When you think about it, this is nothing like the EU’s recent-ish mandate that most electronic devices must support USB-C ports for charging. I still think that law was unnecessary — the market forces had worked, and the whole world had either already moved (like iPads did starting in 2018) or was on the cusp of moving to USB-C (like iPhones). But at least requiring the inclusion of USB-C for charging is actual open interoperability. USB comes from <a href="https://www.usb.org/">a legitimate industry consortium</a>. Same thing with the Chinese government <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2024/02/eu_rcs_imessage">seemingly forcing Apple’s hand to adopt RCS</a> in order to get the necessary <a href="https://www.miit.gov.cn/gzcy/yjzj/art/2023/art_2d5a7969581b4b12a78cd2c455649a8c.html">certifications for 5G cellular networking in China</a> — RCS is an industry standard protocol. Mandating the inclusion of a standardized port or standardized protocol is the sort of thing government regulatory bodies do. That’s very different than if the EC had regulated port compatibility by requiring Apple to open up Lightning, or if China had regulated messaging by requiring Apple to open iMessage for other companies to use as though they’re open standards.</p>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/eu-apple-interop-requirements">The EC’s March mandate</a> basically says that third-party devices must be permitted to do everything Apple’s own devices do when it comes to communicating or interoperating with iPhones and iPads, even if that requires allowing those third-party companies to install and run system-level background processes with broad privileges on iOS. In fact, as Mayo alludes to above, in order to have the same capabilities as Apple’s own devices do, third-party system software extensions might need <em>broader</em> privileges.</p>

<p>I’ve long seen that there are two ways Apple can comply with this mandate, if the EU court declines Apple’s appeal. The first is what most people are thinking, and surely what the European Commission’s bureaucrats are thinking: that Apple will somehow make all third-party devices as capable as Apple’s own when it comes to pairing with and communicating with iPhones and iPads. (And that when Apple is set to unveil new devices, they’ll share the details with third parties in advance so they can do the same things.) The second, though, is that Apple will limit its own devices <em>in the EU and only in the EU</em> to the same features available to third-party devices through open standards like Bluetooth. New features and entire devices will either come late, or never, to the EU. We’re already seeing that <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/120421">with iPhone Mirroring</a> — perhaps the single best feature Apple announced (and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/something_is_rotten_in_the_state_of_cupertino">actually shipped</a>) last year. I use iPhone Mirroring every day while I’m working. We’re one week out from WWDC 2025 and iPhone Mirroring <em>still</em> isn’t available in the EU. I think it’s very clear that under the EC’s current DMA “interoperability” mandate, Apple would be required to somehow make it work with third-party devices and PCs. If AirDrop were brand new, users in the EU wouldn’t get that either, I suspect. And if this mandate holds up, EU users might <em>lose</em> AirDrop. The same is true of entire devices like AirPods and Apple Watch.</p>

<p>Apple’s statement doesn’t say that complying with these breathtaking demands will adversely affect their customers around the world. They’re saying it will lead “to an inferior user experience for our European customers”. Mandating that the public has to be allowed to use the same doorways as a (say) hotel’s own staff doesn’t mean those existing doors will be opened to everyone. It could lead to those doors being closed to everyone. And all of a sudden no one staying at the hotel is getting food from the kitchen.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Apple Appeals EU’s March Ruling on ‘Interoperability’ Requirements Under the DMA</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/05/idiocy_or_jackassery_you_make_the_call_made_in_america_iphone" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wci" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41922</id>
	<published>2025-05-24T20:16:44Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-03T17:20:14Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">My chances of ever landing a job at The New York Times continue to sink.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The New York Times ran a really dumb Tripp Mickle piece yesterday under the headline “<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/05/23/technology/apple-iphone-trump-india-china.html">Is Trump’s ‘Made in America’ iPhone a Fantasy?</a>” The answer should have simply been “<em>Yes, it’s sheer fantasy</em>”, perhaps with explanations why. Instead, Mickle twists the piece into pretzels to make it seem like the answer is <em>maybe</em>, even though there’s not a single fact to back that up. Not one. The only thing that backs up any answer other than “<em>It’s a fantasy, can’t happen, makes no sense</em>” are comments from analysts — named and unnamed — and the bizarre old-school news media practice of treating as fact any nonsense and/or bullshit that comes out of the lips of anyone with the word “analyst” on their business card.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>Could Apple make iPhones in the United States?</em></p>

<p>Yes. Apple could make iPhones in the United States. But doing so
would be expensive and difficult and force the company to more
than double iPhone prices to $2,000 or more, said Wayne Lam, an
analyst with TechInsights, a market research firm. Apple would
have to buy new machines and rely on more automation than it
uses in China because the U.S. population is so much smaller,
Mr. Lam said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is nonsense. The problem isn’t that China has a higher population than the US (about 1.4 billion vs. 340 million, about a 4× difference). <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/apple-iphone-factory-foxconn-china-photos-tour-2018-5">Foxconn employs somewhere between 300–500,000 assembly line workers in China</a> doing final assembly for Apple products. It’s that the United States doesn’t have anyone with the necessary vocational skills, who would want to work tedious factory jobs at factory-job wages, and China does. That’s part of the fever-dream mad-king fantasy of this entire cockamamie endeavor by Trump: <em>these are difficult, low-paying, long-houred jobs that Americans don’t want</em>. That these jobs are all in China and India is proof that America is far ahead, not that we’ve fallen behind. (There are nuances to the overall dynamics, like the national security ramifications of our being reliant on Taiwan for leading-edge chip fabrication, but Trump’s tariff nonsense doesn’t address those issues.)</p>

<p>Worse: $2,000 is just a made-up number. Lam doesn’t even say which iPhone would cost $2,000. Would it be the iPhone 16 Pro Max (current starting price: $1,200) or the base model iPhone 16e (current price: $600)? Mickle reports that Lam is saying prices “would more than double” so let’s just say he’s talking about the regular no-adjective iPhone models. Today the iPhone 16 starts at $800. If assembling even <em>some</em> of them would result in a retail price of $2,000, Apple would sell none of them. Like, almost literally zero.</p>

<p>The math here takes a bit of thinking but it’s not complicated. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/23/trump-cook-apple-india">Trump is claiming he’s going to apply 25% tariffs</a> to India-made iPhones sold in the US.<sup id="fnr1-2025-05-24"><a href="#fn1-2025-05-24">1</a></sup> If Apple passed along the entire 25% tariff on an $800 iPhone to consumers, that would raise the retail price to $1,000. So if stores carried two different iPhone 17 models — same specs, same colors — and one cost $1,000 because it was assembled in India or China, facing 25% Trump tariffs, and the other cost $2,000 because it was assembled in some sort of fantasy factory that somehow popped up in Texas between now and September, how many people would buy the $2,000 US-assembled one? Almost zero. So why even bother? Apple doesn’t even print the “Designed by Apple in California / Assembled in Wherever” small print on the outside of the iPhone any more.</p>

<p>Tariffs would have to be 250% for the price of an Indian- or Chinese-assembled $800 iPhone to get to $2,000. And even if Trump <em>were</em> to apply 250% tariffs to smartphones — which isn’t going to happen — it would be far easier for Apple to just sell Indian and Chinese-assembled iPhones for $2,000 than it would be to spin up assembly — factories, employees, training, components — here inside the US. So even though $2,000 is just a number “analyst” Wayne Lam completely made up, and which reporter Tripp Mickle simply quotes as if it had any basis in reality, it still doesn’t make any sense that Apple would do it. No matter how crazily high tariffs go, it only makes sense for Apple to continue assembling iPhones in China and India for now, and passing some or all of the costs along to consumers.<sup id="fnr2-2025-05-24"><a href="#fn2-2025-05-24">2</a></sup></p>

<p>Of course, raising the price of a base model iPhone to $2,000 would crater consumer demand. And of course it would create <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2025/04/trump-tariffs-smugglers/682303/">a massive gray market bootlegging opportunity</a> where hustlers would smuggle normal-cost iPhones into the US from Canada, Mexico, and overseas. Trump can’t raise the price of iPhones outside the US, and so long as iPhones are priced “normally” everywhere else in the world, the higher Trump’s tariffs might go, the larger and more commonplace bootlegging them will be.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>There would be some benefits to moving the supply chain, including
reducing the environmental costs of shipping products from abroad,
said Matthew Moore, who spent nine years as a manufacturing design
manager at Apple. But the upsides would be trivial compared with
the challenges that would have to be overcome.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Again, just utter nonsense. There <em>might</em> be hypothetical environmental benefits to assembling all US-sold iPhones inside the US, but in the real world, many if not most of the most expensive components would still come from overseas. All iPhone displays come from Asian manufacturers. All A-series chips come from TSMC in Taiwan. (TSMC is building out a chip-fabrication campus in Arizona but even if that went according to plan — <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/05/23/technology/apple-iphone-trump-india-china.html">which it already isn’t</a> — their Arizona fabrication capabilities will remain years behind their leading-edge fabrication technology in Taiwan for at least the next decade, and Apple’s A-series chips are fabbed exclusively on leading-edge technology.)</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Supply chain experts say shifting iPhone production to the United
States in 2025 would be foolish.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Perhaps the one accurate sentence in Mickle’s entire piece.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The iPhone is nearly 20 years old. Apple’s top executives have
said people may not need an iPhone in 10 years because it could be
replaced by a new device built for artificial intelligence. As a
result, Apple would invest a lot of money that it wouldn’t be able
to recoup, Mr. Lam said.</p>

<p>“I would be surprised if there’s an iPhone 29,” he said, noting
that Apple is trying to disrupt the iPhone by making augmented
reality products like the Vision Pro.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The Mac is 41 years old and, last I checked, Apple is still making them. I don’t know if Apple will keep naming iPhones with annually incrementing integers, but I’ll gladly wager Wayne Lam (or Tripp Mickle) any amount of money they wish that Apple will release at least one new iPhone in 2037. Name the wager, fellas. “The iPhone is 20 years old” is the dumbest argument in this entire dumb article.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>What does China offer that the United States doesn’t?</em></p>

<p>Small hands, a massive, seasonal work force and millions of
engineers. Young Chinese women have small fingers, and that has
made them a valuable contributor to iPhone production because they
are more nimble at installing screws and other miniature parts in
the small device, supply chain experts said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Well, now I have to eat my own words. “Young Chinese women have small fingers” is in fact the dumbest argument in this entire incredibly stupid article. It might even be the dumbest thing I’ve read this year, and with Trump in office, I’ve read a lot of dumb things. For chrissake I just read <em>this morning</em> that <a href="https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/news/international/global-trends/us-news-trump-vs-harvard-they-cant-add-22-trump-wildly-claims-harvard-students-cant-even-do-remedial-math/articleshow/121373450.cms">Trump claimed his administration is trying to revoke Harvard’s ability to enroll foreign students</a> because “A lot of the people need remedial math. These students can’t add two and two, and they go to Harvard. They want remedial math and they’re going to teach remedial math at Harvard?” That’s truly profoundly stupid.<sup id="fnr3-2025-05-24"><a href="#fn3-2025-05-24">3</a></sup> But it’s not as ignorant as saying that Chinese women’s finger-size is the reason Apple makes iPhones in China.</p>

<p>I’d pay good money to know the names of the “supply chain experts” (plural!) Mickle got this one from.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>

<li id="fn1-2025-05-24">
<p>Presumably the tariff would be applied to all India-assembled phones sold in the US, because it would be plainly illegal, even in Trumpworld, to put a tariff on the iPhone alone. Tariffs apply to classes of products, not specific brands. But, in practice, a 25% tariff on all Indian-assembled phones sold in the US would, effectively, be a tariff targeted at iPhones alone.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-05-24"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>

<li id="fn2-2025-05-24">
<p>Spitball idea: Apple could start assembling a completely insignificant number of iPhones in, say, Texas. A complete farce. A few hundred US-made iPhones per day, in a country where they sell 150,000 iPhones per day. Make a big show of it. Invite Trump himself down for a dog-and-pony-show photo op <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2019/11/20/apple-ceo-tim-cook-and-preident-trump-tour-texas-computer-factory.html">like Tim Cook did with the Mac Pro plant back in Trump 1.0</a> in 2019. Have Cook emphasize that they’re just getting started and Apple looks forward to ramping up the endeavor. Give Trump the first US-made iPhone off the assembly line. Hope that that’ll satisfy the dumb bastard, he’ll take the tariffs off their backs, and he’ll thereafter start bragging about how he got Apple to start making iPhones in the US even though everyone said it would be impossible, even though, under the scheme I’m spitballing here, Apple would only ever assemble a fraction of a single percent of US-sold iPhones domestically. Trump is so dumb, so prone to succumbing to flattery and the mere illusion that his word is others’ command, and so motivated to declare victory regardless of what’s actually going on, that I bet it would work.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr2-2025-05-24"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
</li>

<li id="fn3-2025-05-24">
<p>From, hilariously, <a href="https://www.vanityfair.com/news/2016/03/how-donald-trump-became-the-short-fingered-vulgarian">a short-fingered vulgarian</a>.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr3-2025-05-24"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
</li>


</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Idiocy or Jackassery, You Make the Call: Tripp Mickle on Whether Trump’s ‘Made in America’ iPhone Is a Fantasy</title></entry></feed><!-- THE END -->
