<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>Daring Fireball</title>
<subtitle>By John Gruber</subtitle>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/" />
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main" />
<id>https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main</id>


<updated>2026-01-12T19:17:34Z</updated><rights>Copyright © 2026, John Gruber</rights><entry>
	<title>Apple, Rather Quietly and With No Details, Announces Partnership With Google to Use Gemini Technology for Apple Foundation Models, and Presumably, the Year-Overdue More Personalized Siri</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.cnbc.com/2026/01/12/apple-google-ai-siri-gemini.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wu5" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/12/apple-google-foundation-models-cnbc" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42557</id>
	<published>2026-01-12T18:35:50Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-12T19:17:34Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>CNBC:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The multi-year partnership will lean on Google’s Gemini and cloud
technology for future Apple foundational models, according to a
joint statement obtained by CNBC’s Jim Cramer.</p>

<p>“After careful evaluation, we determined that Google’s technology
provides the most capable foundation for Apple Foundation Models
and we’re excited about the innovative new experiences it will
unlock for our users,” Apple said in a statement on Monday.</p>

<p>The models will continue to run on Apple devices and the company’s
private cloud compute, they added. Apple declined to comment on
the terms of the deal. Google referred CNBC to the joint
statement.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That’s the whole announcement, at least for now. A statement that, as far as I can see, went only to CNBC (and Jim Cramer specifically, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/search/jim+cramer">of all people</a>).</p>

<p>There’s slightly more detail in <a href="https://x.com/NewsFromGoogle/status/2010746083170046376">this brief announcement from Google</a>, on, of all places, Twitter/X:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Joint Statement: Apple and Google have entered into a multi-year
collaboration under which the next generation of Apple Foundation
Models will be based on Google’s Gemini models and cloud
technology. These models will help power future Apple Intelligence
features, including a more personalized Siri coming this year.</p>

<p>After careful evaluation, Apple determined that Google’s Al
[<em>sic</em>] technology provides the most capable foundation for Apple
Foundation Models and is excited about the innovative new
experiences it will unlock for Apple users. Apple Intelligence
will continue to run on Apple devices and Private Cloud Compute,
while maintaining Apple’s industry-leading privacy standards.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I suspect more details will be forthcoming from Apple sooner rather than later. But for now, that’s it.</p>

<p>This phrasing, in both Apple’s statement to Cramer and the joint Apple/Google statement released by Google, is, I think subtly telling about how significant this news is: “Google’s AI technology provides the most capable foundation for Apple Foundation Models”. There’s a slight redundancy with <em>foundation</em> appearing twice in the span of four words. Imagine if WebKit had been named “Safari Rendering Engine” — there would be times when one might need to write “the rendering engine is Safari Rendering Engine”, because that’s what it is, and that’s the name. But in this case, it’s a bit incongruous. A foundation is a foundation; it doesn’t have a foundation. So this brief bit of phrasing reveals the obvious, awkward truth that Apple Foundation Models didn’t actually have a foundation.</p>

<p>Also, perhaps some evidence of OCR copy-and-pasting: in the tweet of the joint statement, marked by “[<em>sic</em>]” above, AI is spelled uppercase-A lowercase-L.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple, Rather Quietly and With No Details, Announces Partnership With Google to Use Gemini Technology for Apple Foundation Models, and Presumably, the Year-Overdue More Personalized Siri’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/12/apple-google-foundation-models-cnbc">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2026/01/resizing_windows_macos_26" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wu4" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026://1.42556</id>
	<published>2026-01-12T16:27:34Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-12T18:44:04Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">https://noheger.at/blog/2026/01/11/the-struggle-of-resizing-windows-on-macos-tahoe/</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Norbert Heger, with a perfectly illustrated post, “<a href="https://noheger.at/blog/2026/01/11/the-struggle-of-resizing-windows-on-macos-tahoe/">The Struggle of Resizing Windows on macOS Tahoe</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Since upgrading to macOS Tahoe, I’ve noticed that quite often
my attempts to resize a window are failing. This never happened
to me before in almost 40 years of using computers. So why all
of a sudden?</p>

<p>It turns out that my initial click in the window corner
instinctively happens in an area where the window doesn’t respond
to it. The window expects this click to happen in an area of 19 ×
19 pixels, located near the window corner.</p>

<p>If the window had no rounded corners at all, 62% of that area
would lie <em>inside</em> the window.</p>

<p>But due to the huge corner radius in Tahoe, most of it — about
75% — now lies <em>outside</em> the window.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Here is Heger’s illustration of the hit target for the invisible resize button on MacOS 26:</p>

<p><img
    src = "/misc/2026/01/clickable-area-2.webp"
    width = 500
    alt = "Screenshot illustrating the hit target for where you can click to initiate resizing a window in MacOS 26."
></p>

<p>It was, I’d argue, a small mistake for Apple to stop putting a visual affordance in the lower right corner of windows to show where to click to resize the window. It was a bigger mistake to change the scrollbars on MacOS to look and work like those on iOS — invisible, except while you’re actually scrolling (by default, that is — savvy Mac users <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/how-to/make-scroll-bars-always-visible/">keep them always visible</a>). The removal of the resize indicator happened long ago, in Mac OS X 10.7 Lion, released in July 2011. <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2011/07/mac-os-x-10-7/#page-3">John Siracusa’s 10.7 review</a> illustrates the before and after. Before (10.6):</p>

<p><img
    src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2026/01/siracusa-10.6-snow-leopard-gui.png"
    alt = "Screenshot illustrating the standard GUI controls of Mac OS X 10.6 Snow Leopard."
></p>

<p>After (10.7):</p>

<p><img
    src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2026/01/siracusa-10.7-lion-gui.png"
    alt = "Screenshot illustrating the standard GUI controls of Mac OS X 10.6 Snow Leopard."
></p>

<p>I think everything about the 10.7 Lion GUI looks better than the 10.6 Snow Leopard GUI — <em>except</em> for the omission of the resize affordance in the corner. The visible resize affordance didn’t just tell you where to click to resize the window, it also told you that the window <em>could be resized</em> in the first place. In 10.6 and earlier, a window that could be resized showed you that it could be resized because it had a visible indicator. Windows that didn’t have that indicator were windows whose size was fixed. From 10.7 through today, the only way to know if a window even <em>can</em> be resized is to move your mouse cursor to the corner and try. The grippy-strip affordance offered contextual information about the window.</p>

<p>I can imagine the thinking at Apple behind this change, 15 years ago. The visible grippy-strip affordance in the lower-right corner isn’t really <em>necessary</em>. All users “know” that they can resize windows by clicking and dragging from the corner. And, although in ancient times users could <em>only</em> resize windows by clicking in the affordance in the lower-right corner, by 2011 it had long been the case that users could resize windows in two dimensions starting from <em>any corner</em>, or in one dimension starting from any <em>edge</em> of the window. (But windows on the Mac <a href="https://guidebookgallery.org/screenshots/macos90">used to have visible edges denoting the window chrome</a>, too. The Mac’s history is replete with glorious examples of UI clarity and precision.) So why draw the resize affordance in the lower-right corner when you can resize from any corner or window edge? Plus, the space for the lower-right grippy-strip affordance was made by the empty space at the intersection of vertical and horizontal scrollbar channels — and since Apple decided to make scrollbars invisible (by default) in Mac OS X 10.7 in 2011, there was no longer an otherwise unused square space in the corner for the resize affordance to be drawn. (It was sort of like the Free Parking space on <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2026/01/monopoly.jpeg">a Monopoly board</a>.)</p>

<p>One can argue with the logic behind these changes, 15 years ago. I’ll repeat that I think it was a grave error to make scrollbars invisible by default. I would argue that while the visible grippy-strip isn’t <em>necessary</em>, it’s nice to have. (As noted above, its presence showed you whether a window <em>could</em> be resized.) But there was, clearly, logic behind the decisions Apple made in 2011. They were carefully considered. The new logic was that you no longer look for a grippy-strip to click on to resize a window. You simply click inside the edge of a window. And of course Apple added a small affordance to the hit target for those edges, such that if you clicked <em>just</em> outside the window, that would count as “close enough” to assume you intended to click on the edge. Most users surely never noticed that. A lot of nice little touches in UI design go unnoticed because they’re nice little touches.</p>

<p>Until MacOS 26, <em>most</em> of the hit target to initiate the resizing of a window was <em>inside</em> the window. Because, of course, right? Even though MacOS (well, Mac OS X) stopped rendering a visible resize grippy-strip 15 years ago, the user could simply imagine that there was still a grippy area <em>inside</em> the lower right corner of every resizable window. It would make no sense whatsoever for the click target to resize a window to be <em>outside</em> the window. Why would anyone expect that? It would work against what our own eyes, and years of experience, are telling us. You pick up a thing to move it or stretch it by grabbing the thing. Not by grabbing <a href="https://noheger.at/blog/wp-content/uploads/2026/01/scrambled-eggs.mov">next to the thing</a>.</p>

<p>The windows on MacOS 26 Tahoe don’t really have comically large, childish corner radiuses. They just <em>look like they do</em> because some jackasses at Apple — <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/12/bad_dye_job">all of whom, I pray, are now at Meta</a> — thought they looked better that way. It’s a straight-up inversion of Steve Jobs’s maxim that design is about how things <em>work</em>, not how they <em>look</em>. I can think of no better example to prove that the new UI in MacOS 26 Tahoe was designed by people who do not understand or care about the most basic fundamental principles of good design.</p>

<p>The good news is, I have a solution. Do not upgrade to MacOS 26 Tahoe. If you have already upgraded, <a href="https://www.macworld.com/article/671318/how-to-downgrade-macos-revert-back.html">downgrade</a>. Why suffer willingly with a user interface that presents you with absurdities like window resizing affordances that are 75 percent <em>outside</em> the window?</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Why It’s Difficult to Resize Windows on MacOS 26 Dyehoe</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Statement From Federal Reserve Chair Jerome H. Powell</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.federalreserve.gov/newsevents/speech/powell20260111a.htm" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wu3" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/11/powell-statement" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42555</id>
	<published>2026-01-12T02:52:53Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-12T02:54:53Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Shit’s getting real, folks.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Statement From Federal Reserve Chair Jerome H. Powell’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/11/powell-statement">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Copilot Money</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://copilot.money/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=editorial&amp;utm_campaign=daringfireball_122225_web25&amp;utm_term=DARING" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wu1" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/11/copilot-money" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42553</id>
	<published>2026-01-11T21:25:00Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-11T21:25:26Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to Copilot Money for sponsoring last week at DF. Copilot is a personal finance app for the iPhone, iPad, and Mac, and they’ve always deeply believed in the value of embracing the design idioms and technical features of truly native apps for Apple platforms. Apple has noticed, awarding Copilot an <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/copilot-track-budget-money/id1447330651#productRatings">App Store Editor’s Choice</a> and featuring Copilot earlier this year on Apple Developer <a href="https://developer.apple.com/articles/copilot-money/">for their use of Swift Charts</a>.</p>

<p>Copilot’s big news this month is they’ve launched a new web app, bringing access to Copilot from any device, anywhere. It’s designed with all the attention to detail — and concern for privacy and security — as their native apps.</p>

<p>Copilot Money brings all your spending, budgets, investments, and net worth into one organized dashboard, with intelligent categorization and insights that help you stay on track without spreadsheets or app-hopping. Designed to feel calm and intuitive, Copilot makes it easy to understand your finances across all your devices.</p>

<p>Copilot first sponsored DF back in 2021. My wife and I started using it then to track our finances, and we haven’t looked back. Copilot Money isn’t just better than anything we’d used before, it absolutely blew everything else away. It’s easy to connect to your financial accounts, and once you do, you don’t need to spend any effort at all to enter transactions. Copilot just tracks it all automatically, and most importantly, presents it to you in clear, intuitive ways. It’s so good. I’m not saying that because they sponsored DF last week — I’m saying that as a happy paying customer for over four years now.</p>

<p>Copilot is offering DF readers two months free with code <strong>DARING</strong>, plus 26% off your first year for a limited time, <a href="https://copilot.money/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=editorial&amp;utm_campaign=daringfireball_122225_web25&amp;utm_term=DARING">available through this link</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Copilot Money’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/11/copilot-money">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>U.S. Senators Ask Cook and Pichai to Remove X and Grok From App Store and Play Store</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.wyden.senate.gov/imo/media/doc/letter_to_apple_and_google_on_removing_x_and_grok_from_app_store_192026pdf.pdf" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wu2" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/11/senators-app-stores-grok" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42554</id>
	<published>2026-01-11T21:24:47Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-11T21:24:48Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>U.S. Senators Ron Wyden (D, Oregon), Ed Markey (D, Massachussetts), and Ben Ray Luján (D, New Mexico), in a letter addressed to Tim Cook and Sundar Pichai:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Your app stores’ policies are clear. Google’s terms of service
require apps to “prohibit users from creating, uploading, or
distributing content that facilitates the exploitation or abuse of
children” including prohibiting the “portrayal of children in a
manner that could result in the sexual exploitation of children.”
Apps that do not are said to be subject to “immediate removal from
Google Play” for violations. Similarly, Apple’s terms of service
bar apps from including “offensive” or “just plain creepy”
content, which under any definition must include
nonconsensually-generated sexualized images of children and women.
Further, Apple’s terms explicitly bar apps from including content
that is “[o]vertly sexual or pornographic material” including
material “intended to stimulate erotic rather than aesthetic or
emotional feelings.”</p>

<p>Turning a blind eye to X’s egregious behavior would make a mockery
of your moderation practices. Indeed, not taking action would
undermine your claims in public and in court that your app stores
offer a safer user experience than letting users download apps
directly to their phones. This principle has been core to your
advocacy against legislative reforms to increase app store
competition and your defenses to claims that your app stores abuse
their market power through their payment systems.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Emphasizing that leaving X and Grok available in the App Store and Play Store is directly contradictory to Apple and Google’s stated reasons for maintaining control over software distribution is a good pressure point. Do they selectively enforce content moderation based on whims and/or shifting political winds, or rigorously enforce the plain language of their own content guidelines? Which is it? It can’t be both.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘U.S. Senators Ask Cook and Pichai to Remove X and Grok From App Store and Play Store’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/11/senators-app-stores-grok">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2026/01/fuck_you_make_me_without_saying_the_words" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wu0" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026://1.42552</id>
	<published>2026-01-10T21:04:26Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-11T04:32:32Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Make the Trump administration object. Make them defend the indefensible — in public. Make clear why the apps were removed from the app stores and force Musk — and Trump, if he chooses — to argue that those things are A-OK by them. In court.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Elizabeth Lopatto, writing at The Verge, “<a href="https://www.theverge.com/policy/859902/apple-google-run-by-cowards">Tim Cook and Sundar Pichai Are Cowards</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Since X’s users started using <a href="https://www.theverge.com/ai-artificial-intelligence/855832/grok-undressing-children-csam-law-x-elon-musk">Grok to undress women and
children</a> using deepfake images, I have been waiting for
what I assumed would be inevitable: X getting booted from Apple’s
and Google’s app stores. The fact that it hasn’t happened yet
tells me something serious about Silicon Valley’s leadership: Tim
Cook and Sundar Pichai are spineless cowards who are terrified of
Elon Musk.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Lopatto’s outrage and righteous anger are justified, but I think mostly misdirected. Apple and Google — and thus, Cook and Pichai, as the men who sit behind the desks where the buck stops at both companies — are culpable. But this is ultimately not about them, and not about Musk. It’s Trump, as president, they fear. Not Musk. And they are correct to fear Trump.</p>

<p>Year one of Trump 2.0 has crystallized what had become — after decades of deliberate restraint after World War II, and even more so after the end of the Cold War — overlooked. The Presidency of the United States bestows upon its officeholder enormous, unparalleled, power. No one was afraid of Trump after he lost to Joe Biden in 2020. The man was <a href="https://www.npr.org/2024/05/30/g-s1-1848/trump-hush-money-trial-34-counts">convicted of 34 felonies in a cold New York City courtroom in May 2024</a>, a mere 19 months ago. Trump expected and asked for riots outside the courtroom. He got nothing but <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/05/02/nyregion/trump-trial-supporters.html">pathetic support from a handful of kooks</a>. A year earlier, he lost <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/E._Jean_Carroll_v._Donald_J._Trump">a humiliating sexual assault civil lawsuit to E. Jean Carroll</a>. Trump, just a year and a half ago, was a buffoon getting his mug shot taken. Today he’s arguing that his power is <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/08/us/politics/trump-interview-power-morality.html?unlocked_article_code=1.DVA.5wt4.ux02n3D96aZH&amp;smid=url-share">unchecked by anything other than his own sense of morality</a>.</p>

<p>No other president has ever abused (or, if you support him, wielded) the powers of the office like Trump has. The power and influence of Tim Cook and Sundar Pichai, CEOs of two of the top five companies in the world, isn’t merely superseded by Trump’s power and influence as president. Their power and influence are <em>dwarfed</em> by Trump’s. Any credible argument about how they should act must acknowledge that profound imbalance.</p>

<p>Lopatto, in her closing:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I never want to hear any moral grandstanding from these boys ever
again. The next time Tim Cook says “<a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/tech/tech-news/apple-ceo-tim-cook-slams-facebook-privacy-human-right-it-n860816">privacy is a human
right</a>,” the only possible response is to laugh in his face.
I mean, Apple and Google are fine distributing an app that has
created an <a href="https://www.motherjones.com/politics/2026/01/grok-x-musk-deepfake-renee-good-ice/">undressed image Grok made of Renee Nicole Good</a>,
the mother who was shot by ICE in Minneapolis. How <em>do</em> you plan
to defend getting rid of the <a href="https://www.theverge.com/news/791170/iceblock-app-store-removed-by-apple">ICEBlock app</a> while allowing X
to generate degrading images of a woman ICE killed? Can Apple and
Google even identify their values beyond their commitment to
“shareholder value”? What’s your fucking endgame here, guys?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The profound power imbalance here is frustrating. But also terrifying. It’s <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/08/gold_frankincense_and_silicon">folly to think these CEOs should steer their companies into direct confrontation with Trump</a>. It would do no ultimate good for Apple or Google to burn themselves to the ground in protest. These men aren’t beholden to shareholders, per se. They’re doing their duty to institutions they’ve devoted their lives to. Companies that are worth preserving and protecting. Perhaps not in your estimation, but certainly from theirs.</p>

<p>But abject obsequiousness — which more and more seems the path Cook and Pichai are choosing — is no more justifiable a response than corporate suicide. The situation is not binary: acquiescence or war. There is a broad middle ground, founded on principle.</p>

<p>Disney’s response to the Jimmy Kimmel controversy a few months ago <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/10/07/hodges-cook-iceblock">shows the way</a>. Defend the company’s principles while simultaneously defending the company from Trump’s demented wrath. You can take the position of “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/10/03/fuck-you-make-me">Fuck you, make me</a>” without ever saying those words. Objection is not confrontation. Do the right thing and enforce the App Store and Play Store guidelines, and remove X and Grok from the stores. Make Musk object. Make the Trump administration object. Make them defend the indefensible — in public. Make clear why the apps were removed from the app stores and force Musk — and Trump, if he chooses — to argue that those things are A-OK by them. In court.</p>

<p>The judicious path for Apple and Google (and every other U.S. company) may well be to obey the law, even when the law is being actively corrupted. But the correct path is <em>not</em> to <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/24/on-tyranny">obey in advance</a>. Stand behind the law while the law still exists on your side. Disney resisted Trump’s preposterous demand that they fire Jimmy Kimmel without lasting controversy, simply by standing firm in their conviction. Apple and Google could certainly do the same regarding apps that are being used to <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cvg1mzlryxeo">generate CSAM</a> and <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/tech/internet/x-paywall-ai-image-grok-app-bikini-allows-sexual-deepfakes-rcna252647">deepfake harassment</a>, regardless if the apps are part of the private fiefdom of Trump’s ally Elon Musk. It’s wise for Cook and Pichai to <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/08/gold_frankincense_and_silicon">pick their battles</a>. This one, I think, is worth picking. This is a moment when the App Store and Play Store can stand firmly on the side of longstanding and correct societal norms.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ ‘Fuck You, Make Me’ Without Saying the Words</title></entry><entry>
	<title>MAGA’s Foundational Lie</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/2026/02/trump-indecency-jan-6-pardons/685324/?gift=aQyUJR7AIw1mJWdQ6Ed6yKamvkJf5cw73KeIYXcSxQ4" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wtz" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/10/maga-foundational-lie" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42551</id>
	<published>2026-01-10T19:31:07Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-10T19:31:08Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jeffrey Goldberg in The Atlantic (gift link), on the fifth anniversary of the January 6 insurrection and the first year of the second Trump presidency:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We have been watching indecency triumph in the public sphere on
and off for more than 10 years now, since the moment Trump
insulted John McCain’s war record. For reasons that are quite
possibly too unbearable to contemplate, a large group of American
voters was not repulsed by such slander — they were actually
aroused by it — and our politics have not been the same. Much has
been said, including by me, about Trump’s narcissism, his
autocratic inclinations, his disconnection from reality, but not
nearly enough has been said about his fundamental indecency, the
characteristic that undergirds everything he says and does.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘MAGA’s Foundational Lie’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/10/maga-foundational-lie">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Jim Moylan and the Moylan Arrow</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.wsj.com/business/autos/ford-gas-arrow-inventor-jim-moylan-6b2ef066?st=uhr6ym&amp;reflink=desktopwebshare_permalink" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wty" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/09/moylan" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42550</id>
	<published>2026-01-09T14:47:26Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-09T14:48:20Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Ben Cohen, writing last week for The Wall Street Journal (gift link):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>One rainy day 40 years ago, Moylan was headed to a meeting across
Ford’s campus and hopped in a company car. When he saw the fuel
tank was nearly empty, he stopped at a gas pump. What happened
next is something that’s happened to all of us: He realized that
he’d parked on the wrong side.</p>

<p>Unlike the rest of us, he wasn’t infuriated. He was inspired. By
the time he pulled his car around, he was already thinking about
how to solve this everyday inconvenience that drives people
absolutely crazy. And because the gas pump wasn’t covered by an
overhead awning, he was also soaking wet. But when he got back to
the office, Moylan didn’t even bother taking off his drenched coat
when he started typing the first draft of a memo.</p>

<p>“I would like to propose a small addition,” he wrote, “in all
passenger car and truck lines.” The proposal he had in mind was a
symbol on the dashboard that would tell drivers which side of the
car the gas tank was on. [...]</p>

<p>As soon as they read his memo, they began prototyping his little
indicator that would be known as the Moylan Arrow. Within months,
it was on the dashboard of Ford’s upcoming models. Within years,
it was ripped off by the competition. Before long, it was a
fixture of just about every car in the world.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>What a fantastic story. I’m old enough that I remember learning to drive on cars that didn’t have the Moylan Arrow. Then I remember spotting one sometime in the 1990s, and wondering if I’d just never noticed them before. But no: this seemingly incredibly obvious design element had only recently been invented. The Journal has a copy of Moylan’s original memo, and it’s a delight to read. Clear, concise, persuasive.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Society loves the founder who builds new companies, like Henry
Ford,” Ford CEO Jim Farley told me. “I would argue that Jim Moylan
is an equally compelling kind of disrupter: an engineer in a large
company who insisted on making our daily lives better.”</p>

<p>These days, there are two types of drivers: the ones aware of the
Moylan Arrow and the ones who get to find out.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Rest in peace, Jim Moylan.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Jim Moylan and the Moylan Arrow’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/09/moylan">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The New York Times Profiles John Ternus</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2026/01/08/technology/apple-ceo-tim-cook-john-ternus.html?unlocked_article_code=1.DFA.Qm0v.SxztBxvFrAF-&amp;smid=url-share" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wtx" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/08/nyt-ternus" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42549</id>
	<published>2026-01-09T04:14:38Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-10T22:59:59Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Kalley Huang and Tripp Mickle, writing for The New York Times (gift link):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Threading the needle between adding new bells and whistles to
Apple’s products while watching the bottom line has defined the
careful, low-profile style of Mr. Ternus, who joined Apple in
2001. He is now considered by some company insiders to be the
front-runner to replace Tim Cook, Apple’s longtime chief
executive, if Mr. Cook decides to step aside.</p>

<p>Apple last year began accelerating its planning for Mr. Cook’s
succession, according to three people close to the company who
spoke on the condition of anonymity about Apple’s confidential
deliberations. Mr. Cook, 65, has told senior leaders that he is
tired and would like to reduce his workload, the people said.
Should he step down, Mr. Cook is likely to become the chairman of
Apple’s board, according to three people close to the company.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Cook may well be preparing to retire as CEO. He is 65! But it doesn’t ring true to me that he’s telling “senior leaders” that he’s tired. First, I’ve heard otherwise from actual senior leaders at the company. Second, any senior leader he’d tell that to, if true, wouldn’t share it.</p>

<p>It seems to me that aside from the utterly normal and plainly obvious speculation that, at age 65, he might be on the cusp of retiring as CEO, there’s something going on where a narrative is being spread that Cook is in poor health. Mark Gurman included two paragraphs about a tremor in Cook’s hands <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/08/srouji">in his colossal fuck-up at Bloomberg a month ago</a>, falsely reporting that Johny Srouji was unhappy and on the cusp of leaving Apple for a competitor.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Despite his low profile, Mr. Ternus appears to have shot to the
front of the pack to be Apple’s next C.E.O., according to four
people close to the company.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The Times report describes Ternus as “low-profile” three times. This makes no sense. Ternus is one of Apple’s <em>highest</em>-profile executives. I would guess that over the last five years he’s appeared in more keynotes, for more time, than anyone but Cook and Craig Federighi.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>But Mr. Cook is also preparing several other internal candidates
to be his potential successor, two of the people said. They could
include Craig Federighi, Apple’s head of software; Eddy Cue, its
head of services; Greg Joswiak, its head of worldwide marketing;
and Deirdre O’Brien, its head of retail and human resources.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I don’t think there’s any chance that Cook’s successor will be someone who isn’t a frequent presence in Apple keynotes. I can’t recall O’Brien ever appearing in a keynote, and Cue hasn’t appeared in one for several years. Also, Cue is 61 and Joz is 62. Neither is that much younger than Cook.</p>

<p>Two interesting tidbits re: Ternus:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Within about three years, he became a manager, said Steve Siefert,
Mr. Ternus’s first boss at Apple. During that time, their team
moved office floors, switching from a closed office plan to mostly
open seating with a few offices. When he was promoted, Mr. Ternus
had the option to move into one of those offices but declined.</p>

<p>Mr. Ternus was “a man of the people,” Mr. Siefert said, adding
that the decision to sit with his team likely helped Mr. Ternus
manage and motivate his staff. When Mr. Siefert retired in 2011,
freeing up his office, Mr. Ternus once again said he wanted to
remain in the open space.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“If you want to make an iPhone every year, Ternus is your guy,”
said Cameron Rogers, who worked on product and software
engineering management at Apple from 2005 to 2022. [...]</p>

<p>“He’s a nice guy,” Mr. Rogers said. “He’s someone you want to hang
out with. Everyone loves him because he’s great. Has he made any
hard decisions? No. Are there hard problems he’s solved in
hardware? No.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This guy Cameron Rogers sounds like a real asshole.</p>

<p>What complaints does anyone have about Apple hardware over the last five years? Off the top of my head I can’t think of any that are serious. Ternus has overseen what I’d argue is the best sustained stretch of Apple hardware, across more product lines than ever, in the company’s 50-year history. But he didn’t make any hard decisions or solve any hard problems. Sure. Hardware is easy.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The New York Times Profiles John Ternus’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/08/nyt-ternus">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Know Your Rights: Filming and Photographing the Police</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.aclu.org/issues/free-speech/photographers-rights/filming-and-photographing-police" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wtw" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/08/filming-and-photographing-the-police" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42548</id>
	<published>2026-01-09T01:11:33Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-09T13:33:42Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The ACLU:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Taking photographs and video of things that are plainly visible in
public spaces is a constitutional right — and that includes
police and other government officials carrying out their duties.</p>

<p>However, there is a widespread, continuing pattern of law
enforcement officers ordering people to stop taking photographs or
video in public places and harassing, detaining, and arresting
those who fail to comply.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.aclu.org/know-your-rights/protesters-rights#i-want-to-take-pictures-or-shoot-video-at-a-protest">Here’s their advice</a> on what to say and do if you are stopped or detained for taking photographs or video.</p>

<p>Also, as good a time as ever for one of my periodic reminders to remember <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2022/06/require_a_passcode_to_unlock_your_iphone">how to hard-lock your iPhone to temporarily disable Face ID</a>: press and hold the side button and either one of the volume buttons at the same time for a few seconds.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Know Your Rights: Filming and Photographing the Police’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/08/filming-and-photographing-the-police">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Chase to Become New Issuer of Apple Card</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2026/01/chase-to-become-new-issuer-of-apple-card/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wtv" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/08/chase-apple-card-issuer" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42547</id>
	<published>2026-01-09T01:10:33Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-10T21:47:53Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Apple Newsroom:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Today, Apple and Chase announced that Chase will become the new
issuer of Apple Card, with an expected transition in approximately
24 months.</p>

<p>Apple Card users can continue to enjoy the award-winning
experience of Apple Card, which includes up to 3 percent unlimited
Daily Cash back on every purchase, easy-to-navigate spending
tools, Apple Card Family, access to a high-yield Savings account,
and more. Mastercard will remain the payment network for Apple
Card, and Apple Card users can continue to access Mastercard’s
global acceptance and benefits. [...]</p>

<p>During this transition, Apple Card users can continue to use their
card as they normally do. More information, including FAQs, is
available at <a href="https://learn.applecard.apple/transition">learn.applecard.apple/transition</a>. Additional
details will be shared with users as the transition date
approaches.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In the press release, Apple’s only mention of the current issuer, Goldman Sachs, is in the small gray fine print footnotes. (Goldman is mentioned prominently in <a href="https://learn.applecard.apple/transition">the linked FAQ</a>.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Chase to Become New Issuer of Apple Card’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/08/chase-apple-card-issuer">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Why Are Grok and X Still Available in App Stores?</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.wired.com/story/x-grok-app-store-nudify-csam-apple-google-content-moderation/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wtu" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/08/grok-x-app-stores" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42546</id>
	<published>2026-01-08T23:02:35Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-09T13:38:39Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Caroline Haskins, writing for Wired (<a href="https://apple.news/AmKJC6gcCQGGULEgLPnd9xw">News+ link</a>, in case Wired’s paywall blocks you):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Elon Musk’s AI chatbot Grok is <a href="https://archive.ph/o/v4RcV/https://www.wired.com/story/grok-is-generating-sexual-content-far-more-graphic-than-whats-on-x/">being used</a> to flood X with
<a href="https://archive.ph/o/v4RcV/https://www.wired.com/story/grok-is-pushing-ai-undressing-mainstream/">thousands</a> of sexualized images of adults and apparent
minors wearing minimal clothing. Some of this content appears to
not only violate X’s own <a href="https://archive.ph/o/v4RcV/https://help.x.com/en/rules-and-policies/twitter-rules">policies</a>, which prohibit sharing
illegal content such as child sexual abuse material (CSAM), but
may also violate the guidelines of Apple’s App Store and the
Google Play store.</p>

<p>Apple and Google both explicitly ban apps containing CSAM, which
is illegal to host and distribute in many countries. The tech
giants also forbid apps that contain pornographic material or
facilitate harassment. The Apple App Store <a href="https://archive.ph/o/v4RcV/https://developer.apple.com/app-store/review/guidelines/">says</a> it doesn’t
allow “overtly sexual or pornographic material,” as well as
“defamatory, discriminatory, or mean-spirited content,” especially
if the app is “likely to humiliate, intimidate, or harm a targeted
individual or group.” The Google Play store <a href="https://archive.ph/o/v4RcV/https://support.google.com/googleplay/android-developer/answer/9878810?hl=en&amp;ref_topic=9877466&amp;sjid=1253303111790657994-NC">bans</a> apps that
“contain or promote content associated with sexually predatory
behavior, or distribute non-consensual sexual content,” and well
as programs that “contain or facilitate threats, harassment, or
bullying.”</p>

<p>Over the past two years, Apple and Google removed a number of
“nudify” and AI image-generation apps after <a href="https://archive.ph/o/v4RcV/https://www.bbc.com/news/videos/cx205lnplpwo">investigations</a>
by the BBC and 404 Media found <a href="https://archive.ph/o/v4RcV/https://www.404media.co/instagram-advertises-nonconsensual-ai-nude-apps/">they were being advertised</a>
or used to effectively turn ordinary photos into explicit images
of women without their consent.</p>

<p>But at the time of publication, both the X app and the <a href="https://archive.ph/o/v4RcV/https://www.wired.com/story/grok-is-generating-sexual-content-far-more-graphic-than-whats-on-x/">standalone
Grok app</a> remain available in both app stores. Apple, Google,
and X did not respond to requests for comment.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I just browsed through the last five minutes of replies generated by Grok on Twitter/X, and saw both seeming CSAM (all young Asian women) and just outright hardcore pornographic video (that, for what it’s worth, seemed to feature adults, whether real or generated).</p>

<p>It was a barely concealed secret <em>before</em> Musk bought Twitter that Twitter had an active dark underbelly of pornographic content. But you had to know where to look for it. It really wasn’t something you might just stumble upon. Now you get hardcore porno just by looking at the profile page for Grok. And any user can send any photo they want to @grok and tell it to change or remove the subject’s clothing and change their pose. Lord only knows what people are generating privately using the standalone Grok app.</p>

<p>If a new social network app launched featuring this content, it surely would be removed from the App Store and Play Store. X is seemingly untouchable for political reasons.</p>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> Recall that <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/technology-46275138">Apple pulled the Tumblr app from the App Store in 2018</a> for similar content.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Why Are Grok and X Still Available in App Stores?’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/08/grok-x-app-stores">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Gold Trump Phone Still Hasn’t Shipped</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/news/851151/trump-phone-missed-another-release-date" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wtt" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/08/gold-trump-phone-still-hasnt-shipped" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42545</id>
	<published>2026-01-08T22:20:47Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-08T23:11:36Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Maybe “next year” meant “next next year”?</p>

<p>(They’re still accepting <a href="https://phone.trumpmobile.com/t1-phone/MV8y">$100 deposits for pre-orders</a>.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Gold Trump Phone Still Hasn’t Shipped’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/08/gold-trump-phone-still-hasnt-shipped">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2026/01/lets_call_a_murder_a_murder" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wts" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026://1.42544</id>
	<published>2026-01-08T20:01:13Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-08T21:26:24Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Caitlin Callenson’s courage in the face of insane danger is just remarkable.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/video/us/100000010631041/minneapolis-ice-shooting-video.html">The New York Times has frame-by-frame analysis</a>, from three angles, of the murder of 37-year-old Renee Good in Minneapolis yesterday. She was shot to death by <s>a still-unnamed</s> mask-wearing ICE agent <a href="https://www.startribune.com/ice-agent-who-fatally-shot-woman-in-minneapolis-is-identified/601560214">Jonathan Ross</a>, with what was obviously no justification. The shooting is, justifiably, national news. I’m sure you’ve read about it. But this Times analysis coolly and calmly shows just how outrageous it was, and how preposterous the claims from President Trump and <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/atrupar.com/post/3mbwjgwh5xc2u">Secretary of Hats Kristi Noem</a> are ostensibly attempting to defend it — both as an act of self-defense by the cowardly ICE agent and, even more absurdly, as an act of “domestic terrorism” by Good, who was attempting to do nothing more than drive away from the scene.</p>

<p>George Orwell, in <em>1984</em>: “The Party told you to reject the evidence of your eyes and ears. It was their final, most essential command.” Let’s stop pussyfooting around what happened here. This ICE agent murdered Renee Good, in broad daylight, in front of many witnesses and multiple cameras. Trust the evidence of your eyes and ears.</p>

<hr />

<p>But I want to add another note. The main footage here comes from bystander Caitlin Callenson. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=K9CJY5p0xz4">Here’s her full 4m:25s footage</a>, uncensored, hosted — with credit, and I hope, permission — on the YouTube account of Minnesota Reformer. Be warned that it shows Good being shot to death (albeit sans gore), and contains many loud profanities. This is <em>very</em> good and clear footage. It is difficult viewing but you should watch it. Callenson was very close to Good’s vehicle. I’d say about 30 feet or so. You can see why she thought to start filming  <em>before</em> the murderous agent drew his gun and fired. The scene was already chaotic. But then, <em>after</em> the murderous agent fired three shots — just 30 or 40 feet in front of Callenson — Callenson had the courage and conviction to stay with the scene and keep filming. Not to run away, but instead to follow the scene. To keep filming. To continue documenting with as best clarity as she could, what was unfolding.</p>

<p>I’d like to think I’d have done the same. I’m not sure at all that I would have. I definitely might have been using my iPhone to shoot video of the incident up until the shots were fired. But when that happened, my mind would immediately have turned to “<em>These agents are scared and angry and out of control, and</em> that <em>one just went psycho and fired his gun unprovoked. That guy is just as likely to shoot more people as he was the woman he just shot. His angry, scared, obviously undertrained colleagues might join in. And the most likely people they’ll shoot next are people pointing cameras at them.</em>” I do not know what I would have done in that moment. I hope I never find out. But I know with certainty what I would immediately think, which is that if I choose to continue shooting video of the incident, there is a very good chance one of them will shoot or brutalize me next. It would make <em>more</em> sense to shoot someone filming the scene than it did to shoot Renee Good in the first place. Good’s killing was utterly senseless. Shooting a witness with a running camera and then destroying their phone to eliminate the evidence (and a witness) would make some sense. Sick sense, but sense.</p>

<p>But in that moment of pandemonium and obvious danger to herself, Callenson didn’t merely continue filming. She didn’t merely stand her ground. She proceeded <em>into</em> the scene to get closer to Good’s vehicle after it crashed into a parked car, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ixNkVvtC5FY">Mr. Brown-style</a>. She pointed her camera directly at the only-partially-masked face of the murderous agent as he walked away from Good’s crashed vehicle, then got into an unmarked Chevy Tahoe and just fled from the scene like the obvious coward he is. I presume the murderous agent will soon be identified, and Callenson’s clear steady-handed footage may be the reason why. [<strong>Update:</strong> While I was finishing this post, the Minnesota Star Tribune identified and named him — <a href="https://www.startribune.com/ice-agent-who-fatally-shot-woman-in-minneapolis-is-identified/601560214">Jonathan Ross</a> — and indeed, it was Callenson’s footage that made his identification possible.] And, to top it off, all the while — starting <em>before</em> the shooting — Callenson was screaming “Shame!” in the faces of these agents, and calling them out on their abhorrent indefensible actions. To each of their directives to her, she responds, with the definition of righteous anger, “You shot someone in the fucking face!” (Emily Heller, Renee Good’s neighbor, <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2026/01/07/us/video/ebof-minneapolis-ice-shooting-witness-emily-heller">showed similar courage</a>, telling an ICE agent who refused to allow a citizen physician to check on Good (who laid dying or dead inside her car), as she filmed the scene, “How can I relax, you just killed my fucking neighbor! You shot her in the fucking face! You killed my fucking neighbor! How do you show up to work every day?”)</p>

<p>Callenson’s courage in the face of obvious danger is just remarkable. My god. She rose to the moment in a crucible of chaos, insanity, and murderous violence. We all need to think about what she did, to really imagine ourselves in the same moment — the danger she stood up to, and the principles she stood up for — if we hope to do the same if a similar moment comes to us.</p>

<p>And, to top it off, she had the presence of mind to shoot her historic footage in widescreen. </p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Let’s Call a Murder a Murder</title></entry><entry>
	<title>The Obvious, the Easy, and the Possible</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/the-obvious-the-easy-and-the-possible-2e11a3fb" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wtr" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/07/the-obvious-the-easy-and-the-possible" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42543</id>
	<published>2026-01-07T23:41:39Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-07T23:41:40Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>This 2021 post from Jason Fried is a good chaser to his “<a href="https://world.hey.com/jason/the-big-regression-da7fc60d">The Big Regression</a>” this week (which I <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/06/the-big-regression">linked to yesterday</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Much of the tension in product development and interface design
comes from trying to balance the obvious, the easy, and the
possible. Figuring out which things go in which bucket is critical
to fully understanding how to make something useful.</p>

<p>Shouldn’t everything be obvious? Unless you’re making a product
that just does one thing — like a paperclip, for example — everything won’t be obvious. You have to make tough calls about
what needs to be obvious, what should be easy, and what should be
possible. The more things something (a product, a feature, a
screen, etc) does, the more calls you have to make.</p>

<p>This isn’t the same as prioritizing things. High, medium, low
priority doesn’t tell you enough about the problem. “What needs to
be obvious?” is a better question to ask than “What’s high
priority?” Further, priority doesn’t tell you anything about cost.
And the first thing to internalize is that everything has a cost.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><em>Obvious / easy / possible</em> is a good filter through which to create — and critique — designs. To borrow an example from <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/06/the-big-regression">yesterday</a>: old-fashioned analog light switches are exemplars of obviousness; most new-fashioned smart switches are exemplars of possibility.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Obvious, the Easy, and the Possible’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/07/the-obvious-the-easy-and-the-possible">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Howard Oakley on the MacOS 26 Tahoe UI</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://eclecticlight.co/2025/12/28/last-year-on-my-mac-look-back-in-disbelief/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wtq" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/06/howard-oakley-on-the-macos-26-tahoe-ui" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42542</id>
	<published>2026-01-06T23:31:31Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-10T19:05:17Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Howard Oakley, writing at The Eclectic Light Company</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>macOS Tahoe’s visual interface:</p>

<ul>
<li>Fits largely rectangular contents into windows with excessively
rounded corners.</li>
<li>Enlarges controls without any functional benefit.</li>
<li>Results in app icons being more uniform, thus less
distinguishable and memorable.</li>
<li>Fails to distinguish tools, controls and other interface
elements using differences in tone, so making them harder
to use.</li>
<li>Makes a mess where transparent layers are superimposed, and
won’t reduce transparency when that’s needed to render its
interface more accessible.</li>
</ul>

<p>Maybe this is because I’m getting older, but that gives me the
benefit of having experienced Apple’s older interfaces, with their
exceptional quality and functionality.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s just remarkable how much better-looking MacOS was 10 years ago, compared to MacOS 26 Tahoe <em>at its best</em>. And it’s equally remarkable just how bad MacOS 26 Tahoe looks in many typical, non-contrived situations, where entire menus, search fields, and window titles are rendered completely illegible.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Howard Oakley on the MacOS 26 Tahoe UI’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/06/howard-oakley-on-the-macos-26-tahoe-ui">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Icons in Menus Everywhere — Send Help’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.jim-nielsen.com/2025/icons-in-menus/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wtp" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/06/nielsen-icons-in-menus" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42541</id>
	<published>2026-01-06T22:09:48Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-08T21:21:38Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://blog.jim-nielsen.com/2025/icons-in-menus/">Jim Nielsen</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It’s extra noise to me. It’s not that I think menu items should
<em>never</em> have icons. I think they can be incredibly useful (more on
that below). It’s more that I don’t like the idea of “give each
menu item an icon” being the default approach.</p>

<p>This posture lends itself to a practice where designers have an
attitude of “I need an icon to fill up this space” instead of an
attitude of “Does the addition of an icon here, and the cognitive
load of parsing and understanding it, help or hurt how someone
would use this menu system?”</p>

<p>The former doesn’t require thinking. It’s just templating — they
all have icons, so we need to put <em>something</em> there. The latter
requires care and thoughtfulness for each use case and its
context.</p>

<p>To defend my point, one of the examples I always pointed to was
macOS. For the longest time, Apple’s OS-level menus seemed to
avoid this default approach of sticking icons in every menu item.</p>

<p>That is, until macOS Tahoe shipped.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Nielsen’s post on MacOS 26 Tahoe’s tragic “icons for every menu item” design edict was published a month ago, before <a href="https://tonsky.me/blog/tahoe-icons/">Nikita Prokopov’s post</a> on the same subject <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/05/hard-to-justify-tahoe-icons">yesterday</a>. Both posts are crackerjack good, and complement each other. Nielsen makes the point that the Mac stood as a counter to platforms and systems that put icons next to every menu item. Of course Google Docs has icons next to every menu item. It sucks. Google sucks at UI design. We Mac users laugh at their crappy designs.</p>

<p>Well, who’s laughing now? It might sound hyperbolic but this change is <em>the</em> reason why I’ve decided not to upgrade to MacOS 26 Tahoe. I could put up with the rest of Liquid Glass’s half-baked <em>who-thought-this-was-OK-to-ship?</em> <a href="https://wien.rocks/@noheger/115782327146927772">nonsense</a>, but not the whole menu bar. I can tolerate being angry about UI changes Apple makes to the Mac. But I can’t tolerate being heartbroken.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Icons in Menus Everywhere — Send Help’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/06/nielsen-icons-in-menus">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘The Big Regression’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/the-big-regression-da7fc60d" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wto" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/06/the-big-regression" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42540</id>
	<published>2026-01-06T21:41:19Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-06T22:36:06Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://world.hey.com/jason/the-big-regression-da7fc60d">Jason Fried</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>My folks are in town visiting us for a couple months so we rented
them a house nearby.</p>

<p>It’s new construction. No one has lived in it yet. It’s amped up
with state of the art systems. You know, the ones with
touchscreens of various sizes, IoT appliances, and interfaces that
try too hard.</p>

<p>And it’s terrible. What a regression.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Examples include: light switches that require a demo to use, a Miele dishwasher that requires the use of a companion phone app, a confusing-to-use TV (of course), inscrutable thermostats, and:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>And the lag. Lag everywhere. Everything feels a beat or two
behind. Everything. Lag is the giveaway that the system is working
too hard for too little. Real-time must be the hardest problem.</p>

<p>Now look... I’m no luddite. But this experience is close to
conversion therapy. Tech can make things better, but I simply
can’t see in these cases. I’ve heard the pitches too — you can
set up scenes and one button can change EVERYTHING. Not buying it.
It actually feels primitive, like we haven’t figured out how to
make things easy yet.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In this period of the computerization of everything, so many systems have lost the innate intuitiveness from their analog counterparts. Light switches were easy and obvious. Flip the switch. Thermostats were easy and obvious. Turn the dial until the indicator points to the temperature you want. Light switches and Honeywell thermostats were so simple they seemed like they weren’t “interfaces” at all, which is why they were such great interfaces. The best interfaces almost literally disappear.</p>

<p>One of the mottos of the Perl programming language is that <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Learning-Perl-Making-Things-Possible/dp/1491954329/?tag=df-amzn-20">easy things should be easy, and hard things should be possible</a>. That’s the ideal when designing <em>anything</em>. But the more important part is keeping easy things easy. A house full of old-fashioned analog light switches is better than a house full of smart switches that need a demo to use at all, even though with the old-fashioned switches, you can’t do hard things like turn off the lights remotely, or turn off every light in the house with one action. The smart switches might seem like an improvement because they make possible hard things that were previously impossible. Making possible the impossible is surely a win, right? But not necessarily. Making possible the heretofore impossible isn’t axiomatically a win. It’s a <em>loss</em> if it comes at the expense of keeping the easy things easy, consistent, reliable, and intuitive. Nothing exemplifies that more than the decline in user experience of watching TV, and attempting something as previously simple as flipping between two games on two different channels.</p>

<p>The guiding principle when creating computerized versions of analog systems ought to be “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Primum_non_nocere">First, do no harm</a>.” Everything should be as easy, obvious, reliable, and intuitive as in the old system. Only add to that what doesn’t introduce any regressions on those fronts.</p>

<p>Alas, that’s not how the world has proceeded.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘The Big Regression’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/06/the-big-regression">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Who’s Who at X, the Deepfake Porn Site Formerly Known as Twitter’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.ft.com/content/ad94db4c-95a0-4c65-bd8d-3b43e1251091?accessToken=zwAGR7kzep9gkdOtlNtMlaBMZdO9jTtD4SUQkQ.MEYCIQCdZajuC9uga-d9b5Z1t0HI2BIcnkVoq98loextLRpCTgIhAPL3rW72aTHBNL_lS7s1ONpM2vBgNlBNHDBeGbHkPkZj&amp;sharetype=gift&amp;token=a7473827-0799-4064-9008-bf22b3c99711" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wtn" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/06/whos-who-at-x" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42539</id>
	<published>2026-01-06T20:49:02Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-06T20:51:21Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The Financial Times has a nice illustrated guide to the leadership team at Twitter/X, where <a href="https://boingboing.net/2026/01/06/x-faces-global-investigations-as-grok-generates-deepfake-porn-of-women-and-minors.html">things are going about as you’d expect</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Who’s Who at X, the Deepfake Porn Site Formerly Known as Twitter’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/06/whos-who-at-x">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Don Mattingly Joins Phillies as Bench Coach</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/athletic/6942357/2026/01/05/don-mattingly-hired-bench-coach-phillies/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wtm" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/06/mattingly-phillies" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42538</id>
	<published>2026-01-06T16:51:27Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-06T16:51:28Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Welcome to Philadelphia, Donnie Baseball.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Don Mattingly Joins Phillies as Bench Coach’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/06/mattingly-phillies">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘It’s Hard to Justify Tahoe Icons’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tonsky.me/blog/tahoe-icons/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wtl" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/05/hard-to-justify-tahoe-icons" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42537</id>
	<published>2026-01-06T03:24:21Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-06T03:30:17Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>This essay from UI critic Nikita Prokopov is just devastatingly good. If you’ve looked at MacOS 26 Tahoe, you’re surely appalled by the new UI guideline that recommends putting icons next to every single menu item. Prokopov argues — with copious screenshot illustrations every step of the way — that this is a terrible idea in the first place, and that Apple has implemented it poorly. There’s no defense for any of this. Don’t make the mistake of thinking Apple just needs better, more consistent icons. The fact that Tahoe’s menu item icons are glaringly inconsistent and often utterly inscrutable is the fudge icing on a shit cake, but the real embarrassment is that the idea ever got past the proposal stage. No real UI <em>or</em> icon designers think this is a good idea. None.</p>

<p>A shitty idea that works against usability, inconsistently implemented, all in the name of adding some ugly visual bling to the UI. Perhaps the epitome of a Dye job.</p>

<p>Simply <a href="https://tonsky.me/blog/tahoe-icons/">a must-read piece</a>. I have much more to say about the menus in Tahoe, but thanks to Prokopov, I don’t have to say it all.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘It’s Hard to Justify Tahoe Icons’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/05/hard-to-justify-tahoe-icons">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2026/01/pickle_smells_like_a_cult" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wtk" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026://1.42536</id>
	<published>2026-01-06T03:03:01Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-08T21:59:07Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">The only way Pickle could sound *more* like a cult would be if their “employees” (are any of them actually getting paid?) all shaved their heads and wore Hare Krishna-style robes.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Pickle CEO Daniel Park <a href="https://x.com/danifesto/status/2008085704388063634?s=12">posted on Twitter/X</a>, attempting to rebut <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/03/dowd-pickle-expose">the analysis from Matthew Dowd I linked to over the weekend</a> pointing out the ways that Pickle’s AR glasses, for which they’re accepting $800 pre-orders, look like a scam. Park’s rebuttal, in my opinion, boils down to (a) a bunch of handwaving about Pickle conveniently not being able to explain their own hardware because of NDAs, and (b) this claim:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Pickle 1 is not a standalone camera glasses product. It is a
phone-tethered personal intelligence interface.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Pickle’s website FAQ, on launch, <a href="https://x.com/thedowd/status/2008197081941557484">claimed</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>Do I need a smartphone to use Pickle 1?</em><br>
Pickle 1 is a standalone device but pairs with the Pickle OS app
on iOS and Android for initial setup, data management, and
granular privacy controls.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>As of today, <a href="https://pickle.com/order">that FAQ now reads</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>Do I need a smartphone to use Pickle 1?</em><br>
Pickle 1 is not a standalone camera glasses product. it is a
phone-tethered personal intelligence interface.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Which to me already nullifies the entire premise of the fantasy device they showed at launch. Park also claims, in his post today, “Pickle 1 leverages the smartphone that users already carry”, but that can’t be true if the user carries an iPhone because there’s no way Pickle can run tethering software in the background on iOS. I do not believe it’ll do even 1/100th of what they claim when paired to an Android phone, either. But it’s literally impossible with an iPhone.</p>

<p>Anyway, the thing that really caught my eye in Park’s post today was this, near the beginning:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We’re a team that lives together in a house in Hillsborough,
California, and works on this 7 days a week. Our team is small but
we work all day, every day together and it’s helping us make
progress we’re very excited and proud of.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Pickle doesn’t sound a little like a cult. It sounds <em>exactly</em> like a cult.</p>

<p>Impossible claims. A compound where “employees” live and work seven days a week. Spiritual mumbo jumbo (Pickle 1 <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2026/01/pickle-1-soul-computer.png">is described as a “Soul Computer”</a> and <a href="https://pickle.com/1">claims to provide</a> “an intelligence that sees with you, remembers your life, and learns to understand you. A new soul.”) Excuses for why they cannot provide evidence for any of their fantastical claims. The only way Pickle could sound <em>more</em> like a cult would be if their “employees” (are any of them actually getting paid?) all shaved their heads and wore Hare Krishna-style robes.</p>

<p>If you work there, be wary of the Kool-Aid.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Pickle Smells Like a Cult</title></entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://copilot.money/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=editorial&amp;utm_campaign=daringfireball_122225_web25&amp;utm_term=DARING" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wtj" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2026/01/copilot_money_1" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/feeds/sponsors//11.42535</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2026-01-06T01:48:31Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-06T01:48:31Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Copilot Money — the Apple Editor’s Choice money tracker — is expanding beyond iPhone, iPad, and Mac with the launch of its new web app, available now.</p>

<p>Copilot Money brings all your spending, budgets, investments, and net worth into one organized dashboard, with intelligent categorization and insights that help you stay on track without spreadsheets or app-hopping. Designed to feel calm and intuitive, Copilot makes it easy to understand your finances across all your devices.</p>

<p>Copilot is offering DF readers two months free with code DARING, plus 26% off your first year for a limited time, <a href="https://copilot.money/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=editorial&amp;utm_campaign=daringfireball_122225_web25&amp;utm_term=DARING">available through this link</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Copilot Money’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2026/01/copilot_money_1">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] Copilot Money</title></entry><entry>
	<title>NFL Playoff Scenarios</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://nflplayoffscenarios.com/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wti" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/04/nfl-playoff-scenarios" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42534</id>
	<published>2026-01-04T17:09:24Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-04T17:09:36Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>What a great site (<a href="https://bsky.app/profile/nflplayoffscenarios.com">and Bluesky account</a>) this is. Just what it says on the tin: all the scenarios for how the NFL playoff seedings can shake out, presented very plainly but clearly. The old-school World Wide Web still has a beating heart.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘NFL Playoff Scenarios’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/04/nfl-playoff-scenarios">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Listen Later</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.listenlater.net/?referrer=df" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wth" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/03/listen-later" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42533</id>
	<published>2026-01-03T23:05:53Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-03T23:05:53Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to Listen Later for sponsoring this week at DF. Listen Later is a super simple, super useful service that turns articles into podcast episodes. When you sign up, you get a custom email address to send articles to; every article you forward to your Listen Later address is transformed into <em>very</em> human-like narration, and gets delivered to your private podcast feed. You can subscribe to your private Listen Later podcast feed in any podcast app.</p>

<p>In addition to the email gateway, <a href="https://www.listenlater.net/tips">there’s a Shortcut</a> for sending articles from Safari (on Mac or iOS), a web extension for Chrome, and a simple web interface for submitting new articles. It’s very simple and the narrated versions sound great.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.listenlater.net/?referrer=df">Sign up for free and start listening today</a>. New users get $2 in credits to try it out — no commitment. And if you like it, you simply prepay for credits as you go. There’s no subscription — you simply pay for what you use. I wish more services had a pay-as-you-go model like Listen Later’s.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Listen Later’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/03/listen-later">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Matthew Dowd Exposes the Pickle 1 XR Glasses as a Preposterous Fraud</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://x.com/thedowd/status/2007337800430198913?s=20" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wtg" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/03/dowd-pickle-expose" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42532</id>
	<published>2026-01-03T22:32:53Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-04T01:30:30Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Matthew Dowd, in a long, devastatingly careful post on Twitter/X:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>If they’re suggesting their waveguide displays are bright enough
and vibrant enough to see clearly in direct sunlight, that would
be yet another innovation they’ve discovered that every other
player in the market (including the Chinese manufacturers where
the waveguide displays come from) has missed.</p>

<p>Meta has access to every display manufacturer and their <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ray-Ban_Meta?utm_source=chatgpt.com">Display
Glasses’ peak brightness is ~5,000 nits</a>, itself very power
heavy. These glasses came out just last fall and there is no sign
of significantly brighter waveguides shipping for commercial
products since then. It’s also worth noting that Meta Display
Glasses users have <a href="https://www.jotme.io/blog/meta-ray-ban-display">noted poor readability in direct
sunlight</a>, suggesting a greater leap would be necessary to
meet Pickle’s claims.</p>

<p>Put simply, Pickle having much brighter waveguides that also have
a 30-degree FOV is extremely unlikely. It would mean that some
waveguide manufacturer out there (there aren’t many) recently
achieved a breakthrough and has chosen Pickle to be the first
device it’s found in. Oh, and it’s going to ship next quarter.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I don’t know what these scammers at Pickle think is going to happen, but they sure as shit aren’t going to ship a product that does anything vaguely close to what they claim they’re on the cusp of shipping. I doubt they’re going to ship anything at all, ever. The whole thing is like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_lie">the Big Lie</a>, but for technology not politics.</p>

<p>One of two scenarios is true:</p>

<ol type= "a">
<li><p>Pickle, <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/pickle-2">a 15-person startup founded in 2024</a> that has raised less than $10 million, is the most advanced personal computer hardware company in the world, on the cusp of launching multiple hardware and software technologies that put the company 5-10 years ahead of established rivals like Apple, Meta, Samsung, Google, Sony, and Zeiss. The Pickle 1 glasses are the most amazing consumer electronics device since the original iPhone. CEO Daniel Park will go down in history as one of the most innovative leaders and inventors in the history of the world. Or:</p></li>
<li><p>Pickle is a complete and utter sham that is accepting $200 pre-orders for a product that exists only as a fabricated fake in its launch video. CEO Daniel Park is a liar and fraud, and, depending upon what they do with the pre-order payments they are now collecting, perhaps a thief.</p></li>
</ol>

<p>Either (a) is mostly true or (b) is mostly true. Given that there exists not one single independent person other than Park himself who vouches that the Pickle 1 actually exists and functions in prototype form, I think it’s pretty obvious which scenario is the case. Which makes me wonder <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/ji4cvzir2qdpALLHo/ycombinator-fraud-rates">what the hell is going on at Y Combinator</a> these days.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Matthew Dowd Exposes the Pickle 1 XR Glasses as a Preposterous Fraud’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/03/dowd-pickle-expose">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2026/01/clicks_communicator_and_clicks_power_keyboard" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wtf" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026://1.42531</id>
	<published>2026-01-03T00:03:33Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-04T18:37:10Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">I just love the chutzpah of these guys. They started with a good minimal launch product and are back two years later with what looks like a *much* better idea for a phone keyboard accessory. But they’re also now making their own whole goddamn phone.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Two years ago, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2024/01/04/clicks">I linked to</a> the then-new <a href="https://www.clicks.tech/collections/shop-all">Clicks keyboard case</a> — an iPhone case with a built-in BlackBerry-style hardware keyboard jutting out from the bottom. I wrote then:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I don’t know how much I’ll wind up using it but it looks fun,
useful, and clever — and I’m just a sucker for upstart indie
hardware projects. Clicks is even a great name.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I wound up not using it much at all. I never owned a smartphone with a hardware keyboard (I went straight from <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/gruber/3672937486/">this Nokia dumbphone</a> right to an iPhone), so I have neither muscle memory nor nostalgia for hardware phone keyboards. I wound up typing slower — much slower — with my Clicks keyboard case than I did using the on-screen keyboard. Plus the way the keyboard juts out from the bottom makes your phone, when encased, something more akin size-wise to a TV remote control. I’m glad I bought it, was happy to try it, but it just wasn’t for me.</p>

<p>The Clicks team — including co-founders Michael “MrMobile” Fisher and Kevin “CrackBerry” Michaluk — is out today with two <em>major</em> new products. The best place to start is <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=69VgtIJOtdQ">this nicely-done 12-minute keynote</a> introducing both products.</p>

<p>The first is an entire BlackBerry-style phone: <a href="https://clicksphone.com/communicator">Clicks Communicator</a>. It runs Android but ships with a custom launcher that emphasizes messaging and notifications; it has a hardware mute switch and a side button with a color-coded alert light they call the Signal LED. It’s set to ship “later this year” and will cost $500, but you can pre-order one today for just $400. It looks cool. They’re pitching Communicator as a second phone — less distracting, focused on messaging — but one that could be your primary phone if you want it to be. <a href="https://crackberry.com/clicks-communicator">CrackBerry Kevin has a whole write-up about it</a>. I have zero need for one but I kind of want one.</p>

<p>The second is the <a href="https://www.clicks.tech/powerkeyboard">Clicks Power Keyboard</a>. It’s a MagSafe-compatible battery back with a keyboard that slides out, underneath your phone. (Reminiscent of the <a href="https://daringfireball.net/search/palm+pre">Palm Pre</a>?) It’s a Bluetooth keyboard, and you can pair it with up to three devices. Examples they cite include pairing with an iPad, Apple TV, and, intriguingly, a Vision Pro. (I’d rather type with my thumbs on a device like this than peck at the virtual keyboard in VisionOS, I think.) This strikes me as a much better idea for a hardware phone keyboard accessory than a case. Cases need to be made per each device. A Clicks keyboard case for an iPhone 15 won’t fit an iPhone 16. Hell, a case for an iPhone 15 won’t even fit an iPhone 15 Pro. And here we are in January and Clicks still doesn’t have cases for the <s>iPhones 17 or</s> iPhone Air. [<strong>Update:</strong> My bad, they <em>do</em> have cases for <a href="https://www.clicks.tech/products/clicks-keyboard-for-iphone-17">the 17 models</a>.] But MagSafe and Bluetooth mean the same Clicks Power Keyboard will work with any modern iPhone — or Android phone. It’s shipping “in the spring” and will cost $110, but can be pre-ordered for a limited time for $80. It comes in one color, black (the correct color if you’re only going to offer one). I’m going to buy one of these for sure, even though I’m quite certain my thumbs haven’t gained any muscle memory for such keyboards since I abandoned my Clicks keyboard case. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=u7Uz1YZ5hQA">Fisher has a whole video about the Clicks Power Keyboard on his YouTube channel</a>.</p>

<p>I just love the chutzpah of these guys. They started with a good minimal launch product and are back two years later with what looks like a <em>much</em> better idea for a phone keyboard accessory. But they’re also now making their own whole goddamn phone. That’s going big, not going home.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Clicks Communicator and Clicks Power Keyboard</title></entry><entry>
	<title>The Talk Show: ‘2025 Year in Review’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2025/12/31/ep-438" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wte" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/31/the-talk-show-438" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42530</id>
	<published>2025-12-31T21:41:25Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-31T21:41:25Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>A look back at Apple’s 2025, with special guest Rene Ritchie.</p>

<p><audio
    src = "https://traffic.libsyn.com/secure/daringfireball/thetalkshow-438-rene-ritchie.mp3"
    controls
    preload = "none"
/></p>

<p><strong>Sponsored by:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://factormeals.com/talkshow50off">Factor</a>: Healthy eating, made easy. Get 50% off your first box, plus free breakfast for 1 year, with code <strong>talkshow50off</strong>.</li>
<li><a href="https://squarespace.com/talkshow">Squarespace</a>: Save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain using code <strong>talkshow</strong>.</li>
</ul>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Talk Show: ‘2025 Year in Review’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/31/the-talk-show-438">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Photoshop 1.0 and the Early Macintosh HIG</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mastodon.social/@gruber/115770281204538177" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wtc" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/31/photoshop-1-and-the-early-macintosh-hig" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42528</id>
	<published>2025-12-31T17:53:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-31T17:53:08Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>After posting <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/19/photoshop-1-source-code">a link</a> to the Computer History Museum’s <a href="https://computerhistory.org/blog/adobe-photoshop-source-code/">release of the Photoshop 1.0 source code</a> last week, I spent some time paging through the original Photoshop manuals. I found a screenshot of the dialog box where you entered your serial number, and posted it to Mastodon, writing:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>If you’re annoyed by something that is obviously wrong about this
dialog box from Photoshop 1.0, you’re my type of person. (Even
more so if, like me, you remember being annoyed by this at the
time, when you were entering your cracked SN.)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>What a lovely thread it generated, replete with screenshots from early versions of the HIG.</p>

<p><strong>Sidenote:</strong> I would eat my hat if Alan Dye knew what was wrong and gross about this dialog box. This is exactly the sort of <em>sweating the idiomatic usability details</em> thing that has frequently been wrong in Apple software in the last decade. The response from Dye and those in his cohort would be, I’d wager, to roll their eyes with a “<em>Who gives a shit what the UI guidelines were forty fucking years ago?</em>” dismissal. Here’s the thing. <em>Styles</em> have changed as time has marched on. Technical capabilities — screen resolution, color — have marched on. But the fundamental idioms of good Macintosh UI design are timeless (and many of them ought to apply to Apple’s other platforms). These idioms are like grammar. Slang changes. Language forever moves forward. But many important idioms are so fundamental they do not change. Styles and technical advances have advanced over time in filmmaking and print design too, but the basic principles of good cinema and graphic layout are timeless. Only a fool dismisses the collective knowledge passed down by those who came before us. </p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Photoshop 1.0 and the Early Macintosh HIG’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/31/photoshop-1-and-the-early-macintosh-hig">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘The Strange Death of Make America Great Again’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/12/24/opinion/turning-points-americafest-maga.html?unlocked_article_code=1.A1A.viCa.z9zxp3AvMBxV" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wtd" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/31/walther-maga-strange-death" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42529</id>
	<published>2025-12-31T17:52:26Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-31T17:52:26Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Matthew Walther, in an opinion piece last week for The New York Times (gift link):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>MAGA’s internal culture has always rewarded theatrical
confrontation over achievement. Boorishness commands attention,
and boors mistake attention for leverage. Pseudo-martyrdom becomes
an end in itself. Loyalty tests proliferate. Those who counsel
de-escalation find themselves subject to denunciation; prudential
disagreement is allowed to provide cover for rank bigotry.
Partisans celebrate one another for exacerbating tensions even
when exacerbation forecloses coalition building.</p>

<p>There is also a related problem: The Trumpist movement has
generated a lunatic array of semiautonomous online subcultures
that are largely indifferent to strategic considerations and
immune from political consequences while still exercising
influence over actors whose decisions are not so immune. The
disappearance of the informal gate-keeping function once performed
by conservative luminaries such as William F. Buckley Jr. is
probably permanent. In the absence of such authority, informed
argument exists alongside phony outrage, profiteering,
self-aggrandizement and saying things for the hell of it. The
result is not merely the radicalization that Mr. Buckley feared
but a kind of omnidirectional incoherence.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>“A kind of omnidirectional incoherence” is as perfect a description as I’ve seen regarding the whole Trumpist movement in this second administration.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘The Strange Death of Make America Great Again’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/31/walther-maga-strange-death">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘I’m in Charge at This Hertz Location, and Buddy, You’re Not Getting a Car Today’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.mcsweeneys.net/articles/im-in-charge-at-this-hertz-location-and-buddy-youre-not-getting-a-car-today" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wtb" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/30/not-getting-a-car-today" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42527</id>
	<published>2025-12-30T23:57:11Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-30T23:57:12Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Emily Delaney, at McSweeney’s:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Okay, now you’re getting upset. You’re getting upset despite the
fact that we have strict rules against getting upset at this Hertz
location. But tell me, honestly, when you reserved a rental car
through Hertz, you thought… what? That we were going to set aside
a special little car just for you? Seriously? Oh my god.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>(<a href="https://kottke.org/25/12/0047917-im-in-charge-at-this">Via Kottke</a>.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘I’m in Charge at This Hertz Location, and Buddy, You’re Not Getting a Car Today’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/30/not-getting-a-car-today">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The U.S. Conservative Aggrieved Mindset, Explained</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://knowyourmeme.com/videos/433740-just-coffee-black" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wta" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/30/pargin-conservative-mindset" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42526</id>
	<published>2025-12-30T23:46:27Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-30T23:46:27Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jason Pargin is — well, to my tastes — a master of the TikTok video format. This one is so good, and ends with a mic-drop closing line.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The U.S. Conservative Aggrieved Mindset, Explained’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/30/pargin-conservative-mindset">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Using AirPods Live Translation in Japan</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/12/26/travel/airpods-live-translation-japan.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wt9" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/30/using-airpods-live-translation-in-japan" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42525</id>
	<published>2025-12-30T20:26:55Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-30T20:27:53Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Ruffin Prevost, writing at The New York Times:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>As everyone filed out, I repeated, in English, some of the
priest’s comments to my guide, Keiko Hatada, who taught English
for 30 years and has led custom tours of Tokyo for the past
decade. I wanted to make sure I had understood things correctly.</p>

<p>I recounted the priest’s admonition to set aside unwholesome
feelings of anger and greed, and work instead to show compassion
and generosity, as well as his reminder that his temple was still
accepting donations for those affected by the 2011 earthquake and
tsunami.</p>

<p>“You told me you didn’t speak Japanese,” my guide said, pleasantly
surprised.</p>

<p>Beyond a few basic greetings and food terms, I don’t.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I wrote the following two years ago <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2023/09/airpods_pro_2_usbc">in my AirPods Pro 2 review</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The new AirPods Pro are the best single expression of Apple as a
company today. Not the most important product, not the most
complicated, not the most essential. But the one that exemplifies
everything Apple is trying to do. They are simple, they are
useful, and they offer features that most people use and want.
Most people use headphones. A lot of people use them every day — in noisy environments. AirPods Pro are — for any scenario where
big over-ear-style headphones are impractical — the best
headphones in the world.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That was <em>before</em> Live Translation, a feature that until recently existed only in science fiction.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Using AirPods Live Translation in Japan’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/30/using-airpods-live-translation-in-japan">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>ICEBlock App Sues Trump Administration for Censorship</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.npr.org/2025/12/08/nx-s1-5631826/iceblock-app-lawsuit-trump-bondi?ref=platformer.news" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wt8" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/30/iceblock-app-sues-trump-administration-for-censorship" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42524</id>
	<published>2025-12-30T19:44:44Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-30T19:44:45Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Bobby Allyn, reporting three weeks ago for NPR:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The developer of ICEBlock, an iPhone app that anonymously tracks
the presence of Immigration and Customs Enforcement agents, has
sued the Trump administration for free speech violations after
Apple <a href="https://www.npr.org/2025/10/03/nx-s1-5561999/apple-google-iceblock-app-removal">removed</a> the service from its app store under
demands from the White House.</p>

<p>The suit, <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/26360437-iceblock-complaint-as-filed/">filed on Monday </a> in federal court in
Washington, asks a judge to declare that the administration
violated the First Amendment when it threatened to criminally
prosecute the app’s developer and pressured Apple to make the app
unavailable for download, which the tech company did in October. [...]</p>

<p>To First Amendment advocates, the White House’s pressure campaign
targeting ICEBlock is the latest example of what’s known as
“jawboning,” when government officials wield state power to
suppress speech. The Cato Institute calls the practice “censorship
by proxy.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Good on developer Joshua Aaron for filing this suit and defending his work.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘ICEBlock App Sues Trump Administration for Censorship’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/30/iceblock-app-sues-trump-administration-for-censorship">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/12/do_a_better_job_on_the_wings" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wt7" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42523</id>
	<published>2025-12-30T18:54:20Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-30T22:11:56Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Kubrick on the Icarus myth.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Randy Walters wrote a lovely little story, “<a href="https://satori.substack.com/p/christianes-gift">Christiane’s Gift</a>”, originally published back in 2012, about a visit to a Frankfurt museum hosting an exhibit from Stanley Kubrick’s personal archives in 2004. I toured the same exhibit <a href="https://www.thecjm.org/pages/57">at the Contemporary Jewish Museum in San Francisco in 2016</a>; it was <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=a31Gv0lPlAw">remarkable</a>. Included in the exhibit was <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5rZTrZwmMJ0">the famed ƒ/0.7 Zeiss lens</a> (designed for use by NASA for satellite photography in space) and the <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2015/04/02/kubricks-lenses">jury-rigged Mitchell BNC camera Kubrick commissioned</a> so he could use that lens to shoot scenes by candlelight in <em>Barry Lyndon</em>.</p>

<p>In the preface to his story, Walters references this quote from Kubrick, from <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=y5KHGN76AFE">his acceptance speech</a> for the D.W. Griffith lifetime achievement award from the Director’s Guild of America in 1998:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I’ve compared Griffith’s career to the Icarus myth, but at the
same time I’ve never been certain whether the moral of the Icarus
story should only be, as is generally accepted, “Don’t try to fly
too high,” or whether it might also be thought of as “Forget the
wax and feathers, and do a better job on the wings.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That Zeiss lens/Mitchell BNC was a better job on the wings.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ ‘Do a Better Job on the Wings’</title></entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.listenlater.net/?referrer=df" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wt5" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/12/listenlaternet_2" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.42521</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-12-30T00:56:13Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-30T00:56:14Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Turn articles into podcasts and listen on the go. Email any article, and it comes back as natural narration delivered straight to your private podcast feed. Whether it’s a long read or a quick blog post, enjoy it hands-free in any podcast app.</p>

<p>Sign up for free and start listening today. New users get $2 in credits to try it out, no commitment.</p>

<p>Now with many new voices, improved audio quality, and big bonus credits for frequent listeners.</p>

<p>Built by an indie developer. <a href="https://www.listenlater.net/?referrer=df">Try it at listenlater.net</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘ListenLater.net’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/12/listenlaternet_2">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] ListenLater.net</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Copilot Money</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://copilot.money/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=editorial&amp;utm_campaign=daringfireball_122225_web25&amp;utm_term=DARING" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wt3" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/28/copilot-money" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42519</id>
	<published>2025-12-28T19:55:51Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-30T19:02:59Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to Copilot Money for sponsoring last week at DF. Copilot is a personal finance app for the iPhone, iPad, and Mac, and they’ve always deeply believed in the value of embracing the design idioms and technical features of truly native apps for Apple platforms. Apple has noticed, awarding Copilot an <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/copilot-track-budget-money/id1447330651#productRatings">App Store Editor’s Choice</a> and featuring Copilot earlier this year on Apple Developer <a href="https://developer.apple.com/articles/copilot-money/">for their use of Swift Charts</a>.</p>

<p>Copilot’s big news this week is they’ve launched a new web app, bringing access to Copilot from any device, anywhere. It’s designed with all the attention to detail — and concern for privacy and security — as their native apps.</p>

<p>Copilot Money brings all your spending, budgets, investments, and net worth into one organized dashboard, with intelligent categorization and insights that help you stay on track without spreadsheets or app-hopping. Designed to feel calm and intuitive, Copilot makes it easy to understand your finances across all your devices.</p>

<p>Copilot first sponsored DF back in 2021. My wife and I started using it then to track our finances, and we haven’t looked back. Copilot Money isn’t just better than anything we’d used before, it absolutely blew everything else away. It’s easy to connect to your financial accounts, and once you do, you don’t need to spend any effort at all to enter transactions. Copilot just tracks it all automatically, and most importantly, presents it to you in clear, intuitive ways. It’s so good. I’m not saying that because they sponsored DF last week — I’m saying that as a happy paying customer for over four years now.</p>

<p>Copilot is offering DF readers two months free with code <strong>DARING</strong>, plus 26% off your first year for a limited time, <a href="https://copilot.money/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=editorial&amp;utm_campaign=daringfireball_122225_web25&amp;utm_term=DARING">available through this link</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Copilot Money’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/28/copilot-money">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>SoundSource 6</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://weblog.rogueamoeba.com/2025/12/04/soundsource-6-is-here/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wt2" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/28/soundsource-6" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42518</id>
	<published>2025-12-28T19:39:53Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-28T19:42:57Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Major update to Rogue Amoeba’s essential audio utility for the Mac. I’ve written about <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2020/08/09/soundsource-5">versions 5</a> <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2019/04/04/soundsource-4">and 4</a> previously, and everything I wrote then remains true. SoundSource remains the system-wide audio menu item that ought to be built into MacOS, giving you easy, intuitive control over every audio <em>device</em> (input and output), and easy, intuitive control over every <em>app</em> in which you play or record audio. That one seemingly-simple app does both those things is quite the remarkable design achievement. And aside from that usability, SoundSource remains an exemplar of UI design stylistically — distinctive and branded, while looking and feeling in every way like a standard Mac app.</p>

<p>New tentpole features in version 6 include fine-grained AirPlay support (e.g. route output from one app over AirPlay while leaving the rest of your system’s audio output local to your Mac), groups for output devices, and a new “Quick Configs” feature for saving and switching between, well, quick configurations. $49 for a new license, $25 to upgrade from a previous one.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘SoundSource 6’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/28/soundsource-6">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Tim Cook Posts AI Slop in Christmas Message on Twitter/X, Ostensibly to Promote ‘Pluribus’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://x.com/tim_cook/status/2003873311504130173" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wt1" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/27/slopibus" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42517</id>
	<published>2025-12-27T22:32:01Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-30T00:50:02Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The whole illustration is <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/12/milk-and-cookies-tim-cook-keith-thomson.png">just weird looking</a>, for one thing. As for sloppy details, the tree is in soft focus but somehow has a crisp edge, the carton is labeled both “Whole Milk” and “Lowfat Milk”, and the “Cow Fun Puzzle” maze is just goofily wrong. (I can’t recall ever seeing a puzzle of any kind on a milk carton, because they’re waxy and hard to write on. It’s like a conflation of milk cartons and cereal boxes.)</p>

<p>[<strong>Update, 29 December:</strong> Turns out, the “lowfat” milk carton props from the actual show <a href="https://x.com/lionesspike/status/1999675978650648889">have the same mistake</a> with “whole milk” printed above. That doesn’t change that it’s a stupid mistake to copy, or that there are a slew of other telltale signs that the image was generated by AI.]</p>

<p><a href="https://x.com/appletv/status/2003927243245203539">The Apple TV X account retweeted Cook</a>, and added a credit: “We thought you might like this festive artwork by Keith Thomson, made on MacBook Pro.”</p>

<p>Apple didn’t tag the “Keith Thomson” who supposedly created this artwork for them, but if it’s <a href="https://www.keiththomsonart.com/">this Keith Thomson</a>, Apple must have somehow fallen for a scam, because <em>that</em> Keith Thomson’s published paintings are wonderful. It does seem to be <a href="https://x.com/flyosity/status/2004010434844938312">that Keith Thomson’s signature</a> on Apple’s sloppy illustration, though. (I like a bunch of the paintings from that Keith Thomson, and love a few of them, but <a href="https://www.keiththomsonart.com/?itemId=id1bethwvp1f2b3fsm5np1sg5i9p50">this one in particular</a> feels like it was made just for me. It’s perfect.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Tim Cook Posts AI Slop in Christmas Message on Twitter/X, Ostensibly to Promote ‘Pluribus’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/27/slopibus">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>A 3D Tour Inside Trump’s Oval Office</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2025/12/23/us/trump-white-house-oval-office-gold-decor.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wt0" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/25/3d-tour-inside-trumps-oval-office" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42516</id>
	<published>2025-12-25T20:42:57Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-25T20:47:26Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Terrific interaction design from The New York Times. Not so terrific interior design from the president.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘A 3D Tour Inside Trump’s Oval Office’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/25/3d-tour-inside-trumps-oval-office">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Talk Show: ‘A Naughty Citizen’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2025/12/24/ep-437" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wsz" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/24/the-talk-show-437" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42515</id>
	<published>2025-12-25T01:31:53Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-25T01:32:13Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Special guest Quinn Nelson returns for a two-topic holiday spectacular: the iPad in the wake of iPadOS 26, and Apple’s executive changes as Tim Cook seemingly nears the end of his time as CEO.</p>

<p><audio
    src = "https://traffic.libsyn.com/secure/daringfireball/thetalkshow-437-quinn-nelson.mp3"
    controls
    preload = "none"
/></p>

<p><strong>Sponsored by:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://notion.com/talkshow">Notion</a>: The AI workspace where teams and AI agents get more done together.</li>
<li><a href="https://squarespace.com/talkshow">Squarespace</a>: Save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain using code <strong>talkshow</strong>.</li>
</ul>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Talk Show: ‘A Naughty Citizen’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/24/the-talk-show-437">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Quinn Nelson on Apple’s Executive Shuffling</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=e1E-yfcKdUw" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wsy" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/24/snazzy-apple-execs" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42514</id>
	<published>2025-12-24T16:51:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-25T01:27:19Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Another great video from Quinn Nelson. If your dumb cousin who knows you’re an Apple nerd approaches you on Christmas and says “<em>Hey what’s going on at Apple, Bloomberg says it’s rats leaving a sinking ship over there?</em>” and you don’t feel like explaining, just tell him to watch this video. Just the perfect explanation.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Quinn Nelson on Apple’s Executive Shuffling’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/24/snazzy-apple-execs">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘The iPad’s Software Problem Is Permanent’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bnYLpA5kAbo" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wsx" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/24/snazzy-ipad" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42513</id>
	<published>2025-12-24T16:45:39Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-24T16:45:40Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Smart, fair video from Quinn Nelson on the gap that remains between iPadOS 26 and desktop OSes. I think it’s right that there is a gap there. Apple has the Macintosh, the best desktop/workstation platform in the industry. So whatever the ideal is for iPadOS, it ought to fall short of MacOS in terms of technical capabilities, and instead offer a degree of simplicity and can’t-screw-it-up-edness that the Mac can’t match. But, some of the limitations that remain in iPadOS are just frustrating. iPadOS 26 is a huge leap forward, and I think sets the stage for Apple to address those limitations.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘The iPad’s Software Problem Is Permanent’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/24/snazzy-ipad">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>I Guess Nothing Is Foolproof</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/6/28/23777298/sony-ftc-microsoft-confidential-documents-marker-pen-scanner-oops" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wsw" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/23/i-guess-nothing-is-foolproof" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42512</id>
	<published>2025-12-24T02:16:45Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-24T02:17:15Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>From a 2023 report at The Verge:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Sony highly confidential information about its PlayStation
business has just been revealed by mistake. As part of the FTC v.
Microsoft hearing, Sony supplied a document from PlayStation chief
Jim Ryan that includes redacted details on the margins Sony shares
with publishers, its <em>Call of Duty</em> revenues, and even the cost of
developing some of its games.</p>

<p>It looks like someone redacted the documents with a black Sharpie — but when you scan them in, it’s easy to see some of the
redactions. Oops.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is sort of the exception that proves the rule <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/23/trump-doj-pdf-redactions">regarding redactions</a>. If you redact a document digitally, you have to know what to look for (e.g. metadata) to be certain you’ve redacted everything you want to redact. If you redact a document on paper, you can just look at it, with good light and sharp eyes.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘I Guess Nothing Is Foolproof’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/23/i-guess-nothing-is-foolproof">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Terrence Malick’s Disciples’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://yalereview.org/article/bilge-ebiri-terrence-malick" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wsv" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/23/terrence-malicks-disciples" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42511</id>
	<published>2025-12-23T23:19:57Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-23T23:19:58Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Splendid essay by Bilge Ebiri for The Yale Review, a meditation both on the films of Terrence Malick and several filmmakers he’s deeply influenced.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Terrence Malick’s Disciples’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/23/terrence-malicks-disciples">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The White House’s Belligerent, Ignorant Statement on the ‘60 Minutes’ CECOT Story</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://bsky.app/profile/brianstelter.bsky.social/post/3maoiadv5cc2u" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wsu" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/23/white-house-trump-are-removing" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42510</id>
	<published>2025-12-23T19:48:11Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-23T19:48:48Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>CNN media analyst Brian Stelter, on Bluesky:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>As “60 Minutes” finalized its “Inside CECOT” report last Thursday,
CBS sent the White House a request for comment. A WH spokesperson
responded within a few hours. The quote was not included in the
“60” report — so, judge for yourself whether it should have been
included or not.</p>

<p>WH spokesperson Abigail Jackson said “60 Minutes should spend
their time and energy amplifying the stories of Angel Parents,
whose innocent American children have tragically been murdered by
vicious illegal aliens that President Trump are removing from the
country.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Despite the fact that it doesn’t address a single aspect of the report, 60 Minutes should have included that statement, both to reveal the belligerent callousness of the administration, and to highlight the glaring grammatical error. In its way, the statement speaks volumes.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The White House’s Belligerent, Ignorant Statement on the ‘60 Minutes’ CECOT Story’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/23/white-house-trump-are-removing">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Amateur Codebreaker May Have Solved the Black Dahlia and Zodiac Killings</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2025-12-23/black-dahlia-zodiac-killings-connected-one-killer-theory" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wst" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/23/amateur-codebreaker-may-have-solved-the-black-dahlia-and-zodiac-killings" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42509</id>
	<published>2025-12-23T19:36:45Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-23T19:36:46Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Christopher Goffard, reporting for the Los Angeles Times (<a href="https://apple.news/AC4dB7O1XRLmMK5alJLphRg">News+ link</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>When police questioned Marvin Margolis following the murder of
Elizabeth Short — who became known as the Black Dahlia — he lied
about how well he had known her. The 22-year-old Short had been
found mutilated in a weedy lot in South Los Angeles, severed
neatly in half with what detectives thought was surgical skill.</p>

<p>Margolis was on the list of suspects. He was a sullen 21-year-old
premed student at USC, a shell-shocked World War II veteran who
had expressed an eagerness to practice surgery. He was “a
resentful individual who shows ample evidence of open aggression,”
a military psychiatrist had concluded.</p>

<p>At first, Margolis did not tell detectives that he had lived with
Short for 12 days at a Hollywood Boulevard apartment, three months
before her January 1947 murder. [...]</p>

<p>A generation later and hundreds of miles north, a killer who
called himself the Zodiac terrorized the San Francisco Bay Area
with five seemingly random murders from 1968 to 1969, taunting
police and media for years with letters and cryptograms.</p>

<p>The toughest to decipher was the letter he sent in April 1970 to
the San Francisco Chronicle, with the words “My name is —”
followed by a 13-character string of letters and symbols. It came
to be called the Z13 cipher, and its brevity has stymied
generations of PhDs and puzzle prodigies.</p>

<p>Alex Baber, a 50-year-old West Virginia man who dropped out of
high school and taught himself codebreaking, now says he has
cracked the Zodiac killer’s identity — and in the process solved
the Black Dahlia case as well.</p>

<p>“It’s irrefutable,” said Baber, obsessive, hyperfocused and
cocksure in manner, his memory encyclopedic and his speech a
firehose of dates, locations and surprising linkages.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>What a story. The circumstantial evidence pointing to Margolis seems pretty strong. What I can’t find is an explanation of Baber’s solution to the Z13 cypher. The “irrefutable” description hinges on that. There’s a new podcast, “<a href="https://killerinthecode.com/">Killer in the Code</a>”, from author Michael Connelly that details Baber’s supposed solution tying both cases to the same guy. All the publicity about this today stems from the debut of that podcast yesterday.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Amateur Codebreaker May Have Solved the Black Dahlia and Zodiac Killings’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/23/amateur-codebreaker-may-have-solved-the-black-dahlia-and-zodiac-killings">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Trump Justice Department Dopes Made the Rookiest of Rookie Mistakes Attempting to Redact Some Epstein-File PDFs</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.tiktok.com/@krassenstein/video/7586804140869700895" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wss" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/23/trump-doj-pdf-redactions" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42508</id>
	<published>2025-12-23T16:56:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-23T16:56:01Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Everyone who works with official PDFs in any capacity should know that if you start with a PDF containing text you want to redact, and you just place black bars atop that text and resave the file, the original text is all still there in the new PDF file. It’s the digital equivalent of putting sticky notes atop the text. You don’t even need to crack open the new PDF in a text (or hex) editor and hunt for the original text within non-human-readable PDF formatting code. You just open the PDF in Preview or Acrobat or any other PDF viewer, use the regular text selection cursor to select the text under the black bars, copy, and then paste into any other app. Everyone should know this but <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/16/meta-redactions">it keeps happening</a>. Now <a href="https://www.tiktok.com/@krassenstein/video/7586804140869700895">it’s happened</a> with the new batch of Epstein files released by the DOJ.</p>

<p>There are <em>major</em> differences between the Trump 1.0 and 2.0 administrations. In the Trump 1.0 administration, many of the most important officials were very competent men. One example would be then-Attorney General William Barr. Barr is contemptible, yes, but smart AF. When Barr’s DOJ released a redacted version of the Mueller Report, they printed the whole thing, made their redactions with actual ink, and then re-scanned every page <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2019/05/02/mueller-pdf-assessment">to generate a new PDF with absolutely no digital trace of the original PDF file</a>. There are ways to properly redact a PDF digitally, but going analog is foolproof.</p>

<p>The Trump 2.0 administration, in contrast, is staffed top to bottom with fools.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Trump Justice Department Dopes Made the Rookiest of Rookie Mistakes Attempting to Redact Some Epstein-File PDFs’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/23/trump-doj-pdf-redactions">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry></feed><!-- THE END -->
