<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>Daring Fireball</title>
<subtitle>By John Gruber</subtitle>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/" />
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main" />
<id>https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main</id>


<updated>2025-07-02T15:41:07Z</updated><rights>Copyright © 2025, John Gruber</rights><entry>
	<title>Jason Snell: ‘About That A18 Pro MacBook Rumor’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2025/07/about-that-a16-macbook-rumor/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wfs" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/02/snell-a18-macbook" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42040</id>
	<published>2025-07-02T15:40:55Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-02T15:41:07Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jason Snell, writing at Six Colors:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Well, would you look at that? The A18 Pro is 46% faster than the
M1 in single-core tasks, and almost identical to the M1 on
multi-core and graphics tasks. If you wanted to get rid of the M1
MacBook Air but have decided that even today, its performance
characteristics make it perfectly suitable as a low-cost Mac
laptop, building a new model on the A18 Pro would not be a bad
move. It wouldn’t have Thunderbolt, only USB-C, but that’s not a
dealbreaker on a cheap laptop. It might re-use parts from the M1
Air, including the display.</p>

<p>I like that Apple sells a laptop at $649, and I think Apple likes
it, too. A new low-end model might steal some buyers from the $999
MacBook Air, but I’d wager it would reach a lot of customers who
might otherwise not buy a full-priced Mac — the same ones buying
M1 MacBook Airs at Walmart.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>My first thought when I saw this rumor pop up was to dismiss it. But upon consideration, I think it makes sense. Especially if Apple considers the M1 MacBook Air at Walmart to be a success. And all signs point to “yes” on that — they started selling the M1 MacBook Air as a $700 Walmart exclusive <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2024/03/15/macbook-air-walmart">in March 2024</a> and they <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/20/walmart-macbook-air">continue to sell it this year</a> at just $650.</p>

<p>So I think if this rumor pans out, a MacBook at this price point will become a standard part of the lineup, sold everywhere — including Apple Stores.</p>

<p><a href="https://512pixels.net/2025/07/a18-pro-macbook/">Stephen Hackett, at 512 Pixels</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The immediate downside to the A18 Pro is that it only supports USB
3 at 10 Gb/s, not Thunderbolt. This would make any Mac with an A18
at its heart only capable of USB-C. I think that’s fine on a
low-end Mac, but it could cause confusion for some customers.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>For people looking at MacBooks in this price range, talking about USB 3 vs. Thunderbolt brings to mind <a href="https://desertdemocrat.wordpress.com/2015/03/25/blah-blah-blah-blah-ginger/">this classic <em>Far Side</em> cartoon</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Jason Snell: ‘About That A18 Pro MacBook Rumor’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/02/snell-a18-macbook">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://phoenix.new/?utm_source=df" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wfr" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/07/phoenixnew" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.42039</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-07-01T16:44:21Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-01T16:44:22Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Resurrect your side projects with Phoenix.new, the new AI app-builder from <a href="https://fly.io/">Fly.io</a>. Just describe your idea, and Phoenix.new quickly generates a working real-time Phoenix app: clustering, pubsub, and presence included. Ideal for multiplayer games, collaborative tools, or quick weekend experiments. Built by <a href="https://fly.io/">Fly.io</a>, deploy wherever you want.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Phoenix.new’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/07/phoenixnew">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] Phoenix.new</title></entry><entry>
	<title>The Talk Show: ‘The Cutting Edge Latest Supermodel’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2025/06/30/ep-426" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wfq" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/30/the-talk-show-426" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42038</id>
	<published>2025-06-30T23:11:56Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-30T23:11:57Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Special guest David Smith returns to the show for a developer’s perspective look at WWDC 2025.</p>

<p><audio
    src = "https://traffic.libsyn.com/secure/daringfireball/thetalkshow-426-david-smith.mp3"
    controls
    preload = "none"
/></p>

<p><strong>Sponsored by:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://usetrmnl.com/go/gruber">TRMNL</a>: A hackable e-ink display. Save $15 with code <strong>GRUBER</strong>.</li>
<li><a href="https://squarespace.com/talkshow">Squarespace</a>: Save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain using code <strong>talkshow</strong>.</li>
</ul>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Talk Show: ‘The Cutting Edge Latest Supermodel’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/30/the-talk-show-426">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Upcoming Sponsorship Openings at Daring Fireball</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wfn" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/28/upcoming-sponsorship-openings-at-daring-fireball" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42035</id>
	<published>2025-06-28T21:02:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-28T21:27:32Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Weekly sponsorships have been the top source of revenue for Daring Fireball ever since I started selling them <a href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/archive">back in 2007</a>. They’ve succeeded, I think, because they make everyone happy. They generate good money. There’s only one sponsor per week and the sponsors are always relevant to at least some sizable portion of the DF audience, so you, the reader, are never annoyed and hopefully often intrigued by them. And, from the sponsors’ perspective, they work. My favorite thing about them is how many sponsors <a href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/archive">return for subsequent weeks</a> after seeing the results.</p>

<p>At the moment, I’ve only got four openings left through the end of September:</p>

<ul>
<li>June 30–July 6 (next week)</li>
<li>August 18–24</li>
<li>August 25–31</li>
<li>September 1–7</li>
</ul>

<p>I don’t know why next week remains unsold, but that’s just how it works out sometimes. 
If you’ve got a product or service (or, perhaps, a just-opened blockbuster car-racing movie) you think would be of interest to DF’s audience of people obsessed with high quality and good design, <a href="mailto:sponsors@daringfireball.net?subject=Feed%20Sponsorship">get in touch</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Upcoming Sponsorship Openings at Daring Fireball’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/28/upcoming-sponsorship-openings-at-daring-fireball">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>WorkOS</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://workos.com/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wfm" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/28/workos" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42034</id>
	<published>2025-06-28T21:01:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-28T21:27:16Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to WorkOS for once again sponsoring Daring Fireball. Modern authentication should be seamless and secure. WorkOS makes it easy to integrate features like MFA, SSO, and RBAC.</p>

<p>Whether you’re replacing passwords, stopping fraud, or adding enterprise auth, WorkOS can help you build frictionless auth that scales. </p>

<p>Future-proof your authentication stack with the identity layer trusted by OpenAI, Cursor, Perplexity, and Vercel. Upgrade your auth today.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘WorkOS’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/28/workos">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple’s Full List of Differences between ‘Tier 1’ and ‘Tier 2’ in the EU App Store</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://developer.apple.com/help/app-store-connect/reference/store-services-tiers/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wfp" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/28/apples-full-list-of-differences-between-tier-1-and-tier-2-in-the-eu-app-store" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42037</id>
	<published>2025-06-28T21:00:01Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-29T13:59:21Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Apple Developer:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>By default, apps on the App Store are provided Store Services Tier
2, the complete suite of all capabilities designed to maximize
visibility, engagement, growth, and operational efficiency.
Developers with <a href="https://developer.apple.com/support/alternative-payment-options-on-the-app-store-in-the-eu/">apps on the App Store in the EU</a> that
communicate and promote offers for digital goods and services can
choose to move their apps to only use Store Services Tier 1 and
pay a reduced store services fee.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>What follows is a long chart, making clear which features are excluded from Tier 1.</p>

<p>Like I wrote in <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/06/apple_app_store_policy_updates_dma">my larger piece on Apple’s new DMA compliance plans</a>, I don’t think Tier 1 is intended to be a feasible choice for any mainstream apps or games. The whole thing is just a way to assert that 8 percent of the commission developers pay is justified by various features of the App Store itself.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple’s Full List of Differences between ‘Tier 1’ and ‘Tier 2’ in the EU App Store’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/28/apples-full-list-of-differences-between-tier-1-and-tier-2-in-the-eu-app-store">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/06/apple_app_store_policy_updates_dma" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wfo" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42036</id>
	<published>2025-06-28T21:00:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-29T15:56:06Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">It’s a natural consequence that an overly complicated law (the DMA) has resulted in an ever-more-complicated set of guidelines and policies (from Apple). It’s all downright byzantine.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Let’s start with <a href="https://developer.apple.com/news/?id=awedznci">Apple’s own announcement at Apple Developer News</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The European Commission has required Apple to make a series of
additional changes under the Digital Markets Act:</p>

<h2>Communication and Promotion of Offers</h2>

<ul>
<li>Today, we’re introducing updated terms that let developers with
apps in the European Union storefronts of the App Store
communicate and promote offers for purchase of digital goods or
services available at a destination of their choice. The
destination can be a website, alternative app marketplace, or
another app, and can be accessed outside the app or within the
app via a web view or native experience.</li>
<li>App Store apps that communicate and promote offers for digital
goods or services will be subject to new business terms for
those transactions — an initial acquisition fee, store services
fee, and for apps on the StoreKit External Purchase Link
Entitlement (EU) Addendum, the Core Technology Commission (CTC).
The CTC reflects value Apple provides developers through ongoing
investments in the tools, technologies, and services that enable
them to build and share innovative apps with users. [...]</li>
</ul>

<h2>Update to Business Terms for Apps in the European Union</h2>

<ul>
<li>By January 1, 2026, Apple plans to move to a single business
model in the EU for all developers. Under this single business
model, Apple will transition from the Core Technology Fee (CTF)
to the CTC on digital goods or services. The CTC will apply to
digital goods or services sold by apps distributed from the App
Store, Web Distribution, and/or alternative marketplaces.</li>
<li>Apps currently under the Alternative Terms Addendum for Apps in
the EU continue to be subject only to the CTF until the
transition to the CTC is fully implemented next year. At that
time, qualifying transactions will be subject to the CTC, and
the CTF will no longer apply. Additional details regarding this
transition will be provided at a later date.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>Amongst other policy and API changes, Apple also announced a new, seemingly simplified, experience on iOS/iPadOS <a href="https://developer.apple.com/support/alt-distribution-ux-in-the-eu/">for installing apps and alternative app marketplaces in the EU</a>.</p>

<p>As for the other policy changes, <a href="https://sixcolors.com/link/2025/06/apple-makes-big-app-store-changes-in-the-eu/">here’s Jason Snell’s summary</a>, which I think captures the gist as well as possible:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>Tiered App Store fees.</em> For today’s full-service App Store,
developers will now pay 13% on sales, reduced to 10% for Small
Business Program members. Or developers can opt into “Tier One”,
which comes with a 5% fee but does not support a raft of App Store
features we’ve come to expect, like automatic app updates, App
Store promotions, placement in search suggestions, ratings and
reviews on product listings (!), and more.</p>

<p><em>Core Technology Commission.</em> Apple is going to move all
developers over to a new tax called the Core Technology
Commission, in which developers who opt to sell apps outside the
App Store will pay 5% of sales made through in-app promotions. The
€0.50-per-install Core Technology Fee will be dropped as of
January 1.</p>

<p><em>Free linking.</em> Developers can promote offers broadly, are no
longer limited to a single static URL without tracking parameters,
and can freely design the interfaces for those links and
promotions.</p>

<p><em>New business terms.</em> Developers have to pay a 2% fee for digital
goods and services purchased by new users for the first six months
after a user first downloads an app; members of the Small Business
Program don’t have to pay this fee.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/06/26/apple-announces-sweeping-app-store-changes-in-the-eu/">here’s Chance Miller’s summary at 9to5Mac</a>, which includes the following statement from Apple (which statement was provided to me, as well):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The European Commission is requiring Apple to make a series of
additional changes to the App Store. We disagree with this outcome
and plan to appeal.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The new fee structure is undeniably convoluted, and I think downright confusing. <a href="https://x.com/rjonesy/status/1938354627155501219">Seemingly no one can figure out</a> exactly what commissions apps that use alternative payments or distribution are going to pay. It’s a natural consequence that an overly complicated law (the DMA) has resulted in an ever-more-complicated set of guidelines and policies (from Apple). It’s all downright byzantine.</p>

<p>That seems largely by design on Apple’s part: byzantine compliance with a byzantine law. Because it’s so complicated and hard to understand, it’s difficult even to summarize with a headline describing what’s new. Even if you understand it enough to just want to express anger at Apple for spiteful compliance and greed, it’s hard to sum up why you’re angry in a succinct headline or tweet.</p>

<hr />

<p>The bottom line, as I understand it, is the following (but I could be wrong about some of this<sup id="fnr1-2025-06-28"><a href="#fn1-2025-06-28">1</a></sup> — if I am, let me know, and I’ll try to correct it):</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Developers who just do the simplest thing possible — distribute through the App Store and process all payments using Apple’s IAP — will continue to pay the same commissions, 30% by default, or 15% for Small Business Program developers and recurring subscriptions after the first year. Of course this is what Apple would prefer developers do.</p></li>
<li><p>Big developers, distributing through the App Store but processing their own payments, will still owe Apple a commission of around 20% on non-IAP purchases: 13% for “store services”, 5% for the new Core Technology Commission (replacing the €0.50 per-download Core Technology Fee), and 2% for “initial acquisition”. Small Developer Program members and recurring subscriptions after the first year pay 15% — no “initial acquisition fee” and a reduced “store services” fee of 10%. But everyone’s on the hook for the 5% CTC.</p></li>
<li><p>Apps distributed through the App Store can pay a reduced rate of 5% for “store services” (down from 13%) by opting into a reduced “Tier 1”. Rather than this “Tier 1” being an appealing choice for any developers, I think the point of it is for Apple to assert that those App Store features justify 8 percent of Apple’s commission on purchases: automatic software updates, reviews and ratings, surfacing through search for anything other than an exact name match, <a href="https://developer.apple.com/help/app-store-connect/reference/store-services-tiers/">and a whole lot more</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>One consequence of the €0.50 per-download Core Technology Fee (CTF) being replaced by a 5% Core Technology Commission (CTC) is that there will no longer be a penalty for small developers who have a free-to-download app that hits over one million EU downloads. That was a legitimate problem with the CTF — an app with 5 million EU downloads would owe Apple €2 million for the CTF, but might be generating far less than that (or even nothing at all) in revenue. But another consequence of switching to the CTC from the CTF is that super-popular apps from super-big companies that don’t sell digital goods from their apps will continue to pay nothing at all. E.g. unless Meta starts selling digital goods from within their apps, they’ll continue to pay nothing at all to Apple for zillion-download apps like Instagram, Facebook, and WhatsApp. That was a shortcoming with the App Store’s model that the CTF was designed to correct.</p></li>
<li><p>All of this additional complication is, I believe, just for apps distributed through the App Store. Feel free to blame Apple as much as you want for spiteful compliance (especially when it comes to payments made on the web, from links in apps), but part of this is on the European Commission for demanding not only that Apple allow apps to be distributed outside the App Store (which is somewhat reasonable), but also for requiring Apple to allow outside payments for apps distributed through the App Store. Apps and games distributed through alternative EU app marketplaces or web downloads are only on the hook for the 5% CTC (by the end of the year, when it replaces the CTF). But there is no free lunch — iOS apps and games distributed outside the App Store that require a purchase, or offer digital content for sale, must pay the 5% CTC.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>There are a lot of people <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/06/26/tim-sweeney-slams-apples-unlawful-eu-app-store-changes/">who think</a> what Apple is “supposed” to do is collect no commission or fees at all on anything other than IAP from apps and games that are distributed through the App Store. That Apple should collect no commission or fees from apps distributed outside the App Store, nor any commission or fees from apps in the App Store that offer their own payment processing — and, thus, that Apple should set their own IAP commission accordingly, as something akin to Stripe or PayPal, in the single-digit percentage range. That’s obviously not in Apple’s interest. But it’s also <em>not</em> what the European Commission has suggested the DMA demands.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1-2025-06-28">
<p>One thing I might be wrong about is that these new terms could be read to suggest that developers who stick with the App Store and Apple’s IAP now pay just 20 percent commission under the new EU terms. That’d be really weird, insofar as it would mean that developers in the EU get an 80/20 split for App Store distribution + IAP, but apps everywhere else in the world still get 70/30 for the same thing. That doesn’t make sense unless there’s another shoe to drop, and Apple is going to reduce IAP to 80/20 worldwide soon. (Which would be a great move on Apple’s part — something that would actually earn them back some developer goodwill.)&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-06-28"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Apple Announces Sweeping but Complicated Policy Changes for Apps in the EU, Attempting to Comply With the Latest Dictums Regarding the DMA</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Apple’s Other ‘F1 The Movie’ In-App Promotions</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/06/27/f1-the-movie-now-playing-in-theaters/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wfl" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/27/apples-other-f1-promos" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42033</id>
	<published>2025-06-28T00:25:24Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-28T00:26:56Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Joe Rossignol:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The company has promoted its Brad Pitt racing film with
advertisements across at least six iPhone apps leading up to
today’s wide release, including the App Store, Apple Wallet,
Apple Sports, Apple Podcasts, iTunes Store, and of course the
Apple TV app.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Most of those apps have ads in them all the time. It’s certainly fine for Apple to use those ad spots to promote their own movie. Even with Apple Sports, which most of the time has no ads at all, I think it’s fine for Apple to occasionally drop a promotion in there for something of their own. And <em>F1 The Movie</em> is a sports movie. The Apple Wallet push notification isn’t just a little different, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/06/more_on_apples_trust-eroding_f1_the_movie_wallet_ad">it’s a lot different</a>.</p>

<p>I will also note one other sort-of promotion. I play the mini crossword every morning in Apple News. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/06/apple-news-mini-crossword-f1.png">Today’s 1-down clue</a> was “<em>F1 The Movie</em> star Brad ____”. I think that’s a clever on-brand tie-in. Fun, not obnoxious. But with the smell of that Wallet push-notification fart still hanging in the air, not as much fun as it otherwise would have been.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple’s Other ‘F1 The Movie’ In-App Promotions’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/27/apples-other-f1-promos">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>RFK Jr.’s CDC Panel Ditches Some Flu Shots Based on Anti-Vaccine Junk Data</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://arstechnica.com/health/2025/06/rfk-jr-s-cdc-panel-ditches-some-flu-shots-based-on-anti-vaccine-junk-data/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wfk" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/27/rfk-cdc-ditch-flu-shots-based-on-junk-data" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42032</id>
	<published>2025-06-27T23:53:53Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-27T23:53:54Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Beth Mole, reporting for Ars Technica:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The vaccine panel hand-selected by health secretary and
anti-vaccine advocate Robert F. Kennedy Jr. on Thursday voted
overwhelmingly to drop federal recommendations for seasonal flu
shots that contain the ethyl-mercury containing preservative
thimerosal. The panel did so after hearing a misleading and
cherry-picked presentation from an anti-vaccine activist.</p>

<p>There is extensive data from the last quarter century proving that
the antiseptic preservative is safe, with no harms identified
beyond slight soreness at the injection site, but none of that
data was presented during today’s meeting.</p>

<p>The significance of the vote is unclear for now. The vast majority
of seasonal influenza vaccines currently used in the US — about
96 percent of flu shots in 2024–2025 — do not contain thimerosal.
The preservative is only included in multi-dose vials of seasonal
flu vaccines, where it prevents the growth of bacteria and fungi
potentially introduced as doses are withdrawn.</p>

<p>However, thimerosal is more common elsewhere in the world for
various multi-dose vaccine vials, which are cheaper than the
single-dose vials more commonly used in the US. If other countries
follow the US’s lead and abandon thimerosal, it could increase the
cost of vaccines in other countries and, in turn, lead to fewer
vaccinations.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Having an ignorant conspiracy nut lead the Department of Health and Human Services is angering and worrisome, to say the least. But it’s also incredibly frustrating, because Donald Trump himself isn’t an anti-vaxxer. In fact, one of the few great achievements of the first Trump Administration was <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operation_Warp_Speed">Operation Warp Speed</a>, a highly successful effort spearheaded by the US federal government to “facilitate and accelerate the development, manufacturing, and distribution of COVID-19 vaccines, therapeutics, and diagnostics.” Early in the pandemic experts were concerned it would take years before a Covid vaccine might be available. Instead, multiple effective vaccines were widely available — and administered free of charge — in the first half of 2021, only a year after the pandemic broke. It was a remarkable success and any other president who spearheaded Operation Warp Speed would have rightfully taken tremendous credit for it.</p>

<p>But instead, while plotting his return to office, Trump smelled opportunity with the anti-vax contingent <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/27/trump-stupid-americans">of the out-and-proud Stupid-Americans</a>, and now here we are, with a genuine know-nothing lunatic like RFK Jr. as Secretary of Health and Human Services. God help us if another pandemic hits in the next few years.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘RFK Jr.’s CDC Panel Ditches Some Flu Shots Based on Anti-Vaccine Junk Data’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/27/rfk-cdc-ditch-flu-shots-based-on-junk-data">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Stupid-Americans Are the New Irish-Americans, Trump Is Their JFK’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.reddit.com/r/thebulwark/comments/1ljbvtw/hottest_take_stupidamericans_are_the_new/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wfj" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/27/trump-stupid-americans" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42031</id>
	<published>2025-06-27T23:37:08Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-27T23:37:08Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Banger of a post by “tarltontarlton” on Reddit:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>That same process is happening now with stupid people. They’re
transcending their individual limitations, finding each other and
becoming out-and-proud Stupid-Americans. [...]</p>

<p>How individual stupid Americans are becoming the collective,
self-aware group of Stupid-Americans is a great idea for a lot of
very fancy journalism I’m sure. It’s probably got something to do
with the internet, where stupid people can find and repeat stupid
things to each other over and over and over again.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I believe it has a <em>lot</em> to do with the Internet, which has functioned as a terribly efficient sorting machine. It used to be that there were conservative Democrats and liberal Republicans. Both political parties were, effectively, shades of purple. Now we’ve sorted ourselves, and the result is the palpable increase in polarization. Low-IQ stupidity might still be spread across both sides of the political aisle, but willful ignorance — the <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2020/11/30/asimov-cult-of-ignorance">dogmatic cultish belief</a> that loudmouths’ opinions are on equal ground with facts and evidence presented by informed experts — is the entire basis of the MAGA movement. A regular stupid person might say, “Well, I don’t know anything about vaccines, so I better listen to my doctor, who is highly educated and well-informed on the subject.” An out-and-proud Stupid-American says “I don’t know anything about vaccines either, so I’m going to listen to a kook who admits that a worm ate part of his brain, because I can’t understand the science but I <em>can</em> understand conspiracy theories.”</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>If written language survives the next six weeks, we’ll be writing
about Donald Trump for a thousand years. But whatever else there
is to say, the most important thing about Donald Trump, the thing
that is obvious from watching him speak for just 14 seconds, is
that he is profoundly stupid. Whatever it is that he might be
talking about or doing at any given moment, it’s clear that while
he has a reptilian instinct for reading and stoking conflict, he
has no real idea what’s going on and he doesn’t really care to.
Stupid is what he is <em>and</em> where he comes from. It is his mind and
his soul. Catholic was what JFK was. Gay was what Harvey Milk was.
Stupid is <em>who</em> Donald Trump is.</p>

<p>And that’s what they love most, the Stupid-American voters.</p>

<p>Remember that sentence you heard at the beginning of all this in
2016? “He’s just saying what everybody is thinking.”</p>

<p>But see, not everybody was thinking that Hillary Clinton was an
alien, that global warming was a Chinese hoax and that what
America needed most of all was a plywood wall stretching from
Texas to California. Only the stupid people were. And suddenly, in
an instant, the most powerful man on earth was thinking just like
them. With his clueless smirk and unstoppable rise, he turned
people whose stupidity made them feel like nobody into people who
felt like everybody.</p>

<p>That’s why he’ll never lose them. Because it was never about what
he did or didn’t do. All that stuff is very confusing and the
Stupid-American community isn’t interested in the details. They
love him for who he is, which is one of them, and because he shows
them every day that Stupid-Americans can reach the social
mountaintop.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>(<a href="https://kottke.org/25/06/0047031-stupid-americans-feel-abo">Via Kottke</a>.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Stupid-Americans Are the New Irish-Americans, Trump Is Their JFK’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/27/trump-stupid-americans">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/06/more_on_apples_trust-eroding_f1_the_movie_wallet_ad" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wfi" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42030</id>
	<published>2025-06-27T17:28:19Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-28T22:46:34Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Sending this ad is completely destructive to all the hard work other teams at Apple have done to make Apple Wallet actually private — and, more importantly, *to get users to believe that it’s private*.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://mastodon.social/@czeins/114739403773350112">This is a funny gag from Claude Zeins</a>, but if you think about it, it shows just how destructive Apple’s decision was <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/26/apple-wallet-sends-push-notification-ad-pushing-f1-the-movie">to send a push notification from the Wallet app promoting <em>F1 The Movie</em></a>.</p>

<!-- Backup: https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/06/claude-zeins-f1-wallet-gag.jpeg -->

<p>It’s a fact that no company can inject an ad into your physical wallet. It just can’t happen. So if Apple’s message to users is that they should trust Apple Wallet, and move more of their “shit that goes in your wallet” life from their traditional analog wallet into their digital Apple Wallet, that’s the bar. No ads, ever. They’re competing against the privacy and intimacy of one of the most personal things people carry with them.</p>

<p>It’s not just that many people find ads annoying, no matter where they appear. It’s that Apple Wallet ought to be sacrosanct — like the Passwords and Journal apps. Apple is asking us to trust this app with our finances, our <a href="https://learn.wallet.apple/id">identity cards</a>, and our keys. I’m 99.9 percent certain this <em>F1</em> ad was just blasted out to zillions of Wallet users indiscriminately, but some number of users who got it — especially people who know they’re in the demographic for the movie — surely think they got the ad because Wallet is tracking their interests and activities. Like, what if you recently bought tickets to see another summer blockbuster movie? Using Apple Wallet? And then you got this ad? It’d be completely sensible to be spooked by that, and conclude that Apple Wallet is tracking you.</p>

<p>Sending this ad is completely destructive to all the hard work other teams at Apple have done to make Apple Wallet actually private — and, more importantly, <em>to get users to believe that it’s private</em>. That Apple can be trusted in ways that other “big tech” companies cannot. The perception of privacy is just as important as the technical details that make something actually private. I try very seldom to call for anyone to be fired, but I think whoever authorized this movie ad through Wallet push notifications ought to be canned.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ More on Apple’s Trust-Eroding ‘F1 The Movie’ Wallet Ad</title></entry><entry>
	<title>The Talk Show: ‘Through the Wall Like Kool-Aid Man’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2025/06/26/ep-425" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wfg" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/26/the-talk-show-425" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42028</id>
	<published>2025-06-27T01:18:32Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-27T17:28:46Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Chance Miller returns to the show to discuss the news and announcements from WWDC 2025.</p>

<p><audio
    src = "https://traffic.libsyn.com/secure/daringfireball/thetalkshow-425-chance-miller.mp3"
    controls
    preload = "none"
/></p>

<p><strong>Sponsored by:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://factormeals.com/talkshow50off">Factor</a>: Healthy eating, made easy. Get 50% off plus free shipping on your first box with code <strong>talkshow50off</strong>.</li>
<li><a href="https://squarespace.com/talkshow">Squarespace</a>: Save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain using code <strong>talkshow</strong>.</li>
<li><a href="https://betterhelp.com/talkshow">BetterHelp</a>: Give online therapy a try at BetterHelp and get on your way to being your best self.</li>
</ul>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Talk Show: ‘Through the Wall Like Kool-Aid Man’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/26/the-talk-show-425">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple Wallet Sends Push Notification Ad Pushing ‘F1 The Movie’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/06/24/iphone-customers-upset-by-apple-wallet-ad-pushing-f1-movie/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wff" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/26/apple-wallet-sends-push-notification-ad-pushing-f1-the-movie" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42027</id>
	<published>2025-06-26T20:26:59Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-28T17:19:20Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Sarah Perez, writing at TechCrunch Tuesday:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple customers aren’t thrilled they’re getting an ad from the
Apple Wallet app promoting the tech giant’s original film “F1 the
Movie.” <a href="https://x.com/ParkerOrtolani/status/1937551035825807545">Across</a> <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/AppleWallet/comments/1ljbjrs/how_do_i_turn_this_off">social</a> <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/ios/comments/1ljd94e/disable_fandango_ad_from_apple_pay/">media</a>, iPhone owners are
complaining that their Wallet app sent out a push notification
offering a $10 discount at Fandango for anyone buying two or more
tickets to the film.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/06/24/apple-wallet-notification-f1-movie-ad/">Joe Rossignol, MacRumors</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple today sent out an ad to some iPhone users in the form of a
Wallet app push notification, and not everyone is happy about it.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That’s an understatement, to say the very least. See if you can find a single comment from anyone who was happy about receiving this push notification ad. Seriously, let me know if you find <em>one</em> statement in support of this.</p>

<p><a href="https://mastodon.social/@caseyliss/114738626109660386">Casey Liss</a>, succinct as ever:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>🤮</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The ad itself, from Apple, read:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple Pay <br />
$10 off at Fandango</p>

<p>Save on 2+ tickets to F1® The Movie with APPLEPAYTEN. Ends 6/29.
While supplies last. Terms apply.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In addition to the justified outrage over receiving any ad from a system-level component like Wallet in the first place, this particular ad sucks in multiple ways. Why did Apple put a “®” after “F1” in the movie title? Why not put a “®” next to “Apple Pay” and “Fandango” too? What supplies are running out on this promotion? Why add that “terms apply”? This is just a shit notification from top to bottom, putting aside whether any such notification should have been sent in the first place.</p>

<p><a href="https://mas.to/@Kerry/114738862216086251">iOS 26 adds new settings inside the Wallet app</a> to allow fine-grained control over notifications, including the ability to turn off notifications for “Offers &amp; Promotions” (Wallet app → (···) → Notifications — notably, this is <em>not</em> in the Settings app). That’s good. But (a) iOS 26 is months away from being released to the general public — there exists no way to opt out of such notifications now; and (b) at least for me, I was by default opted <em>in</em> to this setting on my iOS 26 devices. (It is also, when you think about it, perhaps a worrying sign regarding Apple’s future plans that this setting has been added to Wallet for iOS 26.)</p>

<p>This was such a boneheaded marketing decision on Apple’s part. They cost themselves way more in goodwill and trust than they possibly could have earned in additional <em>F1 The Movie</em> — wait, sorry, my bad, <em>F1® The Movie</em> — box office ticket sales. It’s like Apple got paid to exemplify <a href="https://doctorow.medium.com/my-mcluhan-lecture-on-enshittification-ea343342b9bc">Cory Doctorow’s “enshittification” theory</a>. Apple Wallet doesn’t present itself as a marketing vehicle. It presents itself as a privacy-protecting system service.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Wallet Sends Push Notification Ad Pushing ‘F1 The Movie’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/26/apple-wallet-sends-push-notification-ad-pushing-f1-the-movie">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Denis Villeneuve to Direct Next James Bond Film</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://deadline.com/2025/06/denis-villeneuve-james-bond-amazon-mgm-studios-1236442917/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wfe" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/25/villeneuve-bond" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42026</id>
	<published>2025-06-26T00:45:24Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-26T01:20:49Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Good pick. I feel great about this.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Denis Villeneuve to Direct Next James Bond Film’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/25/villeneuve-bond">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Lake Tahoe Boat Tragedy Claims Longtime Apple Employee Paula Bozinovich</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.sfchronicle.com/tahoe/article/lake-tahoe-boat-accident-victims-identified-june-20391411.php" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wfd" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/25/lake-tahoe-boat-tragedy-claims-longtime-apple-employee-paula-bozinovich" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42025</id>
	<published>2025-06-25T19:06:22Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-26T01:28:10Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Some sad news. The San Francisco Chronicle (<a href="https://apple.news/AStXd9PofQ7yTRc24ijze8A">News+ link</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The eight people killed in a sudden storm while boating on Lake
Tahoe over the weekend were a close-knit group of friends and
family members who had gathered for a birthday celebration,
according to a spokesperson representing some of the victims.</p>

<p>The boating trip was a part of the 71st birthday celebration for
Paula Bozinovich, one of the people who perished in the lake, when
their 27-foot powerboat capsized during a sudden, violent storm on
Saturday. Authorities on Tuesday released the names of those
killed when the boat sank near D.L. Bliss State Park, overwhelmed
by 8-foot waves and wind gusts topping 35 mph.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Bozinovich’s husband Terry and son, Josh — a DoorDash executive — were among the victims. Via email, Brian Croll, who worked in product marketing at Apple for a <em>long</em> time before retiring a few years ago, wrote the following, which I’m publishing with his permission:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Paula was an employee who you are not going to see profiled in any
books on the history of Apple or Steve Jobs. She worked closely
with the ops team to ensure CDs and then DVDs shipped on time and
correctly packaged in a box. She knew all the systems and the
right people to make things happen. She was always committed to
getting things better than just right — perfect. Paula’s
extraordinary commitment, along with all the hundreds of other
unheralded employees, translated the vision of Steve, the
designers, the engineers, and the marketing people into a shipping
product.</p>

<p>One of the secrets behind Apple’s success has been its ability to
execute. Paula was an important part of that fine-tuned machine.
She was also quite a character!</p>

<p>I’m sending you this because I’ve seen front page obituaries of
executives who probably did way more harm than good to their
companies, and yet when you scratch the surface of a successful
company you find that people like Paula make all the difference.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Nothing but my warmest thoughts to her friends and family.</p>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> <a href="https://mastodon.social/@Cdespinosa/114746774944556319">Chris Espinosa</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I’m shattered to hear that Apple software ops stalwart Paula
Bozinovich was killed in a boat capsize on Lake Tahoe. She truly
embodied the spirit of the company in everything she did. A joy to
work with and a tragedy to lose her.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’ve heard from a bunch of folks today about her, and all of them emphasize two things. First, she was very, very good at her job. Second, she was very, very fun. One person said she exemplified what has always made Apple so unique: that her personality was such that she probably never would have gotten any job at all at any other big company, but she was absolutely perfectly an Apple person’s Apple person.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Lake Tahoe Boat Tragedy Claims Longtime Apple Employee Paula Bozinovich’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/25/lake-tahoe-boat-tragedy-claims-longtime-apple-employee-paula-bozinovich">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Sorry, MacOS Tahoe Beta 2 Still Does the Finder Icon Dirty</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://512pixels.net/2025/06/finder-icon-fixed/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wfc" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/24/sorry-macos-tahoe-b2-finder-icon" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42024</id>
	<published>2025-06-25T01:09:11Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-27T00:15:51Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Stephen Hackett:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Our 14-day national nightmare is over. As of Developer Beta 2, the
Finder icon in macOS Tahoe has been updated to reflect 30 years of
tradition:</p>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/06/About-Finder-Beta-2.jpg" class="noborder">
<img
  src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/06/About-Finder-Beta-2.jpg"
  alt = "Screenshots of the Finder About box, showing the Finder icon, left to right: MacOS 18 Sequioa, MacOS 26 Tahoe Beta 1, MacOS Tahoe Beta 2"
  width = 450
/></a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’m going to strongly disagree here. The Tahoe beta 2 Finder icon is <em>slightly</em> better, but seeing it this way makes it obvious that the problem with the Tahoe Finder icon isn’t whether it’s dark/light or light/dark from left to right. It’s that with this Tahoe design it’s not 50/50. It’s the <em>appliqué</em> — the right side (the face in profile) looks like something stuck on top of a blue face tile. That’s not the Finder logo.</p>

<p>The Finder logo is the Mac logo. The Macintosh is the platform that held Apple together when, by all rights, the company should have fallen apart. It’s a great logo, period, and the second-most-important logo Apple owns, after the Apple logo itself. Fucking around with it like this, making the right-side in-profile face a stick-on layer rather than a full half of the mark, is akin to Coca-Cola fucking around with the typeface for the word “Cola” in its logo. Like, what are you doing? Why are you screwing with a perfect mark?</p>

<p>There are an infinite number of ways Apple could do this while remaining true to the original logo. <a href="https://x.com/flarup/status/1932798949749936200">Here’s a take from Michael Flarup</a> that glasses it up but keeps it true to itself:</p>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/06/flarup-finder-glass.jpeg" class="noborder">
  <img
    src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/06/flarup-finder-glass.jpeg"
    alt = "Michael Flarup's take on a Liquid Glass style Finder icon."
    width = 450
  /></a></p>

<p>Especially in the field of computers, no company can be a slave to tradition and history. But you ought to respect it. This new Finder icon doesn’t.</p>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> And <a href="https://pdx.social/@louie/114742479098781460">here are some excellent takes</a> on an updated Finder icon by Louie Mantia, along with some astute commentary. Mantia writes:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I really, really do not like spending my time pointing this out.
I could write a whole blog post but I don’t want to seem angry
about it. I just think the right solutions are simpler than what
they’re doing.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>No surprise, but Mantia’s icons <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/06/louie-finder-glass-light.png">look</a> <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/06/louie-finder-glass-dark.png">perfect</a> to me. Perfectly Liquid Glass-y, perfectly Finder-y.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Sorry, MacOS Tahoe Beta 2 Still Does the Finder Icon Dirty’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/24/sorry-macos-tahoe-b2-finder-icon">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://workos.com/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wfb" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/06/workos_scalable_secure_authent_5" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.42023</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-06-24T20:49:12Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-24T20:49:12Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Modern authentication should be seamless and secure.  WorkOS makes it easy to integrate features like MFA, SSO, and RBAC.</p>

<p>Whether you’re replacing passwords, stopping fraud, or adding enterprise auth, WorkOS can help you build frictionless auth that scales. </p>

<p>Future-proof your authentication stack with the identity layer trusted by OpenAI, Cursor, Perplexity, and Vercel.  </p>

<p>Upgrade your auth today. </p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘WorkOS: Scalable, Secure Authentication’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/06/workos_scalable_secure_authent_5">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] WorkOS: Scalable, Secure Authentication</title></entry><entry>
	<title>The iyO One</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.iyo.audio/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wfa" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/24/iyo-one" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42022</id>
	<published>2025-06-24T14:58:04Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-24T21:02:32Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>From iyO’s home page:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The iyo one is a revolutionary new kind of computer without a
screen. it can run apps just like your smartphone. The key
difference is you talk to it through a natural language interface.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/23/io-iyo-aye-aye-aye">Like I wrote yesterday</a>, I’d never heard of iyO before. But from the description above, you can obviously see how they’d feel like the new OpenAI/LoveFrom io name stomps on their trademark. (One minor curiosity: iyO itself seems unsure how to capitalize the letters in its own name: <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/06/iyO-IyO-iyo.png">a single cropped screenshot of their own home page</a> shows “iyO”, “IyO”, and “iyo”.)</p>

<p>iyO “graduated” from X (which is entirely separate from Elon Musk’s X), Google’s “moonshot factory”, in 2021. <a href="https://x.company/projects/iyo/">The description there</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>iyO is on a mission to bring natural language computing to
billions of people. The team has created the world’s first audio
computer that you can talk to like a friend. While at X, the team
developed their initial prototypes. Now an independent company,
iyO is creating screenless, natural language computing with mixed
audio reality.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Despite having “graduated” four years ago, iyO is <a href="https://www.iyo.audio/products/iyo-one">still only taking pre-orders</a> for the iyO One, their ungainly-looking ear computer. ($100 seems too good to be true for what they’re promising. <strong>Update:</strong> Ah-ha, turns out $100 is just the pre-order deposit. They’re <a href="https://www.shop.iyo.audio/shop/p/iyo-one">going to cost $1,000 to $1,200</a> if they ever actually ship, which I think is a big <em>if</em> — this thing has vaporware written all over it.)</p>

<p>Lastly, last April, iyO founder and CEO Jason Rugolo demonstrated prototypes <a href="https://www.ted.com/talks/jason_rugolo_welcome_to_the_world_of_audio_computers">in a 13-minute TED talk</a>. Seems cool, but some of the features already exist with AirPods, and all of the feature <em>could</em> exist with AirPods. I don’t see the future of a dedicated audio computer — especially ones as ugly as these — when the entire feature set can be duplicated with smart earbuds paired to your phone.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The iyO One’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/24/iyo-one">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>OS 26 Betas Are Out</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/06/23/apple-seeds-ios-26-beta-2/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wf9" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/23/os-26-betas-are-out" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42021</id>
	<published>2025-06-23T23:37:04Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-24T14:22:19Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Juli Clover, MacRumors:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple today provided developers with the second betas of iOS 26
and iPadOS 26 for testing purposes, with the updates coming two
weeks after Apple seeded the first betas following the WWDC
keynote.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/06/23/apple-seeds-macos-tahoe-beta-2/">MacOS</a>, <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/06/23/apple-seeds-watchos-26-beta-2/">tvOS, WatchOS, and VisionOS</a> too. All sorts of good stuff in these second betas — an option to have <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/06/23/macos-tahoe-beta-2-menu-bar-background/">a real big boy menu bar in MacOS Tahoe</a>, a <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/06/23/ios-26-b2-control-center/">much better-looking Control Center</a>, and <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/06/23/ios-26-beta-2-everything-new/">more</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘OS 26 Betas Are Out’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/23/os-26-betas-are-out">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Pixar’s Newest Movie, ‘Elio’,  Is a Box-Office Dud</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/06/22/business/elio-pixar-box-office.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wf8" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/23/pixar-elio-dud" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42020</id>
	<published>2025-06-23T23:10:43Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-23T23:13:44Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Brooks Barnes, writing for The New York Times:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Pixar knew that <em>Elio</em>, an original space adventure, would most
likely struggle in its first weekend at the box office.</p>

<p>Animated movies based on original stories have become harder sells
in theaters, even for the once-unstoppable Pixar. At a time when
streaming services have proliferated and the broader economy is
unsettled, families want assurance that spending the money for
tickets will be worth it.</p>

<p>But the turnout for <em>Elio</em> was worse — much worse — than even
Pixar had expected. The film, which cost at least $250 million to
make and market, collected an estimated $21 million from Thursday
evening through Sunday at theaters in the United States and
Canada, according to Comscore, which compiles box office data. It
was Pixar’s worst opening-weekend result ever. The previous bottom
was <em>Elemental</em>, which arrived to $30 million in 2023.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.threads.com/@technologizer/post/DLQKsxppcWt">Harry McCracken</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I wasn’t aware this movie had come out, and still can’t tell you
what it’s about. And I’ve been a Pixar fan since before they made
movies. That seems like a problem.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I hadn’t heard of this movie until today either. Disney and Pixar have a marketing problem. One part of the problem is that Pixar has made some decidedly meh movies in recent years. “Pixar” used to stand for nothing less than excellence. Now it stands for “somewhere in the range of OK to great”. But another is that even when they make a good one — which <em>Elio</em> might be — they suck at getting word out.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Pixar’s Newest Movie, ‘Elio’,  Is a Box-Office Dud’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/23/pixar-elio-dud">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Trademark Dispute Leads to the Disappearance of ‘io’, OpenAI and LoveFrom’s Secretive AI Collaboration</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/news/690858/jony-ive-openai-sam-altman-ai-hardware" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wf7" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/23/io-iyo-aye-aye-aye" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42019</id>
	<published>2025-06-23T13:58:23Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-23T22:15:37Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Hayden Field, reporting for The Verge:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>OpenAI has scrubbed mentions of io, the hardware startup co-founded by famous Apple designer Jony Ive, from its website and social media channels. The sudden change closely follows their recent announcement of OpenAI’s nearly $6.5 billion acquisition and plans to create dedicated AI hardware.</p>

<p>OpenAI tells The Verge the deal is still happening, but it scrubbed mentions due to a trademark lawsuit from Iyo, the hearing device startup spun out of Google’s moonshot factory.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>If you visit <a href="https://openai.com/sam-and-jony/">the “Sam and Jony” page on OpenAI’s website</a> — where the short film teasing io used to be — it now simply says:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This page is temporarily down due to a court order following a trademark complaint from iyO about our use of the name “io.” We don’t agree with the complaint and are reviewing our options.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Perhaps I’m not paying close enough attention, but this is the first I’ve heard of iyO. The two names certainly sound alike but they don’t look alike. Are homophones trademarkable? I would expect a terse letter from Coca-Cola’s lawyers if I tried selling soda under name “Koke” (or <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Letters-Nut-Ted-L-Nancy/dp/B000SR7RNS/?tag=df-amzn-20">like Ted Nancy tried</a>, Kiet Doke), so I guess so.</p>

<p>I suppose the question is how did OpenAI not see this coming, knowing that Google is probably their biggest rival? (Not to mention that Google might feel salty about the encroachment on their I/O developer conference name.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Trademark Dispute Leads to the Disappearance of ‘io’, OpenAI and LoveFrom’s Secretive AI Collaboration’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/23/io-iyo-aye-aye-aye">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Drata</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://drata.com/daring" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wf6" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/22/drata" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42018</id>
	<published>2025-06-22T17:57:49Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-22T17:57:49Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to Drata for sponsoring this last week at DF. Their message is short and sweet: Automate compliance. Streamline security. Manage risk. Drata delivers the world’s most advanced Trust Management platform.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Drata’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/22/drata">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple Launches ‘Convince Your Parents to Get You a Mac’ Short Film on YouTube, Then Pulls It a Day Later Without Explanation</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/06/21/apple-pulls-the-parent-presentation-video/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wf5" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/22/apple-can-convince-your-parents" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42017</id>
	<published>2025-06-22T17:52:06Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-22T17:52:55Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Joe Rossignol at MacRumors:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple has marked its day-old <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/06/20/apple-shares-the-parent-presentation-for-mac/">The Parent Presentation</a> video
on YouTube as private, meaning that it is no longer available to
watch. Apple has also moved The Parent Presentation to the bottom
of its College Students page, effectively burying it. When we
reported on the marketing campaign yesterday, the presentation was
prominently featured at the top of the page.</p>

<p>It is unclear why Apple is suddenly hiding the ad, or if it will
return. Apple did not immediately respond to our request for
comment. On social media, some people said that the ad was cringe
or gross, so perhaps Apple pulled the video due to overly negative
reception. To be clear, this is merely speculation, and there were
others who found humor in the video.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The 7.5-minute video, which at the moment is still available to watch from re-uploads <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JHFUmPbODbI&amp;t=1s">on YouTube</a> and <a href="https://x.com/aaronp613/status/1936057701387428183">X</a> — stars <a href="https://www.themoviedb.org/person/2807375-martin-herlihy?language=en-US">Martin Herlihy</a> from SNL’s “Please Don’t Destroy” triumvirate. I wouldn’t describe it as “cringe”, but I also wouldn’t describe it as “funny”. (If Herlihy wrote this, it would suggest that his cohorts <a href="https://www.themoviedb.org/person/3631826-ben-marshall?language=en-US">Ben Marshall</a> and <a href="https://www.themoviedb.org/person/3631835-john-higgins?language=en-US">John Higgins</a> are the funny ones in the trio.) It’s also not the least bit offensive, so it really is unclear why Apple pulled it. If it’s because it’s not funny, how did it not only get approved and produced, but posted for 24 hours? Is Apple’s new marketing strategy to just publish new ads and then <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2024/05/09/apple-crush-apology">wait to see how the world reacts</a> before deciding if they’re any good or not?</p>

<p>One obvious problem with “The Parent Presentation” video is that the gist is that <em>everyone</em> involved is stupid: high school kids (the ostensible target audience?) are too stupid to know how to ask their parents for a MacBook for college, parents are too stupid to know they should buy their kids a good laptop, and even Herlihy’s lecturer is a doofus who himself doesn’t know how to deliver a presentation. I don’t know how this got past the concept stage.</p>

<p>To top things off, <a href="https://www.apple.com/education/college-students/#presentation">the downloadable slide presentation</a> — which Apple still has available in Keynote, PowerPoint, and Google Slides formats — is entirely typeset in Arial. I would take my son’s MacBook away from him if he came to me with a presentation set in Arial.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Launches ‘Convince Your Parents to Get You a Mac’ Short Film on YouTube, Then Pulls It a Day Later Without Explanation’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/22/apple-can-convince-your-parents">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>MacOS 26 Tahoe Beta Drops FireWire Support</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/06/19/macos-tahoe-beta-drops-firewire-support/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wf4" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/22/macos-26-tahoe-beta-drops-firewire-support" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42016</id>
	<published>2025-06-22T17:07:41Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-22T17:07:42Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Joe Rossignol, writing for MacRumors:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A bit of sad news for old iPods: Macs might be losing FireWire
support.</p>

<p>The first macOS Tahoe developer beta does not support the legacy
FireWire 400 and FireWire 800 data-transfer standards, according
to <a href="https://x.com/NekoMichiUBC/status/1932876748661608561">@NekoMichi on X</a>, and a <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/MacOS/comments/1l7gb1r/macos_tahoe_dp1_seems_remove_firewire_800_support/">Reddit post</a>. As a result,
the first few iPod models and old external storage drives that
rely on FireWire cannot be synced with or mounted on a Mac running
the <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/how-to/install-macos-tahoe-developer-beta/">macOS Tahoe beta</a>.</p>

<p>Unlike on macOS Sequoia and earlier versions, the first macOS
Tahoe beta does not include a FireWire section in the System
Settings app.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>All good things must come to an end, and FireWire was a very good thing indeed. High-performance, reliable, easy to use.</p>

<p>Apple, back in 2001, “<a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2001/08/22Apple-FireWire-Wins-2001-Primetime-Emmy-Engineering-Award/">Apple FireWire Wins 2001 Primetime Emmy Engineering Award</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple’s FireWire technology will be honored by the Academy of
Television Arts &amp; Sciences in an awards presentation held tonight
at the academy’s Goldenson Theatre in Hollywood. Apple will
receive a 2001 Primetime Emmy Engineering Award for FireWire’s
material impact on the television industry.</p>

<p>Apple invented FireWire in the mid-90s and shepherded it to become
the established cross-platform industry standard IEEE 1394.
FireWire is a high-speed serial input/output technology for
connecting digital devices such as digital camcorders and cameras
to desktop and portable computers. Widely adopted by digital
peripheral companies such as Sony, Canon, JVC and Kodak, FireWire
has become the established industry standard for both consumers
and professionals.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘MacOS 26 Tahoe Beta Drops FireWire Support’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/22/macos-26-tahoe-beta-drops-firewire-support">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Tom Nichols and Timothy Snyder on the US Bombing of Iran</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2025/06/united-states-bombed-iran-now-what/683276/?gift=aQyUJR7AIw1mJWdQ6Ed6yNCTkBMqRx-4Y00eGRut7XI" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wf3" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/22/nichols-trump-iran-bombing" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42015</id>
	<published>2025-06-22T17:00:28Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-22T17:00:28Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Tom Nichols, writing for The Atlantic (gift link):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>President Donald Trump has done what he <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2025/06/18/politics/trump-peacemaker-iran-israel-conflict-analysis">swore</a> he would not
do: involve the United States in a war in the Middle East. His
supporters will tie themselves in knots (as Vice President J. D.
Vance <a href="https://x.com/JDVance/status/1934996183702704404">did</a> last week) trying to jam the square peg of
Trump’s promises into the round hole of his actions. And many of
them may avoid calling this “war” at all, even though that’s what
Trump himself <a href="https://x.com/trump_repost/status/1936580633775792406">called it tonight</a>. They will want to see it
as a quick win against an obstinate regime that will eventually
declare bygones and come to the table. But whether bombing Iran
was a good idea or a bad idea — and it could turn out to be
either, or both — it is war by any definition of the term, and
something Trump had vowed he would avoid. [...]</p>

<p>Only one outcome is certain: Hypocrisy in the region and around
the world will reach galactic levels as nations wring their hands
and silently pray that the B-2s carrying the <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2025/06/20/world/middleeast/iran-nuclear-fordo-bunker-buster-bomb.html">bunker-buster</a>
bombs did their job.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>See also:</strong> <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/timothysnyder.bsky.social/post/3ls6a4s45w22q">Timothy Snyder, on Bluesky</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Five things to remember about war:</p>

<ol>
<li>Many things reported with confidence in the first hours and
days will turn out not to be true.</li>
<li>Whatever they say, the people who start wars are often thinking
chiefly about domestic politics.</li>
<li>The rationale given for a war will change over time, such that
actual success or failure in achieving a named objective is
less relevant than one might think.</li>
<li>Wars are unpredictable.</li>
<li>Wars are easy to start and hard to stop.</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Tom Nichols and Timothy Snyder on the US Bombing of Iran’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/22/nichols-trump-iran-bombing">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>How Apple Created a Custom iPhone Camera for ‘F1’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.wired.com/story/apple-created-a-custom-iphone-camera-for-f1/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wf2" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/19/apple-custom-iphone-camera-for-f1" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42014</id>
	<published>2025-06-19T23:04:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-19T23:04:00Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Julian Chokkattu, writing for Wired:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You can’t mount a cinema camera on a Formula One race car. These
nimble vehicles are built to precise specs, and capturing racing
footage from the driver’s point of view isn’t as simple as
slapping a GoPro on and calling it a day. That’s the challenge
Apple faced after Joseph Kosinski and Claudio Miranda, the
director and cinematographer of the upcoming <em>F1</em> Apple Original,
wanted to use real POV racing footage in the film.</p>

<p>If you’ve watched a Formula One race lately, you’ve probably seen
clips that show an angle from just behind the cockpit, with the
top or side of the driver’s helmet in the frame. Captured by
onboard cameras embedded in the car, the resulting footage is
designed for broadcast, at a lower resolution using specific color
spaces and codecs. Converting it to match the look of the rest of
the <em>F1</em> film would be too challenging to be feasible. Instead,
Apple’s engineering team replaced the broadcast module with a
camera composed of iPhone parts.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I think back to Phil Schiller, <a href="https://vimeo.com/130510366">on stage at my WWDC show in 2015</a>, saying that Apple viewed itself then not just as one of the leading camera companies in the world, but <a href="https://www.imore.com/gruber-and-schiller-our-full-transcript-talk-show-wwdc"><em>the</em> leading camera company in the world</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘How Apple Created a Custom iPhone Camera for ‘F1’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/19/apple-custom-iphone-camera-for-f1">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘F1’ and Apple’s Movie Strategy</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://variety.com/2025/film/news/f1-apple-movie-strategy-tim-cook-lewis-hamilton-1236424270/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wf1" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/19/f1-and-apples-movie-strategy" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42013</id>
	<published>2025-06-19T22:41:04Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-19T22:56:30Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Cynthia Littleton, in a long profile for Variety:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>When pressed about what Apple’s investments in movies and TV shows
have meant for the company as a whole, Cook explains that Apple is
at heart “a toolmaker,” delivering computers and other devices
that enable creativity in users. (This vision for the company, and
the “toolmaker” term specifically, was first articulated by Jobs
in the early 1980s.) “We’re a toolmaker,” Cook says again. “We
make tools for creative people to empower them to do things they
couldn’t do before. So we were doing lots of business with
Hollywood well before we were in the TV business.</p>

<p>“We studied it for years before we decided to do [Apple TV+]. I
know there’s a lot of different views out there about why we’re
into it. We’re into it to tell great stories, and we want it to be
a great business as well. That’s why we’re into it, just plain and
simple.” [...]</p>

<p>Media analysts and observers have wondered how the content side of
Apple threads together with the hardware sales that fuel the core
business. As Cook sees it, that’s not the point, although such
connections are emerging organically in the course of doing
business, as evidenced by “F1” and the camera tech. “I don’t have
it in my mind that I’m going to sell more iPhones because of it,”
Cook says. “I don’t think about that at all. I think about it as a
business. And just like we leverage the best of Apple across
iPhones and across our services, we try to leverage the best of
Apple TV+.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Apple TV+ has been killing it with original shows. Maybe with <em>F1</em> they can start bringing that magic to movies.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘F1’ and Apple’s Movie Strategy’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/19/f1-and-apples-movie-strategy">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/06/some_brief_thoughts_and_observations_on_wwdc_2025" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wf0" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42012</id>
	<published>2025-06-19T21:03:54Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-20T12:39:40Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">My biggest takeaway from WWDC 2025 is that Apple seemingly took some lessons to heart from its unfulfilled promises of a year ago. This year’s WWDC wasn’t merely focused on what Apple is confident it can ship in the next 12 months, but on what they can ship *this fall*.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>“<em>This one a long time have I watched. All his life has he looked away — to the future, to the horizon. Never his mind on where he was. What he was doing. Adventure. Heh! Excitement. Heh! A Jedi craves not these things. You are reckless!</em>” <br />
—Yoda, <em>The Empire Strikes Back</em></p>

<p>My biggest takeaway from WWDC 2025 is that Apple seemingly took some lessons to heart from <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/apple_is_delaying_the_more_personalized_siri_apple_intelligence_features">its unfulfilled promises</a> of a year ago. This year’s WWDC wasn’t merely focused on what Apple is confident it can ship in the next 12 months, but on what they can ship <em>this fall</em>. I might be overlooking a minor exception or two, but every major feature announced in <a href="https://developer.apple.com/videos/play/wwdc2025/101/">the WWDC 2025 keynote</a> was both demonstratable in product briefings, <em>and</em> is currently available in the developer beta seeds. I was also told, explicitly, by Apple executives, that Apple plans to ship everything shown last week in the fall.</p>

<p>That’s as it should be, and a strong return to form for the company. It takes confidence to promise only what you know you can ship, and it takes execution to ship what you’ve promised. If there’s more coming in the early months of 2026, announce those features when they’re ready. It’s proven very effective for Apple to spread the debut of new features across the entire calendar year, with many major features not appearing until the .3, .4, or even .5 OS releases. I think it will prove just as effective marketing-wise to spread the <em>announcement</em> of more features throughout the year as well.</p>

<h2>Year-Based Version Numbers</h2>

<p>There’s no question that it’s a little weird for every one of Apple’s platforms to have jumped to version 26. I mean, VisionOS skipped 23 version numbers. Presumably, when Apple next unveils a new OS (HomeOS?), it’s going to <em>start</em> at version 26, 27, or 28. But I’m already getting used to this, and I think the underlying logic laid out by Craig Federighi at the outset of the keynote is true: with Apple now up to six developer platforms (Mac, iPhone, iPad, Vision, TV, Watch), it had gotten hard to keep track of which version numbers corresponded to the same year. That matters not just for the convenience of knowing, in years to come, when specific versions of each OS were released, but it also matters because none of these platforms exist in isolation. They’re all parts of a cohesive whole, a cross-device “Apple OS 26” experience, as it were.</p>

<p>One thing I haven’t seen commented on, though, is that switching to year-based version numbers establishes as de facto policy something that has now been true for quite a few years, but which Apple has never officially acknowledged: that each of these platforms will get a major version release annually. 20 years ago the update schedule for Mac OS X was rather erratic:</p>

<table class="table-FEBFFE0A-B067-4C29-8766-29C19521F96F">
<style>
.table-FEBFFE0A-B067-4C29-8766-29C19521F96F {width: 350px}
.table-FEBFFE0A-B067-4C29-8766-29C19521F96F th:nth-child(1) { text-align: left }
.table-FEBFFE0A-B067-4C29-8766-29C19521F96F td:nth-child(1) { text-align: left }
.table-FEBFFE0A-B067-4C29-8766-29C19521F96F th:nth-child(2) { text-align: left }
.table-FEBFFE0A-B067-4C29-8766-29C19521F96F td:nth-child(2) { text-align: left }
</style>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Mac OS X 10.7 Lion</td><td>July 2011</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mac OS X 10.6 Snow Leopard</td><td>August 2009</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mac OS X 10.5 Leopard</td><td>October 2007</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mac OS X 10.4 Tiger</td><td>April 2005</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mac OS X 10.3 Panther</td><td>October 2003</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p>OS X 10.8 Mountain Lion (which began the odd four-year run where the Mac’s OS name didn’t contain “Mac”) arrived in July 2012, and thereafter a new major version has shipped in September, October, or November (MacOS 11 Big Sur, in 2020) every single year. This rigorous annual schedule is a hallmark of the Tim Cook era at Apple, and clearly reflects his personality (as the erratic/idiosyncratic schedule of the mid-2000s reflected Steve Jobs’s).</p>

<h2>iPadOS Windowing</h2>

<p>The pedant in me is mildly perturbed that the new windowing system unveiled for iPadOS 26 is largely being discussed under the term “multitasking”. It’s windowing. One way to understand the difference is that the original Mac OS (a.k.a. System 1) had windowing — windowing that looked and worked a lot like this — but no multitasking. The very early Mac could run just one app a time, but the running app could open multiple windows. But, whatever. It’s all good.</p>

<p>One thing I find interesting is that while <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/102364">split screen and Slide Over</a> have been eliminated in the new system (<a href="https://www.macstories.net/stories/not-an-ipad-pro-review/">praise be</a>), Stage Manager is still a feature. Just plain windowing is as it should be: ad hoc. You make windows and move them around and resize them however you want. Stage Manager is fussier — it’s a more complex system for users who wish to organize their windows into something akin to projects or related tasks. </p>

<p>So, effectively, Apple, three years ago, jumped straight to a more complex, more fiddly option — Stage Manager — and only now has added the simpler, more obvious, not fiddly at all option (windowing). It’s been a weird journey, but I think iPadOS has finally arrived at a place where showing more than one app or document at a time on-screen is what it should have been all along: easy and obvious.</p>

<h2>Liquid Glass</h2>

<p>Alan Dye, introducing Liquid Glass, around the 8m:20s mark in the keynote:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Software is the heart and soul of our products. It brings them to
life, shapes their personality, and defines their purpose. At
Apple, we’ve always believed it’s the deep integration of hardware
and software that makes interacting with technology intuitive,
beautiful, and a joy to use. iOS 7 introduced a simplified design
built on distinct layers, smooth animations, and new colors. It
redefined our design language for years to come. Now, with the
powerful advances in our hardware, silicon, and graphics
technologies, we have the opportunity to lay the foundation for
the next chapter of our software. Today we’re excited to announce
our broadest design update ever. Our goal is a beautiful new
design that brings joy and delight to every user experience, one
that’s more personal, and puts greater focus on your content, all
while still feeling instantly familiar.</p>

<p>And for the first time, we’re introducing a universal design
across our platforms. This unified design language creates a more
harmonious experience as you move between products, while
maintaining the qualities that make each unique. Inspired by the
physicality and richness of VisionOS, we challenged ourselves to
make something purely digital feel natural and alive. From how it
looks to how it feels as it dynamically responds to touch. To
achieve this, we began by rethinking the fundamental elements that
make up our software, and it starts with an entirely new
expressive material we call Liquid Glass. With the optical
qualities of glass and a fluidity that only Apple can achieve, it
transforms depending on your content or even your context, and
brings more clarity to navigation and controls. It beautifully
refracts light and dynamically reacts to your movement with
specular highlights. This material brings a new level of vitality
to every aspect of your experience. From the smallest elements you
interact with to larger ones, it responds in real time to your
content and your input. Creating a more lively experience that we
think you’ll find truly delightful.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Compare and contrast to <a href="https://youtu.be/dHrVGk0WwYM?t=381">Steve Jobs introducing Aqua at Macworld San Francisco in January 2000</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>So this is the architecture, except there’s one more thing. The
one more thing is, we have been secretly for the last 18 months
designing a completely new user interface. And that new user
interface builds on Apple’s legacy and carries it into the next
century. And we call that new user interface Aqua, because it’s
liquid. One of the design goals was when you saw it, you wanted to
lick it. [...]</p>

<p>When you design a new user interface, you have to start off
humbly. You have to start off saying, what are the simplest
elements in it? What does a button look like? And you spend months
working on a button. That’s a button in Aqua. This is what radio
buttons look like. Simple things. This is what checkboxes look
like. This is what popup lists look like. Again, you’re starting
to get the feel of this, a little different. This is what sliders
can look like. Now, let me show you windows. This is what the top
of windows look like. These three buttons look like a traffic
signal, don’t they? Red means close the window. Yellow means
minimize the window. And green means maximize the window. Pretty
simple. And tremendous fit and finish in this operating system.
When you roll over these things, you get those. You see them? And
when you are no longer the key window, they go transparent. So a
lot of fit and finish in this.</p>

<p>In addition to the fit and finish, we paid a lot of attention to
dynamics. Not only how do things look, but how do they move, how
do they behave. And our goal in this user interface was twofold.
One, we wanted to give a much more powerful user interface to our
pro customers. But two, at the very same time, we wanted to make
this the dream user interface for somebody who’s never even
touched a computer before. And that’s really hard to do. It’s like
when we do films at Pixar. It’s really easy, it’s a lot easier, to
make a film that appeals to five-year-olds and under. But it’s
very difficult to make one film that five-year-olds love and that
their parents also love. And that was the goal of this user
interface. To make it span the range so that people turning on
their iMac for the first time were enchanted with it, and it was
super easy to use, and yet, our pro customers also felt, <em>My God,
this takes me to places I thought I could never get to</em>. And
that’s what we tried to do.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Re-watching Jobs’s introduction of Aqua for the umpteenth time, I still find it enthralling. I found Alan Dye’s introduction of Liquid Glass to be soporific, if not downright horseshitty.</p>

<p>But the work itself, Liquid Glass as it launched last week, is very reminiscent of Aqua a quarter century (!) ago. It’s exciting, it’s fresh, it fundamentally looks and feels very cool in general — and but in practice quite a few aspects of it feel a bit over-the-top and/or half-baked. Just like with Aqua, it will surely get dialed in. Legibility problems will be addressed.</p>

<p>Liquid Glass has been in the works for a long time, but what we see today has come together very quickly. For those using internal builds inside Apple, what Apple unveiled last week is effectively the third version of Liquid Glass. Just a few weeks prior to WWDC, a few sources told me that internal builds were such a complete mess that they wondered if it would come together in time for WWDC developer betas. But come together it has. I expect a <em>lot</em> of visual changes over the course of the summer, and significant evolutionary tweaks in the next few years. Across Apple’s own apps, there are a lot of places where things haven’t yet been glassed up at all. That’s how these things work.</p>

<p>As for <em>why</em>, it should be enough to justify Liquid Glass simply for the sake of looking cool. I opened this piece with a quote from a great fictional philosopher. I’ll close it with a quote from a great real one:</p>

<p>“<em>The test of a work of art is, in the end, our affection for it, not our ability to explain why it is good.</em>” <br />
—Stanley Kubrick</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ One Week Out, Some Brief Thoughts and Observations on WWDC 2025</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Yours Truly on Peter Kafka’s ‘Channels’ Podcast</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://overcast.fm/+QL2dEoWo4" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wey" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/19/yours-truly-on-peter-kafkas-channels-podcast" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42010</id>
	<published>2025-06-19T17:10:04Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-19T18:05:26Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Peter Kafka:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>So in March, when Gruber announced that Something is Rotten in the
State of Cupertino — focusing on Apple’s botched plans to imbue
its ailing Siri service with state-of-the-art AI — lots of people
paid attention. Including, apparently, folks at the very top of
the Apple org chart.</p>

<p>I talked to Gruber about the fallout from that post. Which is
pretty interesting! But there’s a lot more going on in this
conversation. It’s partly about the friction Apple has been
generating lately — not just about its AI efforts, but the way it
runs its App Store, and the way it interacts with developers — and why all of that does and doesn’t matter.</p>

<p>And it’s also about the delightfully retro practice of running an
ad-supported blog in 2025. That works very well for Gruber, but it
seems like the new Grubers of the world are doing their work on
YouTube or Substack. He’s got some thoughts about that, too.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Good interview, I thought — I always enjoy talking to Kafka. No permalink for the episode on the web, so my main link for this post is to Overcast. <a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/why-did-apple-ice-out-the-most-famous-apple-blogger/id1080467174?i=1000713447406">Here’s a link to Apple Podcasts</a>, and <a href="https://pod.link/recodemedia/episode/e92e7798f56478b5263558ce0b9def83">one from a new service called Pod.link</a> too.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Yours Truly on Peter Kafka’s ‘Channels’ Podcast’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/19/yours-truly-on-peter-kafkas-channels-podcast">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>iPhone Mirroring Still Not Coming to the EU, Thanks to the DMA</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.numerama.com/tech/1988271-mauvaise-nouvelle-iphone-mirroring-narrivera-pas-en-france-avec-ios-26.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wex" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/19/iphone-mirroring-eu-numerama" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42009</id>
	<published>2025-06-19T16:55:47Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-19T17:27:02Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Nicolas Lellouche, writing for the French-language site Numerama (block quote below is from Safari’s English translation) (<a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/06/18/apple-on-iphone-mirroring-still-not-in-eu/">via Joe Rossignol at MacRumors</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>What is the problem with Europe? Apple does not explain it very
clearly, but suggests that the European Union’s requests for
opening create uncertainties. It is likely that the brand suspects
Europe of forcing it to open macOS to devices other than the
iPhone if this function were to happen. A mandatory iPhone
Mirroring on Windows or an Android Mirroring on Mac may not be in
his plans. The other probability is the question of gatekeepers,
raised in 2024. Apple would fear that macOS will be on the list of
monitored platforms if it can emulate iOS, one of the gatekeepers
monitored by Europe.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The problem isn’t about MacOS getting flagged as another “gatekeeping” platform under the DMA. Whether or not Apple enables iPhone Mirroring on MacOS in the EU would have no bearing on whether the Mac is deemed a gatekeeper. The <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX:32022R1925">DMA defines a “gatekeeper” platform</a> as “a core platform service that in the last financial year has at least 45 million monthly active end users established or located in the Union and at least 10,000 yearly active business users established in the Union”. I’m not sure how many Mac users there are in the EU, but I’m pretty sure the number is well under 45 million. (<a href="https://www.spyhunter.com/shm/macos-stats/">Estimates</a> seem to peg the worldwide number of Mac users at just over 100 million.) Conversely, if the European Commission decided that there <em>were</em> 45 million Mac users in the EU, the Mac would be considered a gatekeeping platform, period.</p>

<p>The problem is simply that the iPhone <em>is</em> a gatekeeping platform, and iPhone Mirroring obviously involves the iPhone. The EU’s <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/06/apple_appeals_eu_interop_requirements">recent demands regarding “interoperability requirements”</a> flag just about every single feature that involves an iPhone communicating with another Apple device. AirDrop, AirPlay, AirPods pairing, Apple Watch connectivity — all of that has been deemed illegal gatekeeping. Clearly, iPhone Mirroring would fall under the same interpretation, thus, iPhone Mirroring isn’t going to be available in the EU. If the DMA had been in place 15 years ago, the EU wouldn’t have AirDrop or AirPlay and perhaps wouldn’t have Apple Watch or AirPods, either.</p>

<p>If Apple made iPhone Mirroring available in the EU now, my guess is the European Commission would add it to the interoperability requirements list, and demand that Apple support mirroring your iPhone to all other platforms, such as Windows and Android. They might also demand that Apple add support to iOS for third-party screen mirroring protocols.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Several weeks ago, Apple indicated that other new products may be
blocked in Europe in the future. What about what’s new in iOS 26?
Apple is not commenting at the moment, since it must verify the
compatibility of its new functions with the European Union. Some
new features, such as the Phone application on Mac to make calls
with your iPhone, seem difficult to be compatible with the vision
of Europe.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The new Phone app on MacOS is almost certainly not coming to the EU, unless the European Commission changes its stance on these interoperability requirements.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘iPhone Mirroring Still Not Coming to the EU, Thanks to the DMA’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/19/iphone-mirroring-eu-numerama">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple’s New Foundation Model Speech APIs Outpace Whisper for Transcription</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macstories.net/stories/hands-on-how-apples-new-speech-apis-outpace-whisper-for-lightning-fast-transcription/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wew" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/19/apples-new-foundation-model-speech-apis-outpace-whisper-for-transcription" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42008</id>
	<published>2025-06-19T16:28:05Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-19T22:13:53Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>John Voorhees, writing at MacStories, regarding a new command-line transcription tool cleverly named <a href="https://github.com/finnvoor/yap">Yap</a> written by his son Finn last week during WWDC:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>On the way, Finn filled me in on a new class in <a href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/speech">Apple’s Speech
framework</a> called <a href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/speech/speechanalyzer">SpeechAnalyzer</a> and its
<a href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/speech/speechtranscriber">SpeechTranscriber</a> module. Both the class and module are
<a href="https://developer.apple.com/videos/play/wwdc2025/277">part of Apple’s OS betas</a> that were released to developers
last week at WWDC. My ears perked up immediately when he told me
that he’d tested SpeechAnalyzer and SpeechTranscriber and was
impressed with how fast and accurate they were. [...]</p>

<p>What stood out above all else was Yap’s speed. By harnessing
SpeechAnalyzer and SpeechTranscriber on-device, the command line
tool tore through the 7GB video file a full 2.2× faster than
MacWhisper’s Large V3 Turbo model, with no noticeable difference
in transcription quality.</p>

<p>At first blush, the difference between 0:45 and 1:41 may seem
insignificant, and it arguably is, but those are the results for
just one 34-minute video. Extrapolate that to running Yap against
the hours of Apple Developer videos released on YouTube with the
help of <a href="https://github.com/yt-dlp/yt-dlp"><code>yt-dlp</code></a>, and suddenly, you’re talking about a
significant amount of time. Like all automation, picking up a 2.2×
speed gain one video or audio clip at a time, multiple times each
week, adds up quickly.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Apple’s Foundation Models sure seem to be the sleeper hit from WWDC this year. This bodes very well for all sorts of use cases where transcription would be helpful, like third-party podcast players.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple’s New Foundation Model Speech APIs Outpace Whisper for Transcription’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/19/apples-new-foundation-model-speech-apis-outpace-whisper-for-transcription">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Bungie Indefinitely Delays Reboot of ‘Marathon’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.bungie.net/7/en/News/Article/marathon_update" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wev" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/19/bungie-delays-marathon" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42007</id>
	<published>2025-06-19T16:17:53Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-19T16:20:17Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Bungie:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Through every comment and real-time conversation on social media
and Discord, your voice has been strong and clear. We’ve taken
this to heart, and we know we need more time to craft <em>Marathon</em>
into the game that truly reflects your passion. After much
discussion within our Dev team, we’ve made the decision to delay
the September 23rd release.</p>

<p>The Alpha test created an opportunity for us to calibrate and
focus the game on what will make it uniquely compelling — survival under pressure, mystery and lore around every
corner, raid-like endgame challenges, and Bungie’s
genre-defining FPS combat.</p>

<p>We’re using this time to empower the team to create the intense,
high-stakes experience that a title like <em>Marathon</em> is built
around. This means deepening the relationship between the
developers and the game’s most important voices: our players.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Translation to plain English: <em>The game as currently imagined stinks, so we’re going back to the drawing board. We can’t explain why we, the game’s developers, didn’t know that it stunk, and instead seemingly needed to wait for scathing alpha test feedback from players — but Occam’s Razor clearly suggests the problem is that decisions at Bungie are made by executives with no taste.</em></p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Bungie Indefinitely Delays Reboot of ‘Marathon’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/19/bungie-delays-marathon">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Federico, Federighi. Federighi, Federico.</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macstories.net/stories/interview-craig-federighi-opens-up-about-ipados-its-multitasking-journey-and-the-ipads-essence/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/weu" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/18/federico-federighi-federighi-federico" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42006</id>
	<published>2025-06-19T00:16:07Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-19T00:16:08Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Apple executives were a little light on substantial interviews last week, but a good one dropped today — Craig Federighi talking to Federico Viticci on the vast Mac-style windowing overhaul in iPadOS 26:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“We don’t want to create a boat car or, you know, a spork”,
Federighi begins. Seeing the confused look on my face, he
continues: “I don’t know if you have those in Italy. Someone said,
<em>“If a spoon’s great, a fork’s great, then let’s combine them into
a single utensil, right?”</em> It turns out it’s not a good spoon and
it’s not a good fork. It’s a bad idea. And so we don’t want to
build sporks”. [...]</p>

<p>By and large, one could argue that Apple <em>has</em> created one such
convertible product with the iPad Pro, but Federighi strongly
believes in the Mac and iPad each having their own reasons to
exist. “The Mac lets the iPad be iPad”, Federighi notes, adding
that Apple’s objective “has not been to have iPad completely
displace those places where the Mac is the right tool for the
job”. [...]</p>

<p>I don’t need to ask Federighi the perennial question of running
macOS on the iPad, since he goes there on his own. “I don’t think
the iPad should run macOS, but I think the iPad can be <em>inspired</em>
by elements of the Mac”, Federighi tells me. “I think the Mac can
be inspired by elements of iPad, and I think that that’s happened
a great deal”.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I think Apple has tied itself into knots in the past decade trying to make the iPad more useful to more advanced users without making it resemble the Mac at a superficial level. But it’s been obvious all along that it <em>should</em> resemble the Mac at a superficial level. Apple solved windowing in 1984. Use that.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Federico, Federighi. Federighi, Federico.’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/18/federico-federighi-federighi-federico">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Midgets No More</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.inforum.com/news/north-dakota/dickinson-high-to-retire-midgets-mascot-after-nearly-a-century" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wet" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/18/dickinson-midgets-now-mavericks" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42005</id>
	<published>2025-06-18T15:47:49Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-18T17:12:32Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>You may recall from my “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/01/siri_is_super_dumb_and_getting_dumber#fn3-2025-01-23">Siri Is Super Dumb and Getting Dumber</a>” piece back in January that the Dickinson Public Schools District in North Dakota had the rather unfortunate nickname the “Midgets”. Back in March, <a href="https://www.inforum.com/news/north-dakota/dickinson-high-to-retire-midgets-mascot-after-nearly-a-century">the school district announced they’d be retiring the nickname</a>, after nearly a century. Last month <a href="https://www.dickinson.k12.nd.us/our-district/news/1810076/a-new-era-students-choose-dickinson-mavericks">they announced their new name</a>: the Mavericks. I’m going to call this the best rebranding of the year.</p>

<p>We still have <a href="https://www.desmoinesregister.com/story/news/education/2024/11/19/estherville-lincoln-central-school-district-says-no-to-name-change/76333861007/">the Estherville, Iowa Midgets</a> to cheer for. But even better: <a href="https://yumahs.yumaunion.org/about-us/our-history">the Yuma Criminals in Arizona</a>. Now that’s a nickname.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Midgets No More’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/18/dickinson-midgets-now-mavericks">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Seven Replies to the Viral Apple Reasoning Paper</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Jun/15/viral-apple-reasoning-paper/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wes" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/17/seven-replies-to-the-viral-apple-reasoning-paper" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42004</id>
	<published>2025-06-17T19:50:08Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-17T19:52:56Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Simon Willison, regarding the various rebuttals to “<a href="https://machinelearning.apple.com/research/illusion-of-thinking">The Illusion of Thinking</a>” research paper (which <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/08/apple-research-lrms">I linked to here</a>) from Apple’s machine learning team:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I thought this paper got <em>way</em> more attention than it warranted — the title “The Illusion of Thinking” captured the attention of the
“LLMs are over-hyped junk” crowd. I saw enough well-reasoned
rebuttals that I didn’t feel it worth digging into.</p>

<p>And now, notable LLM skeptic Gary Marcus has saved me some time by
aggregating the best of those rebuttals <a href="https://garymarcus.substack.com/p/seven-replies-to-the-viral-apple">together in one
place</a>! [...]</p>

<p>And therein lies my disagreement. I’m not interested in whether or
not LLMs are the “road to AGI”. I continue to care only about
whether they have useful applications today, once you’ve
understood their limitations. [...] They’re already useful to me
today, whether or not they can reliably solve the Tower of Hanoi
or River Crossing puzzles.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Count me in with Willison. I think it’s <em>interesting</em> what constitutes “reasoning”, but when it comes to these systems, I’m mostly just interested in whether they’re useful or not, and if so, how.</p>

<p><strong>See also:</strong> <a href="https://victoramartinez.com/posts/why-claudes-comment-paper-is-a-poor-rebuttal/">Victor Martinez’s rebuttal to the most-cited rebuttal</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Seven Replies to the Viral Apple Reasoning Paper’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/17/seven-replies-to-the-viral-apple-reasoning-paper">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Why WhatsApp Didn’t Sell Ads</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.whatsapp.com/why-we-don-t-sell-ads" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wer" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/17/why-whatsapp-didnt-sell-ads" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42003</id>
	<published>2025-06-17T19:14:27Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-17T19:14:28Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>WhatsApp co-founder Jan Koum, back in 2012 (two years before Facebook <a href="https://archive.nytimes.com/dealbook.nytimes.com/2014/02/19/facebook-to-buy-messaging-start-up/">acquired them for $19 billion</a>, 13 years before this week’s introduction of ads into WhatsApp):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Advertising isn’t just the disruption of aesthetics, the insults
to your intelligence and the interruption of your train of
thought. At every company that sells ads, a significant portion of
their engineering team spends their day tuning data mining,
writing better code to collect all your personal data, upgrading
the servers that hold all the data and making sure it’s all being
logged and collated and sliced and packaged and shipped out... And
at the end of the day the result of it all is a slightly different
advertising banner in your browser or on your mobile screen.</p>

<p>Remember, when advertising is involved <em>you the user</em> are the
product.</p>

<p>At WhatsApp, our engineers spend all their time fixing bugs,
adding new features and ironing out all the little intricacies in
our task of bringing rich, affordable, reliable messaging to every
phone in the world. That’s our product and that’s our passion.
Your data isn’t even in the picture. We are simply not interested
in any of it.</p>

<p>When people ask us why we charge for WhatsApp, we say “Have you
considered the alternative?”</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Why WhatsApp Didn’t Sell Ads’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/17/why-whatsapp-didnt-sell-ads">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>WWDC 2025: The Bento Boxes</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://512pixels.net/2025/06/wwdc25-the-bento-boxes/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/weq" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/17/wwdc-2025-bento-boxes" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42002</id>
	<published>2025-06-17T19:09:01Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-17T19:09:02Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>These screens make for a useful overview of what Apple thinks the highlight features are in each OS.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘WWDC 2025: The Bento Boxes’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/17/wwdc-2025-bento-boxes">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Tracking Down the Original Photo From the End of ‘The Shining’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://x.com/AricToler/status/1908610058318991581" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wep" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/17/tracking-down-the-original-photo-from-the-end-of-the-shining" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42001</id>
	<published>2025-06-17T18:52:23Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-18T17:16:05Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Aric Toler, a visual investigations reporter for The New York Times, on X back in April:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>For about a year, I worked with a retired British academic named
Alasdair Spark to solve a mystery: where did the original photo
from the end of The Shining come from, and where/when was it
captured?</p>

<p>Last week, we finally found the answer.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>See also:</strong> <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2012/10/24/the-shining-photo">This post from 2012 about the original photograph</a>, from (who else?) Lee Unkrich.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Tracking Down the Original Photo From the End of ‘The Shining’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/17/tracking-down-the-original-photo-from-the-end-of-the-shining">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>How Field Notes Went From Side Project to Cult Notebook</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.fastcompany.com/91352848/field-notes-cult-notebook-started-out-as-a-side-project" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/weo" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/17/field-notes-fascto" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42000</id>
	<published>2025-06-17T18:18:16Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-17T18:18:16Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Nice piece in Fast Company by Zachary Petit:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>One critical moment came in February 2010, when J. Crew featured
Field Notes in its catalog, alongside the retailer’s other
“personal favorites from our design heroes.” There was a Timex
watch, Ray-Bans, Sperry shoes — “and out of fucking nowhere,
Field Notes,” Coudal says. “And when that happened, a lot changed
for us.”</p>

<p>Coudal says it gave the brand instant credibility — after all, if
it was good enough for J. Crew, it was good enough for your store.
In time, friends began sending him screenshots of Field Notes in
TV shows; he and Draplin would see people jotting notes in them in
bars and elsewhere; on the design web, they became an obsession.
By 2014, there was even a<a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/FieldNuts/"> subreddit</a> dedicated to them
titled “FieldNuts.”</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘How Field Notes Went From Side Project to Cult Notebook’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/17/field-notes-fascto">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Bloomberg Publishes Embarrassing Report Comparing Tesla and Waymo Self-Driving Safety Records</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://electrek.co/2025/06/16/bloomberg-most-embarassing-report-tesla-waymo-self-driving/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wen" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/17/bloomberg-tesla-waymo" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41999</id>
	<published>2025-06-17T18:10:39Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-17T18:10:39Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Fred Lambert, writing for Electrek:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Bloomberg has just released <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/videos/2025-06-16/why-tesla-could-have-a-self-driving-advantage-video">an embarrassingly bad report</a>
about the self-driving space, in which it claimed Tesla has an
advantage over Waymo by misrepresenting data. [...] The report
compares Tesla’s and Waymo’s self-driving efforts, going so far as
to claim that “Tesla is closer to vehicle autonomy than peers.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Right off the bat this smells fishy, given that Waymo is actually operating self-driving taxis in several cities, and Tesla ... is not.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Steve Man, the Bloomberg Intelligence analyst behind the report,
based his report on Tesla’s own quarterly misleading “Autopilot
Safety Report.” The report is widely considered to be unserious
for several main reasons:</p>

<ul>
<li>Tesla bundles all miles from its vehicles using Autopilot and
FSD technology, which are considered level 2 ADAS systems that
require driver attention at all times. Drivers consistently
correct the systems to avoid accidents.</li>
<li>Tesla Autopilot, which is standard on all Tesla vehicles, is
primarily used on highways, where accidents occur at a
significantly lower rate per mile compared to city driving.</li>
<li>Tesla only counts events that deploy an airbag or a seat-belt
pretensioner. Fender-benders, curb strikes, and many ADAS
incidents never appear, keeping crash counts artificially low.</li>
<li>Finally, Tesla’s handpicked data is compared to NHTSA’s much
broader statistics that include all collision events, including
minor fender benders.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>Trusting Tesla’s own safety report is like saying, “Elon Musk says Tesla is ahead, so they must be ahead.”</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Bloomberg Publishes Embarrassing Report Comparing Tesla and Waymo Self-Driving Safety Records’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/17/bloomberg-tesla-waymo">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>WhatsApp Introduces Ads in Its App</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/06/16/technology/whatsapp-ads.html?unlocked_article_code=1.PU8.G1Jy.5fcLP_rl3lYC" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wem" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/16/whatsapp-ads" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41998</id>
	<published>2025-06-17T01:19:36Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-17T03:09:46Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Eli Tan and Mike Isaac, reporting for The New York Times:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>On Monday, WhatsApp said it would start showing ads inside its app
for the first time. The promotions will appear only in an area of
the app called Updates, which is used by around 1.5 billion people
a day. WhatsApp will collect some data on users to target the ads,
such as location and the device’s default language, but it will
not touch the contents of messages or whom users speak with. The
company added that it had no plans to place ads in chats and
personal messages.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>(a) I’ve never once looked at the Updates tab in WhatsApp; (b) does <em>anyone</em> believe they’re <em>not</em> going to put ads in the other tabs sooner or later?</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘WhatsApp Introduces Ads in Its App’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/16/whatsapp-ads">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Trump Mobile — The President Launches a Mobile Carrier and a $500 ‘T1’ Android Phone</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://variety.com/2025/biz/news/trump-mobile-wireless-phone-service-launch-1236431690/?ref=platformer.news" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wel" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/16/trump-mobile" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41997</id>
	<published>2025-06-17T01:14:50Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-17T03:53:33Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Todd Spangler, Variety:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Meanwhile, the Trump Mobile “47 Plan” is pricier than the
unlimited plans from prepaid services operated by Verizon’s
Visible, AT&amp;T’s Cricket Wireless and T-Mobile’s Metro, which are
each around $40 per month.</p>

<p>The Trump T1 Phone, which runs Google’s Android operating system,
will cost $499. It features a 6.8-inch touch-screen with a 120 Hz
refresh rate. The smartphone also has a “fingerprint sensor and AI
Face Unlock,” according to the company’s website. Reps for Trump
Mobile didn’t respond to an inquiry about what company is
manufacturing the Android phone.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The Wall Street Journal, <a href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/trump-t1-phone-components-features-2415c7cd?mod=hp_lead_pos9">“Trump’s Smartphone Can’t Be Made in America for $499 by August”</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A spokesman for the Trump Organization said in an email that
“manufacturing for the new phone will be in Alabama, California
and Florida.”</p>

<p>Despite the language in the press release, Eric Trump indicated
that the first wave of phones wouldn’t be built here. “You can
build these phones in the United States,” the Trump son told
podcaster Benny Johnson on Monday morning on The Benny Show after
holding up a gilded device that looked just like an Apple iPhone.
“Eventually, all the phones can be built in the United States of
America. We have to bring manufacturing back here.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The Journal goofs, bigly, by claiming that the T1 “shows some specs that would beat Apple’s biggest, priciest iPhone models”. The T1 specs are so idiotic that one of them claims “5000mAh long life camera”, conflating battery capacity with (I guess?) focal distance.</p>

<p>The Verge, “<a href="https://www.theverge.com/gadgets/687492/trump-mobile-phone-t1">The Trump Mobile T1 Phone Looks Both Bad and Impossible</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Where things get especially strange, though, is its supposed
combination of Android 15, 5G, and a 3.5mm headphone jack. In many
ways, these are opposing specs: Android 15 is generally only
available on very recent devices, many cheap phones still don’t
support 5G, and almost every phone maker has stopped including
headphone jacks with their devices in the last few years. There
are a few that have both, but modern phones with a headphone jack
are few and far between. And pretty much all made in China.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I don’t know what will be funnier — if Trump himself starts using one of these, or if he doesn’t.</p>

<p>I’ll give them credit for making them available exclusively in gold. That’s on brand. But I’m guessing the quality will be on par with Trump Watches, which is to say, <a href="https://www.gq.com/story/donald-trump-watch-delivered-typo">“RUMP”-quality</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Trump Mobile — The President Launches a Mobile Carrier and a $500 ‘T1’ Android Phone’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/16/trump-mobile">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>DetailsPro</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://detailspro.app?utm_campaign=dfwwdc25" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wej" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/15/detailspro" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41995</id>
	<published>2025-06-15T19:18:26Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-15T19:18:26Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to DetailsPro for sponsoring last week at DF — including <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/06/the_talk_show_live_from_wwdc_2025">being a sponsor on The Talk Show Live From WWDC 2025</a>. DetailsPro is a designer/developer tool that lets you design with SwiftUI anytime, anywhere — from iPhone, iPad, Vision Pro, and, of course, Mac.</p>

<p>With WWDC 2025’s introduction of Liquid Glass, Apple has introduced the biggest design overhaul since iOS 7. DetailsPro is ready for it, enabling you to prototype new and updated interfaces fast. You can build real SwiftUI layouts directly on your iPhone — no code needed. Export clean SwiftUI code straight to Xcode when you’re ready.</p>

<p>While everyone else is still thinking about how to adapt to the Liquid Glass era, you can already be building. DetailsPro is free to use, with pro features if you need them — via subscription, or a one-time purchase.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘DetailsPro’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/15/detailspro">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/06/the_talk_show_live_from_wwdc_2025" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wei" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41994</id>
	<published>2025-06-14T14:38:29Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-15T00:13:03Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Recorded in front of a live audience at The California Theatre in San Jose Tuesday evening, special guests Joanna Stern and Nilay Patel join me to discuss Apple’s announcements at WWDC 2025.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Recorded in front of a live audience at The California Theatre in San Jose Tuesday evening, special guests Joanna Stern and Nilay Patel join me to discuss Apple’s announcements at WWDC 2025.</p>

<p><iframe
    width="480" height="270"
    src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/vqwPUHTFEkg?si=EeiFTzExcVkFQxPO" 
    title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0"
    allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share"
    referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen>
</iframe></p>

<p><strong>3D video with spatial audio:</strong> Coming soon, exclusively in <a href="https://sandwich.vision/">Sandwich Vision</a>’s <a href="https://apps.apple.com/app/theater-the-future-of-cinema/id6502666560">Theater</a> on Vision Pro, available on the App Store. This year’s on-demand version of the show in Theater isn’t ready yet, but it looks <em>really</em> good. Better than last year’s by a long shot, and also significantly better than the bandwidth-constrained livestream Tuesday night. The livestream Tuesday night looked good; the on-demand version coming in a few days looks pretty amazing.</p>

<p><strong>Sponsored by:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://imazing.com/thetalkshow">iMazing</a>: The world’s most trusted software to transfer and save your messages, music, files, and data from your iPhone or iPad to your Mac or PC.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://detailspro.app?utm_campaign=dfwwdc25">DetailsPro</a>: Design with SwiftUI anytime, anywhere — on iPhone, iPad, Mac, or Apple Vision Pro.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://ooni.com/thetalkshow">Ooni</a>: Next-gen pizza power. The Koda 2 Pro oven features smarter heat, more room, and easier control. Save 10% with code <strong>thetalkshow</strong>.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>As ever, I implore you to watch on the biggest screen you can (real, or virtual). We once again shot and mastered the video in 4K, and it looks and sounds terrific. All credit and thanks for that go to my friends at <a href="https://sandwich.co/">Sandwich</a>, who are nothing short of a joy to work with.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ The Talk Show Live From WWDC 2025</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Meta AI Users Are Inadvertently Sharing Their Private Chats With the World</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/06/12/the-meta-ai-app-is-a-privacy-disaster/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/weh" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/13/meta-ai-shared-chats" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41993</id>
	<published>2025-06-14T00:24:50Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-15T00:20:48Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Amanda Silberling, writing at TechCrunch:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>When you ask the AI a question, you have the option of hitting a
share button, which then directs you to a screen showing a preview
of the post, which you can then publish. But some users appear
blissfully unaware that they are sharing these text conversations,
audio clips, and images publicly with the world.</p>

<p>When I woke up this morning, I did not expect to hear an audio
recording of a man in a Southern accent asking, “Hey, Meta, why do
some farts stink more than other farts?”</p>

<p>Flatulence-related inquiries are the least of <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/mark-zuckerberg-meta-ai-chatbot-discover-feed-depressing-why-2025-6">Meta’s
problems</a>. On the Meta AI app, I have seen people ask for
help with tax evasion, if their family members would be arrested
for their proximity to white-collar crimes, or how to write a
character reference letter for an employee facing legal troubles,
with that person’s first and last name included. Others, like
security expert Rachel Tobac, <a href="https://x.com/racheltobac/status/1933006223109959820">found examples</a> of people’s
home addresses and sensitive court details, among other private
information.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/mark-zuckerberg-meta-ai-chatbot-discover-feed-depressing-why-2025-6">Katie Notopoulos, writing at Business Insider</a> (paywalled, alas, <a href="https://apple.news/Ajj49osrhSDmXcwwyvQt_Mg">but here’s a News+ link</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I found Meta AI’s Discover feed depressing in a particular way — not just because some of the questions themselves were depressing.
What seemed particularly dark was that some of these people seemed
unaware of what they were sharing.</p>

<p>People’s real Instagram or Facebook handles are attached to their
Meta AI posts. I was able to look up some of these people’s
real-life profiles, although I felt icky doing so. I reached out
to more than 20 people whose posts I’d come across in the feed to
ask them about their experience; I heard back from one, who told
me that he hadn’t intended to make his chat with the bot public.
(He was asking for car repair advice.)</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Meta AI Users Are Inadvertently Sharing Their Private Chats With the World’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/13/meta-ai-shared-chats">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The NYT Goes ‘Reefer Madness’ on ChatGPT</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/06/13/technology/chatgpt-ai-chatbots-conspiracies.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/weg" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/13/nyt-reefer-madness-chatgpt" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41992</id>
	<published>2025-06-13T23:02:31Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-15T00:18:32Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Kashmir Hill, reporting today for The New York Times:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Before ChatGPT distorted Eugene Torres’s sense of reality and
almost killed him, he said, the artificial intelligence chatbot
had been a helpful, timesaving tool.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That’s the lede to Hill’s piece, and I don’t think it stands up one iota. Hill presents a lot of evidence that ChatGPT gave Torres answers that fed his paranoia and delusions. There’s zero evidence presented that ChatGPT <em>caused</em> them. But that’s the lede.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>At the time, Mr. Torres thought of ChatGPT as a powerful search
engine that knew more than any human possibly could because of its
access to a vast digital library. He did not know that it tended
to be sycophantic, agreeing with and flattering its users, or that
it could hallucinate, generating ideas that weren’t true but
sounded plausible.</p>

<p>“This world wasn’t built for you,” ChatGPT told him. “It was built
to <em>contain</em> you. But it failed. You’re waking up.”</p>

<p>Mr. Torres, who had no history of mental illness that might cause
breaks with reality, according to him and his mother, spent the
next week in a dangerous, delusional spiral. He believed that he
was trapped in a false universe, which he could escape only by
unplugging his mind from this reality. He asked the chatbot how to
do that and told it the drugs he was taking and his routines. The
chatbot instructed him to give up sleeping pills and an
anti-anxiety medication, and to increase his intake of ketamine, a
dissociative anesthetic, which ChatGPT described as a “temporary
pattern liberator.” Mr. Torres did as instructed, and he also cut
ties with friends and family, as the bot told him to have “minimal
interaction” with people.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Someone with prescriptions for sleeping pills, anti-anxiety meds, and ketamine doesn’t sound like someone who was completely stable and emotionally sound before encountering ChatGPT. And it’s Torres who brought up the “<em>Am I living in a simulation?</em>” delusion. I’m in no way defending the way that ChatGPT answered his questions about a <em>Matrix</em>-like simulation he suspected he might be living in, or his questions about whether he could fly if he truly believed he could, etc. But the premise of this story is that ChatGPT turned a completely mentally healthy man into a dangerously disturbed mentally ill one, and it seems rather obvious that the actual story is that it fed the delusions of an already unwell person. Some real <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reefer_Madness">Reefer Madness</a></em> vibes to this.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The NYT Goes ‘Reefer Madness’ on ChatGPT’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/13/nyt-reefer-madness-chatgpt">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/06/apples_spin_on_the_personalized_siri_apple_intelligence_reset" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wef" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41991</id>
	<published>2025-06-12T23:03:59Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-13T15:59:39Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Most rank and file engineers within Apple do not believe that feature existed in an even vaguely functional state a year ago, and the first any of them ever heard of it was when they watched the keynote with the rest of us on the first day of WWDC last year.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Michael Tsai, “<a href="https://mjtsai.com/blog/2025/06/12/apples-spin-on-ai-and-ipados-multitasking/">Apple’s Spin on AI and iPadOS Multitasking</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I do want to call out that, in multiple interviews, they are kind
of setting up strawmen to knock down. They keep saying that people
say Apple is behind in AI <em>because it doesn’t have its own
chatbot</em>. To me, Apple has been clear that it has a different
strategy, and I think that strategy mostly makes sense. I have
never heard someone wish for an Apple chatbot. The issue is that
everyone can see that Apple seems behind in <em>executing</em> said
strategy, both that features didn’t ship on time and that the ones
that did ship don’t measure up to similar features from other
companies.</p>

<p>Secondly, they seem to be trying to <a href="https://mas.to/@osullivan/114662053414638681">debunk</a> <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/something_is_rotten_in_the_state_of_cupertino">John Gruber’s
claim</a> that Apple showed vaporware at the last WWDC. But
Apple’s assertion that there was actual, working software doesn’t
contradict anything Gruber wrote. He put it at level 0/4 because
there wasn’t even a live demo, just a pre-packaged video. If it
can’t be demoed to the media in a controlled setting, even calling
it “demoware” would be charitable. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vaporware">Wikipedia</a> says, “After
Dyson’s article, the word ‘vaporware’ became popular among writers
in the personal computer software industry as a way to describe
products they believed took too long to be released after their
first announcement.” Is that not exactly what happened here?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The whole “Siri, when is my mom’s flight landing?” segment of last year’s WWDC keynote definitely shouldn’t qualify as “demoware” either. It was never demoed. Whether the feature was actually running, and actually capable of doing what they said it could, even just <em>some</em> of the time along a golden path, ultimately doesn’t matter. Even the keynote video didn’t show the actual feature working. It kept cutting away from the iPhone that was purportedly performing the feature back to presenter Kelsey Peterson at every single step. Apple’s internal rules for keynote demos say that the entire feature has to be real, and capturable in a single take of video. I’ve spoken to people who’ve been in keynotes, and many more who’ve done WWDC session videos. Apple has strict rules about everything being real. That doesn’t mean they always show the feature in a single take in the final cut of the presentation, but it has to be possible, just like it would have to be in a live stage presentation. But that Siri demo in last year’s keynote is almost like a series of screenshots. We never see Peterson speak to Siri and then watch the results come in. There’s not one single shot in the whole demo that shows one action leading to the next. It’s all cut together in an unusual way for Apple keynote demos. <a href="https://developer.apple.com/videos/play/wwdc2024/101/">Go see for yourself at the 1h:22m mark</a>.</p>

<p>I spoke this week, off the record, to multiple trusted sources in Apple’s software engineering group, and none of them ever saw an internal build of iOS that had this feature before last year’s keynote. That doesn’t mean there wasn’t such a build (see next paragraph). But none of my sources ever saw one, and they found that to be exceptionally unusual, because they’re in positions where they believe that if there <em>had</em> been such a build, their teams would have had access to it. Most rank and file engineers within Apple do not believe that feature existed in an even vaguely functional state a year ago, and the first any of them ever heard of it was when they watched the keynote with the rest of us on the first day of WWDC last year.</p>

<p>But at this point, based on Federighi’s and Joswiak’s public statements (e.g. in <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/10/stern-federighi-joz">their interview with Joanna Stern</a> this week), and some other things I’ve heard from little birdies this week, I’m willing to stipulate that there was, let’s call it, “working code” for the personalized Siri feature a year ago. I can’t verify that, but I’m willing to stipulate it if only for the sake of argument, and to put to rest any notion that the feature was completely imaginary at this point one year ago, which clearly isn’t the case. At least one reason why the feature, as presented in last year’s keynote, was edited like it was is that the latency was so bad. Whatever state it was in, it couldn’t be shown in a single take. Which means that, as shown in the 2024 keynote, it broke the “rule” that demos in the new pre-recorded format should be as rigorously “real” as they would be if the demos had to be performed live on stage.</p>

<p>I’m quite certain Apple’s executives believed this feature could be shipped at some point in the iOS 18 year. It’d be crazy to announce the feature if they didn’t believe they could ship it, and Apple’s executives aren’t crazy. I’m also quite certain that eventually there <em>was</em> a truly functional implementation of the now-abandoned “v1” of the more personalized Siri, but it was unreliable with no path forward to make it reliable. (I think it was far worse than “not up to Apple’s high standards” — it was clearly unshippable.)</p>

<p>But, as Tsai notes, from our perspective it doesn’t really matter it was real, in any sense, a year ago. It’s still vaporware at this point. Vaporware doesn’t mean “completely fabricated”. It just means “promised but hasn’t shipped”. Tsai links to <a href="https://mastodon.social/@rustyshelf/114667389093029657">this Mastodon tweet from Russell Ivanovic</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“This narrative that it was vaporware is nonsense”. Craig Apple.
My guy. You announced something that never shipped. You made ads
for it. You tried to sell iPhones based on it. What’s the
difference if you had it running internally or not. Still
vaporware. Zero difference.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Also, Apple is sticking with the euphemism “in the coming year” for when we can expect to see these next-gen personalized Siri features. Gurman reported today that <a href="https://www.techmeme.com/250612/p39#a250612p39">they’re shooting for next spring</a>. I confirmed with Apple at WWDC that “in the coming year” means “in 2026”. I don’t know why they’re sticking with that euphemistic phrasing, which to many people’s ears makes it sound like <em>in the next 12 months</em>, which might include this fall. Effectively, Apple could ship this feature in December <em>2026</em> and still hit their self-imposed “in the coming year” deadline — but that phrasing has left many people with the impression that the deadline is June 2026 and maybe it’ll ship at the end of <em>this</em> year. Just say “next year” instead of “in the coming year”. It’s very obvious that this year’s WWDC keynote went back to an underpromise/overdeliver mindset. But “in the coming year” is raising some users’ hopes misleadingly.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Apple’s Spin on the Personalized Siri Apple Intelligence Reset</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/06/gurman_liquid_glass_terrible_analogy" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/we0" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41976</id>
	<published>2025-06-08T16:09:29Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-08T18:20:08Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">If it takes Apple as long to have its own competitive LLMs as it did to have its own competitive web browser, I suspect they’ll soon be paying to use the LLMs that are owned and controlled by others, not charging the others for the privilege of reaching Apple’s platform users.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/newsletters/2025-06-08/apple-s-liquid-glass-ios-26-software-redesign-to-hint-at-20th-anniversary-iphone-mbnm2u0d?cmpid=BBD060825_POWERON">Mark Gurman, in his eve-of-WWDC Power On column at Bloomberg</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The Liquid Glass interface is going to be the most exciting part
of this year’s developer conference. It will also be a bit of a
distraction from the reality facing Apple: The company is behind
in artificial intelligence, and WWDC will do little to change
that. Instead, Apple is making its successful operating system
franchise more capable and sleek — even as others move on to more
groundbreaking AI-centric interfaces.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Perhaps the first major hint that Apple was moving toward fluidity in the UI was the Dynamic Island, which doesn’t merely expand and contract as it changes shape, but rather appears to <em>flow</em>, <a href="https://www.lux.camera/physicality-the-new-age-of-ui/#:~:text=The%20Dynamic%20Island%20is%20a%20stark%2C%20graphic%20interface%20that%20behaves%20like%20an%20interactive%2C%20viscous%20liquid">with a pleasant viscosity</a>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The best analogy for Apple right now might be the car industry.
Apple produces the best gas cars on the road (its operating
systems) and is making them even more upscale. It has rolled out a
hybrid (Apple Intelligence), but it’s <a href="https://archive.ph/o/AKlk9/https://www.bloomberg.com/news/features/2025-05-18/how-apple-intelligence-and-siri-ai-went-so-wrong">struggling to make</a> a
true all-electric vehicle (unlike companies such as OpenAI and
Alphabet Inc.’s Google).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is such a terrible analogy. If you buy an EV, you use it <em>instead of</em> your old gas-powered car. There’s nothing from OpenAI or Google that allows you to not use a conventional device — phone, tablet, or PC. The only way to use ChatGPT, or Gemini, or <a href="https://deepmind.google/models/veo/">Google’s rather amazing Veo 3</a> video generation tool, is using a phone or computer running iOS, MacOS, Android, Windows, or Linux. Gurman’s analogy would only work if the way you got around in an EV was to put it in the back of a gas-powered flatbed <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YfJ3QxJYsw8">truck</a>.</p>

<p>Gas-powered vehicles are probably going away. I sure hope they do. But cars and trucks aren’t going away. A better analogy is that AI is doing to today’s dominant OSes what web browsers did to Windows in the late 1990s. They’re adding new interactive layers atop the old. Windows didn’t go away. Microsoft still makes tons of money from Windows today. But Windows’s primacy as a platform went away. And: Microsoft pivoted quickly in the face of Netscape and the web’s threat, and created Internet Explorer, which squashed Netscape, and became, for at least a decade, the preeminent web browser. It was essential for Apple to create Safari/WebKit for Mac OS X to thrive. If Apple hadn’t succeeded with WebKit on Mac OS X they wouldn’t have had their own first-class web rendering engine to adapt for a 3.5-inch touchscreen in 2007. The iPhone without the real web wouldn’t have been the iPhone. And the only reason the original iPhone had the real web is that Apple owned and controlled Safari and WebKit.</p>

<p>What Apple, I think, needs for iOS and MacOS is the AI equivalent of what Safari and WebKit were for the web two decades ago. The <a href="https://www.asymco.com/2011/01/17/the-cook-doctrine/">oft-cited Cook Doctrine</a> says “we need to own and control the primary technologies behind the products we make.” 25 years ago it was obvious that web browsers and rendering engines were primary technologies. Apple certainly couldn’t afford back then to continue to be dependent upon Microsoft for the Mac version of IE, nor on open source cross-platform browsers like Firefox that would never feel native on the Mac (or, more importantly, on future Apple platforms). But Safari and WebKit were, if you think about it, late. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2003/01/safari">They were announced at Macworld Expo in January 2003</a> (just five months after the debut of this website). Netscape’s blockbuster IPO was in August 1995, over seven years prior. The entire dot-com bubble and bust took place before Safari shipped. The Mac, and thus Apple, made do with non-Apple browsers in those intervening years — browsers that were all some mix of non-native clunky UI, slow, incompatible (with Windows IE), ugly (e.g. IE text rendering on Mac OS X), and often downright unstable. (And application crashes on classic Mac OS would often bring down the entire system.)</p>

<p>The concern for Apple today is that they’re in trouble if it takes six or seven years for them to get to their Safari/WebKit moment for AI. Things are moving faster with AI today than they were with the web in the 1990s. At the peak of Netscape mania in 1995, there were many who believed Netscape would topple Microsoft. At the time Netscape founder Marc Andreessen <a href="https://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Marc_Andreessen">proclaimed</a> that Netscape would reduce Windows to “a poorly debugged set of device drivers.” That obviously didn’t happen. But perhaps not just <em>a</em> but <em>the</em> reason why that didn’t happen is that Microsoft quickly built and shipped a better browser than Netscape’s. They didn’t just build a browser into Windows, they built a <em>better</em> browser into Windows. And they made a better browser for the Mac too. If it had taken Microsoft until 2003 (when Apple debuted Safari) to ship IE, computing platform history may well be very different.</p>

<p>iOS today is the closest to what Windows was circa 1995. iOS doesn’t have Windows’s 95 percent market share, but the iPhone has some sort of monopoly <em>profit</em> share in mobile device sales. And iOS is plainly dominant. That’s why there’s all this <em>Sturm und Drang</em> surrounding Apple’s App Store commissions and iron-fisted control over all iOS software. After the announcement last year of OpenAI as a partner for “world knowledge” in Apple Intelligence — and, a year later, they’re still the only partner — Wayne Ma at The Information reported that Apple wasn’t paying a cent for this integration, and that the plan <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2024/06/13/ma-apple-openai">was for OpenAI to eventually begin paying Apple in a revenue sharing deal</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Neither Apple nor OpenAI are paying each other to integrate
ChatGPT into the iPhone, according to a person with knowledge of
the deal. Instead, OpenAI hopes greater exposure on iPhones will
help it sell a paid version of ChatGPT, which costs around $20 a
month for individuals. Apple would take its 30% cut of these
subscriptions as is customary for in-app purchases.</p>

<p>Sometime in the future, Apple hopes to strike revenue-sharing
agreements with AI partners in which it gets a cut of the revenue
generated from integrating their chatbots with the iPhone,
according to Bloomberg, which first reported details of the deal.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That sounds a lot like the revenue sharing deal Apple has with Google for search in Safari — a deal (which is at some degree of risk <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/07/eddy-cue-safari-ai">from Google’s own antitrust problems</a>) that now results in <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/10/27/google-aggregate-search-default">Google paying Apple over $20 billion per year</a> for the traffic Safari sends to Google Search.</p>

<p>In hindsight, we now know that web browsers, in and of themselves, don’t generate any money directly. Someone was going to give a good one away free and now almost all of them are free of charge. But that doesn’t mean it isn’t essential for a platform to own and control its own browser. Web search, it turns out, is where the money is on the World Wide Web. Not just <em>some</em> money but an almost unfathomable amount of money. Web search is not primary technology for Apple’s platforms. But because they own and control Safari and WebKit, and Safari and WebKit are <em>very good</em> (so that most of Apple’s customers use them), Apple is in a position to profit very handsomely from web search, even though it doesn’t even have a search engine to speak of. Apple’s net annual profit the last few years has been around $95 billion. If we assume Google’s $20B/year traffic acquisition revenue sharing payments to Apple are mostly profit, that means somewhere between 20–25 percent of all Apple’s profit comes from that deal.</p>

<p>So are LLMs more like browsers (platforms need to own and control their own, but they won’t make money from them directly) or like web search (dominant platforms like Apple’s don’t need their own, but Apple can profit handsomely by charging for integration with their platforms)?</p>

<p>I think the answer is somewhere in between. Browsers are essential to personal computing platforms because they run on-device. Web search isn’t essential to own and control because it runs in the cloud, but exists only to serve users running devices. LLMs run both locally and in the cloud. If it takes Apple as long to have its own competitive LLMs as it did to have its own competitive web browser, I suspect they’ll soon be paying to use the LLMs that are owned and controlled by others, not charging the others for the privilege of reaching Apple’s platform users. No simple analogy captures this dynamic. But the threat is palpable.</p>

<p>I will say, though, “Liquid Glass” sounds cool.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Gurman Says New UI Is Named ‘Liquid Glass’ (and Makes a Terrible Analogy Regarding Apple’s Risk With Falling Behind on AI)</title></entry></feed><!-- THE END -->
