<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>Daring Fireball</title>
<subtitle>By John Gruber</subtitle>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/" />
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main" />
<id>https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main</id>


<updated>2025-12-30T23:57:12Z</updated><rights>Copyright © 2025, John Gruber</rights><entry>
	<title>‘I’m in Charge at This Hertz Location, and Buddy, You’re Not Getting a Car Today’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.mcsweeneys.net/articles/im-in-charge-at-this-hertz-location-and-buddy-youre-not-getting-a-car-today" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wtb" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/30/not-getting-a-car-today" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42527</id>
	<published>2025-12-30T23:57:11Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-30T23:57:12Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Emily Delaney, at McSweeney’s:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Okay, now you’re getting upset. You’re getting upset despite the
fact that we have strict rules against getting upset at this Hertz
location. But tell me, honestly, when you reserved a rental car
through Hertz, you thought… what? That we were going to set aside
a special little car just for you? Seriously? Oh my god.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>(<a href="https://kottke.org/25/12/0047917-im-in-charge-at-this">Via Kottke</a>.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘I’m in Charge at This Hertz Location, and Buddy, You’re Not Getting a Car Today’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/30/not-getting-a-car-today">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The U.S. Conservative Aggrieved Mindset, Explained</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://knowyourmeme.com/videos/433740-just-coffee-black" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wta" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/30/pargin-conservative-mindset" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42526</id>
	<published>2025-12-30T23:46:27Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-30T23:46:27Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jason Pargin is — well, to my tastes — a master of the TikTok video format. This one is so good, and ends with a mic-drop closing line.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The U.S. Conservative Aggrieved Mindset, Explained’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/30/pargin-conservative-mindset">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Using AirPods Live Translation in Japan</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/12/26/travel/airpods-live-translation-japan.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wt9" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/30/using-airpods-live-translation-in-japan" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42525</id>
	<published>2025-12-30T20:26:55Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-30T20:27:53Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Ruffin Prevost, writing at The New York Times:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>As everyone filed out, I repeated, in English, some of the
priest’s comments to my guide, Keiko Hatada, who taught English
for 30 years and has led custom tours of Tokyo for the past
decade. I wanted to make sure I had understood things correctly.</p>

<p>I recounted the priest’s admonition to set aside unwholesome
feelings of anger and greed, and work instead to show compassion
and generosity, as well as his reminder that his temple was still
accepting donations for those affected by the 2011 earthquake and
tsunami.</p>

<p>“You told me you didn’t speak Japanese,” my guide said, pleasantly
surprised.</p>

<p>Beyond a few basic greetings and food terms, I don’t.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I wrote the following two years ago <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2023/09/airpods_pro_2_usbc">in my AirPods Pro 2 review</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The new AirPods Pro are the best single expression of Apple as a
company today. Not the most important product, not the most
complicated, not the most essential. But the one that exemplifies
everything Apple is trying to do. They are simple, they are
useful, and they offer features that most people use and want.
Most people use headphones. A lot of people use them every day — in noisy environments. AirPods Pro are — for any scenario where
big over-ear-style headphones are impractical — the best
headphones in the world.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That was <em>before</em> Live Translation, a feature that until recently existed only in science fiction.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Using AirPods Live Translation in Japan’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/30/using-airpods-live-translation-in-japan">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>ICEBlock App Sues Trump Administration for Censorship</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.npr.org/2025/12/08/nx-s1-5631826/iceblock-app-lawsuit-trump-bondi?ref=platformer.news" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wt8" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/30/iceblock-app-sues-trump-administration-for-censorship" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42524</id>
	<published>2025-12-30T19:44:44Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-30T19:44:45Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Bobby Allyn, reporting three weeks ago for NPR:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The developer of ICEBlock, an iPhone app that anonymously tracks
the presence of Immigration and Customs Enforcement agents, has
sued the Trump administration for free speech violations after
Apple <a href="https://www.npr.org/2025/10/03/nx-s1-5561999/apple-google-iceblock-app-removal">removed</a> the service from its app store under
demands from the White House.</p>

<p>The suit, <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/26360437-iceblock-complaint-as-filed/">filed on Monday </a> in federal court in
Washington, asks a judge to declare that the administration
violated the First Amendment when it threatened to criminally
prosecute the app’s developer and pressured Apple to make the app
unavailable for download, which the tech company did in October. [...]</p>

<p>To First Amendment advocates, the White House’s pressure campaign
targeting ICEBlock is the latest example of what’s known as
“jawboning,” when government officials wield state power to
suppress speech. The Cato Institute calls the practice “censorship
by proxy.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Good on developer Joshua Aaron for filing this suit and defending his work.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘ICEBlock App Sues Trump Administration for Censorship’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/30/iceblock-app-sues-trump-administration-for-censorship">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/12/do_a_better_job_on_the_wings" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wt7" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42523</id>
	<published>2025-12-30T18:54:20Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-30T22:11:56Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Kubrick on the Icarus myth.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Randy Walters wrote a lovely little story, “<a href="https://satori.substack.com/p/christianes-gift">Christiane’s Gift</a>”, originally published back in 2012, about a visit to a Frankfurt museum hosting an exhibit from Stanley Kubrick’s personal archives in 2004. I toured the same exhibit <a href="https://www.thecjm.org/pages/57">at the Contemporary Jewish Museum in San Francisco in 2016</a>; it was <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=a31Gv0lPlAw">remarkable</a>. Included in the exhibit was <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5rZTrZwmMJ0">the famed ƒ/0.7 Zeiss lens</a> (designed for use by NASA for satellite photography in space) and the <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2015/04/02/kubricks-lenses">jury-rigged Mitchell BNC camera Kubrick commissioned</a> so he could use that lens to shoot scenes by candlelight in <em>Barry Lyndon</em>.</p>

<p>In the preface to his story, Walters references this quote from Kubrick, from <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=y5KHGN76AFE">his acceptance speech</a> for the D.W. Griffith lifetime achievement award from the Director’s Guild of America in 1998:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I’ve compared Griffith’s career to the Icarus myth, but at the
same time I’ve never been certain whether the moral of the Icarus
story should only be, as is generally accepted, “Don’t try to fly
too high,” or whether it might also be thought of as “Forget the
wax and feathers, and do a better job on the wings.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That Zeiss lens/Mitchell BNC was a better job on the wings.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ ‘Do a Better Job on the Wings’</title></entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.listenlater.net/?referrer=df" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wt5" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/12/listenlaternet_2" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.42521</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-12-30T00:56:13Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-30T00:56:14Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Turn articles into podcasts and listen on the go. Email any article, and it comes back as natural narration delivered straight to your private podcast feed. Whether it’s a long read or a quick blog post, enjoy it hands-free in any podcast app.</p>

<p>Sign up for free and start listening today. New users get $2 in credits to try it out, no commitment.</p>

<p>Now with many new voices, improved audio quality, and big bonus credits for frequent listeners.</p>

<p>Built by an indie developer. <a href="https://www.listenlater.net/?referrer=df">Try it at listenlater.net</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘ListenLater.net’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/12/listenlaternet_2">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] ListenLater.net</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/12/slop_is_slop" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wt4" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42520</id>
	<published>2025-12-30T00:45:42Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-30T02:00:17Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">The image Tim Cook posted on Twitter/X (and which the Apple TV account retweeted) is ugly and awkward. It either *is* AI-generated slop or it looks like AI-generated slop for no artistic or thematic reason whatsoever.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Some follow-up on <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/27/slopibus">the looks-like-AI-slop “painting”</a> Tim Cook <a href="https://x.com/tim_cook/status/2003873311504130173">posted</a> on Twitter/X on Christmas Eve to promote the <em>Pluribus</em> season finale. <a href="https://apple.slashdot.org/story/25/12/28/2048225/did-tim-cook-post-ai-slop-in-his-christmas-message-promoting-pluribus">Slashdot contacted the credited artist</a>, Keith Thomson, and quoted this interaction with him:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Slashdot: I just wanted to confirm that that’s your work... If it
is your work, can you say anything about what software you used
when creating the image?</p>

<p>Thomson: I’m unable to comment on specific client projects. In
general, I always draw and paint by hand and sometimes incorporate
standard digital tools.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That is a non-denial denial that he used generative AI to create the image.</p>

<p><a href="https://piunikaweb.com/2025/12/26/apple-tim-cook-christmas-art-ai-debate-keith-thomson/">Dwayne Cubbins at PiunikaWeb also contacted Keith Thomson and got this statement</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The artist, Keith Thomson, responded to my request for a comment,
stating that they “always draw by hand and sometimes incorporate
standard digital tools.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That is the same non-denial denial, because “standard digital tools” might include generative AI.</p>

<p><a href="https://spyglass.org/apples-pluribus-ai/">MG Siegler wonders</a> if it’s a deliberate allegory to some of the themes from the show, writing:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Keith Thomson using AI to produce art that’s like Keith Thomson’s
art because it’s trained on Keith Thomson’s art. How’s that for a
mindfuck?</p>

<p>I’m sure I’m reading wayyyy too much into that tweet (and
retweet), but given <a href="https://spyglass.org/pluribus-as-ai-allegory/">my previous post about <em>Pluribus</em> as an AI
allegory</a>, I think it’s sort of interesting to think about
in that context.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>MG’s posts have some spoilers re: <em>Pluribus</em>, so follow those links at your own risk. <em>Pluribus</em> is best enjoyed if you start watching it knowing as little about it as possible. But without spoiling anything, I think MG didn’t put enough <em>y</em>’s in the <em>wayyyy</em> in “I’m sure I’m reading wayyyy too much into that tweet”. There is no 3D chess being played here.</p>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/10/16/oatmeal-ai-art">I wrote just a few months ago</a> that I firmly believe generative AI tools not only can be, but already <em>are</em>, used to create genuine art. My problem with AI slop isn’t the <em>AI</em>, it’s the <em>slop</em>. Whatever “standard digital tools” Keith Thomson used to create <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/12/milk-and-cookies-tim-cook-keith-thomson.png">this</a>, the result is a turd.</p>

<p><em>Pluribus</em>, among numerous other merits, is a beautifully filmed show. <a href="https://www.keiththomsonart.com/">Thomson’s published paintings</a> are beautiful. The image Tim Cook posted on Twitter/X (and which the Apple TV account retweeted) is ugly and awkward. It either <em>is</em> AI-generated slop or it looks like AI-generated slop for no artistic or thematic reason whatsoever. Occam’s razor would suggest the conclusion that it simply is AI-generated slop, and Keith Thomson suckered Apple into paying for it.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Slop Is Slop</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Copilot Money</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://copilot.money/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=editorial&amp;utm_campaign=daringfireball_122225_web25&amp;utm_term=DARING" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wt3" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/28/copilot-money" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42519</id>
	<published>2025-12-28T19:55:51Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-30T19:02:59Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to Copilot Money for sponsoring last week at DF. Copilot is a personal finance app for the iPhone, iPad, and Mac, and they’ve always deeply believed in the value of embracing the design idioms and technical features of truly native apps for Apple platforms. Apple has noticed, awarding Copilot an <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/copilot-track-budget-money/id1447330651#productRatings">App Store Editor’s Choice</a> and featuring Copilot earlier this year on Apple Developer <a href="https://developer.apple.com/articles/copilot-money/">for their use of Swift Charts</a>.</p>

<p>Copilot’s big news this week is they’ve launched a new web app, bringing access to Copilot from any device, anywhere. It’s designed with all the attention to detail — and concern for privacy and security — as their native apps.</p>

<p>Copilot Money brings all your spending, budgets, investments, and net worth into one organized dashboard, with intelligent categorization and insights that help you stay on track without spreadsheets or app-hopping. Designed to feel calm and intuitive, Copilot makes it easy to understand your finances across all your devices.</p>

<p>Copilot first sponsored DF back in 2021. My wife and I started using it then to track our finances, and we haven’t looked back. Copilot Money isn’t just better than anything we’d used before, it absolutely blew everything else away. It’s easy to connect to your financial accounts, and once you do, you don’t need to spend any effort at all to enter transactions. Copilot just tracks it all automatically, and most importantly, presents it to you in clear, intuitive ways. It’s so good. I’m not saying that because they sponsored DF last week — I’m saying that as a happy paying customer for over four years now.</p>

<p>Copilot is offering DF readers two months free with code <strong>DARING</strong>, plus 26% off your first year for a limited time, <a href="https://copilot.money/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=editorial&amp;utm_campaign=daringfireball_122225_web25&amp;utm_term=DARING">available through this link</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Copilot Money’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/28/copilot-money">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>SoundSource 6</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://weblog.rogueamoeba.com/2025/12/04/soundsource-6-is-here/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wt2" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/28/soundsource-6" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42518</id>
	<published>2025-12-28T19:39:53Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-28T19:42:57Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Major update to Rogue Amoeba’s essential audio utility for the Mac. I’ve written about <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2020/08/09/soundsource-5">versions 5</a> <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2019/04/04/soundsource-4">and 4</a> previously, and everything I wrote then remains true. SoundSource remains the system-wide audio menu item that ought to be built into MacOS, giving you easy, intuitive control over every audio <em>device</em> (input and output), and easy, intuitive control over every <em>app</em> in which you play or record audio. That one seemingly-simple app does both those things is quite the remarkable design achievement. And aside from that usability, SoundSource remains an exemplar of UI design stylistically — distinctive and branded, while looking and feeling in every way like a standard Mac app.</p>

<p>New tentpole features in version 6 include fine-grained AirPlay support (e.g. route output from one app over AirPlay while leaving the rest of your system’s audio output local to your Mac), groups for output devices, and a new “Quick Configs” feature for saving and switching between, well, quick configurations. $49 for a new license, $25 to upgrade from a previous one.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘SoundSource 6’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/28/soundsource-6">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Tim Cook Posts AI Slop in Christmas Message on Twitter/X, Ostensibly to Promote ‘Pluribus’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://x.com/tim_cook/status/2003873311504130173" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wt1" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/27/slopibus" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42517</id>
	<published>2025-12-27T22:32:01Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-30T00:50:02Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The whole illustration is <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/12/milk-and-cookies-tim-cook-keith-thomson.png">just weird looking</a>, for one thing. As for sloppy details, the tree is in soft focus but somehow has a crisp edge, the carton is labeled both “Whole Milk” and “Lowfat Milk”, and the “Cow Fun Puzzle” maze is just goofily wrong. (I can’t recall ever seeing a puzzle of any kind on a milk carton, because they’re waxy and hard to write on. It’s like a conflation of milk cartons and cereal boxes.)</p>

<p>[<strong>Update, 29 December:</strong> Turns out, the “lowfat” milk carton props from the actual show <a href="https://x.com/lionesspike/status/1999675978650648889">have the same mistake</a> with “whole milk” printed above. That doesn’t change that it’s a stupid mistake to copy, or that there are a slew of other telltale signs that the image was generated by AI.]</p>

<p><a href="https://x.com/appletv/status/2003927243245203539">The Apple TV X account retweeted Cook</a>, and added a credit: “We thought you might like this festive artwork by Keith Thomson, made on MacBook Pro.”</p>

<p>Apple didn’t tag the “Keith Thomson” who supposedly created this artwork for them, but if it’s <a href="https://www.keiththomsonart.com/">this Keith Thomson</a>, Apple must have somehow fallen for a scam, because <em>that</em> Keith Thomson’s published paintings are wonderful. It does seem to be <a href="https://x.com/flyosity/status/2004010434844938312">that Keith Thomson’s signature</a> on Apple’s sloppy illustration, though. (I like a bunch of the paintings from that Keith Thomson, and love a few of them, but <a href="https://www.keiththomsonart.com/?itemId=id1bethwvp1f2b3fsm5np1sg5i9p50">this one in particular</a> feels like it was made just for me. It’s perfect.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Tim Cook Posts AI Slop in Christmas Message on Twitter/X, Ostensibly to Promote ‘Pluribus’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/27/slopibus">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>A 3D Tour Inside Trump’s Oval Office</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2025/12/23/us/trump-white-house-oval-office-gold-decor.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wt0" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/25/3d-tour-inside-trumps-oval-office" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42516</id>
	<published>2025-12-25T20:42:57Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-25T20:47:26Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Terrific interaction design from The New York Times. Not so terrific interior design from the president.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘A 3D Tour Inside Trump’s Oval Office’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/25/3d-tour-inside-trumps-oval-office">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Talk Show: ‘A Naughty Citizen’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2025/12/24/ep-437" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wsz" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/24/the-talk-show-437" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42515</id>
	<published>2025-12-25T01:31:53Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-25T01:32:13Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Special guest Quinn Nelson returns for a two-topic holiday spectacular: the iPad in the wake of iPadOS 26, and Apple’s executive changes as Tim Cook seemingly nears the end of his time as CEO.</p>

<p><audio
    src = "https://traffic.libsyn.com/secure/daringfireball/thetalkshow-437-quinn-nelson.mp3"
    controls
    preload = "none"
/></p>

<p><strong>Sponsored by:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://notion.com/talkshow">Notion</a>: The AI workspace where teams and AI agents get more done together.</li>
<li><a href="https://squarespace.com/talkshow">Squarespace</a>: Save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain using code <strong>talkshow</strong>.</li>
</ul>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Talk Show: ‘A Naughty Citizen’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/24/the-talk-show-437">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Quinn Nelson on Apple’s Executive Shuffling</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=e1E-yfcKdUw" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wsy" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/24/snazzy-apple-execs" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42514</id>
	<published>2025-12-24T16:51:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-25T01:27:19Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Another great video from Quinn Nelson. If your dumb cousin who knows you’re an Apple nerd approaches you on Christmas and says “<em>Hey what’s going on at Apple, Bloomberg says it’s rats leaving a sinking ship over there?</em>” and you don’t feel like explaining, just tell him to watch this video. Just the perfect explanation.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Quinn Nelson on Apple’s Executive Shuffling’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/24/snazzy-apple-execs">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘The iPad’s Software Problem Is Permanent’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bnYLpA5kAbo" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wsx" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/24/snazzy-ipad" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42513</id>
	<published>2025-12-24T16:45:39Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-24T16:45:40Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Smart, fair video from Quinn Nelson on the gap that remains between iPadOS 26 and desktop OSes. I think it’s right that there is a gap there. Apple has the Macintosh, the best desktop/workstation platform in the industry. So whatever the ideal is for iPadOS, it ought to fall short of MacOS in terms of technical capabilities, and instead offer a degree of simplicity and can’t-screw-it-up-edness that the Mac can’t match. But, some of the limitations that remain in iPadOS are just frustrating. iPadOS 26 is a huge leap forward, and I think sets the stage for Apple to address those limitations.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘The iPad’s Software Problem Is Permanent’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/24/snazzy-ipad">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>I Guess Nothing Is Foolproof</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/6/28/23777298/sony-ftc-microsoft-confidential-documents-marker-pen-scanner-oops" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wsw" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/23/i-guess-nothing-is-foolproof" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42512</id>
	<published>2025-12-24T02:16:45Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-24T02:17:15Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>From a 2023 report at The Verge:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Sony highly confidential information about its PlayStation
business has just been revealed by mistake. As part of the FTC v.
Microsoft hearing, Sony supplied a document from PlayStation chief
Jim Ryan that includes redacted details on the margins Sony shares
with publishers, its <em>Call of Duty</em> revenues, and even the cost of
developing some of its games.</p>

<p>It looks like someone redacted the documents with a black Sharpie — but when you scan them in, it’s easy to see some of the
redactions. Oops.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is sort of the exception that proves the rule <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/23/trump-doj-pdf-redactions">regarding redactions</a>. If you redact a document digitally, you have to know what to look for (e.g. metadata) to be certain you’ve redacted everything you want to redact. If you redact a document on paper, you can just look at it, with good light and sharp eyes.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘I Guess Nothing Is Foolproof’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/23/i-guess-nothing-is-foolproof">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Terrence Malick’s Disciples’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://yalereview.org/article/bilge-ebiri-terrence-malick" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wsv" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/23/terrence-malicks-disciples" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42511</id>
	<published>2025-12-23T23:19:57Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-23T23:19:58Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Splendid essay by Bilge Ebiri for The Yale Review, a meditation both on the films of Terrence Malick and several filmmakers he’s deeply influenced.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Terrence Malick’s Disciples’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/23/terrence-malicks-disciples">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The White House’s Belligerent, Ignorant Statement on the ‘60 Minutes’ CECOT Story</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://bsky.app/profile/brianstelter.bsky.social/post/3maoiadv5cc2u" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wsu" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/23/white-house-trump-are-removing" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42510</id>
	<published>2025-12-23T19:48:11Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-23T19:48:48Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>CNN media analyst Brian Stelter, on Bluesky:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>As “60 Minutes” finalized its “Inside CECOT” report last Thursday,
CBS sent the White House a request for comment. A WH spokesperson
responded within a few hours. The quote was not included in the
“60” report — so, judge for yourself whether it should have been
included or not.</p>

<p>WH spokesperson Abigail Jackson said “60 Minutes should spend
their time and energy amplifying the stories of Angel Parents,
whose innocent American children have tragically been murdered by
vicious illegal aliens that President Trump are removing from the
country.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Despite the fact that it doesn’t address a single aspect of the report, 60 Minutes should have included that statement, both to reveal the belligerent callousness of the administration, and to highlight the glaring grammatical error. In its way, the statement speaks volumes.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The White House’s Belligerent, Ignorant Statement on the ‘60 Minutes’ CECOT Story’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/23/white-house-trump-are-removing">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Amateur Codebreaker May Have Solved the Black Dahlia and Zodiac Killings</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2025-12-23/black-dahlia-zodiac-killings-connected-one-killer-theory" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wst" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/23/amateur-codebreaker-may-have-solved-the-black-dahlia-and-zodiac-killings" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42509</id>
	<published>2025-12-23T19:36:45Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-23T19:36:46Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Christopher Goffard, reporting for the Los Angeles Times (<a href="https://apple.news/AC4dB7O1XRLmMK5alJLphRg">News+ link</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>When police questioned Marvin Margolis following the murder of
Elizabeth Short — who became known as the Black Dahlia — he lied
about how well he had known her. The 22-year-old Short had been
found mutilated in a weedy lot in South Los Angeles, severed
neatly in half with what detectives thought was surgical skill.</p>

<p>Margolis was on the list of suspects. He was a sullen 21-year-old
premed student at USC, a shell-shocked World War II veteran who
had expressed an eagerness to practice surgery. He was “a
resentful individual who shows ample evidence of open aggression,”
a military psychiatrist had concluded.</p>

<p>At first, Margolis did not tell detectives that he had lived with
Short for 12 days at a Hollywood Boulevard apartment, three months
before her January 1947 murder. [...]</p>

<p>A generation later and hundreds of miles north, a killer who
called himself the Zodiac terrorized the San Francisco Bay Area
with five seemingly random murders from 1968 to 1969, taunting
police and media for years with letters and cryptograms.</p>

<p>The toughest to decipher was the letter he sent in April 1970 to
the San Francisco Chronicle, with the words “My name is —”
followed by a 13-character string of letters and symbols. It came
to be called the Z13 cipher, and its brevity has stymied
generations of PhDs and puzzle prodigies.</p>

<p>Alex Baber, a 50-year-old West Virginia man who dropped out of
high school and taught himself codebreaking, now says he has
cracked the Zodiac killer’s identity — and in the process solved
the Black Dahlia case as well.</p>

<p>“It’s irrefutable,” said Baber, obsessive, hyperfocused and
cocksure in manner, his memory encyclopedic and his speech a
firehose of dates, locations and surprising linkages.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>What a story. The circumstantial evidence pointing to Margolis seems pretty strong. What I can’t find is an explanation of Baber’s solution to the Z13 cypher. The “irrefutable” description hinges on that. There’s a new podcast, “<a href="https://killerinthecode.com/">Killer in the Code</a>”, from author Michael Connelly that details Baber’s supposed solution tying both cases to the same guy. All the publicity about this today stems from the debut of that podcast yesterday.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Amateur Codebreaker May Have Solved the Black Dahlia and Zodiac Killings’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/23/amateur-codebreaker-may-have-solved-the-black-dahlia-and-zodiac-killings">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Trump Justice Department Dopes Made the Rookiest of Rookie Mistakes Attempting to Redact Some Epstein-File PDFs</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.tiktok.com/@krassenstein/video/7586804140869700895" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wss" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/23/trump-doj-pdf-redactions" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42508</id>
	<published>2025-12-23T16:56:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-23T16:56:01Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Everyone who works with official PDFs in any capacity should know that if you start with a PDF containing text you want to redact, and you just place black bars atop that text and resave the file, the original text is all still there in the new PDF file. It’s the digital equivalent of putting sticky notes atop the text. You don’t even need to crack open the new PDF in a text (or hex) editor and hunt for the original text within non-human-readable PDF formatting code. You just open the PDF in Preview or Acrobat or any other PDF viewer, use the regular text selection cursor to select the text under the black bars, copy, and then paste into any other app. Everyone should know this but <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/16/meta-redactions">it keeps happening</a>. Now <a href="https://www.tiktok.com/@krassenstein/video/7586804140869700895">it’s happened</a> with the new batch of Epstein files released by the DOJ.</p>

<p>There are <em>major</em> differences between the Trump 1.0 and 2.0 administrations. In the Trump 1.0 administration, many of the most important officials were very competent men. One example would be then-Attorney General William Barr. Barr is contemptible, yes, but smart AF. When Barr’s DOJ released a redacted version of the Mueller Report, they printed the whole thing, made their redactions with actual ink, and then re-scanned every page <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2019/05/02/mueller-pdf-assessment">to generate a new PDF with absolutely no digital trace of the original PDF file</a>. There are ways to properly redact a PDF digitally, but going analog is foolproof.</p>

<p>The Trump 2.0 administration, in contrast, is staffed top to bottom with fools.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Trump Justice Department Dopes Made the Rookiest of Rookie Mistakes Attempting to Redact Some Epstein-File PDFs’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/23/trump-doj-pdf-redactions">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Bari Weiss Steps Onto the CBS News Glass Cliff of Doom’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/business/793525/bari-weiss-cbs-news-glass-cliff" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wsr" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/22/glass-cliff-of-doom" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42507</id>
	<published>2025-12-23T02:23:07Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-23T02:23:07Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Elizabeth Lopatto, back in October, after Bari Weiss was first named editor-in-chief of CBS News by David Ellison after his acquisition of Paramount:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This is the glass cliff to end all glass cliffs. You’re Marissa
Mayer at Yahoo without the Googler street cred. You’re Nancy Dubuc
at Vice without the string of hit TV shows. You’re Linda Yaccarino
at Twitter without the advertiser relationships. You have been
hired as a sop to a Trump administration that is actively hostile
to the <em>actual</em> free press, and you will be made to oversee wave
after wave of layoffs until you quit or get fired and the entire
news division is shut down in a final spasm of cost-cutting after
the next inescapable media merger.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The only thing Lopatto missed in her prescient piece is that Weiss might not last long enough to still be leading CBS News by the time Ellison gets to layoffs. It’s simply untenable for a partisan propagandist to be leading a legitimate news organization. Two months into the job and Weiss has already made a complete fool of herself. Her ham-fisted (but <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/22/60-minutes-cecot-samizdat">failed</a>) attempt to <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/22/weiss-60-minutes-cecot">censor a fair and well-reported piece</a> critical of the Trump administration’s deportation policies comes just one week after a televised town hall with Erika Kirk (widow of Charlie Kirk), which Weiss herself hosted, for which <a href="https://variety.com/2025/tv/news/advertisers-wary-cbs-news-bari-weiss-town-hall-1236608265/">the commercial spots were filled by direct marketing dietary supplements</a> and, I swear, Chia Pets.</p>

<p>It’s been an inauspicious two months on the job for Weiss, to say the least.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Bari Weiss Steps Onto the CBS News Glass Cliff of Doom’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/22/glass-cliff-of-doom">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://copilot.money/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=editorial&amp;utm_campaign=daringfireball_122225_web25&amp;utm_term=DARING" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wsq" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/12/copilot_money" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.42506</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-12-23T02:03:20Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-23T02:03:21Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Copilot Money — the Apple Editor’s Choice money tracker — is expanding beyond iPhone, iPad, and Mac with the launch of its new web app, available now.</p>

<p>Copilot Money brings all your spending, budgets, investments, and net worth into one organized dashboard, with intelligent categorization and insights that help you stay on track without spreadsheets or app-hopping. Designed to feel calm and intuitive, Copilot makes it easy to understand your finances across all your devices.</p>

<p>Copilot is offering DF readers two months free with code DARING, plus 26% off your first year for a limited time, <a href="https://copilot.money/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=editorial&amp;utm_campaign=daringfireball_122225_web25&amp;utm_term=DARING">available through this link</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Copilot Money’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/12/copilot_money">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] Copilot Money</title></entry><entry>
	<title>The ‘60 Minutes’ Report on CECOT That Bari Weiss Censored Is Now Internet Contraband</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/policy/849432/60-minutes-cecot-censored-canada-leak" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wsp" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/22/60-minutes-cecot-samizdat" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42505</id>
	<published>2025-12-23T00:55:46Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-23T02:26:47Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Elizabeth Lopatto, writing at The Verge:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>60 Minutes had already begun promoting the now-censored segment
online. Because it was pulled so late, it seems that CBS missed at
least one platform for distribution: Canada’s Global TV. Some
people used a VPN to watch it; at least one person recorded it,
distributing it through an iCloud account.</p>

<p>The segment, which has been reviewed by The Verge, is a little shy
of 14 minutes long. It features video of men, chained and bent
double, being “paraded in front of cameras, pushed onto buses, and
delivered to CECOT,” according to the segment’s narration. One
former detainee, who CBS met in Colombia, said he was told he was
“the living dead” at CECOT. After trying to seek asylum in the US,
he says he was detained by customs and held for 6 months before
being deported. He described horrific conditions at the prison,
saying he was beaten until he bled and that he was thrown into a
wall so hard he broke one of his teeth. He also described sexual
assault by the guards. Another interviewed former detainee
described what can only be called torture: being forced to kneel
for 24 hours, and being put in a dark room, where they were beaten
if they moved from the stress position. [...]</p>

<p>Anyway, best of luck to Weiss in playing DMCA whack-a-mole with
the video of the story. The segment lives as online samizdat now.
Thanks to Weiss’ censorship, it may very well wind up being the
most-talked-about CBS News story this year.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There are a bunch of copies on social media, but <a href="https://www.muellershewrote.com/p/watch-the-60-minutes-cecot-segment">most are video of the TV broadcast in Canada shot from an iPhone</a>. The Internet Archive, however, has <a href="https://archive.org/details/60minutes-cecotsegment">a clean copy that’s a direct screen recording</a>. Watch for yourself.</p>

<p>In addition to being the most-talked-about CBS News story of the year, it’ll almost certainly be the most-watched. But CBS will get none of the views or ad revenue. There’s no better way to make people want to watch something than to tell them they shouldn’t watch it. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Streisand_effect_examples">The Streisand effect</a> is very real.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The ‘60 Minutes’ Report on CECOT That Bari Weiss Censored Is Now Internet Contraband’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/22/60-minutes-cecot-samizdat">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>CBS News Chief Bari Weiss Pulls ‘60 Minutes’ Story on Trump’s CECOT Gulag in El Salvador</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.npr.org/2025/12/22/g-s1-103282/cbs-chief-bari-weiss-pulls-60-minutes-story" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wso" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/22/weiss-60-minutes-cecot" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42504</id>
	<published>2025-12-23T00:48:51Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-23T01:51:52Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>David Folkenflik, reporting for NPR:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Just a day and a half before it was set to be broadcast, new CBS
News Editor-in-Chief Bari Weiss pulled a planned 60 Minutes
investigative segment centering on allegations of abuses at an El
Salvador detention center where the Trump administration sent
hundreds of Venezuelan migrants last March.</p>

<p>Weiss told colleagues this weekend the piece — planned for Sunday
night’s show — could not run without an on-the-record comment
from an administration official. She pushed for 60 Minutes to
interview Stephen Miller, senior advisor to President Trump, or
someone of his stature. That’s according to two people with
knowledge of events at the network who spoke on condition of
anonymity, citing job security.</p>

<p>The correspondent on the story, Sharyn Alfonsi, condemned the
decision in an email to 60 Minutes colleagues on Sunday evening,
saying she believed it was “not an editorial decision, it is a
political one.” [...] Alfonsi wrote that she and her colleagues on
the story had sought comments and interviews from the Department
of Homeland Security, the White House and the State Department.</p>

<p>“Government silence is a statement, not a VETO,” Alfonsi wrote in
the email. “If the administration’s refusal to participate becomes
a valid reason to spike a story, we have effectively handed them a
‘kill switch’ for any reporting they find inconvenient.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It is not surprising in the least bit that Weiss tried to censor a jarring report on Trump’s illegal torture prison in El Salvador. It is, perhaps, slightly surprising how dumb this attempt is. Of course it’s a good principle of journalism to allow the other side of a story to comment or be interviewed. But the idea that the other side can just decline to participate and that means you can’t run the story is like fingers-in-your-ears “I can’t hear you!” playground nonsense. You run the story and say that they declined to comment.</p>

<p>It’s not just that Weiss kiboshed a solid piece of reporting from 60 Minutes. It’s that the editor-in-chief of CBS News is now on the record as saying that the entire staff of 60 Minutes wanted to run an unfair hit piece on the Trump administration. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/07/curse_not_the_king_cbs_colbert_trump">The decline of CBS</a> as an institution continues.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘CBS News Chief Bari Weiss Pulls ‘60 Minutes’ Story on Trump’s CECOT Gulag in El Salvador’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/22/weiss-60-minutes-cecot">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Finalist</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://finalist.works/df" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wsn" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/21/finalist" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42503</id>
	<published>2025-12-21T22:44:54Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-22T17:53:39Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to Finalist for sponsoring last week at Daring Fireball. Finalist is a remarkable, ambitious, and novel app for iPhone, iPad, and the Mac from indie developer Slaven Radic. It’s a planner — a digital take on traditional paper planners. Its motto: “Most productivity apps help you organize tasks. Finalist helps you finish them.”</p>

<p>One aspect of Finalist that makes it different from most to-do/task apps is that instead of setting due dates for tasks, you add tasks to specific days. This <em>really</em> resonates with me. With most apps in this domain, the top-level items are tasks, and tasks have (optional) due dates. With Finalist, the top-level items are <em>days</em>, and days have tasks and events. This might sound like I’m splitting semantic hairs but it gives Finalist a very different feel, one that’s more natural to me. If you’ve got unfinished items from yesterday, Finalist lets you move them all forward to today with one tap. Or, move some forward, and leave others behind. Or, just leave them all behind and move on. Up to you. I like that.</p>

<p>Finalist integrates with the system in all the ways you’d hope, including with the system calendar APIs and the Reminders app. So events in your system calendar and items from Reminders show up on your days in Finalist. Finalist lets you create events (calendar items), reminders (to-dos that are synced with Reminders), tasks (to-dos that exist only in Finalist), journal entries (like notes to yourself), and section headers if you have a busy day and need to group certain items together. Oh, and “habits”, too — recurring to-dos for habits you want to build or break. It sounds like a lot, but it all fits together neatly, covering the gamut of stuff you’d track in a daily paper planner. And everything in Finalist syncs between platforms (iPhone, iPad, Mac) with iCloud. There’s no account to create — it just uses iCloud, which is private and simple.</p>

<p>It’s not minimalist, but it’s not complicated. I’ve had a lot of fun learning to use Finalist just by exploring it. It’s thoughtful and intuitive. Like any civilized app, Finalist’s tags allow you to include spaces and capital letters in tag names, and don’t start with a stupid <code>#</code> character. And, design-wise, Finalist is very handsome — it offers customizable color themes and makes terrific use of the typographic features of the San Francisco system font.</p>

<p>Subscriptions cost $5/month or $30/year. A lifetime license costs just $60. It supports Family Sharing too.</p>

<p>I’m kind of blown away by how robust and thoughtful Finalist is. It’s not a web app with iOS and Mac clients. It’s a suite of native apps designed with care for Apple’s platforms. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2009/01/27/auteur-theory-of-design">Auteur software</a>, with a distinctive brand and vision, while remaining idiomatically native. Bravo to Slaven Radic. <a href="https://finalist.works/df">I strongly encourage you to check it out</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Finalist’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/21/finalist">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/12/apple_japan_msca_compliance" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wsm" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42502</id>
	<published>2025-12-20T22:43:34Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-21T21:16:51Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">It’s the practical results of legislation and regulation that matter, not the intentions. The Japanese government seemingly gets that, and acts accordingly.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/12/17/apple-announces-sweeping-app-store-and-iphone-changes-in-japan/">Chance Miller, reporting for 9to5Mac this week</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>To comply with the <a href="https://www.jftc.go.jp/file/MSCA_Guidelines_tentative_translation.pdf">Mobile Software Competition Act
(MSCA)</a>, Apple has <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2025/12/apple-announces-changes-to-ios-in-japan/">announced</a> a set of major
changes to the App Store and iPhone in Japan. The changes include
new app distribution options for developers and new alternative
payment rules for the App Store.</p>

<p>Apple announced the changes in a post on <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2025/12/apple-announces-changes-to-ios-in-japan/">Apple Newsroom
today</a> and on its <a href="https://developer.apple.com/support/app-distribution-in-japan/">developer website</a>. The
company says that Japan’s “MSCA’s requirements for alternative
app marketplaces and app payments open new avenues for malware,
fraud and scams, and privacy and security risks.” Nonetheless,
the company has collaborated with Japanese regulators to strike
as best a balance as possible to comply with the law and
protect users.</p>

<p>Broadly speaking, Apple says Japan’s MSCA does a better job of
balancing openness with security and user protection than the DMA
in the EU. For example, Apple does not have to support app
downloads from the web in Japan like it does under the DMA. Apple
retains ability to protect users from malware and other security
risks. This is especially true when it comes to protecting
children, as outlined below.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Developers in Japan can now offer their own payment processing within their apps and games, and offer link-outs to the web, but these options must be offered alongside the option to pay using Apple’s own in-app purchase system. Developers are allowed to offer lower prices in alternative payment methods. That strikes me as a decent, but not ideal balance. I think it’s fair for Apple to mandate that its own IAP be offered alongside any form of alternative payment within an app. But, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2024/01/coming_to_grips_with_apples_seemingly_unshakable_sense_of_app_store_entitlement">as I’ve long advocated</a>, links to the web — leaving the app for the system’s default browser — should be permitted without having to offer IAP too. But overall, where Japan landed is reasonable.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/12/17/japan-app-store-feature-updates/">From Juli Clover’s report on Apple’s MSCA compliance</a> at MacRumors:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Here’s a quick rundown of what’s changing as of today:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Side Button</strong> — Users in Japan will be able to change what
the side button does, and it will be able to activate
third-party voice assistants instead of Siri.</li>
<li><strong>Payment options</strong> — Developers can offer in-app purchases,
accept third-party payments in their apps, or direct users to a
website to make a purchase.</li>
<li><strong>Alternative app marketplaces</strong> — Apps can be distributed
through alternative app marketplaces instead of the App Store.
Users can set an alternative app marketplace as their default
marketplace instead of the App Store.</li>
<li><strong>Fee changes</strong> — New fees range from 5% to 26% depending on
distribution method and payment method.</li>
<li><strong>Browser choice</strong> — Users are prompted to select a default
browser at setup.</li>
<li><strong>Search engine choice</strong> — Users are prompted to choose a
default Search engine at setup.</li>
<li><strong>Navigation apps</strong> — Users in Japan can select a different
navigation app.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>Apple, <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2025/12/apple-announces-changes-to-ios-in-japan/">in its own announcement</a>, asserted its disagreement:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The MSCA’s requirements for alternative app marketplaces and app
payments open new avenues for malware, fraud and scams, and
privacy and security risks.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Of course they disagree with Japan’s MSCA on some of these things. If Apple didn’t disagree, they’d implement these features worldwide, not make them specific to Japan. And since they’re not applying these compliance measures worldwide, it’s correct for Apple to explain why.</p>

<p>But on the whole, this is a gentlemen’s disagreement — a polite agreement to disagree, with Apple making their case but then implementing the necessary measures for compliance without complaint. A polite explanation that they see some of these measures as introducing privacy and security risks is not a complaint per se.</p>

<p>This is of a piece with Apple’s longstanding respect for and relationship with the Japanese government. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2021/09/01/apple-anti-steering-relaxation">Back in 2021</a>, Apple changed the rules for “reader” apps in Japan to allow linking to websites, in order to comply with a ruling from the Japan Fair Trade Commission (JFTC). <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2021/09/japan-fair-trade-commission-closes-app-store-investigation/">In Apple’s announcement</a>, App Store chief Phil Schiller said the following:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Trust on the App Store is everything to us. The focus of the App
Store is always to create a safe and secure experience for users,
while helping them find and use great apps on the devices they
love,” said Phil Schiller, Apple Fellow who oversees the App
Store. “We have great respect for the Japan Fair Trade Commission
and appreciate the work we’ve done together, which will help
developers of reader apps make it easier for users to set up and
manage their apps and services, while protecting their privacy and
maintaining their trust.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You can search, but you won’t find quotes from Schiller, nor any other Apple representatives, speaking of their “great respect for” and appreciation of the work they’ve done together regarding the European Commission and the DMA. Chance Miller, in his above-linked report at 9to5Mac, <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/12/17/apple-announces-sweeping-app-store-and-iphone-changes-in-japan/">wrote</a>, “Apple says Japan’s MSCA does a better job of balancing openness with security and user protection than the DMA in the EU.” I was in the same briefing with Apple representatives as Miller, and I’d say Apple was more clear than that. In addition to seeing the MSCA as more aligned with Apple’s own priorities regarding privacy and security than the DMA, Apple repeatedly emphasized that the MSCA respected Apple’s intellectual property in ways that the DMA does not. Complying with the DMA is adversarial and obtuse. An Apple spokesperson confirmed that, in contrast with the DMA, the guidelines that accompany the MSCA provide more clarity on things like privacy, security, safety, and youth protection. (E.g. apps distributed outside the App Store in Japan still require age ratings. There’s no such requirement in the EU.)</p>

<p>Because of the DMA, Apple has delayed and outright withheld major features in the EU. iPhone Mirroring, one of Apple’s best new features in recent years, is still unavailable in the EU. Apple fully expects more features to be delayed or  withheld from the EU as time goes on. (With Apple Watch, they’ve now been forced to <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/11/apple_eu_dma_iphone_accessories_wi-fi_sync">remove (or perhaps better said, hamstring) a feature</a> that existed since Apple Watch debuted in 2015.) There have been no such feature delays (let alone withholdings) in Japan, nor does Apple expect there to be. The MSCA targets specific issues related to competition: how iOS apps are distributed, and how they are monetized. The MSCA choice-screen mandates for web browsers and search engines are clear, and don’t impose any odious or particularly confusing obstacles to users.<sup id="fnr1-2025-12-20"><a href="#fn1-2025-12-20">1</a></sup> Apple has made clear that they don’t agree with every aspect of the MSCA, but if you read between the lines, you can see a begrudging acknowledgement from Apple that the MSCA is well-intended, clear, and attempts to strike a balance between user experience, privacy, and security; respect for Apple’s intellectual property; and the anticompetitive aspects of Apple’s control over app distribution and payments that the law was written to address.</p>

<p>There is a mutual respect here between Apple and Japan that is completely absent between Apple and the European Commission. The MSCA, through its focus and clarity, is also more respectful of <em>users</em>. Users in Japan get the benefit of alternative app distribution (<a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/12/18/altstore-japan-launch/">AltStore is already there</a>) and alternative payment options with no trade-offs like delayed or withheld features. It’s hard to find anything aside from small nits to complain about in the MSCA. It arguably gives Japanese users a better, more robust iOS experience than what Apple offers to the rest of the world.<sup id="fnr2-2025-12-20"><a href="#fn2-2025-12-20">2</a></sup> The DMA, in contrast, has given EU users a worse iOS experience.</p>

<p>It’s the practical results of legislation and regulation that matter, not the intentions. The Japanese government seemingly gets that, and acts accordingly.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>

<li id="fn1-2025-12-20">
<p>I think these mandatory choice screens are rather stupid. They have not proven to be effective in Europe. They’re a feel-good mandate for bureaucrats. <em>Look, here’s a whole screen that we have forced upon every single user — visible, unavoidable proof that we have done something. Who cares whether most people do not know what a “default browser” is, or what a “search engine” is? We’ll make them pick anyway.</em> The end result is that nothing has changed in terms of browser or search engine market share. All they’ve really accomplished is to make first-run onboarding time slightly longer. But — so long as users aren’t forced to face these choice screens repeatedly, they’re only a minor irritation. They’re like a mandatory “you should wear a helmet” warning label on a skateboard. You peel it off and throw it away, and the percentage of skateboarders who wear a helmet remains unchanged.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-12-20"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>

<li id="fn2-2025-12-20">
<p>If we had alternative iOS app marketplaces in the US, like they do in the EU and now have in Japan, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/10/iceblock_removed_from_app_store">ICEBlock</a> might still be available for download. I say <em>might</em> because it’s impossible to know whether Apple would attempt to stymie ICEBlock at the notarization level, given <a href="https://mjtsai.com/blog/tag/notarization/">some of the cases</a> where they’ve <a href="https://mjtsai.com/blog/2024/06/14/utm-blocked-outside-app-store-via-notarization/">used notarization to block apps in the EU</a>. But if alternative app marketplaces were available in the US, ICEBlock certainly <em>should</em> still be available. Really, it should still be available in the App Store.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr2-2025-12-20"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
</li>

</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Apple Announces Changes to iOS in Japan for Compliance With the Mobile Software Competition Act</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Adobe Photoshop 1.0 Source Code</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://computerhistory.org/blog/adobe-photoshop-source-code/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wsl" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/19/photoshop-1-source-code" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42501</id>
	<published>2025-12-19T21:11:23Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-19T21:11:24Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The Computer History Museum:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Thomas Knoll, a PhD student in computer vision at the University
of Michigan, had written a program in 1987 to display and modify
digital images. His brother John, working at the movie visual
effects company Industrial Light &amp; Magic, found it useful for
editing photos, but it wasn’t intended to be a product. Thomas
said, “We developed it originally for our own personal use … it was
a lot a fun to do.”</p>

<p>Gradually the program, called “Display”, became more
sophisticated. In the summer of 1988 they realized that it indeed
could be a credible commercial product. They renamed it
“Photoshop” and began to search for a company to distribute it.
About 200 copies of version 0.87 were bundled by slide scanner
manufacturer Barneyscan as “Barneyscan XP”.</p>

<p>The fate of Photoshop was sealed when Adobe, encouraged by its art
director Russell Brown, decided to buy a license to distribute an
enhanced version of Photoshop. The deal was finalized in April
1989, and version 1.0 started shipping early in 1990.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Along with the 1.0 source code (mostly Pascal, with some 68K assembler), CHM has PDFs of Adobe’s excellent Photoshop 1.0 User Guide and Tutorial. CHM trustee Grady Booch, chief scientist for software engineering at IBM Research Almaden, on the source code:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>There are only a few comments in the version 1.0 source code, most
of which are associated with assembly language snippets. That
said, the lack of comments is simply not an issue. This code is so
literate, so easy to read, that comments might even have gotten in
the way. [...] This is the kind of code I aspire to write.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A little birdie who works at Adobe today told me, regarding the lack of comments, “Let me assure you, that trend continued for the next 35 years.”</p>

<p><a href="https://sixcolors.com/link/2025/12/adobe-photoshop-1-0-source-code-now-available/">Jason Snell, at Six Colors, notes</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The only shame is that this release doesn’t include the code from
the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MacApp">MacApp applications library</a>, which Photoshop used
and is owned by Apple. It would sure be nice if Apple made that
code available as well.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Says my little birdie, “Turns out Adobe got a perpetual license to MacApp and a heavily modified version of it is <em>still</em> the basis of the UI code. It is only recently starting to get replaced. Even more crazy is that parts of that MacApp code are running on iOS and Android and the web versions.”</p>

<p>Quite the legacy for what started as a personal project between two brothers.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Adobe Photoshop 1.0 Source Code’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/19/photoshop-1-source-code">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Still No Release Date for Apple TV’s ‘The Savant’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.apple.com/tv-pr/news/filters/2025/12/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wsk" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/19/still-no-release-date-for-apple-tvs-the-savant" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42500</id>
	<published>2025-12-19T20:51:32Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-23T00:07:03Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Apple TV’s press page has <a href="https://www.apple.com/tv-pr/news/filters/2025/12/">stories this month</a> announcing release dates and first looks for a bunch of shows: <em><a href="https://www.apple.com/tv-pr/news/2025/12/apple-tv-unveils-first-look-at-imperfect-women-new-limited-series-starring-and-executive-produced-by-emmy-award-winners-elisabeth-moss-and-kerry-washington-and-created-for-television-by-annie-weisman/">Imperfect Women</a></em> (a “psychological thriller”), <em><a href="https://www.apple.com/tv-pr/news/2025/12/apple-tv-sets-new-dramedy-beat-the-reaper-starring-and-executive-produced-by-will-poulter-and-adapted-for-television-by-sam-catlin/">Beat the Reaper</a></em> (“dramedy”), <a href="https://www.apple.com/tv-pr/news/2025/12/apple-tv-expands-the-monarch-legacy-of-monsters-universe-with-new-spin-off-series-starring-and-executive-produced-by-wyatt-russell-and-created-by-emmy-award-nominee-joby-harold/">a still-untitled <em>Monarch: Legacy of Monsters</em> spinoff</a>, <em><a href="https://www.apple.com/tv-pr/news/2025/12/apple-tv-unveils-a-first-look-at-widows-bay-new-series-starring-and-executive-produced-by-emmy-award-winner-matthew-rhys/">Widow’s Bay</a></em> (“blends genuine horror with character-driven comedy”), <a href="https://www.apple.com/tv-pr/news/2025/12/apple-tv-debuts-gripping-trailer-for-season-two-of-hijack-starring-and-executive-produced-by-sag-award-winner-and-emmy-award-nominee-idris-elba/">season 2 of the Idris Elba thriller <em>Hijack</em></a>, and <em><a href="https://www.apple.com/tv-pr/news/2025/12/apple-tv-reveals-a-first-look-at-margos-got-money-troubles-starring-elle-fanning-michelle-pfeiffer-nicole-kidman-nick-offerman-and-hailing-from-multiemmy-award-winner-david-e-kelley/">Margo’s Got Money Troubles</a></em>, a series from David E. Kelley starring Elle Fanning, Michelle Pfeiffer, Nicole Kidman, and Nick Offerman (good cast!).</p>

<p>But not a word about Jessica Chastain’s <em>The Savant</em>, which was <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/10/11/the-savant-apple-tv">supposed to debut in September</a>, was postponed after the Charlie Kirk shooting (<a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/DO_V2EyEZmj/">against Chastain’s wishes</a>), and has been in <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/10/23/will-the-savant-ever-air">“At a later date” scheduling limbo</a> ever since.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Still No Release Date for Apple TV’s ‘The Savant’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/19/still-no-release-date-for-apple-tvs-the-savant">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Anonymous Reddit Tipster Cracked the Brown University and MIT Shooting Cases</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/us-news/reddit-tipster-cracked-brown-university-mit-shooting-cases-rcna250036" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wsj" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/19/reddit-tipster-brown-shooting" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42499</id>
	<published>2025-12-19T19:31:44Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-19T19:31:45Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Alexander Smith and Claire Cardona, NBC News:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Online tipsters have had a mixed record when it comes to providing
information about mass casualty incidents. But Rhode Island
Attorney General Peter Neronha said this Reddit user “blew the
case wide open” after posting about their encounter on Saturday
with the suspect.</p>

<p>“I’m being dead serious,” wrote the Reddit user, identified in an
affidavit as “John,” three days after the shootings at Brown. “The
police need to look into a grey Nissan with Florida plates,
possibly a rental.”</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Anonymous Reddit Tipster Cracked the Brown University and MIT Shooting Cases’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/19/reddit-tipster-brown-shooting">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple Changes Processor Architectures More Often Than Its Identity Font</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/18/condensed-serif-typefaces" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wsi" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/19/apple-changes-processor-architectures-more-often-than-its-identity-font" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42498</id>
	<published>2025-12-19T19:23:15Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-20T01:19:31Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Yesterday I wrote:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>For the last 40 years Apple has only gone through three identity
fonts: Garamond → Myriad → San Francisco.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>DF reader Cameron McKay emailed to observe: “It strikes me that Apple changes CPU architectures (68K → PowerPC → Intel → ARM) more often than identity fonts. They’d sooner re-engineer their products’ deepest technical building blocks than change typefaces. I suspect that’s rare among tech companies.”</p>

<p>I wish I’d thought to mention that yesterday.</p>

<p>I’ll add that I suspect San Francisco might effectively be Apple’s “forever font”. Forever is a long time, but San Francisco, in its default appearance, strives for the sort of timelessness that Helvetica achieved. And <a href="https://developer.apple.com/fonts/">San Francisco offers</a> a wide (no pun intended) variety of widths and weights. <a href="https://www.apple.com/iphone-17-pro/">This is San Francisco</a>. <a href="https://www.apple.com/iphone-air/">This is too</a>. (Screenshots for posterity, when Apple’s website changes: <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/12/san-fran-example-iphone-17-pro.jpeg">iPhone 17 Pro</a> and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/12/san-fran-example-iphone-air.jpeg">iPhone Air</a>.)</p>

<p>I also suspect that Apple Silicon is Apple’s “forever architecture”.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Changes Processor Architectures More Often Than Its Identity Font’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/19/apple-changes-processor-architectures-more-often-than-its-identity-font">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/12/a_request_regarding_magic_link_sign-ins_and_apples_passwords_app" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wsh" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42497</id>
	<published>2025-12-19T18:52:37Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-20T01:30:30Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">I despise this design pattern, because it’s inherently slower than signing in using an email/password combination that was saved to my passwords app (which is Apple Passwords) and autofilled by my web browser. It’s not just a little slower but *a lot* slower.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>In Juli Clover’s <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/19/apples-262-os-updates">aforelinked</a> rundown of <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/guide/ios-26-2-features/">what’s new across the whole system in iOS 26.2</a>, I misunderstood this item regarding the Passwords app:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In the Settings section of the Passwords app, there’s an option to
manage websites where passwords are not saved when signing in.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This new setting is about managing sites that you have previously excluded from having a password entry saved. (In the Settings app, go to Apps → Passwords and then tap “Show Excluded Websites”.)</p>

<p>What I was <em>hoping</em> this was about is a feature Passwords doesn’t have, but that I want. There are many sites — and the trend seems to be accelerating — that do not use passwords (or passkeys) for signing in. Instead, they only support signing in via expiring “magic links” sent by email (or, sometimes, via text messages). To sign in with such a site, you enter your email address, hit a button, and the site emails you a fresh link that you need to follow to sign in.<sup id="fnr1-2025-12-19"><a href="#fn1-2025-12-19">1</a></sup> I despise this design pattern, because it’s inherently slower than signing in using an email/password combination that was saved to my passwords app and autofilled by my web browser. My password manager is Apple Passwords and my browser is Safari, but this is true for any good password manager and web browser. It’s not just a little slower but a <em>lot</em> slower to sign in with a “magic link”. It sometimes takes minutes for the  email to arrive, and even in the best case, it takes at least 15 seconds or so. Saved-password autofill, on the other hand, happens <em>instantly</em>.<sup id="fnr2-2025-12-19"><a href="#fn2-2025-12-19">2</a></sup></p>

<p>To make matters worse, when you create a new account using a “magic link”, <em>nothing</em> gets saved to Apple Passwords. I don’t have many email addresses in active use, but I do have several. Sometimes I don’t remember which one I used for my account on a certain site. It doesn’t get autofilled by Apple Passwords because account entries in Apple Passwords require a password. I was hoping the above feature mentioned by Clover was a way to address this — that you could now enable a setting to get Passwords to save just your email address for websites and services that exclusively use “magic links” for signing in. No dice. Apple Passwords team, if you’re reading this, please give this some thought. I can’t be the only person irritated by this.</p>

<p>One workaround I’ve used for a few sites with which I keep running into this situation (<a href="https://www.status.news/">Status</a>, I’m looking in your direction) is to manually create an entry in Apple Passwords for the site with the email address I used to subscribe, and a made-up single-character password. Apple Passwords won’t let you save an entry without something in the password field, and a single-character password is a visual clue to my future self why I did this. When I do this, I also put a note to myself in the notes field for the entry. And by using just a single character for the made-up password, I can tell what I did even when the password is displayed using bullets to obscure its actual characters. (<a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/12/apple-passwords-magic-link-example.png">Screenshot</a>.) If you feel like I do about “magic links”, the 🖕 emoji is a good “password” for such entries. </p>

<p>Once saved like this, my email address still doesn’t autofill on such sites in Safari, but the list of my saved email addresses in the suggestion list that appears when I click in the Email text field will have a “saved password” label next to the one for which I made this entry in Apple Passwords. This at least solves the problem when I can’t remember which address I used to create my account on a site.</p>

<p>Better would be a way for Passwords to ask if you want to save just your email address for sites with “magic link” sign-ins, and then for Safari to autocomplete that address just like it does for username/password combinations. I can see how this would be a tricky problem for Apple Passwords to solve in a way that makes clear to the user why certain entries do not have passwords, but it’s a problem worth solving.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>

<li id="fn1-2025-12-19">
<p>This design pattern is common with paywalled subscription content sites, like email newsletters, to cut down on password sharing. Let’s say someone pays $10/month for a subscription-based newsletter. If they can sign in using an email/password combination, they might be willing to share their email/password combination for that particular site with a few friends or colleagues, to give them access to the same paywalled content without paying for their own subscriptions. Same goes for sharing email/password combinations <a href="https://www.stuff.tv/features/netflix-password-sharing-what-to-do-about-the-steaming-services-crackdown/">for streaming services like Netflix</a>. Well, you can’t share a password if there is no password to share. If the only way to log in to a subscription-based account is via a magic link that expires within minutes, it’s a lot harder for person A to share their account with person B (let alone with persons C, D, E, and F — nor can persons B through F share the account with others, because they don’t have access to the email). Person B has to tell person A that they’re signing in again, then person A has to wait for the email to arrive, and then person B needs to wait for person A to copy and paste the “magic” link, and hope it arrives before it expires. This pattern adds a significant convenience cost to account sharing — but it also makes signing in more annoying for honest users who <em>aren’t</em> sharing their accounts.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-12-19"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>

<li id="fn2-2025-12-19">
<p>Proponents of “magic links” argue that they’re beneficial for technically befuddled users who don’t use a password manager. That’s a good argument for offering “magic links” as an <em>option</em>, but it’s not a good argument for making them the <em>exclusive</em> way to sign in to a site or service. Good password managers are built into modern OSes and web browsers. Those of us who use them should not be punished with a significantly worse experience just because some users do not. When “magic links” are offered as an <em>alternative</em> to a saved password or passkey, there’s a path for all users. When “magic links” are the <em>exclusive</em> method for signing in, all users get the slowest experience.</p>

<p>(And yes, <a href="https://passport.online/">Passport</a>, the subscription system behind <a href="https://dithering.fm/">Dithering</a> and the rest of Ben Thompson’s <a href="https://stratechery.com/stratechery-plus/">Stratechery media empire</a>, exclusively uses “magic links” for sign-in. I don’t like it, but, in Passports’s defense, once you’re signed in, Passport keeps you signed in for a very long time. Other CMSes tend to expire sign-ins far too quickly, which makes for a particularly frustrating experience with “magic links” because you need to keep using them every few weeks.)&nbsp;<a href="#fnr2-2025-12-19"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
</li>

</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ A Request Regarding ‘Magic Link’ Sign-Ins and Apple’s Passwords App</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Apple’s 26.2 OS Updates</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/19/apples-262-os-updates" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wsg" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/19/apples-262-os-updates" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42496</id>
	<published>2025-12-19T17:30:35Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-19T22:25:48Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Apple released all of its OS 26.2 updates a week ago today. A little unusual for Apple to release OS updates on a Friday, but I think they wanted to get these out before Christmas week. And I don’t think it was rushed — for iOS 26.2 at least, there were two release candidate builds during beta testing. I suspect Apple had hoped to release them earlier.</p>

<p>I know it seemed weird back at WWDC when Apple announced that they were re-numbering all their OS versions to start with 26. But now that the change has settled in for a few months, it seems very natural. It’s so easy now to remember that the current major version for each OS is 26. It’s also easier to talk about new features that span across OSes. And, in the future, when you see a reference to, say, iOS 26, you’ll know exactly when that version came out without having to think, because it’s right there in the version number itself.</p>

<p>A few other notes:</p>

<ul>
<li>Juli Clover at MacRumors, as usual, <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/guide/ios-26-2-features/">has a great rundown of what’s new across the whole system in iOS 26.2</a>, copiously illustrated with screenshots. Clover notes: “For pop-out menus that expand from a corner button, iOS 26.2 adds a quicker, bouncier animation that looks like the animation that Apple showed off at WWDC.” Popover menus are just one example, but this is actually true for a lot of Liquid Glass details. iOS 26.2 is the first release that visually delivers on most of what Apple showed in the WWDC keynote.</li>
<li><a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/12/12/apple-releases-ios-26-2-with-liquid-glass-tweaks-carplay-changes-much-more/">Zac Hall has another good iOS 26.2 rundown, also illustrated, at 9to5Mac</a>.</li>
<li>Clover also notes that iOS 26.2, for some users (including me), <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/12/12/ios-26-2-automatic-software-update/">defaults to a first-run screen that encourages you to turn on automatic OS updates</a>. Pay attention if you don’t want that.</li>
<li><a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/12/12/ipados-26-2-is-now-available-for-ipad-heres-everything-new/">A list of iPadOS 26.2 changes from Ryan Christoffel at 9to5Mac</a>.</li>
<li>Nadeem Sarwar at Digital Trends has a good piece showing <a href="https://www.digitaltrends.com/phones/ios-26-2-adds-an-airdrop-security-tool-that-you-shouldnt-ignore-on-your-iphone/">the new AirDrop code feature</a>, to allow AirDropping with people who aren’t in your contacts for up to 30 days.</li>
<li>MacOS 26.2 Tahoe changes, <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/12/12/apple-releases-macos-tahoe-26-2/">from MacRumors</a> and <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/12/12/macos-tahoe-26-2-now-available-whats-new/">from 9to5Mac</a>.</li>
<li>Clover on <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/12/12/apple-releases-tvos-26-2/">tvOS 26.2</a>, <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/12/12/apple-releases-watchos-26-2/">WatchOS 26.2</a>, and <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/12/12/apple-releases-visionos-26-2/">VisionOS 26.2</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://mjtsai.com/blog/2025/12/12/macos-26-2/">Michael Tsai’s roundup of links regarding MacOS 26.2 Tahoe</a>, and <a href="https://mjtsai.com/blog/2025/12/12/ios-26-2/">for iOS 26.2</a>.</li>
</ul>

<p>Lastly, iOS 26.2 seems to be the release that Apple is <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/phone-updates-used-to-be-annoying-the-latest-ios-is-awful/">starting to suggest as an upgrade</a> for users who hadn’t already installed it by choice. Be prepared for questions and complaints from non-nerd friends and family who’ve never even heard of “Liquid Glass”.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple’s 26.2 OS Updates’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/19/apples-262-os-updates">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple Is Adding More Ad Spots to App Store Results</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://ads.apple.com/app-store/help/ad-placements/0082-search-results#ntf" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wsf" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/19/apple-is-adding-more-ad-spots-to-app-store-results" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42495</id>
	<published>2025-12-19T15:43:30Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-19T16:21:15Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Apple, on its Apple Ads site:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Search is the way most people find and download apps on the App
Store, with nearly 65 percent of downloads happening directly
after a search. To help give advertisers more opportunities to
drive downloads from search results, Apple Ads will introduce
additional ads across search queries. You don’t need to change
your campaign in order to be eligible for any new positions. Your
ad will run in either the existing position — at the top of
search results — or further down in search results. If you have a
search results campaign running, your ad will be automatically
eligible for all available positions, but you can’t select or bid
for a particular one.</p>

<p>The ad format will be the same in any position, using a default
product page or custom product page, and an optional deep link.
You’ll be billed as usual based on your pricing model: cost per
tap or cost per install.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I have a bad feeling about this.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Is Adding More Ad Spots to App Store Results’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/19/apple-is-adding-more-ad-spots-to-app-store-results">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>ByteDance Signs Deal to Divest U.S. TikTok App</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.reuters.com/business/american-investor-consortium-acquire-tiktok-us-entity-axios-reports-2025-12-18/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wse" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/18/tiktok-us-divestiture" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42494</id>
	<published>2025-12-19T02:41:25Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-19T21:26:38Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>David Shepardson, reporting for Reuters:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>TikTok’s Chinese owner, ByteDance, said Thursday it signed binding agreements with three major investors to form a joint venture to operate TikTok’s U.S. app led by American and global investors in a bid to avoid a U.S. government ban, a significant step toward ending years of uncertainty.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The craziest aspect of this whole saga is that TikTok has been <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/01/briktok">operating illegally since Trump took office</a>. Not some sort of nitpicking technicality. The whole point of the <a href="https://daringfireball.net/search/pafaca">PAFACA act</a> was to ban TikTok in the US until and unless they were sold to American owners. No cloud service. No app store downloads. Trump directed the Justice Department simply not to enforce the law … and the biggest companies in the world just said <em>OK, sure</em>.</p>

<p>This just isn’t normal. There are always edge cases in the enforcement of any law. Political leanings affect priorities. <a href="https://thelawdictionary.org/article/weird-laws-by-state/">Old laws</a> are often ignored. But PAFACA was a brand new law, with bipartisan support, specifically written to target TikTok, and the Trump administration <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/01/npr_trump_tiktok">decided to just ignore it</a>. This wouldn’t happen anywhere in Europe or in, say, Japan. And it wouldn’t have happened under any previous US administration, Democrat or Republican. It’s not the biggest issue or worst wrongdoing of the Trump 2.0 administration, but it’s clearest indication of their disregard for the rule of law.</p>

<p><strong>See also:</strong> <a href="https://www.techmeme.com/251219/p16#a251219p16">Techmeme’s roundup</a> of news and commentary on the deal. (Karl Bode at Techdirt: “<a href="https://www.techdirt.com/2025/12/19/tiktok-deal-done-and-its-somehow-the-shittiest-possible-outcome-making-everything-worse/">It’s Somehow The Shittiest Possible Outcome, Making Everything Worse</a>”.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘ByteDance Signs Deal to Divest U.S. TikTok App’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/18/tiktok-us-divestiture">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Michael Bierut Told Us What He Really Thinks of ITC Garamond</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://designobserver.com/i-hate-itc-garamond/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wsd" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/18/bierut-itc-garamond" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42493</id>
	<published>2025-12-19T01:19:42Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-19T01:19:43Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Michael Bierut, “I Hate ITC Garamond”, for Design Observer back in 2004:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>ITC Garamond was designed in 1975 by Tony Stan for the
International Typeface Corporation. Okay, let’s stop right there.
I’ll admit it: the single phrase “designed in 1975 by Tony Stan”
conjures up a entire world for me, a world of leisure suits,
harvest gold refrigerators, and “Fly, Robin, Fly” by Silver
Convention on the eight-track. A world where font designers were
called “Tony” instead of “Tobias” or “Zuzana.” Is that the trouble
with ITC Garamond? That it’s dated?</p>

<p>Maybe. Typefaces seem to live in the world differently than other
designed objects. Take architecture, for example. As Paul
Goldberger writes in his new book on the rebuilding of lower
Manhattan, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/1400060176/designobserver-20/"><em>Up From Zero</em></a>, “There are many phases to the
relationships we have with buildings, and almost invariably they
come around to acceptance.” Typefaces, on the other hand, seem to
work the other way: they are enthusiastically embraced on arrival,
and then they wear out their welcome. Yet there are fonts from the
disco era that have been successively revived by new generations.
Think of <a href="http://corporate.gettyimages.com/marketing/Taxi03Gallery/en-us/index.html">Pump</a>, <a href="http://corporate.gettyimages.com/marketing/taxi/Taxi02Gallery/en-us/index.html">Aachen</a>, or even Tony Stan’s own
<a href="https://designobserver.com/unnecessary-revival/">American Typewriter.</a> But not ITC Garamond.</p>

<p>The most distinctive element of the typeface is its enormous
lower-case x-height. In theory this improves its legibility, but
only in the same way that dog poop’s creamy consistency in theory
should make it more edible.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I can’t explain how it is that I’ve never linked to this piece before.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Michael Bierut Told Us What He Really Thinks of ITC Garamond’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/18/bierut-itc-garamond">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Condensed Serif Typefaces, à la Apple Garamond, Are Back in Vogue</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.wsj.com/lifestyle/serif-instrument-skinny-font-e22b8054" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wsc" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/18/condensed-serif-typefaces" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42492</id>
	<published>2025-12-19T01:09:27Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-19T01:43:03Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Katie Deighton, reporting last month for The Wall Street Journal:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Henry Modisett wanted his employer to stand out. Competitors of
the artificial-intelligence firm Perplexity were embracing their
science-fiction roots with futuristic branding that felt cold to
him. So Modisett, the firm’s vice president of design, looked to
the past.</p>

<p>He plowed through graphic-design books and tomes of logos
featuring obscure examples like Hungarian oil companies from the
’80s. But he kept coming back to a slender, bookish typeface
famously used in Apple’s “Think Different” campaign. Modisett in
2023 began slipping a cousin of the font into Perplexity’s
software and marketing materials.</p>

<p>“It felt fresh,” he said.</p>

<p>Not anymore.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Apple’s custom variant of <a href="https://www.myfonts.com/collections/garamond-font-itc/">ITC Garamond</a> was called, appropriately enough, <a href="https://www.dafont.com/apple-garamond.font">Apple Garamond</a>. Apple adopted it in 1984 with the <a href="https://www.cultofmac.com/news/unboxing-vintage-macintosh-128k">introduction of the Macintosh</a>, and continued using it through the early years of the Aqua/iMac aesthetic. For me it evokes the pinnacle of the six-color era. For <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Typography_of_Apple_Inc.">Apple’s brand identity</a> and marketing materials, after Apple Garamond <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2005/06/shuffling">came Myriad</a> — which Apple commissioned custom variants of from Adobe. And then Myriad was succeeded by San Francisco, which I suspect still has many years ahead of it. For the last 40 years Apple has only gone through three identity fonts: Garamond → Myriad → San Francisco.</p>

<p>That this style of font is back in vogue is fun. It’s a good look. Friendly. Serious but not staid. The typeface a lot of these brands are using for this today is <a href="https://github.com/Instrument/instrument-serif">Instrument Serif</a>, which I don’t love. It’s not bad. But it’s not great. Apple Garamond was great.</p>

<p>(ITC Garamond — but not condensed — served, distinctively, as both the display and body text typeface for O’Reilly books <a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=programming+perl+book&amp;udm=2">in their heyday</a>. That typeface doesn’t look or feel Apple-like at all, nor does Apple Garamond look or feel O’Reilly-like at all.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Condensed Serif Typefaces, à la Apple Garamond, Are Back in Vogue’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/18/condensed-serif-typefaces">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>GCDB’s Guide to Gift Card Tampering Scams</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://gcdb.com.au/article/gift-card-scams/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wsb" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/18/gift-card-tampering-scams" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42491</id>
	<published>2025-12-18T19:44:36Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-18T23:02:07Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Gift Card Database (GCDB) has a guide to spotting tampered gift cards:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Whilst it may seem unusual, you should tear open this version of
Apple gift card before you purchase it so that you can inspect the
redemption code. Look for missing or scratched off characters (it
may be as subtle as changing an L to look like an I).</p>

<p>If you’re satisfied that the redemption code is legible and
undamaged, you can purchase the gift card by scanning the barcode
on the other side. If staff question your decision to open it
first, calmly explain why you were checking it and refer them to
the image above if it helps.</p>

<p>The one major downside of this precaution is that it requires you
to basically destroy the gift card packaging so if it’s intended
as a present you may just have to give them the smaller inner card
instead. Still, it’s better to be safe than sorry.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’m not bashful, but I’d be very uncomfortable opening gift cards before I purchased them. The whole point of this is that gift card scams are on the rise. If I saw someone opening gift cards in-store before purchasing them, I’d think they were shameless scammers. If you need to destroy the retail packaging for a gift card to feel certain it hasn’t been tampered with, the whole system seems fundamentally broken. (And just eyeballing the redemption code doesn’t prove it hasn’t been tampered with.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘GCDB’s Guide to Gift Card Tampering Scams’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/18/gift-card-tampering-scams">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Are Apple Gift Cards Safe to Redeem?</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tidbits.com/2025/12/17/compromised-apple-gift-card-leads-to-apple-account-lockout/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wsa" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/17/are-apple-gift-cards-safe-to-redeem" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42490</id>
	<published>2025-12-17T23:14:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-18T20:02:33Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>You will recall <a href="https://hey.paris/posts/appleid/">the Apple Account fiasco of Paris Buttfield-Addison</a>, whose entire iCloud account and library of iTunes and App Store media purchases were lost when his Apple Account was locked, seemingly after he attempted to redeem a tampered $500 Apple Gift Card that he purchased from a major retailer. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/13/buttfield-addison-apple-account">I wrote about it</a>, as did <a href="https://mjtsai.com/blog/2025/12/13/locked-out-of-apple-account-due-to-gift-card/">Michael Tsai</a>, <a href="https://pxlnv.com/linklog/apple-account-lockout/">Nick Heer</a>, <a href="https://appleinsider.com/articles/25/12/13/locked-out-how-a-gift-card-purchase-destroyed-an-apple-account">Malcom Owen at AppleInsider</a>, and <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/12/15/apple_dev_bad_gift_card_code/">Brandon Vigliarolo at The Register</a>. Buttfield-Addison has updated his post a few times, including a note that Executive Relations — Apple’s top-tier support SWAT team — was looking into the matter. To no avail, at least yet, alas.</p>

<p><a href="https://tidbits.com/2025/12/17/compromised-apple-gift-card-leads-to-apple-account-lockout/">Adam Engst, writing at TidBITS today</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>There is one way the Apple community could exert some leverage
over Apple. Since innocently redeeming a compromised Apple Gift
Card can have serious negative consequences, we should all avoid
buying Apple Gift Cards and spread the word as widely as possible
that they could essentially be malware. Sure, most Apple Gift
Cards are probably safe, but do you really want to be the person
who gives a close friend or beloved grandchild a compromised card
that locks their Apple Account? And if someone gives you one,
would you risk redeeming it? It’s digital Russian roulette.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I suspect that one part of Buttfield-Addison’s fiasco is the fact that his seemingly problematic gift card was for $500, not a typical amount like $25, but that’s just a suspicion on my part. We don’t know — because key to the Kafka-esque nature of the whole nightmare is that his account cancellation was a black box. Not only has Apple not yet restored his deactivated Apple Account, at no point in the process have they explained why it was deactivated in the first place. We’re left to guess that it was related to the tampered gift card and that the relatively high value of the card in question was related. $500 is a higher value than average for an Apple gift card, but that amount is less than the average price for a single iPhone. Apple itself <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/12/apple-gift-card-2001-dollars.png">sets a limit of $2,000</a> on <a href="https://www.apple.com/shop/buy-giftcard/giftcard">gift cards in the US</a>, so $500 shouldn’t be considered an inherently suspicious amount. </p>

<p>The whole thing <em>does</em> make me nervous about redeeming, or giving, Apple gift cards. Scams in general seem to be getting more sophisticated. Buttfield-Addison says he bought the card directly from “a major brick-and-mortar retailer (Australians, think Woolworths scale; Americans, think Walmart scale)”. Until we get some clarity on this I feel like I’d only redeem Apple gift cards at an Apple retail store, for purchases <em>not</em> tied to my Apple Accounts. (I’ve <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/02/11/about-migrating-apple-account-purchases-between-accounts">still</a> got two — one for iCloud, one for media purchases.)</p>

<p>In addition to the uncertainty this leaves us with regarding the redemption of Apple gift cards, I have to wonder what the hell happens to these Apple Accounts that are deactivated for suspected fraud. You would think that once escalated high enough in Apple’s customer support system, someone at Apple could just flip a switch and re-activate the account. The fact that Buttfield-Addison’s account has not yet been restored, despite the publicity and apparent escalation to Executive Relations, makes me think it <em>can’t</em> be restored. I don’t know how that can be, but it sure seems like that’s the case. Darth Vader’s “And no disintegrations” admonition ought to be in effect for something like this. I have the sinking feeling that the best Apple is able to do is something seemingly ridiculous, like refund Buttfield-Addison for every purchase he ever made on the account and tell him to start over with a new one.</p>

<p>My other question: Were any humans involved in the decision to deactivate (disintegrate?) his account, or was it determined purely by some sort of fraud detection algorithm?</p>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> Very shortly after I posted the above, Buttfield-Addison <a href="https://hey.paris/posts/appleid/">posted an update</a> that his account was successfully restored by the ninja on Apple’s Executive Relations team assigned to his case. That’s great. But that still leaves the question of how safe Apple gift cards are to redeem on one’s Apple Account. It also leaves the question of how this happened in the first place, and why it took the better part of a week to resolve.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Are Apple Gift Cards Safe to Redeem?’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/17/are-apple-gift-cards-safe-to-redeem">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Story Behind Windows 3.1’s ‘Hot Dog Stand’ UI Color Scheme (Which Isn’t Much of a Story at All)</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.pcgamer.com/software/windows/windows-3-1-included-a-red-and-yellow-hot-dog-stand-color-scheme-so-garish-it-was-long-assumed-to-be-a-joke-so-i-tracked-down-the-original-designer-to-get-the-true-story/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ws9" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/17/windows-3-1-hot-dog-stand" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42489</id>
	<published>2025-12-17T22:25:25Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-17T22:25:36Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Wes Fenlon, writing for PC Gamer:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Did Windows 3.1 really ship with a garish color scheme that was
<em>dared</em> into being? That was a story I needed to hear, so I went
digging for the credits of the Microsoft employees who worked on
the user interface back then and found my way to <a href="https://www.virginiahowlett.com/about">Virginia
Howlett</a>, who joined Microsoft in 1985 as the company’s
first interface designer, and worked there up through the launch
of Windows 95.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Howlett:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I have been mystified about why that particular theme causes so
much comment in the media. Maybe it’s partly the catchy name.
(Never underestimate the power of a good brand name!)</p>

<p>I do remember some discussion about whether we should include it,
and some snarky laughter. But it was not intended as a joke. It
was not inspired by any hot dog stands, and it was not included as
an example of a bad interface — although it was one. It was just
a garish choice, in case somebody out there liked ugly bright red
and yellow.</p>

<p>The ‘Fluorescent’ theme was also pretty ugly, but it didn’t have a
catchy name, so I’ve never heard anything about it.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I remember this color theme, because I had to use Windows 3.1 at a few jobs in the 1990s, and anyone who used it remembers “Hot Dog Stand”. Howlett’s explanation is exactly what I always thought. It wasn’t for accessibility. It wasn’t a dare or a joke. It was something they knew was ugly and they shipped it anyway in case people wanted an ugly UI.</p>

<p>That’s Microsoft.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Story Behind Windows 3.1’s ‘Hot Dog Stand’ UI Color Scheme (Which Isn’t Much of a Story at All)’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/17/windows-3-1-hot-dog-stand">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>James Cameron’s Instructions to Theater Projectionists Regarding ‘Avatar 3: Fire and Ash’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://x.com/avatar3news/status/2000390070256418915" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ws8" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/16/cameron-avatar-3-letter" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42488</id>
	<published>2025-12-17T00:05:28Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-17T22:31:33Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The letter is typeset in Papyrus, the typeface for which James Cameron’s affection inspired not <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jVhlJNJopOQ">one</a> but <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Q8PdffUfoF0">two</a> classic SNL shorts starring Ryan Gosling — which <a href="https://www.tiktok.com/@bbcradio1/video/7179200551207357702?lang=en">Cameron has a good sense of humor about</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://aphelis.net/actual-copy-terrence-malicks-notice-projectionists-tree-life/">Terrence Malick’s letter</a> accompanying <em>Tree of Life</em> in 2011 was plainly and humbly set in Helvetica. <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/movies/comments/7gv7hb/david_lynchs_memos_to_projectionists_for/">David Lynch’s accompanying <em>Mulholland Drive</em></a> was also in Helvetica, but in a very Lynchian way. And then there is Stanley Kubrick, <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/StanleyKubrick/comments/1n5spa8/stanley_kubricks_letter_to_projectionists/">whose letter to projectionists that accompanied <em>Barry Lyndon</em></a> was typeset in Futura — quite the feat in 1975. (It was almost certainly <a href="https://fontsinuse.com/typefaces/148003/mid-century">IBM’s Mid-Century</a> typeface, a <a href="https://typecast.munk.org/2011/04/25/1964-nomda-blue-book-ibm-font-styles/">beautiful adaptation</a> of Futura <a href="https://archive.org/details/ibm-executive-typefaces">for their Executive line of typewriters</a>.) Cool custom letterhead on Kubrick’s as well.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘James Cameron’s Instructions to Theater Projectionists Regarding ‘Avatar 3: Fire and Ash’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/16/cameron-avatar-3-letter">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Typefaces for Dyslexia</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://adrianroselli.com/2015/03/typefaces-for-dyslexia.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ws7" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/16/debunking-special-typefaces-for-dyslexia" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42487</id>
	<published>2025-12-16T19:58:17Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-16T19:58:17Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>I dare say this post from Adrian Roselli — first published in 2015 and updated 16 times (and counting) since — is <em>the</em> definitive debunking of the pseudoscience claims regarding deliberately ugly fonts being somehow beneficial to readers with dyslexia.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Typefaces for Dyslexia’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/16/debunking-special-typefaces-for-dyslexia">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Zara Picken’s ‘Modern Illustration’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.modernillustration.org/?ref=simplebits.com" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ws6" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/16/modern-illustration" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42486</id>
	<published>2025-12-16T19:39:44Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-16T19:51:17Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<blockquote>
  <p>Modern Illustration is a project by illustrator <a href="https://www.zarapicken.com/">Zara Picken</a>,
featuring print artefacts from her extensive personal collection.
Her aim is to preserve and document outstanding examples of
mid-20th century commercial art, creating an accessible resource
for understanding illustration history.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Glorious collection of mid-century illustrations and graphic design. Also <a href="https://www.instagram.com/ephemeramablog">a good follow on Instagram</a>. (<a href="https://simplebits.com/notebook/studio-notes-60/">Via Dan Cederholm</a>.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Zara Picken’s ‘Modern Illustration’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/16/modern-illustration">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/12/apple_tv_new_fanfare" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/ws5" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42485</id>
	<published>2025-12-16T19:08:56Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-16T21:34:13Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Netflix’s “tadum” is so iconic that it’s the name of their company blog. HBO’s static + chanted om is the OG standard-setter. I suspect the new Apple TV fanfare will be seen in that class. The old one was not.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Tim Nudd, <a href="https://adage.com/creativity/work/aa-apple-tv-mnemonic-visual-branding/">writing at Ad Age a few weeks ago</a> (paywalled, alas):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>As we <a href="https://adage.com/creativity/campaigns-commercials/aa-creative-ads-today-apple-kraft-mac-cheese-lexus-philadelphia-cream-cheese/">mentioned in roundup</a> yesterday, Finneas (aka, Finneas
O’Connell) has developed a new sonic logo for Apple TV, the
streaming service previously known as Apple TV+. However, the
rebrand, created with Apple agency TBWA\Media Arts Lab, goes
beyond the audio mnemonics to include a striking new visual look
as well.</p>

<p>The visual branding centers on layers of shifting colored light, a
metaphor for the range of genres and emotions that Apple TV has
cultivated since its 2019 debut.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I held off on posting about this new Apple TV fanfare (a.k.a. <em>sonic logo</em>, a.k.a. <em>mnemonic</em> ) until I’d experienced it a few times, and after a few weeks, watching a bunch of episodes from a few Apple TV series — <em><a href="https://tv.apple.com/us/show/mr-scorsese/umc.cmc.4a06j5lm5pxny9nx505zo5g0y">Mr. Scorsese</a></em>, a 5-star five-part documentary by Rebecca Miller, absolutely riveting; <em><a href="https://tv.apple.com/us/show/pluribus/umc.cmc.37axgovs2yozlyh3c2cmwzlza">Pluribus</a></em>, Vince Gilligan’s excellent new the-less-you-know-about-it-before-you-start-watching-<a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/21/pluribus-carol-sturka-ama">the-better</a> series starring Rhea Seehorn; and <em><a href="https://tv.apple.com/us/show/the-morning-show/umc.cmc.25tn3v8ku4b39tr6ccgb8nl6m">The Morning Show</a></em> season 4, a series that’s skirting <em>just</em> above the good-enough-to-keep-watching line for me — I’m willing to render a verdict.</p>

<p>I love it.</p>

<p>The old one was not bad. But “not bad” should never be good enough for Apple. I can’t find anyone from Apple stating so explicitly, but it seems pretty obvious that the piano chord accompanying the old fanfare was meant to evoke the Macintosh startup chime. That’s a neat idea. And no one is more a fan of the Macintosh than me. I’d argue that the Mac remains <em>the</em> definitive Apple product, the one that best exemplifies everything the company does and should stand for. So harking back to the Macintosh was an interesting idea for the Apple TV fanfare/sonic logo/mnemonic.</p>

<p>But: it just wasn’t great. What makes that chord great for a computer booting up doesn’t make it great for a cinematic sonic logo. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GV3HUDMQ-F8">Netflix’s “tudum”</a> is so iconic that it’s <a href="https://www.netflix.com/tudum">the name of their company blog</a>. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=O08PQRA6MLo">HBO’s static + chanted om</a> is the OG standard-setter. I suspect the new Apple TV fanfare will be seen in that class. The old one was not.</p>

<p>The new one feels like a branding stroke unto itself. Sonically, it doesn’t evoke anything else. It just sounds rich and cool. Visually, with its rotating prism effect, it does evoke the classic six-color Apple logo. Thus, despite moving away from a sonic callback to the Macintosh, the overall effect feels <em>more</em> rooted to Apple’s on-the-cusp-of-a-half-century history. The change makes Apple TV original content feel more like a part of Apple, less like a possible passing fancy (which is what <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/10/17/belloni-cue-interview">many in Hollywood fear</a>).</p>

<p>That prism effect was created practically. From <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/tbwamedia-arts-lab_at-mal-we-partnered-with-apple-tv-to-reimagine-activity-7391899271060582400-8OW9/">a LinkedIn post from Apple’s longtime agency partner TBWA Media Arts Lab</a> (no clue why they posted this on LinkedIn, of all places):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Built from real glass and captured entirely in camera, the new
identity explores reflection, color, and light to express the
cinematic spirit at the heart of Apple TV. Every shimmer was made
for real, no CG shortcuts, a nod to Apple’s belief that craft
should be felt, not faked.</p>

<p>The work spans the entire platform, from a sharp five-second show
open to a full-length cinematic version for films, paired with a
new sonic logo composed by Oscar winner Finneas and a custom
typeface, SF TV, developed with Apple’s design team.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>They include a very short video showing behind the scenes of its creation. It matters not to me that they photographed this practically, rather than via computer-generated graphics, but the bottom line is that it looks cool, timeless, and Apple-y.</p>

<p><a href="https://variety.com/2025/music/news/finneas-discusses-apple-tv-originals-mnemonic-intro-1236568433/">Chris Willman at Variety has an interview with Finneas</a> (O’Connell) regarding the music:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>Mnemonic</em>, Finneas says, “is sort of a beautiful word for a
logo” accompanied by sound. “The things that I think of as real
classic mnemonics are NBC — you can hear that in your head — or
HBO has its static.” Finneas is well aware of how modern
streaming consumption might make this especially ubiquitous,
household by household. “If you’re binge-ing the whole season of
<em>Ted Lasso</em> or <em>Severance</em> or <em>Disclaimer</em>” (the last of those
being the limited series that he composed the score for himself),
“you’re going to hear the mnemonic 10 times in one day. So it’s
gotta be something that’s like the bite of ginger between rolls
or something, you know?”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>See and hear for yourself. Here’s the old Apple TV mnemonic:</p>

<p><video
    width = 500
    controls
    src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/12/Apple-TV-Plus-Mnemonic-Old.mp4">
</video></p>

<p>Here’s the new 5-second version, shown at the beginning of each episode of Apple TV original series:</p>

<p><video
    width = 500
    controls
    src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/12/Apple-TV-Mnemonic-New-5s.mp4">
</video></p>

<p>And here’s the full 12-second version, shown before Apple Original Films:</p>

<p><video
    width = 500
    controls
    src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/12/Apple-TV-Mnemonic-New-12s.mp4">
</video></p>

<p>Bravo.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Apple TV’s New Fanfare</title></entry><entry>
	<title>‘A Brief History of Times New Roman’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://typographyforlawyers.com/a-brief-history-of-times-new-roman.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ws3" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/15/a-brief-history-of-timesnewroman" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42483</id>
	<published>2025-12-16T01:03:17Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-16T05:28:11Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/10/butterick-times-new-roman">One more</a> from Matthew Butterick, from his <em>Typography for Lawyers</em>, and a good <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/15/the-scourge-of-arial">pairing</a> with Mark Simonson’s “<a href="https://www.marksimonson.com/notebook/view/the-scourge-of-arial/">The Scourge of Arial</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Yet it’s an open question whether its longevity is attributable to
its quality or merely its ubiquity. Helvetica still inspires
enough affection to have been the subject of a 2007 documentary
feature. Times New Roman, meanwhile, has not attracted similar
acts of homage.</p>

<p>Why not? Fame has a dark side. When Times New Roman appears in a
book, document, or advertisement, it connotes apathy. It says, “I
submitted to the font of least resistance.” Times New Roman is not
a font choice so much as the absence of a font choice, like the
blackness of deep space is not a color. To look at Times New Roman
is to gaze into the void.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>As Simonson mentions in “The Scourge of Arial”, regarding Helvetica’s enduring popularity:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>As it spread into the mainstream in the ’70s, many designers tired
of it and moved on to other typographic fashions, but by then it
had become a staple of everyday design and printing. So in the
early ’80s when Adobe developed the PostScript page description
language, it was no surprise that they chose Helvetica as one of
the basic four fonts to be included with every PostScript
interpreter they licensed (along with Times, Courier, and Symbol).
Adobe licensed its fonts from the original foundries,
demonstrating their respect and appreciation for the integrity of
type, type foundries and designers. They perhaps realized that if
they had used knock-offs of popular typefaces, the professional
graphic arts industry — a key market — would not accept them.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>To my mind, Helvetica, Times, and Courier are <em>the</em> three canonical “default” fonts. One modern sans, one modern serif, and one for “typewriter”/code. (When I see Courier in print, at display sizes, my mind immediately wonders if the printer was missing the font that the designer specified in the document file.)</p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Symbol_(typeface)">The Symbol font</a> is a different story. It existed and was included with PostScript as one of just four defaults because the 8-bit character encodings of the time only had space for 255 characters. You needed a special font like Symbol to access “exotic” characters like Greek letters, math symbols (e.g. × or ÷), or arrows (↑ ↓ ← →). So there were really only three regular “fonts”, for prose, included with PostScript: Helvetica, Courier, and Times.</p>

<p>Courier and Times were eventually superseded in popular use by rivals that Microsoft licensed for inclusion in Windows: Courier New and Times New Roman, respectively. Times was from Linotype, Times New Roman from Monotype. Both versions of Times are legitimate digital interpretations of the 1929 hot metal design of Times Roman, and <a href="https://creativepro.com/times-roman-vs-times-new-roman/">their differences are minor</a>. Courier New, on the other hand, is <a href="http://www.identifont.com/differences?first=Courier+New&amp;second=Courier">so ugly</a> — anemically thin and weak — that it hurts my teeth whenever I encounter it.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘A Brief History of Times New Roman’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/15/a-brief-history-of-timesnewroman">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘The Scourge of Arial’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.marksimonson.com/notebook/view/the-scourge-of-arial/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ws1" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/15/the-scourge-of-arial" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42481</id>
	<published>2025-12-16T00:05:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-16T00:24:26Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Typographer Mark Simonson, all the way back in 2001:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Arial is everywhere. If you don’t know what it is, you don’t
use a modern personal computer. Arial is a font that is
familiar to anyone who uses Microsoft products, whether on a PC
or a Mac. It has spread like a virus through the typographic
landscape and illustrates the pervasiveness of Microsoft’s
influence in the world.</p>

<p>Arial’s ubiquity is not due to its beauty. It’s actually rather
homely. Not that homeliness is necessarily a bad thing for a
typeface. With typefaces, character and history are just as
important. Arial, however, has a rather dubious history and not
much character. In fact, Arial is little more than a shameless
impostor.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is <em>the</em> exegesis on Arial. There’s also an exemplary illustrated sidebar, “<a href="https://www.marksimonson.com/notebook/view/how-to-spot-arial/">How to Spot Arial</a>”, which shows in detail how to tell the fucking bastard from Helvetica. If you want to be like me, cursed to notice Arial each time it appears in life, study that, and take note how every single way that it’s different from Helvetica is in the direction of making it uglier.</p>

<p>I’ve <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2007/07/iphone_fonts">referenced</a> “The Scourge of Arial” a few times over the years here at DF, but the <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/10/state-department-times-new-roman">recent</a> <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/12/full_text_of_marco_rubio_state_dept_directive_times_new_roman">contretemps</a> over Times New Roman’s return at the US State Department has the general topic of “default fonts” at top of mind. For me, at least.</p>

<p>One of the old posts in which I linked to “The Scourge of Arial” was this gem from September 2007: “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2007/09/hacking_the_iphone_notes_app">Hacking the iPhone Notes App for the Admittedly Nit-Picky Purpose of Changing the Text Font to Helvetica</a>”. This was so early in the iPhone era — just three months after the original iPhone shipped — that we were calling its operating system “mobile OS X”, and none of it was protected in any way, so you could do what I did and delete the Marker Felt font (<a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2007/07/11/marker-felt">Merlin Mann</a>: “Comic Sans with a shave and a breath mint”) and then use a hex editor to modify the Mobile Notes app so it would fall back to Helvetica instead of cursed Arial after Marker Felt was deleted. Good times.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘The Scourge of Arial’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/15/the-scourge-of-arial">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>A Note on Current SMS Marketing Practices</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/15/note-on-sms-marketing" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ws2" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/15/note-on-sms-marketing" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42482</id>
	<published>2025-12-16T00:02:08Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-20T01:08:36Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Back on November 28, I bought a new cap from <a href="https://www.neweracap.com/pages/our-story">New Era</a>’s web store. They offered a discount of some sort if I gave them a phone number and permitted them to send me marketing messages. That got me curious about what they’d do with my number, and it was a 50-some-dollar cap, so I took the discount and gave them my Google Voice number. That was 17 days ago. They sent me 19 SMS marketing messages since then, before I’d seen enough today and called it quits on this experiment. (Or called “STOP”, perhaps, which was the magic word to opt out.) They didn’t send a text every day, and on some days, they sent more than one. But the overall effect was relentlessly annoying.</p>

<p>I’m sure some of the people who sign up for these texts in exchange for a discount code wind up clicking at least one of the offers sent via SMS and buying more stuff, and the marketing team running this points to those sales as proof that it “works”. You can measure that. It shows up as a number. Some people in business only like arguments that can be backed by numbers. 3 is more than 2. That is indeed a fact.</p>

<p>But there are an <em>infinite</em> number of things in life that cannot be assigned numeric values. Many of these things matter too. Like the fact that in my mind, after experiencing this, the New Era company smells like a sweaty hustler in a cheap polyester suit. If their brand were a man, I’d check my pants pocket for my wallet after interacting with him.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘A Note on Current SMS Marketing Practices’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/15/note-on-sms-marketing">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Disney, Immediately After Partnering With OpenAI for Sora, Sends Google a Cease-and-Desist Letter Accusing Them of Copyright Infringement on ‘Massive Scale’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://variety.com/2025/digital/news/disney-google-ai-copyright-infringement-cease-and-desist-letter-1236606429/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ws0" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/15/disney-google-cease-and-desist" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42480</id>
	<published>2025-12-15T21:13:40Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-15T21:14:10Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Todd Spangler, reporting last week for Variety:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>As Disney has <a href="https://variety.com/2025/digital/news/disney-openai-deal-200-characters-to-sora-video-invests-1-billion-1236606401/">gone into business with OpenAI</a>, the Mouse
House is accusing Google of copyright infringement on a “massive
scale” using AI models and services to “commercially exploit and
distribute” infringing images and videos. On Wednesday evening,
attorneys for Disney sent a cease-and-desist letter to Google,
demanding that Google stop the alleged infringement in its AI
systems. [...]</p>

<p>According to the letter, which Variety has reviewed, Disney
alleges that Google’s AI systems and services infringe Disney
characters including those from “Frozen,” “The Lion King,”
“Moana,” “The Little Mermaid,” “Deadpool,” “Guardians of the
Galaxy,” “Toy Story,” “Brave,” “Ratatouille,” “Monsters Inc.,”
“Lilo &amp; Stich,” “Inside Out” and franchises such as Star Wars, the
Simpsons, and Marvel’s Avengers and Spider-Man. In its letter,
Disney included examples of images it claims were generated by
text prompts in Google’s AI apps, including of Darth Vader
(<em>pictured above</em>).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s very Disney-esque to embrace a new medium. Alone among the major movie studios in the 1950s, Disney embraced television. TV <em>was</em> a threat to the cinema, but it was also an enormous opportunity. The other studios only saw the threat. Walt Disney focused on the opportunity. But Disney did this not by giving their content to television on the cheap or for free. They did it by getting paid. That’s what they’re doing with generative AI.</p>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/12/disney-google-ai-cease-and-desist-darth-vader.png">Here’s the Gemini-generated Darth Vader image</a>. Note the blood splatter — which was un-<em>Star Wars</em>-like even before Disney’s purchase of Lucasfilm. Also, even worse, his lightsaber is totally wrong.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Disney, Immediately After Partnering With OpenAI for Sora, Sends Google a Cease-and-Desist Letter Accusing Them of Copyright Infringement on ‘Massive Scale’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/15/disney-google-cease-and-desist">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Roomba Maker iRobot Declares Bankruptcy, Falls Into Chinese Hands</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.wsj.com/business/roomba-maker-declares-bankruptcy-but-tries-to-ease-bricking-fears-fe73dff2?st=XATuAs" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wrz" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/15/roomba-maker-irobot-declares-bankruptcy" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42479</id>
	<published>2025-12-15T18:50:21Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-15T18:50:21Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>John Keilman, reporting for The Wall Street Journal (gift link):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The company that makes Roomba robotic vacuums declared bankruptcy
Sunday but said its devices will continue to function normally
while the company restructures.</p>

<p>Massachusetts-based iRobot has struggled financially for
years, beset by foreign competition that made cheaper and, in the
opinion of some buyers, technologically superior autonomous
vacuums. When a proposed sale to Amazon.com fell through in 2024
<a href="https://www.wsj.com/business/retail/amazon-irobot-scrap-acquisition-deal-7072122f">because of regulatory concerns</a>, the company’s share price
plummeted.</p>

<p>Founded in 1990, iRobot’s autonomous vacuum cleaners helped
pioneer robotics for consumers. Many recent versions of the Roomba
have features that are controlled through the brand’s app. Some
owners have worried that, similar to other products tied to the
internet, their Roombas could “brick” — or stop working — if the
company went under. iRobot said it anticipates no disruptions to
its product support or app functionality.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Matt Stoller, author of the (generally excellent) website <a href="https://www.thebignewsletter.com/">Big</a>, <a href="https://x.com/matthewstoller/status/2000567118207828114">on Twitter/X today</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>iRobot is selling itself to Chinese manufacturers, a result of
hedge fund attack a decade ago that gutted the company. Wall
Street is a threat to our national sovereignty.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Matt Stoller, author of the (generally knee-jerk anti-acquisition) website Big, <a href="https://x.com/matthewstoller/status/1555530144407867392">on Twitter back in 2022</a>, when Amazon announced its intended acquisition:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Amazon just bought iRobot, which has immense amounts of data about
people’s physical homes. It never ends. Congress should have
passed <a href="https://x.com/TomCottonAR">@TomCottonAR</a>’s bill to bar big tech mergers.</p>

<p>[Press release: “<a href="https://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/amazon-and-irobot-sign-an-agreement-for-amazon-to-acquire-irobot-301600720.html">Amazon and iRobot sign an agreement for Amazon to acquire iRobot</a>”]</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You can’t have it both ways. If Amazon’s proposed acquisition would have gone through, iRobot, an American company, would now be a (small) subsidiary of Amazon, another American company. The acquisition did not go through, which is what Stoller wanted, and now here we are with iRobot — which in Stoller’s own description “has immense amounts of data about people’s physical homes” — in the hands of a Chinese company.</p>

<p>iRobot’s demise wasn’t caused by hedge fund investments a decade ago. The hedge fund vultures swooped in after the Amazon acquisition collapsed in early 2024. Here’s Connie Loizos, writing yesterday for TechCrunch:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It seemed like a fairy tale ending — the scrappy MIT spinoff
absorbed into the Everything Store’s sprawling empire.</p>

<p>Except European regulators had other ideas. Indeed, amid threats
they would block the deal — they believed Amazon could foreclose
rivals by restricting or degrading access to its marketplace — Amazon and iRobot agreed to <a href="https://www.wsj.com/business/retail/amazon-irobot-scrap-acquisition-deal-7072122">kill the deal</a> in January 2024,
with Amazon paying a $94 million breakup fee and walking away.
Angle resigned. The company’s shares nosedived. It shed 31% of its
workforce.</p>

<p>What followed afterward was a slow-motion collapse. Earnings had
been declining since 2021 thanks to supply chain chaos and Chinese
competitors flooding the market with cheaper robot vacuums.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>iRobot didn’t get big enough on its own quickly enough. It was under fierce competitive pressure from Chinese robot vacuums. Roombas seemed groundbreaking and innovative at first, but technical progress stalled. Amazon’s hands aren’t exactly clean in terms of putting the squeeze on iRobot: the primary place where the cheaper Chinese robot vacuums were being sold was, of course, Amazon.</p>

<p>By 2022, the Amazon acquisition was iRobot’s lifeline. <a href="https://www.wsj.com/business/retail/amazon-irobot-scrap-acquisition-deal-7072122f">EU regulators wanted it shot down</a>, and despite the fact that it was one American company trying to acquire another, the anti-big-tech Biden administration clearly preferred to let the deal collapse. The US should have told the EU to mind their own companies.</p>

<p>Now iRobot is in Chinese hands, the worst possible outcome. The Amazon acquisition wasn’t anti-competitive — it was iRobot’s last chance to remain competitive.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Roomba Maker iRobot Declares Bankruptcy, Falls Into Chinese Hands’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/15/roomba-maker-irobot-declares-bankruptcy">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/12/full_text_of_marco_rubio_state_dept_directive_times_new_roman" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wrk" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42464</id>
	<published>2025-12-10T23:53:51Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-11T22:10:36Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Good on Rubio for rescinding a bad decision, and even better for doing so with a fair and informative explanation.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>I’m a big believer in reading original source material. For example, when Apple provided me, <a href="https://www.techmeme.com/250307/p12#a250307p12">alongside only a handful of other outlets</a>, with a statement regarding their decision to delay the “more personalized Siri” back in March, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/apple_is_delaying_the_more_personalized_siri_apple_intelligence_features">I ran the full statement</a>, verbatim. I added my own commentary, but I wanted to let Apple’s own statement speak for itself first. It drives me nuts when news sites in possession of a statement or original document do not make the full original text available, even if only in a link at the bottom, and choose only to quote short excerpts.</p>

<p>With regard to <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/10/state-department-times-new-roman">today’s news</a> regarding Marco Rubio’s directive re-establishing Times New Roman as the default font for U.S. State Department documents (rescinding the Biden administration’s 2023 change to Calibri), I very much wanted to read the original. The New York Times broke the news, stated that they had obtained the memo, and quoted phrases and words from it, but they did not provide a copy of the original. </p>

<p>The State Department has not made this document publicly available, and to my knowledge, no one else has published it. I have obtained a copy from a source, and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/12/state-department-return-to-tradition.text">have made it available here in plain text format</a>. The only change I’ve made is to replace non-breaking spaces (<code>U+00A0</code>) with regular spaces.<sup id="fnr1-2025-12-10"><a href="#fn1-2025-12-10">1</a></sup></p>

<p>Please do <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/12/state-department-return-to-tradition.text">read it yourself</a>, and do so with an open mind.</p>

<p>It seems clear to me that The New York Times did Rubio dirty in their characterization of the directive. The Times story, credited to reporters Michael Crowley and Hamed Aleaziz, ran under the headline “<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/12/09/us/politics/rubio-state-department-font.html?unlocked_article_code=1.7k8.NI-S.Il8KdkMKKnGV">At State Dept., a Typeface Falls Victim in the War Against Woke</a>”, and opens thus:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Secretary of State Marco Rubio waded into the surprisingly fraught
politics of typefaces on Tuesday with an order halting the State
Department’s official use of Calibri, reversing a 2023 Biden-era
directive that Mr. Rubio called a “wasteful” sop to diversity.</p>

<p>While mostly framed as a matter of clarity and formality in
presentation, Mr. Rubio’s directive to all diplomatic posts around
the world blamed “radical” diversity, equity, inclusion and
accessibility programs for what he said was a misguided and
ineffective switch from the serif typeface Times New Roman to sans
serif Calibri in official department paperwork.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Rubio’s memo ran about 950 words. Here are the full quotes the Times pulled from it, consisting of just 56 words, aside from the memo’s subject line (“Return to Tradition: Times New Roman 14-Point Font Required for All Department Paper”):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“wasteful”</p>

<p>“radical”</p>

<p>“restore decorum and professionalism to the department’s
written work.”</p>

<p>“informal”</p>

<p>“clashes”</p>

<p>“was not among the department’s most illegal, immoral, radical or
wasteful instances of D.E.I.A.”</p>

<p>“accessibility-based document remediation cases”</p>

<p>“Switching to Calibri achieved nothing except the degradation of
the department’s official correspondence.”</p>

<p>“generally perceived to connote tradition, formality and ceremony”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Rubio’s memo wasn’t merely “mostly framed as a matter of clarity and formality in presentation”. That’s entirely what the memo is about. Serif typefaces like Times New Roman <em>are</em> more formal. It was the Biden administration and then-Secretary of State Antony Blinken who categorized the 2023 change to Calibri as driven by accessibility. I do not have access to Blinken’s memo making that change (under the cringe-inducing subject line “The Times (New Roman) are a-Changin”), but it was <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/world/2023/01/18/state-department-times-new-roman-calibri/">first reported by John Hudson and Annabelle Timsit at The Washington Post</a>, where they wrote:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The secretary’s decision was motivated by accessibility issues and
not aesthetics, said a senior State Department official familiar
with the change.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Rubio’s memo makes the argument — correctly — that aesthetics matter, and that the argument that Calibri was in any way more accessible than Times New Roman was bogus. Rubio’s memo does not lash out against accessibility as a concern or goal. He simply makes the argument that Blinken’s order mandating Calibri in the name of accessibility was an empty gesture. Purely performative, at the cost of aesthetics. Going back to that 2023 story at the Post, they quote from Blinken’s memo thus:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In its cable, the State Department said it was choosing to shift
to 14-point Calibri font because serif fonts like Times New Roman
“can introduce accessibility issues for individuals with
disabilities who use Optical Character Recognition technology or
screen readers. It can also cause visual recognition issues for
individuals with learning disabilities,” it said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The bit here about OCR <a href="https://mastodon.social/@pesh/115696514979388477">is utter nonsense</a>, a voodoo belief. No OCR or screen-reader software in use today has any problem whatsoever with Times New Roman. That’s just made-up nonsense, and I’d like to see sources for the claim about “visual recognition issues for individuals with learning disabilities”. I don’t think it’s true, and citing it alongside a provably wrong claim about OCR software makes me even more skeptical.</p>

<p>Rubio brings actual numbers to make his case, which is more than can be said for anyone I’ve found arguing that Calibri is somehow more accessible than Times New Roman. Rubio’s argument is alluded to in the Times’s article thus:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>But Mr. Rubio called it a failure by its own standards, saying
that “accessibility-based document remediation cases” at the
department had not declined.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Here’s the full passage from Rubio’s memo:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>And although switching to Calibri was not among the Department’s
most illegal, immoral, radical, or wasteful instances of DEIA
(see, e.g., Executive Orders 14151, 14173, 14281, and Memorandum
on Removing Discrimination and Discriminatory Equity Ideology From
the Foreign Service (DCPD202500375)) it was nonetheless cosmetic:
the switch was promised to mitigate “accessibility issues for
individuals with disabilities,” and employees were promised, “Your
adoption supports the Department’s commitment to create a more
accessible workplace,” but these promises were false. In fact, the
number of accessibility-based document remediation cases at the
Department of State was the same in the year after adopting
Calibri as in the year before (1,192 cases in FY2024 versus 1,193
cases in FY2022). And the costs of remediation actually increased
by $145,000 in that period — nearly a 20% jump. Switching to
Calibri achieved nothing except the degradation of the
Department’s official correspondence.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>2024 was a Biden year, not a Trump year, so there’s no reason to think the remediation numbers were counted differently. The change to Calibri was the worst kind of accessibility effort: one that was founded on nothing more than feel-good performance. It was a change everyone could see and notice, but one that had no practical benefit whatsoever. Good on Rubio for rescinding a bad decision, and even better for doing so with a fair and informative explanation.<sup id="fnr2-2025-12-10"><a href="#fn2-2025-12-10">2</a></sup> (His memo even explains, “Fonts are specific variations of a typeface....  Through common use, the word font has come to mean both typeface and font.”)</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>

<li id="fn1-2025-12-10">
<p>The memo, per State Department standards perhaps, uses two spaces after sentences and colons. In the original copy I received, those double-spaces were sometimes in the sequence <em>NON-BREAK-SPACE + SPACE</em>, and other times the other way around: <em>SPACE + NON-BREAK-SPACE</em>. There were also a handful of seemingly random non-breaking space characters between words, mid-sentence. All of them, I suspect, just invisible-to-the-eye detritus from Microsoft Word. I replaced all of them with regular spaces, preserving, in plain text, two spaces wherever two spaces were intended.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-12-10"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>

<li id="fn2-2025-12-10">
<p>Do I think it was “fair and informative” to describe all of the Biden State Department’s DEIA initiatives as “illegal, immoral, radical, or wasteful”? No. Did I bother reading any of the documents Rubio referenced as proving such? No. Do I think this particular memorandum, specific to changing State’s font back to Times New Roman, would have been stronger without that line, leaving his defenestration of the Calibri font change to speak for itself? Yes. But that line was just one aside in an otherwise focused, sober, and, yes, fair and informative memo.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr2-2025-12-10"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
</li>

</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ The Full Text of Marco Rubio’s Directive on State Department Typography, Re-Establishing Times New Roman</title></entry></feed><!-- THE END -->
