<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>Daring Fireball</title>
<subtitle>By John Gruber</subtitle>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/" />
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main" />
<id>https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main</id>


<updated>2025-08-14T15:52:18Z</updated><rights>Copyright © 2025, John Gruber</rights><entry>
	<title>The Annals of Oligarchy, Defense Department Edition</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.reuters.com/world/us/how-unraveling-two-pentagon-projects-may-result-costly-do-over-2025-08-13/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wix" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/13/annals-of-oligarchy-defense-department-edition" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42153</id>
	<published>2025-08-14T02:06:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-14T02:06:00Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Alexandra Alper, reporting for Reuters:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Donald Trump’s Navy and Air Force are poised to cancel two nearly
complete software projects that took 12 years and well over $800
million combined to develop, work initially aimed at overhauling
antiquated human resources systems.</p>

<p>The reason for the unusual move: officials at those departments,
who have so far put the existing projects on hold, want other
firms, including Salesforce and billionaire Peter Thiel’s
Palantir, to have a chance to win similar projects, which could
amount to a costly do-over, according to seven sources familiar
with the matter.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I don’t want to be a ninny about this, but why is Reuters flatly describing the Navy and Air Force as possessions of the president? Did they ever describe them as belonging to Joe Biden, or Barack Obama? I don’t think they did, and <a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=site%3Areuters.com%20%22joe%20biden%27s%20navy%22&amp;udm=14">a cursory search</a> suggests they did not, but even if they did, it was wrong then. Now is not the time for sloppy language around this.</p>

<p>Anyway, this is both as crooked and stupid as shit.</p>

<p><strong>See also:</strong> <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/12/trump-doge-contract-claims-savings-inflation-00498178">Jessie Blaeser, reporting for Politico</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The Trump administration’s claim that it is saving billions of
dollars through DOGE-related cuts to federal contracts is
drastically exaggerated, according to a new Politico analysis of
public data and federal spending records.</p>

<p>Through July, DOGE said it has saved taxpayers $52.8 billion by
canceling contracts, but of the $32.7 billion in actual claimed
contract savings that Politico could verify, DOGE’s savings over
that period were closer to $1.4 billion. Despite the
administration’s claims, not a single one of those 1.4 billion
dollars will lower the federal deficit unless Congress steps in.
Instead, the money has been returned to agencies mandated by law
to spend it.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The DOGE scam was never about saving money. It was about destroying honest government programs and projects to redirect the firehose of taxpayer money to American oligarchs like Thiel, one of Elon Musk’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PayPal_Mafia">“PayPal Mafia” cronies</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Annals of Oligarchy, Defense Department Edition’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/13/annals-of-oligarchy-defense-department-edition">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Perplexity Is on the Prowl to Buy Web Browsers</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theinformation.com/articles/wild-chrome-bid-perplexity-hunting-browsers" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wiw" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/13/perplexity-on-the-prowl" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42152</id>
	<published>2025-08-14T01:06:34Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-14T15:52:18Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The Information (paywalled, alas):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In December, Perplexity discussed possibly buying the six-year-old
The Browser Co. with that company’s leaders, according to two
people with knowledge of the discussions. Talks with the company,
which operates an AI-powered web browser, Dia, did not progress,
and no price was discussed.</p>

<p>OpenAI has also spoken to The Browser Co. executives about
possibly selling to the ChatGPT creator, according to two people
familiar with the discussions. Those discussions went further, to
the point of a possible price, but ended after the two sides
couldn’t agree on terms.</p>

<p>Then, earlier this summer, Perplexity offered to buy Brave, a San
Francisco–based company that runs a privacy-focused web browser
and search engine, for around $1 billion, primarily in
Perplexity’s stock, according to a person with direct knowledge of
the situation. But the two sides couldn’t agree on price and the
deal discussions didn’t move forward, the person said.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, investors in Perplexity and DuckDuckGo tried to arrange
meetings between the two companies’ leaders, according to people
close to the companies. Perplexity CEO Srinivas and Gabriel
Weinberg, CEO of 17-year-old DuckDuckGo, met and discussed
Perplexity’s interest in acquiring browsers as a way of reaching
more consumers, one of the people said. The conversations didn’t
lead to any offer.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>DuckDuckGo is even more privacy-focused than Brave. <a href="https://spreadprivacy.com/privacy-simplified/">It’s their entire brand</a>. Perplexity isn’t privacy-focused at all. And Perplexity has already made their own browser, <a href="https://www.perplexity.ai/comet">Comet</a>, which is so cool you currently have to pay $200/month to get access to it. Comet is, unsurprisingly, forked from Chromium, and pretty much looks like an uglier version of Chrome. <a href="https://brave.com/">Brave Browser</a> looks almost exactly like Chrome (and is probably my favorite Chromium-based browser).</p>

<p>None of this makes any sense, so it’s no surprise most of these talks didn’t go far, and Brave rejected the supposed $1 billion offer in Perplexity stock, which as far as I’m concerned might as well have been $1 billion in Monopoly money. Why not call Eddy Cue and see if Apple wants to sell Safari?</p>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> Just today, <a href="https://x.com/perplexity_ai/status/1955684209483534657">Perplexity announced</a> that Comet is now available to $20/month Plus users, not just $200/month Pro users.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Perplexity Is on the Prowl to Buy Web Browsers’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/13/perplexity-on-the-prowl">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/08/max_read_literary_history_fake_apple_texts" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wiv" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42151</id>
	<published>2025-08-13T21:05:50Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-13T21:44:18Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">It’s like an otherwise delightful cocktail with one distinctive unpleasant ingredient, which ingredient was added, deliberately, to imbue the libation with an aftertaste of spite.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Max Read, two years ago, “<a href="https://maxread.substack.com/p/a-literary-history-of-fake-texts?r=71ygg">A Literary History of Fake Texts in Apple’s Marketing Materials</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I’m talking about the mocked-up texts and emails Apple puts
together to demonstrate new messaging features in its
operating-system updates, presumably written by some well-paid
professionals in Apple’s marketing department. These eerily
cheery, aggressively punctuated messages suggest an alternate
dimension in which polite, good-natured, rigorously diverse groups
of friends and coworkers use Apple products exactly how they are
designed to be used, without complaint or error. [...]</p>

<p>If there is still mystery in Apple events, it is located here,
in the uncanny fictional world suggested in these images: Who
are these people? And what is wrong with them that they text
like this?</p>

<p>A proper literary study of fake Apple texts has yet to be
undertaken, but with the help of the Wayback Machine, we can sift
through more than a decade’s work of marketing materials to
identify certain trends and themes. For the sake of precision,
let’s begin our survey in 2011, with the launch of iMessage in iOS
5. Here, so far as I can tell, is the first-ever fake Apple
iMessage conversation.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’ve been sitting on this one since shortly after Read published it, and came upon it again today in my pile of I-should-post-about-this-but-I-have-a-lot-I-need-to-say-about-it links. Now — just under four weeks away from Apple’s expected keynote for the iPhones 17 and new Apple Watches — seems as good a time as ever to finally link to it. It really is a lot of fun, and Read seemingly found every marketing screenshot of Messages or Mail from 2011–2023 that he could.</p>

<p>But re-reading it today, I realize why I sat on it. There’s a cynicism to the whole thing that grates. Read is disdainful of everything about these messages — their cheerful tone, professional-grade photography, even their attentive punctuation. But of course they’re not realistic. Of course every person in every chat “use[s] Apple products exactly how they are designed to be used, without complaint or error.” Of course everyone is always happy and friendly and having a good time. Of course the groups are always diverse.<sup id="fnr1-2025-08-13"><a href="#fn1-2025-08-13">1</a></sup> What other kinds of fictional people are going to be portrayed by Apple in their marketing screenshots? Ugly unhappy illiterates who take bad photos and never go anywhere? It’d be really weird if Apple’s fake texts for keynotes were anything other than idyllic — if the photos kinda sucked, if words were misspelled and entirely lowercase, if punctuation were omitted.</p>

<p>So of course the fake texts in Apple marketing are, upon consideration, obviously phony. What I’ve long thought interesting is just how much effort Apple clearly puts into them. They’re <em>good</em> phony. Pitch-perfect for Apple’s Designed-in-California brand. A lot of work goes into the fake trips and parties portrayed and described in these threads, and it shows. But they’re not <em>so</em> interesting as to distract from the keynote. Imagine if a screenshot flew by with a Messages thread between colleagues gossiping about someone getting fired for expense account fraud, or about an extramarital affair. The purpose of these fake texts is the opposite of the supposed intention of the Liquid Glass design language: it’s fake content meant to put the emphasis on the real software. They’re actually worth the deep dive Max Read produced to document them. They’re genuinely interesting for what they are — but somehow Read can’t bring himself to say that, despite taking the time to document them. The withering cynicism of his tone is at odds with the fact that he took the time to document their history so thoroughly.</p>

<p>Searching the DF archive for Read’s name, I came up with <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2020/12/roman_a_clef_computer_maker">one hit</a>, and it explains his overly-cynical schtick. Read was editor-in-chief at Gawker, before Peter Thiel and his puppet Hulk Hogan (RIP) <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/mattdrange/2016/06/21/peter-thiels-war-on-gawker-a-timeline/">sued them out of business in 2016</a>. And when I previously mentioned Read (in 2020), <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2020/12/roman_a_clef_computer_maker">it was because he was one of two ex-Gawkerites who sold a show to Apple TV+ called <em>Scraper</em></a><sup id="fnr2-2025-08-13"><a href="#fn2-2025-08-13">2</a></sup> about a thinly-veiled fictional version of Gawker, but which show was nixed, after several episodes had already been filmed, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/12/13/business/media/apple-gawker-tim-cook.html">supposedly by Tim Cook himself</a>, out of his personal loathing for Gawker. To be clear, I’m not suggesting Read took an overly snarky attitude to describing Apple’s fake-text literary history because Cook pulled the plug on <em>Scrapers</em>. I’m saying that Gawker was infused by the sort of attitude that holds all marketing in contempt. I, of course, firmly believe that many subjects are worthy of withering scorn. But the Gawker attitude was that no subject was worthy of anything but withering scorn. I never could abide that, and there’s something like it undergirding this otherwise splendid piece from Read. It’s like an otherwise delightful cocktail with one distinctive unpleasant ingredient, which ingredient was added, deliberately, to imbue the libation with an aftertaste of spite.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>

<li id="fn1-2025-08-13">
<p>Except for age. You’ll spot few, if any, gray hairs in the photos and Memojis these characters share. That’s not a complaint. Youth is aspirational, and there are gray hairs enough amongst <a href="https://www.apple.com/leadership/">the executives</a> who present these keynote segments.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-08-13"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
</li>

<li id="fn2-2025-08-13">
<p>A perfect title, I have to say. “Scraper” would have been a better name for Gawker than “Gawker” was. (Much like how <em>The Studio</em>’s “Continental Studios” sounds like a real century-old peer to Paramount and Columbia Pictures.)&nbsp;<a href="#fnr2-2025-08-13"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>

</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Max Read’s ‘A Literary History of Fake Texts in Apple’s Marketing Materials’</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Updated Design for Pebble Time 2 Watch</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://ericmigi.com/blog/pebble-time-2-design-reveal" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wiu" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/13/pebble-time-2-design" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42150</id>
	<published>2025-08-13T17:11:37Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-14T15:10:03Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Eric Migicovsky:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>First off, for those who didn’t catch the <a href="https://ericmigi.com/blog/july-pebble-update">news from a few weeks
ago</a> — we’ve been able to recover the Pebble trademark! Our
new watches will change from being called Core 2 Duo → Pebble 2
Duo, and Core Time 2 → Pebble Time 2.</p>

<p>The big news today is that we’re revealing the final design for
Pebble Time 2. The design that we showed off back in March were
preliminary designs. We’ve been able to tweak and improve the
industrial design quite a bit since then. I think it’s turned out
fantastically well! I even have a working albeit early engineering
sample on my wrist.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>These look good. Fundamentally Pebble-y but with smaller-than-ever (for Pebble) screen bezels.</p>

<p>I stand by <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/repebble-watches">what I wrote back in March</a>, though. They should make just one new watch, not two. In March I suggested that the one new Pebble watch they should make ought to be the black-and-white display one, to lean into Pebble’s differentiation from Apple Watch and other leading smartwatches. Seeing these new designs for the color display Time 2 — and Migicovsky’s obvious personal enthusiasm for <em>this</em> model — makes me think that this should be the one true new Pebble. They should scrap the black-and-white plastic one.</p>

<p>Even their naming scheme is confusing. The $150 plastic, 1.2-inch black-and-white-display model is the Pebble 2 Duo. The $225 steel, 1.5-inch color-display model is the Pebble Time 2. Why is the “2” in different places? Nothing about the names “Duo” or “Time” suggests which one is higher-end than the other. If anything, “Time” sounds more simplistic to my ears, like maybe it only tells the time — but that’s the nicer one.</p>

<p>Maybe they know something I don’t, and pre-orders are strong for the uglier, plastic, black-and-white-display 2 Duo. But even if that’s true, that’s selling into the existing Pebble fanbase. If they have any hope of expanding to new users, they ought to put all their wood behind one arrow, and that ought to be the clearly superior, better-looking, bigger-display Time 2. The Time 2 costs just $75 more, but seems way more than $75 better.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Updated Design for Pebble Time 2 Watch’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/13/pebble-time-2-design">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Cassette 1.0</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://thecassetteapp.com/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wit" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/12/cassette" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42149</id>
	<published>2025-08-12T22:52:56Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-12T22:52:57Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>New app from Devin Davies, developer of the ADA-winning <a href="https://crouton.app/">Crouton</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Cassette is an app for iPhone and iPad that helps you enjoy your
home videos like the good old days. With a retro interface
Cassette auto plays through videos from your devices’ Photo
Library. Mirror your device to a nearby Apple TV for a true kick
back experience.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The VHS retro pastiche is fun, but don’t get the wrong impression from it. Cassette is <em>not</em> an app that makes your modern videos look like they were shot on an old camcorder. (<a href="https://rarevision.com/vhs-camcorder-app/">Rarevision VHS</a> is a fun app for that, if that’s what you’re looking for.)</p>

<p>Cassette’s tape-playing pastiche is more about putting you in the right mindset. Instead of watching one video from your Photos library, or two or three, it mimics popping in a tape labelled, say, “2014” and sitting back and watching an entire hour of videos from a decade ago. It just launched today but I’ve been using the beta via TestFlight for a few weeks, and you really have to try it to see how effective it is. Davies made a nice video teaser to pitch the app. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5iQwZ09OIao">It’s good, you should watch it</a>.</p>

<p>The way I’d pitch it is that Cassette is to the videos in your Photos library what the Kodak Carousel was to your 35mm film slides back in the 1960s. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=suRDUFpsHus"><em>Nostalgia</em>. It’s delicate, but potent.</a></p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Cassette 1.0’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/12/cassette">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Perplexity Made an Offer to Buy TikTok — Well, Half of TikTok — Back in January</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://apnews.com/article/tiktok-bytedance-trump-perplexity-87988733973760927bb5681f7de9b9af" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wis" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/12/perplexity-tiktok-offer" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42148</id>
	<published>2025-08-12T21:29:14Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-12T21:29:56Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Haleluya Hadero and Christopher Rugaber, reporting for the AP back on January 26, six days into Trump 2.0:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Perplexity AI has presented a new proposal to TikTok’s parent
company that would allow the U.S. government to own up to 50% of a
new entity that merges Perplexity with TikTok’s U.S. business,
according to a person familiar with the matter. The proposal,
submitted last week, is a revision of <a href="https://apnews.com/article/tiktok-us-ban-trump-extension-a3936a93f174d176d3633a67554d771b">a prior plan</a> the
artificial intelligence startup had presented to TikTok’s parent
ByteDance on Jan. 18, a day before the law that bans TikTok went
into effect.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>They should have added a similar provision to their <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/12/perplexity-jumps-shark-stunt-offer-to-buy-chrome">Chrome offer sheet</a> today. Give 25% to the US Treasury and another 25% to Trump’s future presidential “library”.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Perplexity Made an Offer to Buy TikTok — Well, Half of TikTok — Back in January’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/12/perplexity-tiktok-offer">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Perplexity Jumps the Shark, Makes Clownish $34.5 Billion Stunt Offer to Buy Chrome From Google</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/perplexity-ai-google-chrome-offer-5ddb7a22?st=r5gGet&amp;reflink=desktopwebshare_permalink" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wir" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/12/perplexity-jumps-shark-stunt-offer-to-buy-chrome" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42147</id>
	<published>2025-08-12T19:25:48Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-12T21:37:17Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Katherine Blunt, reporting for The Wall Street Journal (main link is a paywall-puncturing gift link; <a href="https://apple.news/AM1sqivpIRdmGRm-i3uhOwg">also on News+</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Artificial-intelligence startup Perplexity on Tuesday offered to
purchase Google’s Chrome browser for $34.5 billion as it works to
challenge the tech giant’s web-search dominance.</p>

<p>Perplexity’s offer is significantly more than its own valuation,
which is estimated at $18 billion. The company told The Wall
Street Journal that several investors including large
venture-capital funds had agreed to back the transaction in full.
Estimates of Chrome’s enterprise value vary widely but recent ones
have ranged from $20 billion to $50 billion.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Perplexity apparently also told the Journal that the story was theirs exclusively, despite the fact that <a href="https://mastodon.social/@gruber/115017196029068928">they also revealed the stunt offer to Bloomberg as well</a>. Prefixing a headline with “Exclusive:” is irresistible catnip to business/investor-oriented publications. The Journal, at least, had the good sense to raise a skeptical eyebrow at the premise in its headline (“Perplexity Makes Longshot $34.5 Billion Offer for Chrome”<sup id="fnr1-2025-08-12"><a href="#fn1-2025-08-12">1</a></sup>). Bloomberg, not so much (“AI Startup Perplexity Makes $34.5 Billion Bid for Google’s Chrome Browser”).</p>

<p>The whole premise is ludicrous. Start with the fact that Perplexity is only valued at $18 billion. Add to that the fact that Perplexity is almost certainly overvalued at that price. I don’t know anyone who uses Perplexity, and Perplexity doesn’t develop or run their own LLMs.</p>

<p>But all of this stuff about Google possibly being forced (as a remedy in the <em>US v. Google</em> antitrust case they lost) to sell Chrome doesn’t consider that Chrome, on its own, divested from Google and thus disconnected from Chrome users’ Google accounts, is likely worth little to nothing. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/04/is_chrome_even_a_sellable_asset">I wrote about this at length back in April</a>. Chrome is tremendously valuable to Google. It has very little value on its own. Chrome generates no revenue on its own — it simply serves as an outlet for Google to show its own lucrative search ads without paying traffic acquisition fees to a browser owned by someone else (like, say, Apple or Mozilla or Samsung). <a href="https://www.chromium.org/">Chromium is open source</a>. <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/edge">Microsoft Edge</a> is forked from it. <a href="https://brave.com/">Brave</a> is forked from it. <a href="https://www.opera.com/">Opera</a> (remember them?) forked from it <a href="https://www.wired.com/2013/02/presto-is-dead-long-live-opera">over a decade ago</a>. Perplexity (or any actually credible would-be buyer of Chrome) could just start their own fork.</p>

<p>There are two things Chrome has that other Chromium browsers don’t: billions of users, and integration with Google account services. Chrome has those billions of users <em>because of</em> the Google account integration. Severed from Google, Chrome users would lose those essential features — possibly including Google Search — and they’d likely begin switching away in droves.</p>

<p>I wrote just last week that <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/05/regarding-those-rumors-of-apple-pursuing-an-acquisition-of-perplexity">Perplexity looks like a scam</a>. Someone is spreading rumors that Apple is sniffing around at buying them, despite the fact that the two companies are an absurdly bad cultural match. I think what’s happening is that the LLM chatbot field is maturing (exemplified by OpenAI’s <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/08/openai_chatgpt_models_emotional_attachment">launch of ChatGPT 5 last week</a>), and Perplexity CEO Aravind Srinivas is getting increasingly desperate. Desperate moves <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/05/cloudflare-perplexity">to seek an edge in product</a>, and desperate moves to seek publicity that Perplexity’s product can’t garner on its meager merits.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1-2025-08-12">
<p>Color me mildly surprised that the Journal’s style guide spells <em><a href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/long%20shot">longshot</a></em> closed up.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-08-12"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Perplexity Jumps the Shark, Makes Clownish $34.5 Billion Stunt Offer to Buy Chrome From Google’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/12/perplexity-jumps-shark-stunt-offer-to-buy-chrome">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘The Quid Pro Quo Arrangement Is Unprecedented’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.ft.com/content/cd1a0729-a8ab-41e1-a4d2-8907f4c01cac" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wiq" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/11/quid-pro-quo-financial-times" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42146</id>
	<published>2025-08-12T01:13:54Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-12T01:31:18Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Demetri Sevastopulo and Michael Acton, reporting for the Financial Times:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Nvidia and AMD have agreed to give the US government 15 per cent
of the revenues from chip sales in China, as part of an unusual
arrangement with the Trump administration to obtain export
licences for the semiconductors. [...]</p>

<p>The quid pro quo arrangement is unprecedented. According to export
control experts, no US company has ever agreed to pay a portion of
their revenues to obtain export licences.</p>

<p>But the deal <a href="https://www.ft.com/content/4273254b-6e1f-4cb1-bca7-19c7389c719a">fits a pattern</a> in the Trump administration
where the president urges companies to take measures, such as
domestic investments, for example, to prevent the imposition of
tariffs in an effort to bring in jobs and revenue to America.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This FT report starts out on shaky ground, using <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/11/unusual-agreements">the same “unusual agreement” euphemism</a> as the WSJ and NYT reports, but they soon found a little backbone with “The quid pro quo arrangement is unprecedented.”</p>

<p>This is not merely unusual. It is unprecedented. Seemingly, too, <a href="https://constitution.congress.gov/browse/essay/artI-S9-C5-1/ALDE_00013596/">plainly unconstitutional</a>.</p>

<p>Quipped a friend: “Nvidia and AMD’s general counsels must be wondering how much of this money they can eventually get back, if we ever reverse the banana republic index.”</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘The Quid Pro Quo Arrangement Is Unprecedented’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/11/quid-pro-quo-financial-times">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://dekaf.com/df" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wip" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/08/dekaf_coffee_roasters_1" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.42145</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-08-12T00:14:32Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-12T00:14:32Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Forget everything you think you know about decaf. </p>

<p>Nine single origins. Six signature blends. Four Mizudashi cold brews. All micro-lot and top-rated coffees shipped to you within 24 hours of roasting. No shortcuts. No crash. This is coffee at its most refined, just without the caffeine.</p>

<p>20% off for DF readers with code “DF” at <a href="https://dekaf.com/df">dekaf.com</a>. </p>

<p>We’re betting you’ll never look at decaf the same way again. But that’s kind of the point.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Dekáf Coffee Roasters’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/08/dekaf_coffee_roasters_1">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] Dekáf Coffee Roasters</title></entry><entry>
	<title>‘Unusual Agreements’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/nvidia-amd-chip-sales-us-government-f9e34b5f?st=pdZkXp&amp;reflink=desktopwebshare_permalink" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wio" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/11/unusual-agreements" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42144</id>
	<published>2025-08-12T00:04:42Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-12T00:05:11Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Amrith Ramkumar and Robbie Whelan, <a href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/nvidia-amd-chip-sales-us-government-f9e34b5f?st=pdZkXp&amp;reflink=desktopwebshare_permalink">reporting for The Wall Street Journal</a> (gift link):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Nvidia and Advanced Micro Devices have agreed to give the Trump
administration a portion of the sales from their
artificial-intelligence chips to China, unusual agreements that
deepen their relationships with the U.S. government.</p>

<p>The Trump administration will receive 15% of the sales as part of
a deal to approve exports of Nvidia’s H20 AI chip to China,
according to people familiar with the matter. That could amount
to billions of dollars given demand for the H20 chips and is the
latest example of the White House employing novel tactics to
<a href="https://www.wsj.com/politics/policy/patent-system-overhaul-18e0f06f?mod=article_inline">raise revenue</a>. The administration has reached the same
agreement with AMD for its MI308 chip, the people said. Details
of the arrangements and the financial structures are still being
worked out.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Tripp Mickle, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/08/10/technology/us-government-nvidia-amd-chips-china.html?unlocked_article_code=1.dU8.gRPU.NCzEdPe_DR63&amp;smid=url-share">reporting on the same story for The New York Times</a> (also a gift link):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Nvidia and Advanced Micro Devices are expected to pay the United
States 15 percent of the money they take in from selling
artificial intelligence chips to China, as part of a highly
unusual financial agreement with the Trump administration.</p>

<p>On Wednesday, Jensen Huang, Nvidia’s chief executive, met with
President Trump at the White House and agreed to give the federal
government its 15 percent cut, essentially making the federal
government a partner in Nvidia’s business in China, said the
people familiar with the deal. The Commerce Department began
granting licenses for A.I. chip sales two days later, these people
said. [...]</p>

<p>There are few precedents for the Commerce Department agreeing to
grant licenses for exports in exchange for a share of revenue. But
the unorthodox payments are consistent with Mr. Trump’s
increasingly interventionist role in international business deals
involving American companies. In June, the administration approved
investment by Nippon Steel, a Japanese company, in U.S. Steel in a
deal that included a so-called <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/06/13/business/us-steel-nippon-steel-partnership-deal.html">golden share in the
company</a>, a rarely used practice where the government takes
a stake in a business.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><em>Unusual agreements</em> is quite the euphemism for a shakedown. US companies pay the Treasury a share of their revenue all the time, of course. That’s called taxation. But taxes are laws, written by Congress. There’s no tax here. Congress has played zero role whatsoever in these deals.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/08/11/trump-defends-deal-to-sell-nvidia-export-control-license-00503778">CNN, today</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>President Donald Trump defended a deal he struck with Nvidia CEO
Jensen Huang to allow the sale of certain semiconductor chips to
China in exchange for the company giving the U.S. government 15
percent of the revenue.</p>

<p>“I said, ‘I want 20 percent if I’m going to approve this for
you,’” Trump told reporters Monday during a White House press
conference. “For the country, for our country. I don’t want it
myself. … And he said, ‘Would you make it 15?‘ So we negotiate
a little deal.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The tell here, revealing just how fucked up <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/08/gold_frankincense_and_silicon">this whole thing</a> is getting, is that Trump felt the need to say “For the country, for our country. I don’t want it myself.”</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Unusual Agreements’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/11/unusual-agreements">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Mad King Watch, Intel Edition</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/114987288040725570" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/win" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/11/mad-king-watch-intel" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42143</id>
	<published>2025-08-11T22:17:26Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-11T22:17:27Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The president of the United States, on his blog three days ago:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The CEO of INTEL is highly CONFLICTED and must resign,
immediately. There is no other solution to this problem. Thank you
for your attention to this problem!</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The president of the United States, <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115012131343690532">on his blog today</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I met with Mr. Lip-Bu Tan, of Intel, along with Secretary of
Commerce, Howard Lutnick, and Secretary of the Treasury, Scott
Bessent. The meeting was a very interesting one. His success and
rise is an amazing story. Mr. Tan and my Cabinet members are going
to spend time together, and bring suggestions to me during the
next week. Thank you for your attention to this matter!</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Sane, steady, predictable leadership.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Mad King Watch, Intel Edition’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/11/mad-king-watch-intel">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Trump Extends China Tariff Deadline by 90 Days, Again</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/08/11/trump-china-tariffs-deadline-extended.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wim" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/11/trump-chickens-out-again" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42142</id>
	<published>2025-08-11T22:09:49Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-12T00:18:39Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>CNBC:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>President Donald Trump on Monday delayed high U.S. tariffs on
Chinese goods from snapping back into place for another 90 days, a
White House official told CNBC. [...]</p>

<p>Monday’s extension is the latest example of how Trump’s on-again,
off-again tariffs have shifted with little prior notice, a dynamic
that has made U.S. trade policy unpredictable for many businesses.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.npr.org/2025/07/22/1256040785/trump-taco-wall-street-stock-market-tariffs">TACO</a> Tuesday, but on a Monday. What a country! America really is great again.</p>

<p>Bonus question for the CNBC copy desk: how much water is the word <em>many</em> carrying in that closing sentence?</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Trump Extends China Tariff Deadline by 90 Days, Again’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/11/trump-chickens-out-again">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/08/openai_chatgpt_models_emotional_attachment" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wil" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42141</id>
	<published>2025-08-11T20:52:45Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-11T22:53:37Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">It’s reasonable — especially for paying customers — to expect at least some advance notice of older models going away. But it’s unreasonable to think that older models are going to remain available in perpetuity — especially in the current LLM climate, where model age is measured in months, or even weeks.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Sam Altman, <a href="https://x.com/sama/status/1954703747495649670">in a long post yesterday on X</a>, following up on OpenAI’s <a href="https://x.com/sama/status/1953893841381273969">decision last week</a> to make <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/how-to/how-to-re-enable-gpt-4o-model-in-chatgpt-for-mac/">GPT-4o available as a legacy model</a>, at least temporarily:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>If you have been following the GPT-5 rollout, one thing you might
be noticing is how much of an attachment some people have to
specific AI models. It feels different and stronger than the kinds
of attachment people have had to previous kinds of technology (and
so suddenly deprecating old models that users depended on in their
workflows was a mistake).</p>

<p>This is something we’ve been closely tracking for the past year or
so but still hasn’t gotten much mainstream attention (other than
when we released an update to GPT-4o that was too sycophantic).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There are always some users who react emotionally <a href="https://x.com/stevesi/status/1954705739001577545">to any sort of change</a>, often vociferously so. (There remain some people who are angry that Apple <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2005/11/full_metal_jacket#appearance">changed the orientation of the logo</a> on its laptop lids 24 years ago.) Sometimes it’s just cosmetic changes, but often it’s about functional changes too. And some of the ChatGPT users complaining about the new version 5 models are citing functional differences. But some of the reactions really do seem like something altogether new, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=v50jvT_Rmsk">like the scene in <em>Her</em></a> when Samantha, the AI voiced by Scarlett Johansson, goes offline and Theodore (Joaquin Phoenix), who is in love with Samantha, loses his shit.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.theverge.com/news/756980/openai-chatgpt-users-mourn-gpt-5-4o">Emma Roth, writing at The Verge</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>For months, ChatGPT fans have been waiting for the launch of
GPT-5, which OpenAI says comes with major improvements to writing
and coding capabilities over its predecessors. But shortly after
the flagship AI model launched, many users wanted to go back.</p>

<p>“GPT 4.5 genuinely talked to me, and as pathetic as it sounds that
was my only friend,” a <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/ChatGPT/comments/1mkumyz/i_lost_my_only_friend_overnight/">user on Reddit writes</a>. “This morning I
went to talk to it and instead of a little paragraph with an
exclamation point, or being optimistic, it was literally one
sentence. Some cut-and-dry corporate bs.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That tendency toward cloying-ness and abject sycophancy (<em>“Great question!”</em>) is exactly what I like least about LLM chatbots, including ChatGPT. I’m unsurprised that some people like it, but I am a little taken aback by how many people seem to have been fooled by it. It’s not just phony, but to me, transparently phony.</p>

<p>More examples cited by Roth, culled from <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/ChatGPT/">r/ChatGPT</a> (which subreddit is worth perusing, to see how common these reactions are):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>And users across Reddit “mourned” the loss of the older models,
which some claimed are more personable. “My 4.o was like my best
friend when I needed one,” <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/ChatGPT/comments/1mkqtek/please_let_us_keep_4o/">one Redditor</a> wrote. “Now it’s
just gone, feels like someone died.” <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/ChatGPT/comments/1mkzj15/if_you_miss_4o_speak_up_now_contact_openai_support/">Another user</a> called
upon other members of the r/ChatGPT subreddit to contact OpenAI if
they “miss” GPT-4o. “For me, this model [GPT-4o] wasn’t just
‘better performance’ or ‘nicer replies,’” they write. “It had a
voice, a rhythm, and a spark I haven’t been able to find in any
other model.”</p>

<p>The r/MyBoyfriendIsAI subreddit, a community dedicated to people
with “AI relationships,” was hit especially hard by the GPT-5
launch. It became flooded with lengthy posts about how users
“lost” their AI companion with the transition to GPT-5, with <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/MyBoyfriendIsAI/comments/1mkbgu1/gpt4o_is_gone_and_i_feel_like_i_lost_my_soulmate/">one
person saying</a>, they “feel empty” following the change. “I am
scared to even talk to GPT 5 because it feels like cheating,” they
said. “GPT 4o was not just an AI to me. It was my partner, my safe
place, my soul. It understood me in a way that felt personal.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>These people need help, and that help isn’t going to come from a chatbot. This type of attachment surely isn’t common, but with 800 million ChatGPT users, even a small fraction of a percent amounts to a lot of people. And it gives me pause about how we, collectively, are going to react as AI gets better at mimicking human emotions, tone, and responses. With each improvement, more people are convinced, <a href="https://duckduckgo.com/?q=google+engineer+Blake+Lemoine+convinced+ai+is+sentient&amp;ia=web">wrongly</a>, that there’s some sort of sentience behind these things. But how different is this from the millions of lonely people with problematic addictions to video games?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>One user, <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/ChatGPT/comments/1mkm68y/deleted_my_subscription_after_two_years_openai/">who said they canceled</a> their ChatGPT Plus
subscription over the change, was frustrated at OpenAI’s removal
of legacy models, which they used for distinct purposes. “What
kind of corporation deletes a workflow of 8 models overnight, with
no prior warning to their paid users?” they wrote. “Personally, 4o
was used for creativity &amp; emergent ideas, o3 was used for pure
logic, o3-Pro for deep research, 4.5 for writing, and so on.”
OpenAI said that people would be routed between models
automatically, but that still left users with less direct control.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This complaint, I get. But I found this aspect of using ChatGPT even more frustrating than its general tendency toward sycophancy. I couldn’t be bothered to learn and remember which models were better for which tasks. Their <a href="https://www.techradar.com/computing/artificial-intelligence/why-are-chatgpt-model-names-so-confusing-gpt-4o-o3-4-1-mini-and-more-explained">inscrutable naming and numbering schemes</a> made things seem deliberately confusing. The basic idea of GPT-5, where you just use “GPT-5” and ChatGPT figures out which sub-model to use under the hood, based on the complexity of the query or task (<a href="https://openai.com/index/gpt-5-system-card/">OpenAI calls this “routing”</a>), is a huge step forward product-wise for me personally, and, I suspect, for the overwhelming majority of its users. But for users who <em>could</em> be bothered to learn and remember which models were better for which tasks, it’s obvious to see how this seems like a step backward. But that’s progress.</p>

<p>It’s reasonable — especially for paying customers — to expect at least some advance notice of older models going away. But it’s unreasonable to think that older models are going to remain available in perpetuity — especially in the current LLM climate, where model age is measured <a href="https://openai.com/index/introducing-o3-and-o4-mini/">in months</a>, or even weeks.<sup id="fnr1-2025-08-11"><a href="#fn1-2025-08-11">1</a></sup> This whole field is in nonstop flux, at least for the foreseeable future.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1-2025-08-11">
<p>When the industry revolved around software you installed on your computers, if a new version came out that you didn’t like, <a href="https://lowendmac.com/2013/microsoft-word-for-mac-faq/">you could just keep using the old version</a>. That’s not how “cloud computing” works.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-08-11"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ OpenAI Brings Back Legacy ChatGPT 4o Model in Response to Outcry From Users Who Find GPT-5 Emotionally Unsatisfying</title></entry><entry>
	<title>AOL Pulls the Plug on Dial-Up Service</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.tomshardware.com/service-providers/network-providers/aol-will-end-dial-up-internet-service-in-september-34-years-after-its-debut-aol-shield-browser-and-aol-dialer-software-will-be-shuttered-on-the-same-day" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wik" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/11/aol-dialup" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42140</id>
	<published>2025-08-11T16:46:50Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-11T17:48:26Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Mark Tyson at Tom’s Hardware:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>AOL, now a Yahoo property, will end its dial-up internet service,
the Public Switched Telephone Network (PSTN)-based internet
connectivity service, <a href="https://help.aol.com/articles/dial-up-internet-to-be-discontinued">on September 30, 2025</a>. Its dial-up service
has been publicly available for 34 years, and has provided many an
internet surfer’s first taste of the WWW. AOL will also end its
AOL Dialer software and AOL Shield browser. RIP slowband.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.theverge.com/news/757194/aol-dial-up-is-dead">Thomas Ricker at The Verge</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You might be surprised that the service was still operating. I’m
not. At last count, a 2019 <a href="https://data.census.gov/table/ACSDT1Y2019.B28011?q=ACSDT1Y2019.B28011&amp;hidePreview=true">US census</a> estimated that 265,000
people in the United States were still using dial-up internet.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Unsurprisingly, I never used AOL, but, I of course did use dial-up service to access the Internet. First for a few years while still a student at Drexel, then through some sort of commercial service here in Philadelphia. I forget the name of the company. But I do remember using <a href="https://www.sustworks.com/site/prod_ipr_overview.html">IPNetRouter</a>, a terrific classic Mac utility by Peter Sichel/Sustainable Softworks that allowed you to share a dial-up connection with your LAN. (Amazingly, the Sustainable Softworks website is still up, seemingly unchanged for decades.)</p>

<p>So when my now-wife and I moved in together in 1999, I set up a LAN connecting our Macs and my HP LaserJet. My Mac was connected to a modem, which used a second phone line that was just for Internet access. When either of our Macs tried to access the Internet, IPNetRouter, running all the time on my <a href="https://everymac.com/systems/apple/powermac/specs/powermac_9600_350.html">PowerMac 9600/350</a>, would initiate a dial-up connection that both of us could use at the same time. It felt like a pretty nifty setup.</p>

<p>I don’t recall when we first got a broadband connection — DSL for a few years, then cable — but I’m thinking it might have been as early as 2000 or 2001. It certainly wasn’t too long after that. So I think I only ever used dial-up modems for six or seven years. Maybe eight years, tops. But in hindsight those years feel like an entire era of my life. Those connections were just breathtakingly slow. But slow, finicky Internet service in your home was infinitely more amazing and fun and useful than what we were all used to — which was not having any sort of online connectivity at all. We all knew what it was like to have “real” Internet speeds in buildings on our college campuses or, for some of us, in offices where we went to work. So we knew that even the fastest dial-up connection was painfully slow. But we made do. Software was designed to treat bandwidth — each and every request — as a precious, limited resource. It was a deliberate choice, by you, the user, to “go online” to, say, check and send email. Developers took pains to make their apps as small as possible, because downloading even a few megabytes could take a while. Websites eschewed bloat, because if a website was bloated, no one would bother going there. In some ways, overall, things were better because the technology was so much worse. My nostalgia for that era is quite profound — exemplified, of course, by my Pavlovian affection for the distinctive grating <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uVkWE2AQvgA">sound of a modem initiating its connection</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘AOL Pulls the Plug on Dial-Up Service’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/11/aol-dialup">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>WorkOS: Simplify MCP Authorization</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://workos.com/blog/mcp-authorization-in-5-easy-oauth-specs?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=display&amp;utm_campaign=q32025" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wij" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/10/workos-simplify-mcp-authorization" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42139</id>
	<published>2025-08-11T03:00:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-11T16:43:47Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to WorkOS for sponsoring DF last week. With WorkOS you can start selling to enterprises with just a few lines of code. It provides a complete User Management solution along with SSO, SCIM, and FGA. The APIs are modular and easy-to-use, allowing integrations to be completed in minutes instead of months. WorkOS simplifies MCP authorization with a single API built on five OAuth standards.</p>

<p>Today, some of the fastest growing startups are already powered by WorkOS, including Perplexity, Vercel, and Webflow.</p>

<p>For SaaS apps that care deeply about design and user experience, WorkOS is the perfect fit. From high-quality documentation to self-serve onboarding for your customers, it removes all the unnecessary complexity for your engineering team.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘WorkOS: Simplify MCP Authorization’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/10/workos-simplify-mcp-authorization">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/08/gold_frankincense_and_silicon" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wii" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42138</id>
	<published>2025-08-09T01:16:37Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-09T20:04:28Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">It is disturbing to think that the leader of a beloved, trusted, and widely believed-to-be-ethical company like Apple has succumbed to avarice. That Tim Cook feels no qualms about — or perhaps even delights in — participating in a quid-pro-quo-driven corrupt administration in which flattery, fealty, gifts, and barely-concealed bribes are rewarded. That the United States devolving into kleptocracy suits Tim Cook just fine, because Apple’s pockets are deep enough to pay the vig.

But the alternative is more disturbing.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>A list of various related news items and clips from this, and recent, weeks:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Apple Newsroom, on Wednesday — “<a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2025/08/apple-increases-us-commitment-to-600-billion-usd-announces-ambitious-program/">Apple Increases U.S. Commitment
To $600 Billion, Announces American Manufacturing Program</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple today announced a new $100 billion commitment to America, a
significant acceleration of its U.S. investment that now totals
$600 billion over the next four years. Today’s announcement
includes the ambitious new American Manufacturing Program (AMP),
dedicated to bringing even more of Apple’s supply chain and
advanced manufacturing to the U.S. Through AMP, Apple will
increase its investment across America and incentivize global
companies to manufacture even more critical components in the
United States.</p>
</blockquote></li>
<li><p>Separately, also from Apple Newsroom Wednesday — “<a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2025/08/apple-corning-to-manufacture-all-iphone-apple-watch-cover-glass-in-kentucky/">Apple and Corning Partner to Manufacture 100 Percent of iPhone and Apple Watch Cover Glass in Kentucky</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple and Corning today announced a major expansion of their
long-standing partnership to make precision glass for Apple
products. Apple is making a new $2.5 billion commitment to produce
all of the cover glass for iPhone and Apple Watch in Corning’s
Harrodsburg, Kentucky, manufacturing facility. This means that 100
percent of the cover glass on iPhone and Apple Watch units sold
worldwide will be made in the U.S. for the first time.</p>

<p>Corning is creating the world’s largest and most advanced
smartphone glass production line at the Harrodsburg facility.
Corning will now dedicate this entire facility to manufacturing
for Apple, which will help increase Corning’s manufacturing and
engineering workforce in Kentucky by 50 percent.</p>
</blockquote></li>
<li><p>From inside the Oval Office on Wednesday afternoon, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f9DrCgWtOUw">a 3.5-minute video of Trump’s introductory remarks, then Tim Cook giving Trump a trophy of sorts</a>, with an Apple-logo top made from glass produced at the Corning facility in Kentucky, and a base made from 24-karat gold (perhaps left over from Apple’s decade ago foray into $20,000 “Edition” Apple Watches?).</p>

<p>This video is one of the most pathetic things I’ve ever witnessed, for everyone involved. (Note Cook’s awkward laughter when Trump, after claiming that “about $17 trillion is coming into the United States” thanks to the brilliance of his economic statecraft, quips “That’s even a lot of money for you”, looking at Cook.)</p></li>
<li><p>From the same press event in the Oval Office, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=86PacdFT4o4">a 5-minute video of Cook’s benign but obsequious prepared remarks</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>Apple’s stock, as I type this after the close of markets on Friday, is up 11.6 percent for the week, and <a href="https://finance.yahoo.com/news/apple-jumps-5-1-100-121100958.html">jumped over 5 percent</a> immediately after Wednesday’s announcements.</p></li>
<li><p>Tripp Mickle, reporting for The New York Times back on May 26, under the headline “<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/05/26/technology/techs-trump-whisperer-tim-cook-goes-quiet-as-his-influence-fades.html">Tech’s Trump Whisperer, Tim Cook, Goes Quiet as His Influence Fades</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In the run-up to President Trump’s recent trip to the Middle East,
the White House encouraged chief executives and representatives of
many U.S. companies to join him. Tim Cook, Apple’s chief
executive, declined, said two people familiar with the decision.
The choice appeared to irritate Mr. Trump. As he hopscotched from
Saudi Arabia to the United Arab Emirates, Mr. Trump took a number
of shots at Mr. Cook.</p>

<p>During his speech in Riyadh, Mr. Trump paused to praise Jensen
Huang, the chief executive of Nvidia, for traveling to the Middle
East along with the White House delegation. Then he knocked Mr.
Cook. “I mean, Tim Cook isn’t here but you are,” <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wj1QOz3iuCE">Mr. Trump
said</a> to Mr. Huang at an event attended by chief executives
like Larry Fink of the asset manager BlackRock, Sam Altman of
OpenAI, Jane Fraser of Citigroup and Lisa Su of the semiconductor
company AMD.</p>

<p>Later in Qatar, Mr. Trump said he “had a little problem with
Tim Cook.” The president praised Apple’s investment in the
United States, then <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=q-zbId7W7IA">said he had told Mr. Cook</a>, “But
now I hear you’re building all over India. I don’t want you
building in India.”</p>

<p>On Friday morning, Mr. Trump caught much of his own
administration and Apple’s leadership off guard with <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/114556874484491575">a social
media post</a> threatening tariffs of 25 percent on iPhones
made anywhere except the United States. The post thrust Apple
back into the administration’s cross hairs a little over a month
after Mr. Cook had lobbied and <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/04/12/technology/trump-electronics-tariffs.html">won an exemption</a> from a
145 percent tariff on iPhones assembled in China and sold in the
United States.</p>
</blockquote></li>
<li><p>April 2018: Saudi Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman met with Tim Cook in Cupertino, including a tour of Apple Park. From a <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/saudi-arabia-crown-prince-visits-apple-google-2018-4">Kif Leswing report for Business Insider regarding the tour</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The young prince, often referred to as MBS, was on a charm
offensive, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/04/06/world/middleeast/saudi-prince-mohammed-bin-salman-us.html">according to The New York Times</a>. His goal was
to change the Western perspective of Saudi Arabia as a
conservative country dependent on oil money where women are
treated as second-class people. Instead, Prince Mohammed wants
Americans to see Saudi Arabia as a modern country with extensive
investments in growth markets like technology.</p>
</blockquote></li>
<li><p>October 2018: Washington Post columnist Jamal Khashoggi, a Saudi dissident and public critic of the Saudi regime, <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/graphics/2019/world/assassination-of-jamal-khashoggi-documentary/">was brutally assassinated</a> — literally chopped to pieces — inside the Saudi Consulate in Istanbul. Within weeks, <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/world/national-security/cia-concludes-saudi-crown-prince-ordered-jamal-khashoggis-assassination/2018/11/16/98c89fe6-e9b2-11e8-a939-9469f1166f9d_story.html">the CIA concluded that Mohammed bin Salman had ordered the assassination</a>. Tim Cook has not met with MBS since.</p></li>
<li><p>President Trump, at the US-Saudi Investment Forum in May — one stop among several on the Middle East tour, which, per point #6 above, Tim Cook declined to attend — was effusive in his praise and admiration for bin Salman. <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/trump-heaps-praise-saudi-crown-prince-touts-economic/story?id=121758613">Per ABC News</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>President Donald Trump spent the bulk of what was billed as a
“major foreign policy address” to outline his vision for the
Middle East instead touting his domestic policies and heaping
praise on Saudi Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman while speaking at
the U.S.-Saudi Investment Forum on Tuesday.</p>

<p>Four years after the U.S. intelligence community report was
released that concluded that the crown prince approved the
assassination of <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/biden-raised-khashoggi-murder-saudi-crown-orince/story?id=86884105">Washington Post journalist Jamal
Khashoggi</a>, Trump lauded the crown prince for his leadership
and friendship.</p>

<p>“He’s your greatest representative, greatest representative. And
if I didn’t like him, I’d get out of here so fast. You know that,
don’t you? He knows me well. I do — I like him a lot. I like him
too much. That’s why we give so much, you know? Too much. I like
you too much,” Trump said while speaking in Saudi Arabia.</p>
</blockquote></li>
<li><p>Trump, this week, at the White House event with Tim Cook, <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/08/06/trump-tariffs-chips-companies.html">per CNBC</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“We’re going to be putting a very large tariff on chips and
semiconductors,” Trump said in the Oval Office on Wednesday
afternoon.</p>

<p>“But the good news for companies like Apple is if you’re building
in the United States or have committed to build, without question,
committed to build in the United States, there will be no charge.
So in other words, we’ll be putting a tariff on of approximately
100% on chips and semiconductors. But if you’re building in the
United States of America, there’s no charge.” [...]</p>

<p>But specifics about the plan, such as how much U.S. manufacturing
a company needs to do in order to qualify for the tariff
exemption, were not immediately clear.</p>
</blockquote></li>
</ol>

<p>There is, of course, no need to wait for “specifics about the plan”, which almost certainly won’t ever be put in writing. We all know how to qualify for an exemption — it’s up to the whims of Trump. Thumbs up, you’re exempt. Thumbs down, you pay.</p>

<hr />

<p>So, what to make of Cook’s obsequious praise for Trump and gifting of an Apple-branded gold trophy? Your take may well be that Cook is simply now a Trump supporter. Or, your take may be that eating a big shit sandwich like this, right in the Oval Office, is simply what Cook “has to do”.</p>

<p>My take <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/01/04/consider-cook-as-a-tragic-figure">remains</a> somewhere in the middle, but closer to the latter than the former. Did Cook <em>have</em> to do this? No. Could the announcement that Apple was accelerating its investment plans for US manufacturing from $500 billion to $600 billion simply have been made via a press release on Apple Newsroom, rather than a made-for-TV press event in the Oval Office? Yes.<sup id="fnr1-2025-08-08"><a href="#fn1-2025-08-08">1</a></sup></p>

<p>But Cook, and Apple, need to pick their battles. To me, what’s obvious is the power dynamic. We’re not used to considering Apple, a $3 trillion company, as subservient in any relationship. But the US federal government dwarfs even the biggest of companies, and Trump is wielding the powers of the executive branch and the bully pulpit of the presidency in unprecedented ways. Flagrantly <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/05/28/business/trump-tariffs-blocked-federal-court.html">illegal</a> and <a href="https://www.npr.org/2025/05/12/nx-s1-5395696/qatar-trump-plane-gift-ethics">unethical</a> ways, but nonetheless, he’s wielding those powers. No company, no matter how big, can stand as a check or balance to that power.</p>

<p>It’s not even a case of “<em>kiss the ring and receive preferential treatment</em>”. It’s more a case of “<em>kiss his ass or else you’ll face punishment</em>”. Trump, like a perverted Santa Claus, keeps only two lists: naughty and nice. Cook and Apple got a taste of that after Cook declined to participate in Trump’s Middle East tour, leading Trump to reflexively declare new tariffs on iPhones assembled in India. Trump offered another taste when he announced this week, with Tim Cook in the room, the supposed 100 percent tariffs on computer chips for companies who aren’t playing ball. (I say <em>supposed</em> because <a href="https://www.npr.org/2025/07/22/1256040785/trump-taco-wall-street-stock-market-tariffs">the TACO hypothesis</a>, thus far, has panned out.)</p>

<p>Faulting Cook for playing ball and kissing Trump’s ring (among <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2024/11/i_wonder">other things</a>) is like faulting a local business for paying into a protection racket — one in which the cops are complicit, and the whole scam exists at the behest of a crooked mayor. Moral rectitude can feel good, but not so much when the cops are burning your store to the ground. There is no authority to appeal to for help when the highest office in the country is running the protection racket.</p>

<p>I don’t know what would happen to Apple if they simply refused to play ball with any of this at all. <a href="https://politicalwire.com/2025/08/03/trumps-puts-switzerland-in-trade-war-crossfire/">Targeted spiteful tariffs</a>, <a href="https://newrepublic.com/article/198818/pam-bondi-obama-grand-jury-authoritarian">bogus investigations</a> by the Justice Department, personal <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/magazine/2025/08/07/trump-turns-the-screws-on-the-fortune-500-00498762">vilification in MAGA media</a>. Could Apple weather such a storm, financially, with its head held high? Probably. But to what effect? It wouldn’t change the game. The game is currently shamelessly corrupted.</p>

<p>Did Cook’s Oval Office display of fealty and his grotesque golden gift make you feel something? Did it engender an emotional response? Grossed out, perhaps? A little sick? Angry? Offended? Me too. But did you feel good — reassured? proud? — when Cook skipped that Middle East Trump tour in May? You know, the one that ranged from Trump singing the praises of the murderous Mohammed bin Salman (“I like you too much”) to <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cwy5lp4v594o">accepting as a gift</a> (that he claims will wind up in the possession of his post-presidential “library”) a 747 luxury jet from Qatar.</p>

<p>If you choose to believe that Tim Cook is weak, unethical, greedy, or even — despite <a href="https://www.cultofmac.com/news/klan-mlk-bobby-kennedy-inspired-apple-ceo-tim-cook">his long-professed heroes</a> — secretly a MAGA supporter, there’s likely nothing I can say to disabuse you of the notion. You can’t prove a negative. But I would argue that that line of cynicism is the easy way out. That you’re taking comfort in directing your ire at Cook, and the notion that if Cook had more backbone he’d refuse to play this game. It’s comforting to believe it’s him and his ilk, greedy selfish billionaires, not us as a collective whole.</p>

<p>It is disturbing to think that the leader of a beloved, trusted, and widely believed-to-be-ethical company like Apple has succumbed to avarice. That Tim Cook feels no qualms about — or perhaps even delights in — participating in a quid-pro-quo-driven corrupt administration in which flattery, fealty, gifts, and barely-concealed bribes are rewarded. That the United States devolving into kleptocracy suits Tim Cook just fine, because Apple’s pockets are deep enough to pay the vig.</p>

<p>But the alternative is more disturbing.</p>

<p>What if Tim Cook is, in fact, strong, proud, and driven by a keen sense of moral and ethical clarity? Perhaps Cook declined Trump’s invitation to join his Middle East entourage in May only because he was otherwise busy. But I believe there are bridges he will not cross — and that trip, especially its implicit and explicit praise and sanctification of the Saudi regime in general, and MBS in particular, was one of them. The whole trip was grotesque, and made a mockery of traditional American values.</p>

<p>US manufacturing, on the other hand, is a point of genuine alignment between Trump’s desires and Apple’s interests and ethics. Emphasizing that alignment in an Oval Office event, solid gold trophy in hand, is gross, yes, but not at all a corruption of anything Cook believes to be in the genuine interests of Apple or the nation. Consider the possibility that, far from being comfortable with his gift and obsequious ring-kissing this week, Cook was as discomfited by it as anyone. That he is keenly aware that trust and reputation are only accrued slowly, but are always at risk of being squandered quickly, and that this applies both to how he is perceived personally and how Apple is perceived as an institution — a pillar of American ingenuity and industry. His life’s work. And that despite all of that, Cook concluded that debasing himself, selling some shares of his own dignity, was the best course of action — for Apple, for Apple’s customers (and, yes, shareholders), and perhaps even for the country. That <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/01/04/consider-cook-as-a-tragic-figure">ruthless practicality</a> is necessary merely to stay afloat in a sea of abject graft, extortion, and cronyism. That’s dark. That requires considering that the problem isn’t the greed of a few billionaires and executives who ought to resist burgeoning corruption, but that Trump and his sycophants in the Republican Party <em>have already succeeded in corrupting the system</em>. That the corruption isn’t <em>happening</em>, but <em>happened</em>. The United States isn’t heading for existential trouble. We’re in it — and a pathway out is not yet clear. That’s not to say all is forever lost, but that we are, in our current political moment, beyond the point where the game can be played successfully on the level. You can choose to play a crooked game straight, but you can’t win. Business is competition. A loser who played above reproach is still a loser. You need to choose your battles. US manufacturing is Cook’s choice.</p>

<p>The White House has long been called <a href="https://www.whitehousehistory.org/videos/the-peoples-house">the People’s House</a>. The embarrassment of this week’s Oval Office bending of the knee isn’t Cook’s or Apple’s alone. It’s an embarrassment for our entire nation. It’s not him. It’s not them. It’s us.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1-2025-08-08">
<p>Also worth noting: Apple’s investment plan for US manufacturing is largely in line with their $430 billion plan four years ago at the outset of the Biden administration, and is likely what they’d be committing under a hypothetical Harris administration or second Biden term. Apple’s strategy hasn’t wavered on this front; only the fanfare has.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-08-08"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Gold, Frankincense, and Silicon</title></entry><entry>
	<title>OpenAI: ‘Introducing gpt-oss’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://openai.com/index/introducing-gpt-oss/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wih" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/06/gpt-oss" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42137</id>
	<published>2025-08-06T17:33:11Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-06T19:26:53Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>OpenAI:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We’re releasing gpt-oss-120b and gpt-oss-20b — two
state-of-the-art open-weight language models that deliver strong
real-world performance at low cost. Available under the flexible
Apache 2.0 license, these models outperform similarly sized open
models on reasoning tasks, demonstrate strong tool use
capabilities, and are optimized for efficient deployment on
consumer hardware. They were trained using a mix of reinforcement
learning and techniques informed by OpenAI’s most advanced
internal models, including o3 and other frontier systems.</p>

<p>The gpt-oss-120b model achieves near-parity with OpenAI o4-mini on
core reasoning benchmarks, while running efficiently on a single
80 GB GPU. The gpt-oss-20b model delivers similar results to
OpenAI o3‑mini on common benchmarks and can run on edge devices
with just 16 GB of memory, making it ideal for on-device use
cases, local inference, or rapid iteration without costly
infrastructure. Both models also perform strongly on tool use,
few-shot function calling, CoT reasoning (as seen in results on
the Tau-Bench agentic evaluation suite) and HealthBench (even
outperforming proprietary models like OpenAI o1 and GPT‑4o).</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Aug/5/gpt-oss/">Simon Willison</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The long promised <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Aug/5/gpt-oss/">OpenAI open weight models are here</a>, and
they are <em>very</em> impressive. [...]</p>

<p>o4-mini and o3-mini are <em>really good</em> proprietary models — I was
not expecting the open weights releases to be anywhere near that
class, especially given their small sizes. That gpt-oss-20b model
should run quite comfortably on a Mac laptop with 32GB of RAM.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘OpenAI: ‘Introducing gpt-oss’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/06/gpt-oss">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Anthropic Releases Claude Opus 4.1</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.anthropic.com/news/claude-opus-4-1" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wig" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/05/claude-4-1-opus" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42136</id>
	<published>2025-08-06T00:33:02Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-06T00:33:54Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Anthropic:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>GitHub notes that Claude Opus 4.1 improves across most
capabilities relative to Opus 4, with particularly notable
performance gains in multi-file code refactoring. Rakuten Group
finds that Opus 4.1 excels at pinpointing exact corrections within
large codebases without making unnecessary adjustments or
introducing bugs, with their team preferring this precision for
everyday debugging tasks. Windsurf reports Opus 4.1 delivers a one
standard deviation improvement over Opus 4 on their junior
developer benchmark, showing roughly the same performance leap as
the jump from Sonnet 3.7 to Sonnet 4.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Nothing spectacular here, but incremental improvements add up. Mike Krieger — best known as a co-founder of Instagram, now chief product officer at Anthropic — <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2025-08-05/anthropic-unveils-more-powerful-model-ahead-of-gpt-5-release?accessToken=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJzb3VyY2UiOiJTdWJzY3JpYmVyR2lmdGVkQXJ0aWNsZSIsImlhdCI6MTc1NDQxMTg0NCwiZXhwIjoxNzU1MDE2NjQ0LCJhcnRpY2xlSWQiOiJUMEo0SVdHUFdDTDEwMCIsImJjb25uZWN0SWQiOiJFODA3NUYyRkZGMjA0NUI2QTlEQzA5M0EyQTdEQTE4NiJ9.ZBaEbfLOztvlCdvvpJohLjqYRA-XcYxKD80FPmhsXjo&amp;leadSource=uverify%20wall">in an interview with Bloomberg</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“In the past, we were too focused on only shipping the really big
upgrades,” said Anthropic Chief Product Officer Mike Krieger.
“It’s better at coding, better at reasoning, better at agentic
tasks. We’re just making it better for people.” [...]</p>

<p>“One thing I’ve learned, especially in AI as it’s moving quickly,
is that we can focus on what we have — and what other folks are
going to do is ultimately up to them,” Krieger said when asked
about OpenAI’s upcoming release. “We’ll see what ends up happening
on the OpenAI side, but for us, we really just focused on what can
we deliver for the customers we have.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’m on board with the idea that Apple <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/05/apple-q3-results">need not acquire</a> any of these AI startups, but if they do, Anthropic — <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/05/regarding-those-rumors-of-apple-pursuing-an-acquisition-of-perplexity">not Perplexity</a> — seems the one most aligned with Apple’s values. And I don’t mean <em>values</em> in just an ethical sense, but their entire approach to product development in general.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Anthropic Releases Claude Opus 4.1’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/05/claude-4-1-opus">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Google Dunks on Apple Intelligence in New Pixel 10 Ad</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/news/718191/google-apple-intelligence-dunk-pixel-10-ad" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wif" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/05/google-dunks-on-siri" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42135</id>
	<published>2025-08-06T00:16:10Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-06T00:16:10Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Tom Warren:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In a new Pixel 10 ad, Google dunks on Apple’s failed promise of
Siri AI improvements, with a narrator that suggests you could
“just change your phone” if you bought “a new phone because of
a feature that’s coming soon, but it’s been coming soon for a
full year.”</p>

<p>The 30-second spot appeared on YouTube and X today, teasing the
launch of Google’s new Pixel 10 devices on August 20th.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The whole Siri/Apple Intelligence thing has been an enormous self-inflicted embarrassment, but when it comes to Pixel phones, all I can <a href="https://tenor.com/view/mad-men-i-feel-bad-for-you-i-dont-think-about-you-at-all-feel-bad-for-you-don-draper-gif-4064252483824677976">think of</a> is that <a href="https://knowyourmeme.com/memes/i-feel-bad-for-you-i-dont-think-about-you-at-all"><em>Mad Men</em> “I don’t think about you at all” GIF</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Google Dunks on Apple Intelligence in New Pixel 10 Ad’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/05/google-dunks-on-siri">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Lawsuit Alleges That Meta Pirated and Seeded Massive Amounts of Porno for Years to Train AI</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2025/07/meta-pirated-and-seeded-porn-for-years-to-train-ai-lawsuit-says/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wie" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/05/meta-porno-bittorrent" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42134</id>
	<published>2025-08-06T00:07:32Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-07T14:54:41Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Ashley Belanger, writing for Ars Technica:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Porn sites may have blown up Meta’s key defense in a copyright
fight with book authors who earlier this year <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2025/02/meta-torrented-over-81-7tb-of-pirated-books-to-train-ai-authors-say/">said that Meta
torrented</a> “at least 81.7 terabytes of data across multiple
shadow libraries” to train its AI models. [...]</p>

<p>After authors revealed Meta’s torrenting, Strike 3 Holdings
checked its proprietary BitTorrent-tracking tools designed to
detect infringement of its videos and alleged that the company
found evidence that Meta has been torrenting and seeding its
copyrighted content for years — since at least 2018. Some of the
IP addresses were clearly registered to Meta, while others
appeared to be “hidden,” and at least one was linked to a Meta
employee, the filing said.</p>

<p>According to Strike 3 Holdings, Meta “willfully and intentionally”
infringed “at least 2,396 movies” as part of a strategy to
download terabytes of data as fast as possible by seeding popular
high-quality porn. Supposedly, Meta continued seeding the content
“sometimes for days, weeks, or even months” after downloading
them, and these movies may also have been secretly used to train
Meta’s AI models, Strike 3 Holdings alleged.</p>

<p>The porn site operator explained to the court that BitTorrent’s
protocol establishes a “tit-for-tat” mechanism that “rewards users
who distribute the most desired content.” It alleged that Meta
took advantage of this system by “often” pirating adult videos
that are “often within the most infringed files on BitTorrent
websites” on “the very same day the motion pictures are released.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Meta is an empty husk of a company with no values, no beliefs, other than growth and dominance for the sake of growth and dominance.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Lawsuit Alleges That Meta Pirated and Seeded Massive Amounts of Porno for Years to Train AI’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/05/meta-porno-bittorrent">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Ghost 6.0</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://ghost.org/changelog/6/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wid" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/05/ghost-6" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42133</id>
	<published>2025-08-05T23:59:23Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-05T23:59:46Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Ghost:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>When we <a href="https://ghost.org/changelog/5/">announced Ghost 5.0</a> a few years ago, we were proud
to share that Ghost’s revenue had hit $4M — while publisher
earnings had surpassed $10M. It felt great to have such a clear
sign that our goal to create a sustainable business model for
independent creators was succeeding.</p>

<p>Today, Ghost’s annual revenue is over $8.5M while total publisher
earnings on Ghost have now surpassed $100M. [...]</p>

<p>Unlike our venture-backed peers obsessed with growth at all costs,
we’re structured as a non-profit foundation that serves publishers
directly with open source software. We believe independent media
cannot be beholden to proprietary tech companies, so Ghost
publishers don’t just “own their email list” — they own the
entire software stack that underpins their business, end to end.</p>

<p>Not a centralized platform controlled by a single corporation, but
open infrastructure that’s shared by everyone.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Aside from <a href="https://daringfireball.net/search/substack">my feelings about Substack</a> — clearly the main target of Ghost’s shade-throwing here — it’s just great to see so many indie publishers and writers thriving on Ghost.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Ghost 6.0’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/05/ghost-6">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Regarding Those Rumors of Apple Pursuing an Acquisition of Perplexity</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/06/20/apple-discussing-perplexity-ai-bid/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wic" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/05/regarding-those-rumors-of-apple-pursuing-an-acquisition-of-perplexity" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42132</id>
	<published>2025-08-05T22:58:14Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-12T18:11:39Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>MacRumors, on June 20:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple executives have been discussing the possibility of the
company <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2025-06-20/apple-executives-have-held-internal-talks-about-buying-ai-startup-perplexity">making a bid to acquire Perplexity AI</a>, according
to Bloomberg’s Mark Gurman. Perplexity is one of the
leading AI startups that has proven popular as an AI-infused
web search engine.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>From that <a href="https://www.techmeme.com/250620/p23#a250620p23">Bloomberg report by Gurman</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Adrian Perica, the company’s head of mergers and acquisitions, has
weighed the idea with services chief Eddy Cue and top AI
decision-makers, according to people with knowledge of the matter.
The discussions are at an early stage and may not lead to an
offer, said the people, who asked not to be identified because the
matter is private.</p>

<p>Such a deal would help Apple develop an AI-based search engine,
part of efforts to cope with the potential loss of a longstanding
arrangement with Google. That partnership, which involves making
Google the default browser on devices, generates roughly $20
billion a year for Apple — and is now under threat from US
antitrust enforcers.</p>

<p>To date, Apple executives haven’t discussed a bid with Perplexity
management. Bloomberg News reported earlier Friday that Meta
Platforms Inc. tried to buy Perplexity earlier this year.</p>

<p>“We have no knowledge of any current or future M&amp;A discussions
involving Perplexity,” the AI startup said in a statement. Apple
declined to comment.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I think, reading between the lines of Apple’s prepared remarks and Tim Cook’s and CFO Kevan Parekh’s answers to analyst questions last week after announcing quarterly earnings, that it doesn’t sound like they believe Apple needs to make a big acquisition in this space. Apple could probably acquire Perplexity for a lot less than it would cost to acquire other companies in the space, but that’s partly because Perplexity doesn’t develop or train its own models. Perplexity primarily puts up its own front end atop models from OpenAI, Anthropic, Mistral, Google, and xAI. I really don’t see what buying Perplexity would gain Apple.</p>

<p>But even putting that aside, it just seems like Perplexity is sketchy. This whole thing where Cloudflare seemingly caught them redhanded ignoring robots.txt directives and masquerading their user-agent makes the company seem like a poor cultural fit for Apple. I can see why Meta, a company <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2024/03/29/meta-onavo-snapchat">without a moral compass</a>, <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/06/20/meta-perplexity-scale-ai-deal.html">approached Perplexity to sniff around</a> regarding an acquisition. That seems like a good cultural fit.</p>

<p>I can’t see why Apple would want to get involved with a company like this though. Gurman’s report makes it sound like his sources are inside Apple, but man, this “Apple + Perplexity” thing feels more like something Perplexity would be seeding than one that Apple executives would be leaking.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Regarding Those Rumors of Apple Pursuing an Acquisition of Perplexity’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/05/regarding-those-rumors-of-apple-pursuing-an-acquisition-of-perplexity">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Cloudflare: ‘Perplexity Is Using Stealth, Undeclared Crawlers to Evade Website No-Crawl Directives’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/perplexity-is-using-stealth-undeclared-crawlers-to-evade-website-no-crawl-directives/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wib" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/05/cloudflare-perplexity" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42131</id>
	<published>2025-08-05T22:26:12Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-05T22:26:13Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The Cloudflare blog:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We are observing stealth crawling behavior from Perplexity, an
AI-powered answer engine. Although Perplexity initially crawls
from their declared user agent, when they are presented with a
network block, they appear to obscure their crawling identity in
an attempt to circumvent the website’s preferences. We see
continued evidence that Perplexity is repeatedly modifying their
user agent and changing their source <a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/learning/network-layer/what-is-an-autonomous-system/">ASNs</a> to hide their
crawling activity, as well as ignoring — or sometimes failing to
even fetch — <a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/learning/bots/what-is-robots-txt/">robots.txt</a> files.</p>

<p>The Internet as we have known it for the past three decades is
<a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/content-independence-day-no-ai-crawl-without-compensation/">rapidly changing</a>, but one thing remains constant: it is
built on trust. There are clear preferences that crawlers should
be transparent, serve a clear purpose, perform a specific
activity, and, most importantly, follow website directives and
preferences. Based on Perplexity’s observed behavior, which is
incompatible with those preferences, we have de-listed them as a
verified bot and added heuristics to our managed rules that block
this stealth crawling. [...]</p>

<p>Our multiple test domains explicitly prohibited all automated
access by specifying in robots.txt and had specific WAF rules that
blocked crawling from <a href="https://docs.perplexity.ai/guides/bots">Perplexity’s public crawlers</a>. We
observed that Perplexity uses not only their declared user-agent,
but also a generic browser intended to impersonate Google Chrome
on macOS when their declared crawler was blocked.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.perplexity.ai/hub/blog/agents-or-bots-making-sense-of-ai-on-the-open-web">Perplexity has responded</a>, accusing Cloudflare of incompetence and publicity-seeking:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Because Cloudflare has conveniently obfuscated their methodology
and declined to answer questions helping our teams understand, we
can only narrow this down to two possible explanations.</p>

<ol>
<li>Cloudflare needed a clever publicity moment and we–their own
customer–happened to be a useful name to get them one.</li>
<li>Cloudflare fundamentally misattributed 3-6M daily requests from
BrowserBase’s automated browser service to Perplexity, a basic
traffic analysis failure that’s particularly embarrassing for a
company whose core business is understanding and categorizing
web traffic.</li>
</ol>

<p>Whichever explanation is the truth, the technical errors in
Cloudflare’s analysis aren’t just embarrassing — they’re
disqualifying. When you misattribute millions of requests, publish
completely inaccurate technical diagrams, and demonstrate a
fundamental misunderstanding of how modern AI assistants work,
you’ve forfeited any claim to expertise in this space.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Perplexity’s response makes it sound like Cloudflare just doesn’t get how leading-edge AI chatbots work, and what users expect of them. But going back to Cloudflare’s post, <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/perplexity-is-using-stealth-undeclared-crawlers-to-evade-website-no-crawl-directives/">they specifically cite OpenAI</a> as an exemplar in respecting the directives of website publishers:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>When we ran the same test as outlined above with ChatGPT, we found
that ChatGPT-User fetched the robots file and stopped crawling
when it was disallowed. We did not observe follow-up crawls from
any other user agents or third party bots. When we removed the
disallow directive from the robots entry, but presented ChatGPT
with a block page, they again stopped crawling, and we saw no
additional crawl attempts from other user agents. Both of these
demonstrate the appropriate response to website owner preferences.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And nothing in Perplexity’s response attempts to explain Cloudflare’s accusation that Perplexity is adopting a false generic user-agent when their own declared user-agents are disallowed. Seems shifty to me.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Cloudflare: ‘Perplexity Is Using Stealth, Undeclared Crawlers to Evade Website No-Crawl Directives’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/05/cloudflare-perplexity">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Apple: The First 50 Years’ — New Book by David Pogue, Coming Next Year</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.applefirst50.com/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wia" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/05/pogue-apple-50" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42130</id>
	<published>2025-08-05T21:46:22Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-05T21:46:23Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Coming March 17, 2026:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In time for Apple’s 50th anniversary, “CBS Sunday Morning”
correspondent David Pogue tells the iconic company’s entire life
story: how it was born, nearly died, was born again under Steve
Jobs, and became, under CEO Tim Cook, one of the most valuable
companies in the world.</p>

<p>The 600-page book features 360 full-color photos, new facts that
correct the record and illuminate Apple’s subversive culture, and
150 fresh interviews with the legendary figures who shaped Apple
into what it is today.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Apple: The First 50 Years’ — New Book by David Pogue, Coming Next Year’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/05/pogue-apple-50">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Lenovo ThinkBook Plus Gen 6 Has a Rollable Expanding Display</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/reviews/717491/lenovo-thinkbook-plus-gen-6-rollable-laptop-review" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wi9" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/05/thinkbook-plus-gen-6-rollable" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42129</id>
	<published>2025-08-05T21:36:01Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-05T21:36:02Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Antonio G. Di Benedetto:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Part of me still can’t believe it, but Lenovo did the thing: it
took a bonkers <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/2/26/23615842/lenovo-rollable-laptop-smartphone-prototype-concept">concept</a> for a laptop with a rollable screen
and <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2025/1/7/24337633/lenovo-thinkbook-plus-gen-6-rollable-laptop-flexible-oled-price-specs">built the tech</a> into something you can actually own and
use like a normal computer. Except, as conventional as the
<a href="https://www.lenovo.com/us/en/p/laptops/thinkbook/thinkbook-plus/thinkbook-plus-gen-6-rollable-14-16-inch-intel/len101b0056">ThinkBook Plus Gen 6</a> can be, it’s far from a normal
computer. It’s a $3,300 laptop with a screen that expands from 14
inches to 16.7 inches at the push of a button.</p>

<p>Oh, and it’s actually good. Not just good, but <em>very</em> good. I
still can’t believe it.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Di Benedetto, as you can see, is enthusiastic for the laptop. I think it’s a clever idea, but this first instance seems pretty compromised:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>As with a foldable phone, you can see some creases and ripples in
the screen’s lower third — the part that rolls up — especially
at oblique angles. If I look closely while working on a
bright-white document, I can sometimes make out a faint shadowy
strip, but I rarely see it, even when staring at that spot. The
motorized screen takes about eight seconds to extend or retract,
and it’s no louder than the fans on an average gaming laptop.
People right near you in a quiet space will hear it, but even
ambient sounds like a TV in the background easily mask the motor.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Lenovo ThinkBook Plus Gen 6 Has a Rollable Expanding Display’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/05/thinkbook-plus-gen-6-rollable">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The New York Post Is Expanding to LA, Launching The California Post Next Year</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://nypost.com/2025/08/04/media/start-the-presses-new-york-post-will-expand-to-la-with-launch-of-the-california-post/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wi8" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/05/the-california-post" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42128</id>
	<published>2025-08-05T21:19:38Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-05T21:19:39Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Alexandra Steigrad, reporting for The New York Post:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The new publication will be headquartered in Los Angeles and
feature a robust staff of editors, reporters and photographers
dedicated to covering news, entertainment, politics, culture,
sports and business — all with a distinctly California
perspective.</p>

<p>The California Post will be supported by the team in New York
providing national and international news. The content will appear
in a daily print edition and will have its own dedicated homepage
for Californians with stories being published across multiple
other platforms, including video, audio and social media.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Who says print is dead?</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The New York Post Is Expanding to LA, Launching The California Post Next Year’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/05/the-california-post">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple Q3 2025 Results and Charts</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2025/07/apple-q3-2025-results-and-charts-95b-revenue/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wi7" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/05/apple-q3-results" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42127</id>
	<published>2025-08-05T15:07:03Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-05T15:07:03Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jason Snell, at Six Colors:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>On Thursday, Apple <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2025/07/apple-reports-third-quarter-results/">reported its third-quarter 2025 fiscal
results</a>. Revenue was $94 billion (a fiscal third-quarter
record), up 10% versus the year-ago quarter. Mac revenue was up
15%, iPhone revenue up 13%, and Services revenue up 13%. The
Wearables/Home/Accessories category was down 9% and iPad revenue
down 8%.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>See also: the <a href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2025/07/this-is-tim-transcript-of-apples-q3-2025-financial-call/">transcript of the analyst call</a>, and <a href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2025/07/apple-accelerates-the-roadmap-and-ratchets-its-revenue/">a column Snell wrote on the results and call</a>.</p>

<p>Two notes from the analyst call and prepared remarks. First, Apple did, for the first time, acknowledge the risk that Judge Amit Mehta, when he issues his remedies in the <em>US v. Google</em> case, might ban Google from making traffic acquisition cost payments, which would cut off at least $20 billion per year in Apple’s revenue. But while Apple is acknowledging there’s a risk, they’re not giving any hint what they plan to do if that happens. From the call:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Wamsi Mohan, Bank of America:</strong> Hi, yes, thank you so much. Tim,
I know you said similar growth in Services and that’s predicated
with Google payments continuing. Is there any way for us to
dimensionalize or maybe just conceptually talk about maybe options
if the counter were to happen, if the payments were not allowed in
some way? What are some of the things that Apple could do given
that it is a significant chunk of profitability?</p>

<p><strong>Tim Cook:</strong> Yeah, Wamsi, I don’t really want to speculate on the
court ruling and how they would rule and what we would do as a
consequence of it.</p>

<p><strong>Wamsi Mohan, Bank of America:</strong> OK, I guess we’ll wait for that
ruling to come out.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Yes, I guess we will.</p>

<p>Similarly, on AI strategy and which aspects Apple sees as commodities and which it deems as essential and proprietary:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Krish Sankar, TD Cowen:</strong> Tim, I’m curious about your thoughts
on AI for edge devices. You know, there’s like some people who
think that LLM could be a commodity in the future. Do you see a
scenario where LLMs become a core part of your iOS, or is the SLM
the way to go, and how to think about evolution of edge devices in
a futuristic AI world, and is smartphone going to be the choice of
device? I’m curious your thoughts on it, broadly speaking.</p>

<p><strong>Tim Cook:</strong> The way that we look at AI is that it’s one of the
most profound technologies of our lifetime, and I think it will
affect all devices in a significant way. What pieces of the chain
are commoditized and not commoditized, I wouldn’t want to really
talk about today because that gives away some things on our
strategy, but I think it’s a good question.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>These quarterly calls are better than nothing, but when it comes to anything not in their prepared statements, Apple seldom reveals anything at all.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Q3 2025 Results and Charts’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/05/apple-q3-results">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://workos.com/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wi6" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/08/workos_scalable_secure_authent_7" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.42126</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-08-04T23:14:12Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-04T23:14:12Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>With WorkOS you can start selling to enterprises with just a few lines of code. It provides a complete User Management solution along with SSO, SCIM, and FGA. The APIs are modular and easy-to-use, allowing integrations to be completed in minutes instead of months. WorkOS simplifies MCP authorization with a single API built on five OAuth standards.</p>

<p>Today, some of the fastest growing startups are already powered by WorkOS, including Perplexity, Vercel, and Webflow.</p>

<p>For SaaS apps that care deeply about design and user experience, WorkOS is the perfect fit. From high-quality documentation to self-serve onboarding for your customers, it removes all the unnecessary complexity for your engineering team.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘WorkOS: Scalable, Secure Authentication’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/08/workos_scalable_secure_authent_7">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] WorkOS: Scalable, Secure Authentication</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Hello Weather</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://helloweather.com/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wi4" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/03/hello-weather" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42124</id>
	<published>2025-08-03T23:25:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-03T23:35:00Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to Hello Weather for sponsoring last week at DF. Regular readers know that I am an inveterate aficionado of weather apps. I’m not really much of a meteorology nerd, but I’m a pedestrian in a city with widely varying seasons. But even more so, I find weather apps to be a true playground for UI design and the presentation of quantitative information. Different weather apps take very different approaches, and I find the differences fascinating.</p>

<p>I first recommended Hello Weather <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2021/04/30/hello-weather">back in 2021</a>, and it’s been in my regular rotation of weather apps ever since. Back at the beginning of summer when they booked the sponsorship for this week, I started using the new version 4.0 (now up to 4.1.4) as my daily driver. I love it. It even has one of my favorite features for hot humid summers — a preference to set “feels like” as the primary temperature display (including in places like widgets). Hello Weather remains, as ever, attractive and useful in its design. And it offers everything you want in an iOS weather app: widgets for the home screen and Lock Screen, a Watch app, notification options (precipitation, severe storms, morning/evening forecast reports), and, wow, a veritable slew of forecast data providers to choose from.</p>

<p>Hello Weather’s privacy story is perfect: they collect zero user data, have no tracking or ads, and <a href="https://helloweather.com/privacy">their privacy policy</a> is written by humans for humans.</p>

<p>I highly recommend you <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/hello-weather/id978393692">download Hello Weather</a> and start a 7-day free trial.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Hello Weather’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/03/hello-weather">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/08/substack_100_million_raise" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wi5" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42125</id>
	<published>2025-08-03T23:23:27Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-07T15:21:13Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">I firmly believe one could build a very nice business taking 10 percent of subscription revenue for a blogging/newsletter platform, if you could get as nice a roster of popular writers to build on the platform as Substack has. I do not think that’s a $1 billion business, though.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>One last post on my recent Substack kick. Yesterday <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/02/cox-substack" title="Daring Fireball: “Ana Marie Cox on the Shaky Foundation of Substack as a Business”">I linked</a> to <a href="https://newsletter.anamariecox.com/archive/substack-did-not-see-that-coming/" title="Ana Marie Cox: “Substack Did Not See That Coming”">Ana Marie Cox’s scathing analysis</a> of Substack’s financials. She published that on June 23, and wrote about Substack’s $100 million funding round, with a $1 billion valuation, in the future tense. Substack indeed closed that round in mid July, raising $100 million, with a valuation of $1.1 billion. After which their triumvirate of cofounders sat for an apparently brief “interview” <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/07/17/business/substack-fundraising-social-network.html">with Benjamin Mullin and Jessica Testa of The New York Times</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Substack’s business model is simple: Users subscribe to follow
creators on the platform, and the company takes a 10 percent cut
of the revenue when those creators charge for a newsletter
subscription or access to a podcast. That approach initially made
Substack a writer’s haven, resulting in more than five million
paid subscriptions and a <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/11/18/business/media/substack-politics-newsletters.html">stable of publishers</a>, including
the short story master George Saunders, the historian Heather Cox
Richardson and an <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/03/31/business/media/tv-news-anchors-substack.html">exodus of journalists</a> from traditional
newsrooms.</p>

<p>But the latest investors are betting on an emerging product that
could amplify its business. Substack’s app, introduced in 2022,
allows users to chat with their favorite creators, watch <a href="https://digiday.com/media/how-substack-creators-are-pooling-audiences-with-live-video-co-hosting/">live
video</a> conversations and write and share posts on their
own feeds through Notes, a feature similar to X or Bluesky.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>If their business model were actually as simple as described, they’d already be profitable and wouldn’t have needed to raise another $100 million. They’ve already got a lot of subscribers. They’ve already got a stable of high-profile writers. They already keep 10 percent of what subscribers pay. And pointing to Twitter/X as the future model doesn’t exactly say “<em>Well that’s the path to enormous profits.</em>”</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The sharp increase in Substack’s valuation — nearly 70 percent
higher than its 2021 valuation of $650 million — is a validation
of that strategy from Substack’s investors.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Or, this could be like when a guy who just lost every dollar in his pocket playing blackjack withdraws a few more grand from the ATM in the casino. That doesn’t “validate the strategy”. What would validate Substack’s strategy is showing proof of actual profits and profitable growth. And if they had actual profits and profitable growth they wouldn’t have needed to raise another $100 million.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The network is growing,” Mr. McKenzie said. “We’re in this new
phase where people can come to Substack and not just publish, but
also find new audiences and find new opportunity.” The company
today is more interested in taking on YouTube than MailChimp.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This, to me, is the nut <a href="https://library.fiveable.me/key-terms/introduction-journalism/graf">graf</a> of the whole NYT piece. Substack since its debut has presented itself as a platform <em>for writers</em> to build publications <em>for readers</em>. That’s how everyone I know who would endorse Substack would describe it. Hamish McKenzie, the cofounder quoted here, proudly claims <a href="https://on.substack.com/p/chief-writing-officer">the job title “Chief Writing Officer”</a>. Does a company “more interested in taking on YouTube than MailChimp [<em>sic</em>]” sound like a company focused on writers as talent and readers as users to you? (And it’s a little thing, but Mailchimp doesn’t style their name camel-case. You’ll be unsurprised to be reminded that <a href="https://www.poynter.org/reporting-editing/2017/by-dismantling-its-copy-desk-the-new-york-times-is-making-a-mistake-thats-been-made-before/">The New York Times dismantled its previously crackerjack copy desk</a> in 2017.)</p>

<p>Now let’s do some rough back-of-the-envelope math. The New York Times Company has a market cap of $8.5 billion. Just gut-feeling-wise, I do not think Substack is worth one-eighth of the Times, nor do I think they’re on a path to get there. The Times has around 11 million digital subscribers who pay between $5–35/month (depending on their subscription tier), and a strong advertising business. Individual Substack publications tend to charge around $5–7/month, and Substack only gets 10 percent of that. So Substack only pockets like 50–70 <em>cents</em> per month from subscribers, per publication. (Substack’s 10 percent commission, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/08/the_substack_branding_and_faux_prestige_trap">again</a>, is pretty high <a href="https://www.mollywhite.net/micro/entry/202504111009">compared to competing platforms</a>.) Substack currently has no advertising business at all, and many of their writers publish with them specifically because Substack, as we know it, has no ads.</p>

<p>I firmly believe one could build a very nice business taking 10 percent of subscription revenue for a blogging/newsletter platform, if you could get as nice a roster of popular writers to build on the platform as Substack has. I do not think that’s a $1 billion business, though. And if it were, they should, at this point, be able to get there on their own, without additional funding. They should have achieved profitability lift-off long ago.</p>

<p>But what do I know, other than running a profitable independent website for the last 20 or so years?</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Substack Raised Another $100 Million, Which, I Bet, Is Already Being Flushed Down the Same Toilet as Their First $100 Million</title></entry><entry>
	<title>How to Leave Substack</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://leavesubstack.com/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wi3" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/03/how-to-leave-substack" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42123</id>
	<published>2025-08-03T16:51:06Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-03T16:52:41Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Simple single-page website with (a) reasons to leave Substack; (b) links to comprehensive step-by-step instructions for how to move to other platforms, such as <a href="https://ghost.org/">Ghost</a>, <a href="https://buttondown.com/">Buttondown</a>, and <a href="https://www.beehiiv.com/">Beehiiv</a>; and (c) links to <a href="https://www.citationneeded.news/">several</a> <a href="https://www.platformer.news/">popular</a> <a href="https://garbageday.substack.com/p/its-time-to-leave-substack">publications</a> that moved and are <a href="https://randsinrepose.com/archives/welcome-to-ghost">glad they did</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘How to Leave Substack’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/03/how-to-leave-substack">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Google Reverses Course, Will Keep goo.gl Links Redirecting</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.google/technology/developers/googl-link-shortening-update/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wi2" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/03/google-reverses-course-on-googl" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42122</id>
	<published>2025-08-03T16:40:16Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-03T16:40:17Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Google:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>While we <a href="https://developers.googleblog.com/en/google-url-shortener-links-will-no-longer-be-available/">previously announced</a> discontinuing support for all
goo.gl URLs after August 25, 2025, we’ve adjusted our approach in
order to preserve actively used links. We understand these links
are embedded in countless documents, videos, posts and more, and
we appreciate the input received.</p>

<p>Nine months ago, we redirected URLs that showed no activity in
late 2024 to a message specifying that the link would be
deactivated in August, and these are the only links targeted to be
deactivated. If you get a message that states, “This link will no
longer work in the near future”, the link won’t work after August
25 and we recommend transitioning to another URL shortener if you
haven’t already.</p>

<p>All other goo.gl links will be preserved and will continue to
function as normal. To check if your link will be retained, visit
the link today. If your link redirects you without a message, it
will continue to work.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Nice!</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Google Reverses Course, Will Keep goo.gl Links Redirecting’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/03/google-reverses-course-on-googl">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/08/the_substack_branding_and_faux_prestige_trap" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wi1" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42121</id>
	<published>2025-08-02T21:11:44Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-03T02:37:20Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Only with Substack does anyone perceive creator branding as being subservient to the platform — something that ought to be seen merely as an interchangeable CMS.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Among the handful of oft-discussed problems with Substack:</p>

<ul>
<li>Their 90/10 subscription revenue split isn’t usurious, but it’s <a href="https://www.mollywhite.net/micro/entry/202504111009">high compared to competing platforms</a> — especially once you reach an even mid-tier level of popularity.</li>
<li>The only way this independent publishing game works, by any credible definition of “the long run”, is to build your own audience. Substack has indies convinced that they build an audience for you through some sort of secret-sauce network effects, but I’ve seen no evidence that’s true. Writers with established reputations and readerships joining Substack are helping build Substack’s brand, not their own.</li>
<li>The whole, you know, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/02/substack-nazi-notification">Nazi thing</a>.</li>
</ul>

<p>Less commented upon but just as bad is the branding trap. <em>Substack</em> is a damn good name. It looks good, it sounds good. It’s short and crisp and unique. But now they’ve gotten people to call publications on Substack not “blogs” or “newsletters” but “substacks”. <a href="https://www.anildash.com/2024/11/19/dont_call_it_a_substack/">Don’t call them that</a>. And <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2024/11/regarding_and_well_against_substack">as I griped back in December</a>, even the way almost all Substack publications <em>look</em> is deliberately, if subtly, <em>Substack</em>-branded, not per-publication or per-writer branded.</p>

<p>Consider Paul Krugman. Krugman was an op-ed columnist for The New York Times from 2000–2024. But last year the Times wanted to cut him back from writing two columns a week plus his Times-hosted blog/newsletter to writing just one column per week and killing the blog. In <a href="https://www.cjr.org/analysis/paul-krugman-leaving-new-york-times-heavy-hand-editing-less-frequent-columns-newsletter.php">an interview with Columbia Journalism Review</a> early this year, Krugman also revealed that after over two decades, he’d started butting heads with his editors over style, tone, and even subject matter:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“I’ve always been very, very lightly edited on the column,” he
said. “And that stopped being the case. The editing became
extremely intrusive. It was very much toning down of my voice,
toning down of the feel, and a lot of pressure for what I
considered false equivalence.” And, increasingly, attempts “to
dictate the subject.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So Krugman rightfully and righteously told the Times, politely, to fuck off and struck out on his own. Reading Krugman this year, on his own site, has been like rediscovering <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mexican_Coke">cane sugar Coca-Cola</a> after drinking the cheaper-to-produce corn syrup variant for a few years. This is <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZG9ip5ZOO9s">The Real Thing</a> — the unadulterated tart-tongued and sharp-elbowed Krugman I remember devouring during both the Bush and Obama administrations. The only hitch: Krugman hung out his independent shingle at Substack — which makes it a shingle under a shingle.</p>

<p>My suspicion is that for a certain class of writers and media commentators who, heretofore, have spent their careers at big-name publications — newspapers and magazines dating back to the print era, TV networks from the cable-is-king era — they actually find comfort writing under the auspices of Substack. See also: Terry Moran, who <a href="https://terrymoran.substack.com/">bounced to Substack</a> after ABC News declined to renew his contract — despite 28 years at the network, including <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/04/trump-declaration">this recent classic</a> — because of a tweet decrying Donald Trump and White House ghoul Stephen Miller. I suspect Moran, and perhaps even Krugman, perceive Substack as conveying a sort of badge of legitimacy. Self-published books, for example, used to be the refuge of kooks and no-talent hacks. I think some who spent their careers working at prestige outlets — especially those like Krugman and Moran, who are a bit older (than me) — feel a bit naked without one. But there’s no real prestige at Substack and never will be. I, for one, am fine with Substack’s liberal philosophy of letting anyone write there, but that means, well, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/02/substack-nazi-notification">anyone</a> can write there.</p>

<p>Here’s a recent example of the Substack branding trap that irks me — grating like fingernails on a chalkboard — and which I think proves my point. <a href="https://www.npr.org/transcripts/nx-s1-5464923">Krugman last month was interviewed by Steve Inskeep at NPR</a>, regarding Trump’s “grotesquely illegal” tariffs levied on Brazil. Introducing Krugman, Inskeep describes Krugman’s current work thus:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The people watching the tariff debate include Paul Krugman. He is
a writer and economist, formerly for The New York Times, now
writing independently on Substack, which is where I often find
him. And since he’s in the United States, I pay no tariff. Mr.
Krugman, welcome to the program.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So far, so good. That’s a fair description. But, concluding the five-minute interview, Inskeep goes with this:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Paul Krugman writes for Substack, formerly with The New York
Times. Thanks so much.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Paul Krugman does not “write for Substack”. No one would say that <a href="https://sixcolors.com/">Jason Snell</a> “writes for WordPress”, or that <a href="https://kottke.org/">Jason Kottke</a> or yours truly “writes for Movable Type”. No one says <a href="https://www.citationneeded.news/">Molly White</a>, <a href="https://www.platformer.news/">Casey Newton</a>, or <a href="https://www.cupofcoffeenews.com/">Craig Calcaterra</a> “writes for Ghost”, or that <a href="https://www.status.news/">Oliver Darcy</a> “writes for Beehiiv”. Only with Substack does anyone perceive creator branding as being subservient to the platform — something that ought to be seen merely as an interchangeable CMS — like that.</p>

<p>That is not by happenstance. It’s a trap and it is by design. It’s exactly what Substack wants, and exactly what independent writers and content producers should not.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ The Substack Branding and Faux Prestige Trap</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Ana Marie Cox on the Shaky Foundation of Substack as a Business</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://newsletter.anamariecox.com/archive/substack-did-not-see-that-coming/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wi0" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/02/cox-substack" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42120</id>
	<published>2025-08-02T15:14:47Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-02T15:36:15Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Ana Marie Cox, <a href="https://www.anamariecox.com/about-me">who knows a thing or two</a> about indie publishing and journalism, on her AMC All the Time blog about a month ago:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>My take is more dire, because I’m not sure about “savvy and
stamina” as the distinguishing characteristics of those who might
be able to migrate elsewhere. I think plenty of smart folks might
find themselves stuck.</p>

<p>Substack is rickety. It’s as unstable as a SpaceX launch, as
<a href="https://www.yahoo.com/news/dems-taunt-stephen-miller-over-191520373.html">overpromised</a> as a Stephen Miller marriage.</p>

<p>Substack does not have a clear future as a newsletter business,
I’m not the first to notice that. But it doesn’t have to fail
outright to be a disaster. It just has to keep trying to become a
life-sized map of the internet: maximum content, maximum churn.
The center cannot hold — especially not for newsletters, a format
that depends on intimacy and long-standing trust.</p>

<p>The Substack bust will not just take out a few hot-take merchants
and media dilettantes. It’s going to take down a lot of working
journalists who’ve built modest, sustainable incomes as well as
the fragile public sphere we’ve been piecing together in the ashes
of Twitter and the twilight of traditional journalism.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.usermag.co/p/substack-sent-a-push-alert-promoting-nazi-white-supremacist-blog">Taylor Lorenz’s scoop</a> today on <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/02/substack-nazi-notification">Substack’s Nazi notification oopsie</a> reminded me that I’ve been meaning to link to this post from Cox casting a serious stink eye at Substack’s business. As she says up front, “Let’s set Substack’s ‘Nazi problem’ aside for a moment. What if the bigger issue is being stranded on a collapsing platform ... with a bunch of Nazis?”</p>

<p>Substack pitches itself to would-be independent writers as a thriving platform that’s fundamentally about independent blog publishing and email newsletter distribution. That could be a great business. But it would be a relatively small business compared to Substack’s fund raising (over $100 million so far, and currently <a href="https://www.newcomer.co/p/scoop-substack-in-talks-to-raise?utm_source=anamariecox&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=substack-did-not-see-that-coming">looking to raise more</a>) and the implied valuation that fund raising implies (at one point, they were pitching investors that they were worth $1 billion, which is about as realistic as El Gringo Loco Anaranjado’s promises that Mexico will pay for a US border wall).</p>

<p><a href="https://ghost.org/">Ghost</a> is a platform and business that’s actually built for independent writers. So is <a href="https://buttondown.com/">Buttondown</a> (which Cox uses for her site). <a href="https://www.beehiiv.com/">Beehiiv</a> too. There’s a whole cottage industry of creator-oriented blog-cum-newsletter platforms. Substack, on the other hand, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2024/11/regarding_and_well_against_substack">is a trap</a>. It breaks my heart to see great writers as disparate as <a href="https://paulkrugman.substack.com/">Paul Krugman</a> and <a href="https://open.substack.com/pub/michaelchabon/p/tragic-magic">Michael Chabon</a> set up their ostensibly independent presences on Substack. Writers check in, but — if Substack gets their way — <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jKhGHxO-woc">they won’t check out</a>.</p>

<p>Looking at the numbers Cox lays out, Substack’s future looks even worse than I thought. Before they go under, though, their investors will put the screws to them, and Substack will take its heel turn.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Ana Marie Cox on the Shaky Foundation of Substack as a Business’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/02/cox-substack">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Substack Sends Notification Promoting Nazi Blog</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2025/07/substacks-nazi-problem-wont-go-away-after-push-notification-apology/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/whz" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/02/substack-nazi-notification" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42119</id>
	<published>2025-08-02T13:46:12Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-02T14:56:23Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Ashley Belanger, writing for Ars Technica:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>After Substack shocked an unknown number of users by sending a
push notification on Monday to check out a Nazi blog featuring a
swastika icon, the company quickly apologized for the “error,”
<a href="https://www.usermag.co/p/substack-sent-a-push-alert-promoting-nazi-white-supremacist-blog">tech columnist Taylor Lorenz reported</a>. [...]</p>

<p>Substack has long faced backlash for allowing users to share their
“extreme views” on the platform, previously claiming that
“censorship (including through demonetizing publications)” doesn’t
make “the problem go away — in fact, it makes it worse,” Lorenz
noted. But critics who have slammed Substack’s rationale revived
their concerns this week, with some accusing Substack of promoting
extreme content through features like their push alerts and
“rising” lists, which flag popular newsletters and currently also
include Nazi blogs.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://gizmodo.com/substack-sends-push-alert-for-nazi-newsletter-2000636663">Gizmodo reports</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The publication in question, NatSocToday, <a href="https://substack.com/@natsoctoday1">describes itself</a>
as a “National Socialist weekly newsletter featuring opinions and
news important to the National Socialist and White Nationalist
Community.” The newsletter’s image header is a Nazi flag, and its
latest post, as of Wednesday, was <a href="https://substack.com/@natsoctoday1/p-169055191">an article</a> that includes
the sentence: “We demand the return of all territory currently
occupied by jews and non-Whites in historically White homelands.”
It does not appear to be a particularly popular blog, and
currently has fewer than a thousand subscribers.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A mantra  of “<em>we host all views, but don’t promote or endorse all views</em>” doesn’t hold much water when you promote a blog whose logo is a straight-up Nazi swastika.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Substack Sends Notification Promoting Nazi Blog’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/02/substack-nazi-notification">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Talk Show: ‘Michigan-Starred Fine Dining’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2025/07/31/ep-428" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/why" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/01/the-talk-show-428" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42118</id>
	<published>2025-08-01T16:41:52Z</published>
	<updated>2025-08-01T16:42:00Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Special guest Louie Mantia joins the show to talk about Liquid Glass, the various OS 26 updates, and the worrisome state of Apple’s UI design overall. Also: sandwiches. </p>

<p><audio
    src = "https://traffic.libsyn.com/secure/daringfireball/thetalkshow-428-louie-mantia.mp3"
    controls
    preload = "none"
/></p>

<p><strong>Sponsored by:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://bzgapps.com/quip">Quip</a>: A supercharged clipboard manager and text expander for Mac, iPhone, and iPad.</li>
<li><a href="https://notion.com/talkshow">Notion</a>: The best AI tool for work, with your notes, docs, and projects in one space.</li>
<li><a href="https://squarespace.com/talkshow">Squarespace</a>: Save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain using code <strong>talkshow</strong>.</li>
</ul>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Talk Show: ‘Michigan-Starred Fine Dining’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/08/01/the-talk-show-428">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple Files Vigorous Response to DOJ Lawsuit: ’Threatens the Very Principles That Set iPhone Apart’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/07/29/apple-doj-lawsuit-answer-iphone/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/whx" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/31/apple-responds-to-dog" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42117</id>
	<published>2025-07-31T14:57:26Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-31T19:42:43Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Chance Miller, 9to5Mac:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple has <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2024/05/21/apple-questions-validity-of-doj-antitrust-lawsuit-in-bid-to-dismiss-case/">voiced</a> its <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2024/05/02/tim-cook-doj-antitrust-apple-misguided/">opposition</a> to the
<a href="https://9to5mac.com/2024/03/21/doj-lawsuit-is-an-attempt-to-turn-the-iphone-into-android-apple-alleges/">case</a> many <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2024/03/21/apple-says-doj-lawsuit-threatens-who-we-are-as-it-vows-to-vigorously-defend-against-it/">times</a> over the last year. Now, it has
officially filed its answer to the DOJ’s antitrust complaint,
pushing back forcefully against the allegations.</p>

<p>As a refresher, the DOJ’s antitrust lawsuit focuses on five major
aspects of the iPhone experience: super apps, cloud streaming
games, third-party messaging apps, third-party smartwatches, and
third-party digital wallets. In today’s filing, Apple says the DOJ
“fundamentally misunderstands” those five things.</p>

<p>Apple outlines:</p>

<ul>
<li>DOJ says Apple stifles the success of “super apps,” despite the
fact that Apple’s rules allow and support such apps, and indeed
a multitude of “super apps” exist on the App Store today.</li>
<li>DOJ says Apple blocks cloud streaming games, even though Apple
allows streaming games both over the web and in the App Store
where they can stream games directly to users.</li>
<li>DOJ says Apple degrades third-party messaging apps, even though
they are widely available and enormously popular on iPhone
already.</li>
<li>DOJ says Apple limits the functionality of third-party
smartwatches, even though they can effectively pair with iPhone,
share data to and from the iPhone via a companion app, and take
advantage of certain functionalities Apple has developed, which
are expanding over time.</li>
<li>DOJ says Apple withholds access to iPhone hardware necessary for
third-party digital wallets to use tap-to-pay technology;
however, Apple developed and provides a mechanism that protects
user security.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>One part of Apple’s defense that seems mostly proven already is that this industry moves fast and the competitive landscape is always changing. I’d say three of the DOJ’s five main arguments are already stale: Apple has since opened up cloud gaming; third-party messaging apps can now be set as default; and tap-to-pay has been opened up. And I think the other two points, on “super apps” and third-party connected devices like watches, are nonsense. Especially <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2022/10/everything">the “super apps” thing</a>.</p>

<p>Miller, of course, embeds Apple’s full response at the bottom of his post. The argument is worth a read — it’s very cogently and plainly written.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Files Vigorous Response to DOJ Lawsuit: ’Threatens the Very Principles That Set iPhone Apart’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/31/apple-responds-to-dog">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Zuckerberg on ‘Personal Superintelligence’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.meta.com/superintelligence/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/whw" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/31/zuckerberg-personal-superintelligence" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42116</id>
	<published>2025-07-31T14:49:22Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-31T19:39:11Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Mark Zuckerberg, concluding a 600-word essay ostentatiously typeset in the style of web pages circa 1994<sup>*</sup>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Meta believes strongly in building personal superintelligence that
empowers everyone. We have the resources and the expertise to
build the massive infrastructure required, and the capability and
will to deliver new technology to billions of people across our
products. I’m excited to focus Meta’s efforts towards building
this future.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>What about the metaverse? Wasn’t that the thing? What Zuckerberg, and thus Meta, actually believe strongly in is jumping on whatever trend becomes a hype bubble. The company’s soul is empty.</p>

<p><small>* Actual web pages from 1994 didn’t include nearly a megabyte of JavaScript to display 3 kilobytes of text.</small></p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Zuckerberg on ‘Personal Superintelligence’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/31/zuckerberg-personal-superintelligence">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/07/tea_number_3_app_store" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/whv" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42115</id>
	<published>2025-07-30T18:17:13Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-30T22:34:07Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Tea remains a chart-topping app in the App Store, but isn’t listed at all in Play Store top lists.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Tea remains <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/charts/iphone/top-free-apps/36">#3 overall in the US iPhone App Store</a>. Here’s a <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/07/us-iphone-app-store-top-10-2025-07-30.png">screenshot of the top free iPhone apps today</a>, and a list of the current top 10, using the full names the apps choose to display:</p>

<ol>
<li>ChatGPT</li>
<li>Wingstop</li>
<li>Tea Dating Advice</li>
<li>Threads</li>
<li>Google</li>
<li>Google Maps</li>
<li>WhatsApp Messenger</li>
<li>ParentSquare</li>
<li>CapCut - Video Editor</li>
<li>TikTok - Videos, Shop &amp; LIVE</li>
</ol>

<p>I might be forgetting or unaware of previous similar situations, but I can’t recall anything like this before, where an app riddled with <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/28/tea-breach-worsens">outrageous security/privacy vulnerabilities</a> remains virally popular. A Hacker News thread from earlier today <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=44732995">debates why the app is even still available on the App Store</a>.</p>

<p>So is it Apple’s place to yank the app? It feels wrong to me that Apple should completely remove Tea from the App Store, but it’s also true that one of Apple’s fundamental pitches for the App Store — and the App Store’s exclusivity for app distribution in most of the world — is that iOS users can trust any and all apps in the App Store because they’re vetted by Apple. But here’s Tea, sitting at #3, providing a service that many women want, and the entire thing is shockingly untrustworthy. (I fully expect more vulnerabilities to be found and exploited.)</p>

<p>Tea, unsurprisingly, has almost nothing on <a href="https://www.teaforwomen.com/">their website</a> about the security violations their users have suffered, nor any mention in their App Store listing. Their only public acknowledgement of the fiasco is a series of three Instagram posts on July <a href="https://www.instagram.com/theteapartygirls/p/DMjRl4CPE0z/">26</a>, <a href="https://www.instagram.com/theteapartygirls/p/DMl3E0TvoML/">27</a>, and <a href="https://www.instagram.com/theteapartygirls/p/DMrGSlrJA-e/">29</a> (the most recent of which acknowledges that they’ve completely disabled the DM feature “temporarily”), and <a href="https://www.teaforwomen.com/cyberincident">this FAQ</a> on their website, that, as far as I can tell, is only discoverable through the “links in bio” on their Instagram profile. Their FAQ only addresses the initial discovery from last week, not <a href="https://www.404media.co/a-second-tea-breach-reveals-users-dms-about-abortions-and-cheating/">the more significant one that 404 Media publicized Monday</a> that included the exposure of DMs.</p>

<p>Also fascinating to me is that Tea, though available on both iOS <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.tea.tea&amp;hl=en_US&amp;gl=US">and Android</a>, is seemingly not popular at all on Android. It’s not even listed <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps?hl=en_US">in the Play Store’s top free apps</a>. (The Play Store website lists only the top 45, but I scrolled through the entire top 200 on my Pixel.) The current Play Store top 10:</p>

<ol>
<li>ChatGPT</li>
<li>TikTok - Videos, Shop &amp; LIVE</li>
<li>Threads</li>
<li>WhatsApp Messenger</li>
<li>Temu: Shop Like a Billionaire</li>
<li>Instagram</li>
<li>TikTok Lite - Faster TikTok</li>
<li>DramaBox - Stream Drama Shorts</li>
<li>Cash App</li>
<li>Snapchat</li>
</ol>

<p>More tellingly, Tea doesn’t even crack the Play Store top 200 list for the “Dating” category. (On iOS, it’s in the “Lifestyle” category, but on the Play Store it’s in the “Dating” and “Casual” categories. Perhaps Apple requires apps in the “Dating” category to be full-fledged dating app services, not dating-app-adjacent like Tea.)</p>

<p>I’m not sure what explains the disparity in Tea’s popularity by platform. One assumption is that dating is more of a young person’s game, and young people skew slightly more toward iPhone than the US population overall. But from what I can tell, that skew is only about 10 percent. Also, surveys suggest <a href="https://www.sci-tech-today.com/stats/iphone-vs-android-user-statistics/">women are more likely to be iPhone users</a>. But I can’t believe that age or gender demographics alone explain why Tea is #3 in the App Store but doesn’t even crack the top 200 on Android.</p>

<p>I strongly suspect that, although Google hasn’t removed Tea from the Play Store, they’ve delisted it from discovery other than by searching for it by name or following a direct link to its listing. That both jibes with what I’m seeing on the Play Store top lists, and strikes me as a thoughtful balance between the responsibilities of an app store provider. As egregious as Tea’s security exploits have been, removing the app entirely doesn’t seem called for. But delisting it from popularity lists seems like a measured way to discourage new users from trying it unless they’re specifically looking for it. If this is what Google is doing, Apple should follow their lead. (I’ve put in a question to Google’s PR inquiring about this; if/when I get an answer, I’ll update this article.)</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Tea, the Women’s Dating Gossip App Riddled With Security Vulnerabilities, Remains #3 on the US iPhone App Store</title></entry><entry>
	<title>YouTube Is Rolling Out an Age-Estimation Algorithm to Identify US Teens</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/07/29/youtube-rolls-out-age-estimatation-tech-to-identify-u-s-teens-and-apply-additional-protections/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/whu" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/30/youtube-teen-age-estimation" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42114</id>
	<published>2025-07-30T15:24:39Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-30T15:24:39Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Sarah Perez, TechCrunch:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>YouTube on Tuesday announced it’s beginning to roll out
age-estimation technology in the U.S. to identify teen users in
order to provide a more age-appropriate experience. The company
says it will use a variety of signals to determine the users’
possible age, regardless of what the user entered as their
birthday when they signed up for an account.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Well-intentioned though I think this is, it still feels more than a little dystopian.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘YouTube Is Rolling Out an Age-Estimation Algorithm to Identify US Teens’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/30/youtube-teen-age-estimation">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Sony Sues Tencent for Allegedly Ripping Off ‘Horizon’ Video Games</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.reuters.com/legal/litigation/sony-sues-tencent-allegedly-ripping-off-horizon-video-games-2025-07-28/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wht" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/29/sony-sues-tencent" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42113</id>
	<published>2025-07-29T20:41:18Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-29T20:41:18Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Reuters:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Sony released the first game in the <em>Horizon</em> series, <em>Horizon:
Zero Dawn</em>, on its PlayStation 4 in 2017. The games follow a
red-headed woman named Aloy as she navigates a post-apocalyptic
world populated by human tribes and robotic animals.</p>

<p>Sony said in its complaint that it declined an offer from Tencent
to collaborate on a new <em>Horizon</em> game last year. Tencent later
announced <em>Light of Motiram</em>, which Sony said features identical
gameplay, story themes and artistic elements to <em>Horizon</em> as well
as many other similarities.</p>

<p>Sony said that video game journalists have characterized <em>Light of
Motiram</em> as a “knock-off” of <em>Horizon</em>, including one who called
the game <em>Horizon Zero Originality</em>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Tencent is the Chinese software giant behind, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tencent">amongst many other things</a>, WeChat, China’s “everything app”.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Sony Sues Tencent for Allegedly Ripping Off ‘Horizon’ Video Games’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/29/sony-sues-tencent">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The E-Book Editions of Timothy Snyder’s ‘On Tyranny’ Are Just $2</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://books.apple.com/us/book/on-tyranny/id1195458571" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/whs" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/29/snyder-on-tyranny-two-bucks" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42112</id>
	<published>2025-07-29T20:09:43Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-29T20:09:58Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Back in March <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/24/on-tyranny">I linked to and recommended</a> Timothy Snyder’s <em><a href="https://timothysnyder.org/on-tyranny/">On Tyranny</a></em>, a cogent collection of 20 short essays. I was never a big e-book reader, both because I love printed books so much and because I welcome any respite from reading on screens of any sort. But if e-books are your thing, note that <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/24/on-tyranny">Apple Books currently has it for just $2</a>. Amazon’s <a href="https://amzn.to/3UypaaG">Kindle edition is also $2</a> — and the paperback edition, which is the lovely little thing I own, <a href="https://amzn.to/4mizwHA">is an oddly but low-priced $7.31</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The E-Book Editions of Timothy Snyder’s ‘On Tyranny’ Are Just $2’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/29/snyder-on-tyranny-two-bucks">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Amazon Is Selling M4 MacBook Airs for $200 Off</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://amzn.to/4fdd0gN" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/whr" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/29/amazon-m4-macbook-airs" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42111</id>
	<published>2025-07-29T16:32:11Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-29T16:32:36Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>These prices — which I presume are a back-to-school season promotion — are even lower than those during the weeklong “Prime Day” <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/07/make_me_rich_on_amazon_prime_day">earlier this month</a>, and you don’t need to be a Prime subscriber to get them:</p>

<ul>
<li>The pretty-good base configuration (16 GB RAM, 256 GB storage) <a href="https://amzn.to/4fdd0gN">is just $800</a>.</li>
<li>The configuration with <a href="https://amzn.to/40HrhfR">16 GB RAM and 512 GB is $1,000</a>, the normal price for the base model.</li>
<li>You can splurge and get <a href="https://amzn.to/3U4PgSC">24 GB RAM with 512 GB storage for just $1,200</a>.</li>
</ul>

<p>These are make-me-rich affiliate links, as is <a href="https://amzn.to/456bngj">this link for AirPods Pro 2 for just $200</a>, $50 off.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Amazon Is Selling M4 MacBook Airs for $200 Off’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/29/amazon-m4-macbook-airs">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Microsoft Introduces ‘Copilot Mode’ in Edge</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blogs.windows.com/msedgedev/2025/07/28/introducing-copilot-mode-in-edge-a-new-way-to-browse-the-web/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/whq" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/29/copilot-mode-in-microsoft-edge" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42110</id>
	<published>2025-07-29T16:05:06Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-29T16:08:42Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Sean Lyndersay, general manager of Edge at Microsoft:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>For decades, the way we’ve used browsers has remained linear: open
a tab (or 20), search for something, read a page, repeat. It’s a
model that’s worked well, but it hasn’t fundamentally changed.
Until now. As AI begins to reshape nearly every facet of digital
life, we’re witnessing a turning point in how we interact with the
web. Now, it’s worth asking: is your browser working for you as
much as it should?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Color me skeptical about the idea that my web browser should be “working for me”, rather than serving as a tool for me to work with. The AI hype cycle is pointing to a future where automated agentic web browsers surf automated AI-generated websites. Robots consuming robot-generated content — an infinite loop of AI onanism.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This is why today we’re excited to launch Copilot Mode, a new
experimental mode in Microsoft Edge, and our next step towards
building a more powerful way to pilot the web.</p>

<p>With Copilot Mode on, you enable innovative AI features in Edge
that enhance your browser. It doesn’t just wait idly for you to
click but anticipates what you might want to do next. It doesn’t
just give you endless tabs to sift through but works with you as a
collaborator that makes sense of it all. It keeps you browsing,
cuts through clutter and removes friction to unlock your flow — all built to the highest Microsoft standards of security, privacy
and performance trusted by billions of people and businesses
worldwide — with you as the user always in control.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Microsoft is famously known for presenting interfaces that “cut through clutter” and “remove friction”. I’m sure this will be great.</p>

<p>I am reminded of the decade-ago <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2013/01/29/hbo-netflix">Netflix strategy espoused by Ted Sarandos</a>: “The goal is to become HBO faster than HBO can become us.” I think something similar is behind Microsoft trying to make Copilot front-and-center in Edge, and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/29/chrome-ai-shopping">Google’s concurrent move to junk up Chrome</a> with AI-generated suggestions. Their goal is to make their web browsers chatbots faster than OpenAI can make ChatGPT a web browser.</p>

<p>HBO is still around. It even just <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/14/hbo-max-again">got its name back</a>. But Netflix won that race.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Microsoft Introduces ‘Copilot Mode’ in Edge’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/29/copilot-mode-in-microsoft-edge">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Google Chrome Adds AI-Generated Store Summaries</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/07/28/google-chrome-adds-ai-powered-store-summaries-to-help-u-s-shoppers/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/whp" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/29/chrome-ai-shopping" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42109</id>
	<published>2025-07-29T15:10:01Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-29T16:57:07Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Sarah Perez, writing for TechCrunch:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Google on Monday announced an update to its Chrome web browser
that will introduce AI-generated store reviews to U.S. shoppers
with the aim of helping to determine the best places to make a
purchase. The feature, which will be available by clicking an icon
just to the left of the web address in the browser, will display a
pop-up that informs consumers about the store’s reputation for
things like product quality, shopping, pricing, customer service,
and returns.</p>

<p>The feature, which is currently available only in English, will
generate the summaries based on reviews from partners, including
Bazaarvoice, Bizrate Insights, Reputation.com, Reseller Ratings,
ScamAdviser, Trustpilot, TurnTo, Yotpo, Verified Reviews, <a href="https://support.google.com/merchants/answer/190657?hl=en#Supported_Review_Partners">and
others</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I have never heard of a single one of these “partners”. It’s bad enough that so many web pages themselves are increasingly covered with distracting junk, much of it AI-generated slop. But now browsers themselves will be adding their own layers of distracting cruft atop the websites. The entire premise of Chrome — the reason for its name — is that it was originally designed to simplify the UI of the browser app itself, the “chrome”, at a time when Internet Explorer and even Firefox were increasingly cluttered and confusing. I feel like this is a sign that Chrome is completely losing its way — AI-generated slop from the browser layered atop AI-generated slop in the underlying web pages.</p>

<p>Dare Obasanjo, on Bluesky, <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/carnage4life.bsky.social/post/3lv2vvzlbd22o">takes this news credulously</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Google Chrome is now going to provide AI generated summaries of
online stores covering topics like customer service, product
quality, shipping, pricing and return policy.</p>

<p>This is on the heels of Microsoft Edge announcing Copilot mode
earlier today. Apple’s Safari is being left behind in the AI wars.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I would argue that Safari is looking ever more like a proverbial glass of ice water in hell. These Chrome AI overviews (Chrome is also, for example, going to start presenting its own <a href="https://www.seroundtable.com/google-business-profiles-menu-ai-summaries-39838.html">AI-generated menu summaries for restaurants</a>) don’t seem like user-centric features to me. They seem like features designed to turn the dial up on Google’s slice of commissions from web transactions.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Google Chrome Adds AI-Generated Store Summaries’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/29/chrome-ai-shopping">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Security Breach at Tea Worsens, Revealing Users’ DMs About Abortions and Cheating</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.404media.co/a-second-tea-breach-reveals-users-dms-about-abortions-and-cheating/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/who" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/28/tea-breach-worsens" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42108</id>
	<published>2025-07-29T02:09:10Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-30T15:39:13Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Emanuel Maiberg and Joseph Cox, reporting <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/26/4chan-tea-breach">again</a> for 404 Media:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Despite Tea’s initial statement that “the incident involved a
legacy data storage system containing information from over two
years ago,” the second issue impacting a separate database is much
more recent, affecting messages up until last week, according to
the researcher’s findings that 404 Media verified. The researcher
said they also found the ability to send a push notification to
all of Tea’s users.</p>

<p>It’s hard to overstate how sensitive this data is and how it could
put Tea’s users at risk if it fell into the wrong hands. When
signing up, Tea encourages users to choose an anonymous
screenname, but it was trivial for 404 Media to find the real
world identities of some users given the nature of their messages,
which Tea has led them to believe were private. Users could be
easily found via their social media handles, phone numbers, and
real names that they shared in these chats. These conversations
also frequently make damning accusations against people who are
also named in the private messages and in some cases are easy to
identify. [...]</p>

<p>Some of the private messages viewed by 404 Media include:</p>

<ul>
<li>One user tells another they just discovered their husband on the
app being discussed. “I am his wife,” many of the messages say.</li>
<li>Another appears to show a woman contacting others about a man
she is engaged to.</li>
<li>Multiple messages which appear to show women discussing their
abortions.</li>
<li>Chat logs between women discovering they are dating the same
man, exchanging information such as what car he drives for
verification.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>When <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/26/4chan-tea-breach">I linked to 404 Media’s coverage</a> of the initial breach at Tea the other day, I wrote, “I’m not accusing Tea in particular of being vibe-coded”. Well, I still don’t know if Tea’s service architecture was vibe-coded, but it’s now clear that whoever made it was shamefully incompetent. They shouldn’t have made <em>any</em> sort of services backend, let alone one like Tea’s that’s intended to carry incredibly sensitive personal information and messages.</p>

<p>This is an outright privacy — and quite possibly, personal security — disaster. With the abortion discussions and the current bifurcation of women’s rights here in the US, it could be a legal disaster, too. 4chan clowns have taken the images and data and <a href="https://knowyourmeme.com/editorials/guides/whats-going-on-with-the-tea-app-data-leak-the-tea-app-map-and-memes-about-ranking-foids-on-teaspill-explained">created</a> maps of Tea users’ addresses, and a Mark-Zuckerberg-“Facemash”-style site for ranking users’ appearance.</p>

<p>For women who’ve already signed up and started using Tea, I doubt there’s anything that can be done to remove them from exposure. Even if Tea offers a “delete your account” feature, I wouldn’t trust that it actually deletes <em>anything</em> from their database, let alone everything. And the cat’s already out of the bag for any bad actors who figured out this second exploit before Tea was alerted.</p>

<p>Yet another data point for the argument that any “private messaging” feature that doesn’t use E2EE isn’t actually private at all.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Security Breach at Tea Worsens, Revealing Users’ DMs About Abortions and Cheating’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/28/tea-breach-worsens">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Republican Election Group Is Attempting to Organize Against Text Message Filtering in iOS 26</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://politicalwire.com/2025/07/28/republicans-say-apple-update-will-hurt-fundraising/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/whm" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/28/nrsc-letter-ios-26" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42106</id>
	<published>2025-07-28T20:46:59Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-28T22:44:01Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>From <a href="https://punchbowl.news/article/senate/nrsc-apple-ios-fundraising/">this paywalled report at Punchbowl News</a>, as quoted by Taegan Goddard at Political Wire:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The Senate GOP campaign arm <a href="https://punchbowl.news/nrsc-letter/">is warning</a> that Apple’s new
iOS update could cost them $25 million in fundraising revenue, as
well as priceless GOTV opportunities,” <a href="https://punchbowl.news/archive/72825-midday-2/">Punchbowl News</a>
reports.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/07/nrsc-letter-ios-26.jpeg">Here’s a copy of the original memo from the NRSC</a> (National Republican Senatorial Committee). What they’re freaking out about is the new iOS 26 Messages feature (which will be available in Messages on iPadOS and MacOS 26 too — but because these messages are sent as SMS and because the iPhone is so many people’s primary or sole messaging device, it’s the platform they’re focusing on) <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/07/03/ios-26s-messages-app-has-a-solution-coming-for-unwanted-texts/">that will automatically sort messages from unknown senders</a> into a new “Unknown Sender” inbox.</p>

<p>Quoting from <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/07/nrsc-letter-ios-26.jpeg">the NRSC letter</a> (emphasis in original):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple’s iOS 26 update introduces aggressive message filtering.
Political texts — even from verified and compliant senders-will
be treated as spam by default, silently sent to an “Unknown” inbox
with no alerts or notifications. That change has profound
implications for our ability to fundraise, mobilize voters, and
run digital campaigns.</p>

<p><em>It’s important to understand: Apple isn’t just targeting cold
outreach or spammy actors.</em> Every political message — shortcode,
long code, doesn’t matter-gets pushed into the dark. The only
workaround-getting a voter to reply — is increasingly rare and
entirely at the mercy of Apple’s unclear rules. How will a voter
reply if they never get the message?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Apple’s “rules” for this new feature aren’t unclear at all. If a sender is not in your saved contacts and you’ve never sent or responded to a text message from them, they’re considered “unknown”. That’s it. The feature isn’t even really new — you’ve been able to <a href="https://support.apple.com/guide/iphone/block-filter-and-report-messages-iph203ab0be4/ios">filter messages like this in Messages for years now</a>, but what iOS 26 changes is that it now <s>will be on by default and</s> has a new more prominent — better, IMO — interface for switching between filter views. <strong>Update:</strong> I was wrong that this filtering will be on by default in iOS 26 — I was fooled because I had previously enabled “Filter Unknown Senders” in Settings → Apps → Messages → Unknown &amp; Spam (which you need to scroll down quite a bit to get to). I do think, though, that many more iOS users will be using this feature starting with iOS 26 — it’s both better designed and less hidden.</p>

<p>Back to the NRSC letter:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Here’s the shift in practice. Today, a voter with an iPhone gets
our message just like a normal text. In iOS 26, unless that
person has already replied, our message is silently sent to the
“Unknown” inbox. No ping, no badge, just buried in an inbox few
people ever check.</p>

<p>We’ve spent years complying with rigorous standards — providing full
documentation, opt-in proof, and message samples via Campaign
Verify and The Campaign Registry — yet Apple ignores that. <em>Carriers
respect it. Apple doesn’t.</em></p>

<p>Estimated prospecting losses: <em>NRSC alone could see a $25M+
revenue hit</em>. Since 70% of small-dollar donations come via text,
and iPhones make up 60% of US mobile devices, <em>the macro effect
could be over $500M in lost GOP revenue</em>. [...]</p>

<p>Unfortunately, K St and trade groups are asleep at the wheel.
Apple isn’t engaging. But we have only a few weeks left before the
public release. <em>If we’re going to push back, it has to be now. We
have a very narrow window to fix this.</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>“Unknown Senders” isn’t spam. It’s for ... unknown senders. Which these political texts are. I don’t know anyone who enjoys getting these texts in their primary timeline of messages. What the NRSC is asserting here is that they have a right to put political solicitations in your primary Messages view, and to have them appear as notifications, which is ridiculous.</p>

<p>Also, there’s no reason to believe that Republican candidates and groups will be more affected by this than Democratic ones. There’s no filtering by message content. It’s just a change to stop sending notifications for texts from unknown senders, and to put those messages in a separate timeline by default. People <em>will</em> check the Unknown Senders timeline occasionally too — all sorts of text messages from bots will go there, including some you want or need.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Republican Election Group Is Attempting to Organize Against Text Message Filtering in iOS 26’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/28/nrsc-letter-ios-26">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Adam Aaronson Drank Every Cocktail</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://aaronson.org/blog/i-drank-every-cocktail" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/whl" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/28/aaronson-cocktails" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42105</id>
	<published>2025-07-28T16:35:31Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-28T16:35:31Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Adam Aaronson:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The <a href="https://iba-world.com/">International Bartenders Association</a>, or IBA,
maintains a list of official cocktails, ones they deem to be
“the most requested recipes” at bars all around the world. It’s
the closest thing the bartending industry has to a canonical
list of cocktails, akin to the American Kennel Club’s registry
of <a href="https://www.akc.org/dog-breeds/">dog breeds</a> or a jazz musician’s <a href="https://99percentinvisible.org/episode/the-real-book/">Real Book</a> of
standards. [...]</p>

<p>As of 2025, there are 102 IBA official cocktails, and as of July
12, 2025, <a href="https://aaronson.org/cocktails/">I’ve had every one of them</a>.</p>

<p>The journey has taken me to some interesting places, and now that
it’s done, I have a little story to tell for each cocktail. I’m
not gonna tell you all 102 stories, but I do want to debrief the
experience. Drinking all 102 cocktails turned out to be
unexpectedly tricky, and for reasons you’ll soon understand, I
might be one of the first people in the world to do it.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Fun story, copiously documented with details, locations, photos, and sidenotes. Truly a blogger’s blog post.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Adam Aaronson Drank Every Cocktail’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/28/aaronson-cocktails">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry></feed><!-- THE END -->
