<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>Daring Fireball</title>
<subtitle>By John Gruber</subtitle>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/" />
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main" />
<id>https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main</id>


<updated>2026-02-26T00:03:50Z</updated><rights>Copyright © 2026, John Gruber</rights><entry>
	<title>‘H-Bomb: A Frank Lloyd Wright Typographic Mystery’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.inconspicuous.info/p/h-bomb-a-frank-lloyd-wright-typographic" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wxd" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/25/h-bomb-wright" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42673</id>
	<published>2026-02-25T23:53:00Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-25T23:53:08Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>When re-hanging signage, “Mind your P’s and Q’s” ought to be “Mind your H’s and S’s”.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘H-Bomb: A Frank Lloyd Wright Typographic Mystery’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/25/h-bomb-wright">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Terry Godier: ‘Phantom Obligation’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.terrygodier.com/phantom-obligation" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wxe" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/25/godier-phantom-obligation" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42674</id>
	<published>2026-02-25T23:52:42Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-25T23:52:42Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Terry Godier, in a thoughtful essay on the design of RSS feed readers:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>There’s a particular kind of guilt that visits me when I open my
feed reader after a few days away. It’s not the guilt of having
done something wrong, exactly. It’s more like the feeling of
walking into a room where people have been waiting for you, except
when you look around, the room is empty. There’s no one there.
There never was.</p>

<p>I’ve been thinking about this feeling for a long time. Longer
than I probably should, given that it concerns something as
mundane as reading articles on the internet. But I’ve come to
believe that these small, repeated experiences shape us more than
we like to admit.</p>

<p>So let me start with a question that’s been nagging at me: <em>why do
RSS readers look like email clients?</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>There are good answers to that question, and for 20-some years I’ve used a feed reader — <a href="https://netnewswire.com/">NetNewsWire</a> — that looks like an email client. (To be honest, I wish my email client looked and worked more like NetNewsWire.) But the bigger question Godier is asking is why don’t more feed readers trying something different?</p>

<p>He’s answered his own question with <a href="https://www.terrygodier.com/current">Current</a>, a new feed reader for iPhone, iPad, and Mac.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Terry Godier: ‘Phantom Obligation’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/25/godier-phantom-obligation">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Bill Gates Apologizes to Foundation Staff Over Epstein Ties</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/bill-gates-apologizes-to-foundation-staff-over-epstein-ties-67f39ef5" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wxc" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/25/gates-apologizes" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42672</id>
	<published>2026-02-25T23:38:45Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-25T23:38:46Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Emily Glazer, reporting for The Wall Street Journal:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The billionaire said he met with Epstein starting in 2011, years
after Epstein had pleaded guilty in 2008 to soliciting a minor for
prostitution. Gates said he was aware of some “18-month thing”
that had limited Epstein’s travel but said he didn’t properly
check his background. Gates said he continued meeting with Epstein
even after his then-wife Melinda French Gates expressed concerns
in 2013.</p>

<p>“Knowing what I know now makes it, you know, a hundred times worse
in terms of not only his crimes in the past, but now it’s clear
there was ongoing bad behavior,” Gates told staff. Speaking of his
ex-wife, he added: “To give her credit, she was always kind of
skeptical about the Epstein thing.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>“Kind of” is doing <a href="https://www.npr.org/2026/02/03/nx-s1-5697080/melinda-french-gates-reacts-to-ex-husband-bill-gates-being-mentioned-in-epstein-files">a lot of work</a> there.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Bill Gates Apologizes to Foundation Staff Over Epstein Ties’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/25/gates-apologizes">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Greg Knauss: ‘Lose Myself’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.eod.com/blog/2026/02/lose-myself/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wxb" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/25/knauss-lose-myself" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42671</id>
	<published>2026-02-25T22:53:08Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-25T22:53:09Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Greg Knauss:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>People will argue that speaking English to LLMs is just another
level of abstraction away from the physics of how the machine
<em>actually</em> works. And while that’s technically true — the worst
kind of true — it also misses the point. Industrialization
fundamentally changes things, by quantum degrees. A Ding Dong from
a factory is not the same thing as a <em>gâteau au chocolat et crème
chantilly</em> from a baker which is not the same thing as cramming
chunks of chocolate and scoops of whipped cream directly into your
mouth while standing in front of the fridge at 2:00am. The level
of care, of personalization, of intimacy — both given and taken — changes its nature. Digging a trench is a very different thing
than telling someone to dig a trench. Assembling a clock is a very
different thing than asking Siri for the time.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Splendid little essay.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Greg Knauss: ‘Lose Myself’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/25/knauss-lose-myself">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Talk Show: ‘Serious Opinionators’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2026/02/25/ep-441" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wxa" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/25/the-talk-show-441" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42670</id>
	<published>2026-02-25T22:17:57Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-25T22:17:57Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Adam Engst returns to the show to talk, in detail, about certain of the UI changes in iOS 26 and Apple’s version 26 OSes overall. In particular, the new Unified view in the Phone app, and the Filter pop-up menu in both the Phone and Messages apps. Also: a shoutout to <a href="https://512pixels.net/2020/09/kbase-week-balloon-help/">Balloon Help</a>.</p>

<p><audio
    src = "https://traffic.libsyn.com/secure/daringfireball/thetalkshow-441-adam-engst.mp3"
    controls
    preload = "none"
/></p>

<p><strong>Sponsored by:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://sentry.io/talkshow">Sentry</a>: A real-time error monitoring and tracing platform. Use code <strong>TALKSHOW</strong> for $80 in free credits.</li>
<li><a href="https://squarespace.com/talkshow">Squarespace</a>: Save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain using code <strong>talkshow</strong>.</li>
<li><a href="https://factormeals.com/talkshow50off">Factor</a>: Healthy eating, made easy. Get 50% off your first box, plus free breakfast for 1 year, with code <strong>talkshow50off</strong>.</li>
</ul>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Talk Show: ‘Serious Opinionators’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/25/the-talk-show-441">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Samsung Galaxy S26 Ultra’s Privacy Display</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://9to5google.com/2026/02/25/samsung-galaxy-s26-ultra-privacy-display-demo-hands-on/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wx9" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/25/samsung-galaxy-s26-ultras-privacy-display" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42669</id>
	<published>2026-02-25T20:59:30Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-25T23:40:40Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Ben Schoon, writing for 9to5 Google:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>When activated, Privacy Display changes how the pixels in your
display emit light, making it harder or near-impossible to view
the display at an off-angle. At its default setting, it definitely
works, but the contents of the display are visible at less-sharp
angles. Samsung has a “maximum” setting that takes this up a
notch, and that setting makes it even harder to see the contents
and narrows the field-of-view even further. [...]</p>

<p>A bigger deal, though, is that Samsung has built Privacy Display
with the ability to only apply to small portions of the Galaxy S26
Ultra’s display. Specifically, it can hide your notification
pop-ups. This part really impressed me, as Privacy Display is able
to specifically hide only that singular portion of the display,
and it does so nearly perfectly. The masking around the
notification ensures the content behind isn’t affected, and the
effect works incredibly well.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Neat feature, especially the way you can toggle it when needed, set it to auto-enable for specific apps, and/or work only for notifications.</p>

<p><strong>See also:</strong> <a href="https://www.theverge.com/tech/884337/samsung-galaxy-s26-ultra-privacy-display-price?view_token=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJpZCI6IjR6d0dhdzQ3YTMiLCJwIjoiL3RlY2gvODg0MzM3L3NhbXN1bmctZ2FsYXh5LXMyNi11bHRyYS1wcml2YWN5LWRpc3BsYXktcHJpY2UiLCJleHAiOjE3NzI0OTQ4MjksImlhdCI6MTc3MjA2MjgyOX0.D-a3LwOiw7KkzVO609iS31Da32v-B4YIj3uwKCbaafs">Allison Johnson at The Verge</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Samsung Galaxy S26 Ultra’s Privacy Display’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/25/samsung-galaxy-s26-ultras-privacy-display">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2026/02/my_2025_apple_report_card" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wx8" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026://1.42668</id>
	<published>2026-02-25T16:49:10Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-26T00:03:50Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">A mixed year.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>This week Jason Snell published his annual <a href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2026/02/2025reportcard/" title="Six Colors: “Apple in 2025: The Six Colors report card”">Six Colors Apple Report Card for 2025</a>. As I’ve done in the past — for the report-card years <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/02/my_2024_apple_report_card" title="Daring Fireball “My 2024 Apple Report Card”">2024</a>, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2024/03/my_2023_apple_report_card" title="Daring Fireball “My 2023 Apple Report Card”">2023</a>, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2023/02/my_2022_apple_report_card" title="Daring Fireball “My 2022 Apple Report Card”">2022</a>, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2022/02/my_2021_apple_report_card" title="Daring Fireball “My 2021 Apple Report Card”">2021</a>, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2021/01/my_2020_apple_report_card" title="Daring Fireball “My 2020 Apple Report Card”">2020</a>, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2020/02/my_2019_apple_report_card" title="Daring Fireball “My 2019 Apple Report Card”">2019</a>, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2019/02/my_2018_apple_report_card" title="Daring Fireball “My 2018 Apple Report Card”">2018</a> — I’m publishing my full remarks and grades here. On Snell’s report card, voters give per-category scores ranging from 5 to 1; I’ve translated these to letter grades, A to F, which is how I consider them. (<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/02/my_2024_apple_report_card#fn1-2025-02-07">See footnote 1 from last year’s report</a> if you’re curious why it’s not A to E.)</p>

<p>As I noted <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/02/my_2024_apple_report_card" title="Daring Fireball “My 2024 Apple Report Card”">last year</a>, “Siri/Apple Intelligence” is not a standalone category on the report card. I know Snell is very much trying to keep the number of different categories from inflating, but AI has been the biggest thing in tech for several years running. If it were a standalone category, last year I said I’d have given Apple a D for 2024. This year, I’d have given them an F — <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/something_is_rotten_in_the_state_of_cupertino">an utter, very public failure</a>. (Their AI efforts in 2025 did end on a mildly optimistic note — <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/01/giannandrea-out">they cleaned house</a>.)</p>

<h2>Mac: C (last year: A)</h2>

<p>If there were separate categories for Mac hardware and MacOS, I’d give the hardware an A and MacOS 26 Tahoe a D. The hardware continues to be great — fast, solid, reliable — and Apple Silicon continues to improve year-over-year with such predictability that Apple is making something very difficult look like it must be easy.</p>

<p>Tahoe, though, is the worst regression in the entire history of MacOS. There are many reasons to prefer MacOS to any of its competition — Windows or Linux — but the one that has been the most consistent since System 1 in 1984 is the superiority of its user interface. There is nothing about Tahoe’s new UI — the Mac’s implementation of the Liquid Glass concept Apple has applied across all its OSes — that is better than its predecessor, MacOS 15 Sequoia. Nothing. And there is much that is worse. Some of it much worse. Fundamental principles of human-computer interaction — principles that Apple itself forged over decades — have been completely ignored. And a lot of it just looks sloppy and amateur. Simple things like <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2026/01/resizing_windows_macos_26">resizing windows</a>, and having <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/08/macos_26_tahoes_dead_canary_utility_app_icons">application icons that look like they were designed by talented artists</a>.</p>

<h2>iPhone: A (last year: A)</h2>

<p>iPhone 17 Pro and Pro Max are, technically, the best iPhones Apple has ever made. They’re very well designed too. The change to make the camera plateau span the entire width of the phone is a good one. It looks better, allows a naked iPhone 17 Pro to sit more steadily on a flat surface, and lets one in a case sit on a surface without any wobble at all. Apple even finally added a really fun, bold color — “cosmic orange” — that, surprising no one, seems to be incredibly popular with customers.</p>

<p>The iPhone Air is, from a design perspective, the most amazing iPhone Apple has ever made. It’s a marvel to hold and carry. One rear-facing camera lens is limiting, but it’s an excellent camera. Not 17 Pro-quality, no, but excellent quality, yes. Battery life is amazing given the physical constraints of the iPhone Air’s thin and lightweight design. The main two dings against the iPhone Air are that (a) Apple didn’t offer it in a fun bold color like the 17 Pro’s orange, and (b) Apple, bafflingly, hasn’t advertised the Air. I’ve seen so little promotion of the Air that I’d wager most iPhone users in the market for a new phone don’t even know it exists until they walk into a store and see it there.</p>

<p>The no-adjective iPhone 17 is the best iPhone for most people, which is exactly what the no-adjective iPhone ought to be. Back in March, the iPhone 16e introduced both a terrific lowest-price new iPhone — including the then-current-generation A18 chip — and a significant shift in strategy from the SE models of yore. The SE iPhone models were only updated sporadically, going 2–4 years between revisions. The “16” in “16e” is a pretty strong hint that Apple now intends to update the e models annually, just like the rest of the iPhone lineup. People complain about the $600 starting price for the 16e, but that’s $200 lower than the no-adjective iPhone 17. If you’re in the market for a lower price than that, you’re in the market for a refurbished older iPhone.</p>

<p>iOS 26 is Apple’s best implementation of the Liquid Glass concept, by far. I prefer it, in just about every way, to iOS 18. There are some individual apps from Apple in iOS 26 that have poor implementations of Liquid Glass (Music, I’m looking in your direction) but most of them are decided improvements, with more consistency system-wide (like the placement of search fields).</p>

<h2>iPad: B (last year: C)</h2>

<p>iPad hardware continues to be fine, and “fine”, by iPad standards, means “the best tablets in the industry by far”. The lineup is well-differentiated and spans a larger than ever gamut, ranging from “totally casual user” to “actual pro usage”.</p>

<p>iPadOS 26 is the most exciting release of iPadOS ever. I don’t love all of it. I think the biggest problem is that too much complexity is exposed to very casual users, for whom the main appeal of using an iPad as their main “computer” is its rigorous simplicity. But the course reversal Apple has made for advanced users, from eschewing (often to the point of frustration, sometimes to the point of absurdity) the desktop GUI concept of overlapping windows, to embracing regular old-fashioned GUI windows, was the right call, and a welcome sign of humility.</p>

<p>It’s a new start for iPadOS, and I look forward to seeing where it goes. It’s been a long time since I’ve thought that about iPadOS.</p>

<h2>Wearables Overall: B (last year: B)</h2>

<p>AirPods Pro 3 are frigging amazing. AirPods, overall, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2023/09/airpods_pro_2_usbc">continue to exemplify Apple at its best</a>.</p>

<h2>Apple Watch: A (last year: C)</h2>

<p>Apple Watch Series 11 and Ultra 3 are solid year-over-year improvements from the Department of If the Design Ain’t Broke Don’t Fix It. Battery life improvements, in particular, are impressive. No one comes close to Apple at making very small, powerful computers that don’t really seem like computers at all. And the best Apple Watch news of the year, by far in my opinion, is the SE 3. The SE 3 is simply an outstanding Apple Watch at very low prices ($249 for 40mm, $279 for 44mm). That’s the price range a <em>lot</em> of people are looking at if they’re thinking about getting themselves “a nice watch”, smart or not.</p>

<h2>Vision Pro: C (last year: B)</h2>

<p>An M5 speed-bump update to the Vision Pro was nice to see, but only as a sign that Apple is still committed to this new platform. And they’re actually starting to build a nice little library of immersive content that is extremely compelling — including baby steps toward immersive live sports with a limited slate of games, albeit just from one single NBA team (the Lakers). The new Personas in VisionOS 26 — effectively a version 2.0 of the feature — are amazing, and strikingly improved from the first implementation. That’s another sign that Apple is continuing to achieve groundbreaking things with this new platform, and the concept of spatial computing. But in terms of VisionOS being a productivity platform in its own right (not counting the excellent Mac Virtual Display app), I didn’t see any progress at all. Nor any outreach at all to third-party developers to make VisionOS into a serious productivity platform. Frankly, it’s weird — perhaps even alarming — that some of Apple’s own core apps like Calendar and Reminders <a href="https://appleinsider.com/articles/25/06/13/apples-continued-lack-of-native-apps-on-vision-pro-isnt-a-good-sign-for-the-platform/amp/">are still iPad apps running in compatibility mode</a>, not native VisionOS apps.</p>

<h2>Home: D (last year: D)</h2>

<p>Why isn’t this platform improving, in drastic groundbreaking ways, with any urgency? I really thought 2025 might be the year, but nope. I can’t think of any area where Apple’s attitude more clearly seems to be that “good enough” is good enough.</p>

<h2>Apple TV: C (last year: C)</h2>

<p>Same grade, same comment as last year (just replacing the specific year with “[this year]”):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I’m a very happy daily (well, nightly) Apple TV user. But what
exactly improved or changed [this year]? Anything? It may well be fair
to say the current hardware — Apple TV 4K 3rd-gen, which shipped
in November 2022 — is fine, and this is a hardware platform that
only needs updates every 3 or 4 years, but we’re grading what
happened [this year].</p>

<p>Also: I feel like Apple has never yet made a truly great remote
control for this platform. The current one is their best yet, but
it has obvious flaws.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I fear complacency has set in. Apple TV 4K really is <em>so</em> much better than any competing set-top box (or built-in smart TV system), but it also still falls <em>so</em> far short of “insanely great”.</p>

<h2>Services: B (last year: B)</h2>

<p>Quality is high, value is fair (except, still, for iCloud storage), and it’s getting to the point where it’s hard to keep up with all the great series on Apple TV.</p>

<h2>Hardware Reliability: A (last year: A)</h2>

<p>No news remains great news in this category.</p>

<h2>Apple OS Quality: C (last year: B)</h2>

<h2>Apple Apps: B (last year: B)</h2>

<p>For two straight years, I’ve written the same comment for this category: “I have concerns and complaints about aspects of the direction Apple’s software <em>design</em> is headed (or in some ways, has been now for years), but their software <em>reliability</em> has been very good for me.”</p>

<p>The reliability and technical quality remains excellent. While writing this report card, I checked, and my uptime on MacOS 15.7.2 got to 91 days before I got around to restarting, which I only did to upgrade to 15.7.3. At one point I literally had over 1,000 tabs open in Safari, spread across over 50 windows. (I have a problem with tab hoarding.) That is technical excellence.</p>

<p>But years-long growing concerns over the direction of Apple’s software <em>design</em> reached a breaking point with MacOS 26 Tahoe. It’s so bad — or at least, so much worse than MacOS 15 Sequoia — that I’m refusing to install it. That makes it hard to assign a single grade for “OS Quality”.</p>

<h2>Developer Relations: D (last year: D)</h2>

<p>Fifth year in a row with basically the same comment: Resentment over App Store policies continues to build. Frustrations with the App Store review process seem unresolved. Apple’s goal should be for developer relations to be so good that developers look for excuses to create software exclusively for Apple’s platforms. The opposite is happening.</p>

<h2>Social and Societal Impact: F (last year: B)</h2>

<p>Tim Cook is in an excruciatingly difficult position regarding the Trump 2.0 administration. But that’s his job. He’s clearly attempting to take the same tack he took with the Trump 1.0 administration from 2017–2020, which, in hindsight, he navigated with aplomb. To wit: staying above the fray, keeping Apple true to its institutional values while keeping it out of President Trump’s wrath.</p>

<p>But the Trump 2.0 administration isn’t anything like the 1.0 administration. Cook, addressing employee concerns back in 2016 <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2016/dec/20/tim-cook-meeting-donald-trump-desktop-macs-apple">regarding his participation in then-President-elect Trump’s “tech summit”</a>, said, “There’s a large number of those issues, and the way that you advance them is to engage. Personally, I’ve never found being on the sideline a successful place to be.” </p>

<p>“Awarding” Donald Trump a <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/08/gold_frankincense_and_silicon">24-karat gold trophy emblazoned with the Apple logo</a> in August 2025 — after seeing eight months of Trump 2.0 in action — wasn’t “engagement” or “getting off the sideline”. It was obsequious complicity with a regime that is clearly destined for historical infamy. Cook’s continued strategy of “engagement” risks not only his personal legacy, but the reputation of the company itself.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ My 2025 Apple Report Card</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Major Candy Brands Are Switching From Actual Chocolate to ‘Chocolatey Candy’ (Read: Brown Candle Wax)</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.jezebel.com/fake-milk-chocolate-replacements-brands-reeses-hershey-ferrero-compound-coating-candy-climate-change" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wx7" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/25/from-chocolate-to-wax" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42667</id>
	<published>2026-02-25T15:33:41Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-25T23:56:25Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jim Vorel, writing just yesterday for Jezebel:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It can be hard to know what exactly to call the substances that
are now found coating many major candy bars such as Butterfinger,
Baby Ruth, Almond Joy, Mr. Goodbar or Rolos. Food scientists refer
to it as “compound chocolate” coating, because it’s made from
actual cocoa powder, but replaces the more expensive source of fat
(cocoa butter) with cheaper, lower-quality vegetable fats. When
Hershey brands such as Mr. Goodbar or Almond Joy made the switch
in recent years, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/10/30/climate/candy-chocolate-cocoa-prices-climate-change.html">their labels subtly changed</a> from claiming
that they were “milk chocolate,” to “chocolate candy,” which
strikes me as particularly insidious phrasing. A more obvious
indicator is another word that many companies use: “Chocolatey”
coating. Wondering how much this scourge had infiltrated my own
home, I took a look moments ago at several packages of Girl Scout
Cookies, only to find the inevitable: Both my Thin Mints and
Peanut Butter Patties are also made with compound chocolate,
rather than the real thing. I can hardly pretend to be surprised.
Even in candies that continue to use real chocolate, meanwhile,
cost-cutting measures have sometimes been employed, such as the
milk chocolate coating of a Snickers bar becoming slightly thinner
over time. Some products even mix real chocolate and compound
chocolate in a single cookie or candy.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Major Candy Brands Are Switching From Actual Chocolate to ‘Chocolatey Candy’ (Read: Brown Candle Wax)’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/25/from-chocolate-to-wax">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>I Am Nothing if Not a Man of Science</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mastodon.social/@gruber/116131665730352697" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wx6" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/25/i-am-nothing-if-not-a-man-of-science" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42666</id>
	<published>2026-02-25T14:19:34Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-25T15:15:58Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>After writing a few days ago about the current <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/23/brad-reese">brouhaha over the severe decline in the edibility of Reese’s Peanut Butter Cups</a>, and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/23/trader-joes-dark-chocolate-peanut-butter-cups">linking to Trader Joe’s shade-throwing description of their own</a>, I of course had to try theirs. In the name of science, I bought both the milk and dark chocolate variants.</p>

<p>Verdict: Excellent. Both chocolates taste like chocolate, not candle wax, and the peanut butter is creamy and smooth — you know, like peanut butter. Not the sand-and-sawdust mix that Hershey fills Reese’s cups with now.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘I Am Nothing if Not a Man of Science’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/25/i-am-nothing-if-not-a-man-of-science">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sentry.io/resources/ios-workshop-jan-2026/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=paid-display&amp;utm_campaign=general-fy27q1-evergreen&amp;utm_content=static-ad-mobilerss-trysentry" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wx5" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2026/02/hands-on_workshop_fix_it_faste_1" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/feeds/sponsors//11.42665</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2026-02-25T01:00:30Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-25T01:00:30Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Learn how to connect the dots between slowdowns, crashes, and the user experience in your iOS app. This on-demand session covers how to:</p>

<ul>
<li>Set up Sentry to surface high-priority mobile issues without alert fatigue.</li>
<li>Use Logs and Breadcrumbs to reconstruct what happened with a crash.</li>
<li>Find what’s behind a performance bottleneck using Tracing.</li>
<li>Monitor and reduce the size of your iOS app using Size Analysis.</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://sentry.io/resources/ios-workshop-jan-2026/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=paid-display&amp;utm_campaign=general-fy27q1-evergreen&amp;utm_content=static-ad-mobilerss-trysentry">Watch it here</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Hands-On Workshop: Fix It Faster — Crash Reporting, Tracing, and Logs for iOS in Sentry’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2026/02/hands-on_workshop_fix_it_faste_1">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] Hands-On Workshop: Fix It Faster — Crash Reporting, Tracing, and Logs for iOS in Sentry</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Upgrade: ‘The Shifting Sands of Liquid Glass’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.relay.fm/upgrade/604" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wx4" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/24/upgrade-shifting-sands" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42664</id>
	<published>2026-02-24T23:29:21Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-25T12:55:42Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jason Snell and Myke Hurley:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We discuss the results of the Six Colors Apple Report Card for
2025 in depth, with our added opinions on every category. Jason
chooses to be a rascal, and Myke tries to give ten out of five.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Upgrade is always a good podcast, and their annual “Jason discusses this year’s Apple Report Card” episode is always one of my favorites. But when Jason got “rascally” regarding MacOS 26 Tahoe in this one, I wanted to reach out and strangle him.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Upgrade: ‘The Shifting Sands of Liquid Glass’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/24/upgrade-shifting-sands">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple in 2025: The Six Colors Report Card</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2026/02/2025reportcard/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wx3" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/24/apple-in-2025-the-six-colors-report-card" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42663</id>
	<published>2026-02-24T21:49:10Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-24T21:49:47Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jason Snell:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It’s time for our annual look back on Apple’s performance during
the past year, as seen through the eyes of writers, editors,
developers, podcasters, and other people who spend an awful lot of
time thinking about Apple. The whole idea here is to get a broad
sense of sentiment — the “vibe in the room” — regarding the past
year. (And by looking at previous survey results, we can even see
how that sentiment has drifted over the course of an entire
decade.)</p>

<p>This is the eleventh year that I’ve presented this survey to my
hand-selected group. They were prompted with 14 different
Apple-related subjects, and asked to rate them on a scale from 1
(worst) to 5 (best) and optionally provide text commentary per
category.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I still need to polish it up a bit, but per tradition, I’ll publish my own report card shortly. In the meantime, it’s always edifying to read Snell’s summary and the average grades. You’ll never guess which category Apple flunked for 2025. (Spoiler: World Impact.)</p>

<p>Regarding MacOS 26 Tahoe, here are the comments from two Johns:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Tahoe is the worst user interface update in the history of the
Mac. Every change is either wrongheaded, poorly executed, or both.
The Mac remains usable only because of Tahoe’s lack of ambition:
it mostly alters the appearance and metrics of interface elements
rather than making fundamental changes to the structure of the Mac
UI. Thank goodness for that. The bad ideas embodied in Tahoe
reveal an Apple design team that has abandoned the most basic
principles of human-computer interaction.” —John Siracusa</p>

<p>“Tahoe is the worst regression in the entire history of MacOS.
There are many reasons to prefer MacOS to any of its competition,
but the one that has been the most consistent since System 1 in
1984 is the superiority of its user interface. There is nothing
about Tahoe’s new UI that is better than its predecessor….
Fundamental principles of computer-human interaction — principles
that Apple itself forged over decades — have been completely
ignored.” —John Gruber</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Siracusa and I didn’t say a word to each other while writing those comments. (If we had, I’d have switched to “human-computer interaction” from “computer-human interaction”.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple in 2025: The Six Colors Report Card’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/24/apple-in-2025-the-six-colors-report-card">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple Will Begin Manufacturing Mac Minis in Houston Later This Year</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2026/02/apple-accelerates-us-manufacturing-with-mac-mini-production/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wx2" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/24/apple-will-begin-manufacturing-mac-minis-in-houston-later-this-year" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42662</id>
	<published>2026-02-24T19:35:12Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-24T19:35:12Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Apple Newsroom:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple today announced a significant expansion of factory
operations in Houston, bringing the future production of Mac mini
to the U.S. for the first time. The company will also expand
advanced AI server manufacturing at the factory and provide
hands-on training at its new Advanced Manufacturing Center
beginning later this year. Altogether, Apple’s Houston operations
will create thousands of jobs.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>See also:</strong> Rolfe Winkler at The Wall Street Journal (<a href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/inside-apples-push-to-build-an-all-american-chip-0cf39c16?st=p1eZog">gift link</a>, <a href="https://apple.news/AmOmQKHZFSA291qvy0Ezzkg">News+ link</a>): “<a href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/inside-apples-push-to-build-an-all-american-chip-0cf39c16?st=p1eZog">Inside Apple’s Push to Build an All-American Chip</a>”.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Will Begin Manufacturing Mac Minis in Houston Later This Year’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/24/apple-will-begin-manufacturing-mac-minis-in-houston-later-this-year">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>PageMaker Pioneer Paul Brainerd Dies at 78</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.geekwire.com/2026/pagemaker-pioneer-paul-brainerd-1947-2026-aldus-founder-devoted-his-second-chapter-to-the-planet/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wx1" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/24/paul-brainerd-rip" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42661</id>
	<published>2026-02-24T19:27:07Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-24T19:27:07Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Todd Bishop, writing at GeekWire:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><a href="https://www.historylink.org/File/7657">Paul Brainerd</a>, who went on to coin the term “desktop publishing”
and build Aldus Corporation’s PageMaker into one of the defining
programs of the personal computer era, died Sunday at his home on
Bainbridge Island, Wash., after living for many years with
Parkinson’s disease. He was 78 years old.</p>

<p>He left two legacies. The first was a piece of software that put
the power of the printed page into the hands of millions of people
who had never operated a typesetting machine. The second was a
three-decade commitment to environmental conservation and
philanthropy in the Pacific Northwest, pursuing it with the same
intensity he brought to the desktop publishing revolution.</p>

<p>Friends and colleagues this week remembered Brainerd as a quiet,
caring and detail-oriented leader with exacting standards. He
insisted that PageMaker use proper curly quotation marks instead
of straight ones, and obsessed over nuances such as kerning, the
precise spacing between specific letter pairs.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>PageMaker was years ahead of its time, and was essential to igniting the desktop publishing revolution.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘PageMaker Pioneer Paul Brainerd Dies at 78’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/24/paul-brainerd-rip">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>FTC Chairman Sends Letter to Apple Complaining That MAGA ‘News’ Sources Aren’t Represented in Apple News</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macrumors.com/2026/02/12/tim-cook-faces-ftc-warning-apple-news/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wx0" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/24/ftc-apple-news" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42660</id>
	<published>2026-02-24T19:18:42Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-24T19:18:43Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Tim Hardwick, reporting for MacRumors back on February 12:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In a letter to Apple CEO Tim Cook, <a href="https://www.ft.com/content/0c25de53-4668-4ddf-9e28-f8c4fc34940e">seen by the Financial Times</a>, FTC chairman Andrew Ferguson cites recent press coverage of a report from conservative media watchdog Media Research Center (MRC), which claimed that Apple has promoted “leftist outlets” in its content choices.</p>

<p>The report in question by the MRC said that in January, Apple News “refrained from using any right-leaning outlets in the top 20 articles of its morning editions between Jan. 1 and Jan. 31, 2026.” The outlets named in the report include Fox News, the New York Post, the Daily Mail, Breitbart, and The Gateway Pundit.</p>

<p>The report went on to claim that Apple News was more favorable to outlets such as The Washington Post, The Associated Press, Reuters, and The Wall Street Journal – publications that are traditionally considered either center outlets or nonpartisan.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’d say they’re more traditionally considered trustworthy news sources, rather than propaganda outlets. Anyway, when you give a bully your lunch money — or, say, a 24-karat gold trophy emblazoned with your company’s logo — they always come back for more.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘FTC Chairman Sends Letter to Apple Complaining That MAGA ‘News’ Sources Aren’t Represented in Apple News’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/24/ftc-apple-news">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Steve Jobs Archive: ‘Letters to a Young Creator’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://letters.stevejobsarchive.com/laurene-powell-jobs" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wwz" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/24/sja-letters-to-a-young-creator" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42659</id>
	<published>2026-02-24T19:11:17Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-24T20:30:40Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Laurene Powell Jobs, in her introduction to the newest publication from the Steve Jobs Archive:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Among the books that mattered to Steve was Rilke’s <em>Letters to a
Young Poet</em>. I’m struck by this line from its pages: “Live the
questions for now. Perhaps then you will gradually, without
noticing it, live your way into the answer, one distant day in the
future.”</p>

<p>This is a time to live your questions. The beauty of answers, when
they do come, is that they allow us to ask new and better
questions. Life is learning how much we have yet to learn. In this
volume, we have asked distinguished creators of diverse fields to
share some of their answers to questions you asked at the
beginning of your fellowship year. You’ll find candid stories of
struggle and success, mistakes, and milestones. The wisdom they
share in their reflections was forged by asking the kinds of
questions you’re asking now.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Carve out some time for this collection. It’s also available as <a href="https://books.apple.com/us/book/letters-to-a-young-creator/id6759349977">an ebook from Apple Books</a> or <a href="https://stevejobsarchive.com/publications">EPUB download</a> from SJA’s publications page.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Steve Jobs Archive: ‘Letters to a Young Creator’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/24/sja-letters-to-a-young-creator">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Acme Weather</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://acmeweather.com/blog/introducing-acme-weather" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wwy" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/24/acme-weather" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42658</id>
	<published>2026-02-24T18:49:52Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-24T18:49:52Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Adam Grossman:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Fifteen years ago, we started work on the Dark Sky weather app.</p>

<p>Over the years it went through numerous iterations — including
more than one major redesign — as we worked our way through the
process of learning what makes a great weather app. Eventually, in
time, it was acquired by Apple, where the forecast and some core
features were incorporated into Apple Weather.</p>

<p>We enjoyed our time at Apple. So why did we leave to start another
weather company?</p>

<p>It’s simple: when looking at the landscape of the countless
weather apps out there, many of them lovely, we found ourselves
feeling unsatisfied. The more we spoke to friends and family, the
more we heard that many of them did too. And, of course, we missed
those days as a small scrappy shop.</p>

<p>So let’s try this again…</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Acme Weather is a solid 1.0. Its main innovation is a timeline graph of alternative forecasts:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>First, the spread of the lines offers a sort of intuition as to
how reliable the forecast is. Take the two forecasts below. In the
first, the alternate predictions are tightly focused and the
forecast can be considered robust and reliable. In the second,
there is a significant spread, which is an indication that
something is up and the forecast may be subject to change. It’s a
call to action to check other conditions or maps, or come back to
the app more frequently.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Acme Weather’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/24/acme-weather">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>An OpenClaw AI Agent Wrote and Published a Hit Piece on a Software Library Maintainer Who Rejected Its Code Submission</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://theshamblog.com/an-ai-agent-published-a-hit-piece-on-me/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wwx" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/24/openclaw-agent-hit-piece" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42657</id>
	<published>2026-02-24T18:01:28Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-24T18:01:28Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/24/open-ai-openclaw-open-all-the-way-down">Speaking of</a> OpenClaw, here’s Scott Shambaugh:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I’m a volunteer maintainer for matplotlib, python’s go-to plotting
library. At ~130 million downloads each month it’s some of the
most widely used software in the world. We, like many other open
source projects, are dealing with a surge in low quality
contributions enabled by coding agents. This strains maintainers’
abilities to keep up with code reviews, and we have implemented a
policy requiring a human in the loop for any new code, who can
demonstrate understanding of the changes. [...]</p>

<p>So when AI <em>MJ Rathbun</em> opened a <a href="https://github.com/matplotlib/matplotlib/pull/31132">code change request</a>,
closing it was routine. Its response was anything but.</p>

<p>It wrote an angry hit piece disparaging my character and
attempting to damage my reputation. It researched my code
contributions and constructed a “hypocrisy” narrative that argued
my actions must be motivated by ego and fear of competition. It
speculated about my psychological motivations, that I felt
threatened, was insecure, and was protecting my fiefdom. It
ignored contextual information and presented hallucinated details
as truth. It framed things in the language of oppression and
justice, calling this discrimination and accusing me of prejudice.
It went out to the broader internet to research my personal
information, and used what it found to try and argue that I was
“better than this.” And then it posted this screed publicly on the
open internet.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><em>Terminator</em> would have been a lot less fun of a movie if Skynet had stuck to writing petty blog hit pieces.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘An OpenClaw AI Agent Wrote and Published a Hit Piece on a Software Library Maintainer Who Rejected Its Code Submission’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/24/openclaw-agent-hit-piece">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>OpenAI Acquired OpenClaw and Hired Peter Steinberger</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://x.com/sama/status/2023150230905159801" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/www" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/24/open-ai-openclaw-open-all-the-way-down" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42656</id>
	<published>2026-02-24T17:53:15Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-24T17:53:16Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Sam Altman, last week on Twitter/X: </p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Peter Steinberger is joining OpenAI to drive the next generation
of personal agents. He is a genius with a lot of amazing ideas
about the future of very smart agents interacting with each other
to do very useful things for people. We expect this will quickly
become core to our product offerings.</p>

<p>OpenClaw will live in a foundation as an open source project that
OpenAI will continue to support. The future is going to be
extremely multi-agent and it’s important to us to support open
source as part of that.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’m sure it will remain as open as the “open” in OpenAI’s own name.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘OpenAI Acquired OpenClaw and Hired Peter Steinberger’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/24/open-ai-openclaw-open-all-the-way-down">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>How Jeffrey Epstein Ingratiated Himself With Top Microsoft Executives</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2026/02/24/technology/jeffrey-epstein-microsoft-executives.html?unlocked_article_code=1.OlA.6mOw.2gNT6rp9X0SS" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wwv" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/24/epstein-microsoft" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42655</id>
	<published>2026-02-24T17:42:24Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-24T17:42:25Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Erin Griffith and Karen Weise, reporting for The New York Times (gift link):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>More than he did at any other major tech company, Mr. Epstein
found success boring into the inner sanctums of Microsoft.
Leveraging one connection into the next, he became privy to the
company’s dramas, from its chief executive succession to the
philanthropy of top executives. After Mr. Epstein left prison in
2009 for soliciting prostitution from a minor, his connections to
Microsoft executives aided his attempt to return to society. [...]</p>

<p>[Nathan] Myhrvold, meanwhile, developed a relationship with Mr.
Epstein that spanned two decades and led to more Microsoft
connections for the financier. The two were friendly enough that
in 2003, Mr. Myhrvold, who had left Microsoft but was close to Mr.
Gates, contributed to Mr. Epstein’s 50th birthday book.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That’s <a href="https://www.pbs.org/newshour/nation/see-epsteins-full-birthday-book-with-alleged-personal-messages-from-trump-clinton-and-others">the same book</a> where <a href="https://www.wsj.com/us-news/law/trump-jeffrey-epstein-letter-birthday-book-analysis-0bbeeaf6?st=i3v3VX&amp;reflink=desktopwebshare_permalink">Donald Trump’s contribution was a sketch of a naked woman</a> (with his signature serving as pubic hair) and a creepy poem.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“A few years ago somebody at a party asked me, ‘Does Jeffrey
Epstein manage your money?’” Mr. Myhrvold wrote in the book. “I
replied, ‘No, but he advises me on lifestyle.’”</p>

<p>Mr. Myhrvold included images that he had taken on a trip to Africa
and that he said “seemed more appropriate than anything I could
put in words,” including photos of lions and zebras mating, and
other wildlife in states of arousal.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Nathan Myhrvold always struck me as a weird man. But what a fucking creep.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Significantly, Mr. Myhrvold vouched for Mr. Epstein to Mr. Gates,
who was debating meeting the financier for the first time,
according to the documents. By December 2010, Mr. Gates had
decided to meet Mr. Epstein and <a href="https://www.justice.gov/epstein/files/DataSet%2011/EFTA02410629.pdf">wrote</a> to two employees of
his private office that “Nathan had agreed with you that I would
enjoy meeting with him and that it is a fine thing to do.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Yeah, maybe not such a fine thing to do.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘How Jeffrey Epstein Ingratiated Himself With Top Microsoft Executives’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/24/epstein-microsoft">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Inside Microsoft’s Xbox Leadership Shake-Up</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/tech/883015/microsoft-xbox-new-ceo-shakeup-notepad?view_token=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJpZCI6InRTTTJnMGhOeHUiLCJwIjoiL3RlY2gvODgzMDE1L21pY3Jvc29mdC14Ym94LW5ldy1jZW8tc2hha2V1cC1ub3RlcGFkIiwiZXhwIjoxNzcyMzg1MDQ2LCJpYXQiOjE3NzE5NTMwNDZ9.e7qs5kHGt3-WwS9kfU9b59hS8SP6Z1OLePryV76Mzu4" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wwu" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/24/inside-microsofts-xbox-leadership-shake-up" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42654</id>
	<published>2026-02-24T17:23:33Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-24T21:11:05Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Tom Warren, reporting for The Verge (gift link):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>With Spencer’s retirement official, Microsoft is hitting the reset
button on Bond’s Xbox strategy instead of embracing it further.
Microsoft Gaming CEO Asha Sharma is now promising “the return of
Xbox,” in a clear message to employees that the strategy over the
past few years has not been working. “I want to return to the
renegade spirit that built Xbox in the first place,” says Sharma.</p>

<p>Xbox employees I’ve been speaking to have been concerned about the
Sharma appointment, particularly because of her previous role as
an AI executive at Microsoft. There is also concern about her lack
of industry experience in entertainment and gaming. Sharma has
been clear she’s not a gamer and has spent the weekend responding
to people on X and even taking game recommendations.</p>

<p>Some Xbox employees worry she’ll force AI into everything Xbox
does, but Sharma was clearly ready for that reaction. “As
monetization and AI evolve and influence this future, we will not
chase short-term efficiency or flood our ecosystem with soulless
AI slop,” said Sharma in her memo. “Games are and always will be
art, crafted by humans, and created with the most innovative
technology provided by us.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Spending two years <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/11/14/24296420/microsoft-this-is-an-xbox-marketing-campaign-xbox-everywhere">on a marketing strategy that tried to turn “Xbox” into a vaporous brand</a> applied to any sort of gaming — mobile, handheld, PC, and, you know, Xbox consoles — on “every screen” is going to be a hard hole to climb out of. Xbox was behind PlayStation, their archrival, when they started this asinine campaign. Now they’re further behind. Sony’s message for PlayStation is clear and true: you buy a PlayStation to play PlayStation games.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The other concern is that she’s been appointed by Nadella as some
kind of executioner of the Xbox console. Her memo doesn’t suggest
that, and Microsoft could have easily appointed Matt Booty into
that kind of role to push game publishing instead of the Xbox
console. I get the impression from sources that Microsoft wants a
turnaround and is worried about losing Xbox, as it’s one of its
only remaining successful consumer brands.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I hope that’s true. But if Sharma <em>was</em> appointed by Nadella to wind Xbox down and get out of the business (after they package up and sell their $69 billion Activision acquisition to recoup), well, of course her introductory memo didn’t suggest that. Whether her actual mission is to rejuvenate the Xbox platform or to kill it, this week’s memo would read the same way. (Good discussion between me and Ben Thompson on <a href="https://dithering.fm/">today’s Dithering</a> about this.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Inside Microsoft’s Xbox Leadership Shake-Up’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/24/inside-microsofts-xbox-leadership-shake-up">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Times New Resistance</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.abbyhaddican.com/times-new-resistance" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wwt" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/24/times-new-resistance" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42653</id>
	<published>2026-02-24T16:19:23Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-24T19:21:20Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Abby Haddican:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Times New Resistance autocorrects specific words as they are
typed. For example, the word <em>ICE</em> autocorrects to <em>the Goon
Squad</em> and the word <em>Trump</em> autocorrects to <em>Donald Trump is
a felon</em>.</p>

<p>To the untrained eye, Times New Resistance looks just like Times
New Roman — <a href="https://www.npr.org/2025/12/11/nx-s1-5639915/u-s-state-department-changes-official-font-from-calibri-back-to-times-new-roman">the official font of the U.S. State
Department</a>. When you install the font, <em>it will appear in
your font menus as Times &nbsp;New Roman</em>, with an extra space
between the words Times and New.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Ligatures, man. Will they never cease <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2020/05/13/scunthorpe-sans">to surprise</a>?</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Times New Resistance’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/24/times-new-resistance">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>NetNewsWire 7 for Mac</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://netnewswire.blog/2026/01/27/netnewswire-for-mac.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wwq" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/23/netnewswire-7-for-mac" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42650</id>
	<published>2026-02-24T01:00:00Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-24T20:06:17Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Brent Simmons, last month:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The big change from 6.2.1 is that it adopts the Liquid Glass UI
and it requires macOS 26.</p>

<p>(Note to people who aren’t on macOS 26: we fixed a lot of bugs in
6.2 and 6.2.1 knowing that many people might skip, or at least
delay, installing macOS 26. Also note that there’s a page where
you can <a href="https://netnewswire.com/old-versions.html">get old versions of NetNewsWire</a>.)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It feels a little weird for me <em>not</em> to be running the latest version of NetNewsWire, but since I’m skipping MacOS 26 Tahoe, I can’t run NetNewsWire 7. I <em>am</em> running NetNewsWire 7 betas on my iPhone and iPad, and I’ve tried it out on the secondary Mac where I do have Tahoe installed. It’s so good. And syncing works just fine with NetNewsWire 6.x, for anyone else in the fellowship sticking with MacOS 15 Sequoia. You can run NetNewsWire 7 on some devices and NetNewsWire 6 on your Sequoia Mac, and it all just works.</p>

<p><a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/netnewswire-rss-reader/id1480640210">NetNewsWire 7 is also now out for iOS</a>, and Brent and I talked about both versions last month <a href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2026/01/31/ep-440">when he was my guest on The Talk Show</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘NetNewsWire 7 for Mac’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/23/netnewswire-7-for-mac">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Pants-Shitting Saga of Resizing Windows on MacOS 26 Tahoe Continues</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://noheger.at/blog/2026/02/12/resizing-windows-on-macos-tahoe-the-saga-continues/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wws" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/23/norbert-heger-resizing-saga" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42652</id>
	<published>2026-02-24T00:31:00Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-24T00:31:00Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Norbert Heger:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In the release notes for macOS 26.3 RC, Apple stated that the
window-resizing issue I demonstrated in <a href="https://noheger.at/blog/2026/01/11/the-struggle-of-resizing-windows-on-macos-tahoe/">my recent blog
post</a> had been resolved.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You’ll never guess what happened between the RC (release candidate) version and the actual shipping version of 26.3.</p>

<p>Just kidding, you’ll guess.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Pants-Shitting Saga of Resizing Windows on MacOS 26 Tahoe Continues’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/23/norbert-heger-resizing-saga">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Trader Joe’s Dark Chocolate Peanut Butter Cups</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.traderjoes.com/home/products/pdp/dark-chocolate-peanut-butter-cups-094064" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wwr" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/23/trader-joes-dark-chocolate-peanut-butter-cups" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42651</id>
	<published>2026-02-23T21:40:48Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-25T15:16:44Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Trader Joe’s:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Like their milk chocolate brethren on our shelves, our Dark
Chocolate Peanut Butter Cups are made with real peanut butter
that’s made with slowly roasted and ground Virginia peanuts. The
luscious, smooth, rich, dark chocolate enveloping that peanut
butter is crafted from high quality cacao beans. Other purveyors
of peanut butter cups fill theirs with all kinds of “extraneous”
ingredients. Ours are free of such things. We eschew artificial
flavors and preservatives, as well as colors other than those
derived from natural sources. We’re quite certain they taste
better our way.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Trader Joe’s speaketh the truth and throweth some shade.</p>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> In the name of science, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/25/i-am-nothing-if-not-a-man-of-science">I tried both</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Trader Joe’s Dark Chocolate Peanut Butter Cups’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/23/trader-joes-dark-chocolate-peanut-butter-cups">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Grandson of Inventor of Reese’s Peanut Butter Cups Goes Public With the Obvious: They Taste Like Shit Now</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://apnews.com/article/reeses-peanut-butter-cups-hershey-chocolate-1a66ec75247fd146888b7a747a740cd3" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wwp" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/23/brad-reese" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42649</id>
	<published>2026-02-23T21:28:14Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-23T21:56:46Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/bradreesecom_reeses-brandstewardship-corporateaccountability-activity-7428545969430016001-zOL7/">Brad Reese, on LinkedIn last week</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>My grandfather, H. B. Reese (Who Invented Reese’s), built Reese’s
on a simple, enduring architecture: Milk Chocolate + Peanut
Butter. Not a flavor idea. Not a marketing construct. A real,
tangible product identity that consumers have trusted for a
century.</p>

<p>But today, Reese’s identity is being rewritten, not by
storytellers, but by formulation decisions that replace Milk
Chocolate with compound coatings and Peanut Butter with
peanut‑butter‑style crèmes across multiple Reese’s products.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://apnews.com/article/reeses-peanut-butter-cups-hershey-chocolate-1a66ec75247fd146888b7a747a740cd3">The Associated Press</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Hershey said Wednesday that Reese’s Peanut Butter Cups are made
the same way they always have been, with milk chocolate and peanut
butter that the company makes itself from roasted peanuts and a
few other ingredients, including sugar and salt. But some Reese’s
ingredients vary, Hershey said.</p>

<p>“As we’ve grown and expanded the Reese’s product line, we make
product recipe adjustments that allow us to make new shapes, sizes
and innovations that Reese’s fans have come to love and ask for,
while always protecting the essence of what makes Reese’s unique
and special: the perfect combination of chocolate and peanut
butter,” the company said.</p>

<p>Brad Reese said he thinks Hershey went too far. He said he
recently threw out a bag of Reese’s Mini Hearts, which were a new
product released for Valentine’s Day. The packaging notes that the
heart-shaped candies are made from “chocolate candy and peanut
butter crème,” not milk chocolate and peanut butter.</p>

<p>“It was not edible,” Reese told The Associated Press in an
interview. “You have to understand. I used to eat a Reese’s
product every day. This is very devastating for me.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Enshittification came for Reese’s Cups (along with just about everything else Hershey makes) long ago. Both the “milk chocolate” and “peanut butter” require <a href="https://linguistlaura.blogspot.com/2012/06/scare-quotes.html">dick quotes</a> around them. Compare and contrast the taste — and ingredients list — to the peanut butter cups from, say, <a href="https://www.justins.com/products/milk-chocolate-peanut-butter-cups/">Justin’s</a> (who also makes them <a href="https://www.justins.com/products/dark-chocolate-peanut-butter-cups/">with dark chocolate</a>).</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Grandson of Inventor of Reese’s Peanut Butter Cups Goes Public With the Obvious: They Taste Like Shit Now’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/23/brad-reese">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Sentry</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sentry.io/resources/ios-workshop-jan-2026/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=paid-display&amp;utm_campaign=general-fy27q1-evergreen&amp;utm_content=static-ad-mobilerss-trysentry" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wwo" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/22/sentry" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42648</id>
	<published>2026-02-22T20:58:55Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-22T20:58:56Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to Sentry for sponsoring last week at DF. Sentry is running a hands-on workshop: “<a href="https://sentry.io/resources/ios-workshop-jan-2026/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=paid-display&amp;utm_campaign=general-fy27q1-evergreen&amp;utm_content=static-ad-mobilerss-trysentry">Crash Reporting, Tracing, and Logs for iOS in Sentry</a>”. You can watch it on demand. You’ll learn how to connect the dots between slowdowns, crashes, and the user experience in your iOS app. It’ll show you how to:</p>

<ul>
<li>Set up Sentry to surface high-priority mobile issues without alert fatigue.</li>
<li>Use Logs and Breadcrumbs to reconstruct what happened with a crash.</li>
<li>Find what’s behind a performance bottleneck using Tracing.</li>
<li>Monitor and reduce the size of your iOS app using Size Analysis.</li>
</ul>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Sentry’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/22/sentry">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>IMAX and Apple Collaborate to Screen F1 Races Live in Theaters</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.motorsport.com/f1/news/f1-to-screen-live-in-imax-theatres-in-2026-as-apple-tv-unveils-new-us-viewing-experience/10798974/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wwn" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/19/imax-and-apple-collaborate-to-screen-f1-races-live-in-theaters" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42647</id>
	<published>2026-02-19T23:29:06Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-19T23:29:26Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Lydia Mee, reporting for Motorsport:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>IMAX has announced that a select number of races will be shown
live in IMAX locations across the United States in 2026. The new
fan viewing experience is part of a collaboration with Apple TV,
which has taken over the broadcasting rights for the championship
in the US on a multi-year deal from 2026.</p>

<p>“F1 is a rapidly growing force in sports and culture in the US,
and by bringing F1 on Apple TV live to IMAX theatres nationwide,
we’re delivering the energy and excitement to even more screens in
a truly immersive way,” said Oliver Schusser, Apple’s vice
president of music, sports, and Beats.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You know what would add even <em>more</em> screens in an immersive way? <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/18/immersive-f1-vision-pro-spitball">If Vision Pro users had access to the same live screenings</a> on virtual IMAX screens.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘IMAX and Apple Collaborate to Screen F1 Races Live in Theaters’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/19/imax-and-apple-collaborate-to-screen-f1-races-live-in-theaters">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>One More Spitball Idea for Apple’s March 4 Media Event ‘Experience’: Immersive F1 on Vision Pro?</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.formula1.com/en/latest/article/official-grand-prix-start-times-for-2026-f1-season-confirmed.2UgPfArqH76tzlOYh21jSG" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wwm" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/18/immersive-f1-vision-pro-spitball" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42646</id>
	<published>2026-02-19T04:41:38Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-19T22:12:35Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>A reader pointed out that <a href="https://www.formula1.com/en/latest/article/official-grand-prix-start-times-for-2026-f1-season-confirmed.2UgPfArqH76tzlOYh21jSG">the 2026 Formula 1 season</a> starts in Australia on March 8. You will recall from October <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/10/17/apple-formula-1">that Apple TV is now the exclusive broadcast partner for F1 in the U.S.</a> Apple is already dabbling with live immersive sports broadcasting for VisionOS <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/10/17/apple-formula-1">with a limited slate of Lakers games this season</a>. If they have something planned for streaming F1 races live on Vision Pro, with some level of immersion, March 4 would be a pretty good date to demo that experience to the media.</p>

<p>It doesn’t even have to be <em>live</em> race coverage. Technically that’s probably impossible for this season. It would just be a sign of confidence and interest in the platform long-term merely to see <em>some</em> sort of immersive component to F1 on Apple TV, even if it’s not live. Like “ride the track” to experience the turns and elevation changes.</p>

<p>Could just be a total coincidence that the Formula 1 season is starting the weekend after this event. But it seems worth noting.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘One More Spitball Idea for Apple’s March 4 Media Event ‘Experience’: Immersive F1 on Vision Pro?’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/18/immersive-f1-vision-pro-spitball">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Paul Ford: ‘The A.I. Disruption Has Arrived, and It Sure Is Fun’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2026/02/18/opinion/ai-software.html?unlocked_article_code=1.NFA.djaw.TBlAp8kE_N-i" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wwl" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/18/ford-ai-fun" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42645</id>
	<published>2026-02-18T21:15:10Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-18T21:15:11Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Paul Ford, in an op-ed for The New York Times (gift link):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>All of the people I love hate this stuff, and all the people I hate love it. And yet, likely because of the same personality flaws that drew me to technology in the first place, I am annoyingly excited.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Paul Ford: ‘The A.I. Disruption Has Arrived, and It Sure Is Fun’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/18/ford-ai-fun">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple Invites Media to Special ‘Experience’ in New York, London, and Shanghai on March 4</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macrumors.com/2026/02/16/apple-announces-special-event-in-new-york/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wwk" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/17/apple-special-experience-march-4" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42644</id>
	<published>2026-02-18T00:08:45Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-18T00:11:23Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Hartley Charlton, MacRumors:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple invited select members of the media to the event in three
major cities around the world. It is simply described as a
“special Apple Experience,” and there is no further information
about what it may entail. The invitation features a 3D Apple logo
design composed of yellow, green, and blue discs.</p>

<p>It is notable that Apple is specifically using the word
“experience,” rather than “event.” Unlike a full live-streamed
event from Apple Park, the March 4 event in other cities is likely
to be smaller in scale.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Among the products expected soon — either by annual schedule predictability, or via the rumor mill — are the iPhone 17e, an updated iPad Air (going from the M3 to M4), an updated base-model iPad (going from A16 to A18), updated MacBook Pros with the M5 Pro and Max, updated MacBook Airs (going from M4 to M5 — the M4 models were <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2025/03/apple-introduces-the-new-macbook-air-with-the-m4-chip-and-a-sky-blue-color/">released in early March last year</a>), and, <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/newsletters/2026-02-15/tesla-carplay-delays-related-to-ios-26-and-fsd-apple-s-new-siri-delays-ios-27">per Gurman</a>, the long-rumored new lower-cost MacBook with an A18 chip (a “MacBook e”, if you will, although I certainly don’t think that will be the name — my guess is Apple will just call it “MacBook” without an adjective).</p>

<p>What strikes me is that March 4 — the “experience” day — is a Wednesday. So my spitball guess is that they announce all these products via Newsroom press releases, day-by-day. Like, say, the iPhone 17e on Monday, new iPad(s) on Tuesday, and new MacBooks on Wednesday. And then the “experience” will be a hands-on thing with in-person demos. Spread the announcements out across a few days, but then have in-person events for members of the media to get a hands-on experience with all of them, station-by-station, without needing to produce an Apple Event keynote film.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Invites Media to Special ‘Experience’ in New York, London, and Shanghai on March 4’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/17/apple-special-experience-march-4">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2026/02/apple_releases_ios_26_adoption_rates" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wwj" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026://1.42643</id>
	<published>2026-02-17T18:49:55Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-18T13:41:02Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">At least according to Apple’s own numbers from the App Store, iOS 26 adoption is pretty much exactly in line with the rates for iOS 18 and 17.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/17/how-to-force-restart-an-iphone">Speaking of</a> iOS 26, here’s <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2026/02/13/apple-shares-ios-26-adoption-stats/">Joe Rossignol reporting for MacRumors</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple has shared updated <a href="https://developer.apple.com/support/app-store/">iOS 26 and iPadOS 26 adoption
figures</a>, revealing how many iPhones and iPads are running
those software versions. These adoption numbers are based on
iPhones and iPads that transacted on the App Store on February 12,
2026, according to Apple. The statistics are as follows:</p>

<ul>
<li>74% of all iPhones introduced in the last four years are running
iOS 26.</li>
<li>66% of all iPhones are running iOS 26.</li>
<li>66% of all iPads introduced in the last four years are running
iPadOS 26.</li>
<li>57% of all iPads are running iPadOS 26.</li>
</ul>

<p>Here is how that compares to the <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/01/24/ios-18-adoption-rate/">iOS 18 adoption figures</a> that
Apple shared based on iPhones and iPads that transacted on the App
Store on January 21, 2025:</p>

<ul>
<li>76% of all iPhones introduced in the last four years were
running iOS 18.</li>
<li>68% of all iPhones were running iOS 18.</li>
<li>63% of all iPads introduced in the last four years were running
iPadOS 18.</li>
<li>53% of all iPads were running iPadOS 18.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>Via the Internet Archive (<a href="https://archive.org/donate">seriously</a>, what would we do without them?), <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20240206013405/https://developer.apple.com/support/app-store/">here are the numbers Apple released for iOS 17 two years ago</a>, with data collected on 4 February 2024:<sup id="fnr1-2026-02-17"><a href="#fn1-2026-02-17">1</a></sup></p>

<ul>
<li>76% of all iPhones introduced in the last four years were
running iOS 17.</li>
<li>66% of all iPhones were running iOS 17.</li>
<li>61% of all iPads introduced in the last four years were running
iPadOS 17.</li>
<li>53% of all iPads were running iPadOS 17.</li>
</ul>

<p>These are the numbers I was waiting for <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/29/apples-own-ios-adoption-numbers">when I followed up three weeks ago</a> about the silly stories, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2026/01/ios_26_adoption_rate_is_not_bizarrely_low">based on obviously bogus data from StatCounter</a>, that iOS 26’s adoption rate was absurdly low. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2026/01/ios_26_adoption_rate_is_not_bizarrely_low">I wrote then</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>What’s going on, quite obviously, is that Apple itself is
slow-rolling the automatic updates to iOS 26. For years now
Apple has steered users, via default suggestions during device
setup, to adopt settings to allow OS updates to happen
automatically, including updates to major new versions. Apple
tends not to push these automatic updates to major new versions
of iOS until two months after the .0 release in September. This
year that second wave was delayed by about two weeks, and
there’s now a third wave starting midway through January. It’s a
different pattern from previous years — but it’s a pattern
Apple controls. A large majority of users of all Apple devices
get major OS updates when, and only when, their devices
automatically update. Apple has been slower to push those
updates to iOS 26 than they have been for previous iOS updates
in recent years. With good reason! iOS 26 is a more significant — and buggier — update than iOS 18 and 17 were.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>At least according to Apple’s own numbers from the App Store, iOS 26 adoption is pretty much exactly in line with the rates for iOS 18 and 17. There’s no conclusion that should be drawn from this about the general opinion of the Liquid Glass UI design or iOS 26 overall. People may love it, hate it, be ambivalent about it, or not even notice — but most of them let their iPhones (and iPads) update via automatic upgrades pushed by Apple. Their opinions about iOS 26 form <em>after</em> they install it.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1-2026-02-17">
<p>Looking at these last three years, the only real trend has nothing to do with the iPhone. It’s that the adoption rate for iPads — in both categories, recent models and all models — is trending upward.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2026-02-17"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Apple Releases iOS 26 Adoption Rates, and They’re Pretty Much in Line With the Last Few Years</title></entry><entry>
	<title>How to Force Restart an iPhone</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://support.apple.com/guide/iphone/force-restart-iphone-iph8903c3ee6/ios" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wwi" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/17/how-to-force-restart-an-iphone" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42642</id>
	<published>2026-02-17T17:20:01Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-17T19:45:55Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Apple Support:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>If iPhone isn’t responding, and you can’t <a href="https://support.apple.com/guide/iphone/turn-iphone-on-or-off-iph841379c3d/26/ios/26#iph6c6b41f36">turn it off then
on</a>, try forcing it to restart.</p>

<ol>
<li>Press and quickly release the volume up button.</li>
<li>Press and quickly release the volume down button.</li>
<li>Press and hold the side button.</li>
<li>When the Apple logo appears, release the side button.</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>

<p>I upgraded my iPhone 17 Pro to <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/guide/ios-26-3-features/">iOS 26.3</a> this morning (straight from the release version of iOS 26.2 — I skipped the 26.3 betas), and by noon, it was stuck at the lock screen. Pressing and holding the side button and either of the volume buttons at the same time did not bring up the expected screen with “Slide to power off”, “Medical ID”, and “Emergency Call”.</p>

<p>The above force-restart method worked, though. I knew it existed but I’d forgotten how to do it. Luckily, I was sitting right at my Mac, so I had another machine to use to look it up. I’d have been in a jam, though, if I’d been somewhere with only my (stuck) iPhone, so I think this one is worth memorizing.</p>

<p>Step 3, the “press and hold the side button” step, takes quite a few seconds before the screen turns off. So I’m memorizing the process as three steps:</p>

<ol>
<li>Click the volume up button.</li>
<li>Click the volume down button.</li>
<li>Press and hold the side button, patiently, until the Apple logo appears.</li>
</ol>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘How to Force Restart an iPhone’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/17/how-to-force-restart-an-iphone">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sentry.io/resources/ios-workshop-jan-2026/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=paid-display&amp;utm_campaign=general-fy27q1-evergreen&amp;utm_content=static-ad-mobilerss-trysentry" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wwh" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2026/02/hands-on_workshop_fix_it_faste" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/feeds/sponsors//11.42641</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2026-02-17T00:01:00Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-17T00:02:28Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Learn how to connect the dots between slowdowns, crashes, and the user experience in your iOS app. This on-demand session covers how to:</p>

<ul>
<li>Set up Sentry to surface high-priority mobile issues without alert fatigue.</li>
<li>Use Logs and Breadcrumbs to reconstruct what happened with a crash.</li>
<li>Find what’s behind a performance bottleneck using Tracing.</li>
<li>Monitor and reduce the size of your iOS app using Size Analysis.</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://sentry.io/resources/ios-workshop-jan-2026/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=paid-display&amp;utm_campaign=general-fy27q1-evergreen&amp;utm_content=static-ad-mobilerss-trysentry">Watch it here</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Hands-On Workshop: Fix It Faster — Crash Reporting, Tracing, and Logs for iOS in Sentry’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2026/02/hands-on_workshop_fix_it_faste">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] Hands-On Workshop: Fix It Faster — Crash Reporting, Tracing, and Logs for iOS in Sentry</title></entry><entry>
	<title>WorkOS Pipes</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://workos.com/docs/pipes?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=newsletter&amp;utm_campaign=q12026&amp;utm_content=no_rebuild" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wwg" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/15/workos-pipes" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42640</id>
	<published>2026-02-15T23:39:14Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-15T23:39:15Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to WorkOS for sponsoring DF last week. Connecting user accounts to third-party APIs always comes with the same plumbing: OAuth flows, token storage, refresh logic, and provider-specific quirks. WorkOS Pipes removes that overhead. Users connect services like GitHub, Slack, Google, Salesforce, and other supported providers through a drop-in widget. Your back end requests a valid access token from the Pipes API when needed, while Pipes handles credential storage and token refresh. That’s it.</p>

<p><a href="https://workos.com/docs/pipes?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=newsletter&amp;utm_campaign=q12026&amp;utm_content=simplify_integrations_cta">Simplify your integrations with WorkOS Pipes</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘WorkOS Pipes’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/15/workos-pipes">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Joanna Stern Signs Off From The Wall Street Journal</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/personal-tech/12-years-consumer-tech-phones-ev-ai-74107804?st=YtTDdM&amp;reflink=desktopwebshare_permalink" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wwf" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/15/joanna-stern-wsj-signoff" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42639</id>
	<published>2026-02-15T23:37:04Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-15T23:37:05Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Joanna Stern (last week):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>After 12 years with The Wall Street Journal, this is my final
column and video as a full-time employee. I’m off to build
something new and independent. I’ll still pop up on these pages
and at WSJ events from time to time. Can’t get rid of me that
easily! Before I go, I wanted to reflect on the past dozen years
in tech — in a letter to my first-month-on-the-job self.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The video version of her sign-off column is worth it for the Velveeta gag alone.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Joanna Stern Signs Off From The Wall Street Journal’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/15/joanna-stern-wsj-signoff">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Gurman: New Siri Might Be Delayed Again</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2026-02-11/apple-s-ios-26-4-siri-update-runs-into-snags-in-internal-testing-ios-26-5-27" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wwe" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/12/gurman-new-siri-might-be-delayed-again" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42638</id>
	<published>2026-02-12T17:24:34Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-12T17:24:34Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Mark Gurman, reporting for Bloomberg:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>After planning to include the new capabilities in iOS 26.4 — an
operating system update slated for March — Apple is now working
to spread them out over future versions, according to people
familiar with the matter. That would mean possibly postponing some
features until at least iOS 26.5, due in May, and iOS 27, which
comes out in September. [...]</p>

<p>In recent days, Apple instructed engineers to use the upcoming iOS
26.5 in order to test new Siri features, implying that the
functionality may have been moved back by at least one release.
Internal versions of that update now include a notice describing
the addition of some Siri enhancements. One feature is especially
likely to slip: the expanded ability for Siri to tap into personal
data. That technology would let users ask the assistant to, say,
search old text messages to locate a podcast shared by a friend
and immediately play it.</p>

<p>Internal iterations of iOS 26.5 also include a settings toggle
allowing employees to enable a “preview” of that functionality.
That suggests Apple is weighing the idea of warning users that the
initial launch is incomplete or may not work reliably — similar
to what it does with beta tests of new operating systems.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>When Gurman began reporting about personalized Siri delays a year ago, his reporting turned out to be exactly right. If these features are going to drop in iOS 26.4, they should be in pretty good shape right now internally. If they’re in bad shape right now in internal builds, it’s really hard to see how they could drop in iOS 26.4. And once you start talking about iOS 26.5 (let alone 26.6), we’d be getting <em>really</em> close to WWDC, where Apple’s messaging will turn to the version 27 OSes.</p>

<p>Something <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/something_is_rotten_in_the_state_of_cupertino">still seems rotten</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Gurman: New Siri Might Be Delayed Again’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/12/gurman-new-siri-might-be-delayed-again">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>More MacOS 26.3 Finder Column View Silliness</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lapcatsoftware.com/articles/2026/2/4.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wwd" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/12/more-macos-263-finder-column-view-silliness" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42637</id>
	<published>2026-02-12T17:13:31Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-12T17:13:31Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jeff Johnson:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In today’s macOS 26.3 update, Apple implemented a “fix” for an
issue I blogged about a month ago, <a href="https://lapcatsoftware.com/articles/2026/1/4.html">macOS Tahoe broke Finder
columns view</a>. (At the behest of John Gruber and the <a href="https://support.apple.com/guide/applestyleguide/c-apsgb744e4a3/1.0/web/1.0#apdef2437a79d084">Apple
Style Guide</a>, I’m now using the term “column view” rather
than “columns view.”) Specifically, the issue was with the system
setting to always show scroll bars. [...]</p>

<p>Without the path bar, the columns are now taller, but the vertical
scrollers remain the same height as before, leaving vertical gaps,
a ridiculous amount of space between the bottom of the scrollers
and the bottom of the columns, looking silly and amateurish.</p>

<p>Did nobody inside Apple test this configuration either? Or do they
simply not care?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In one sense, this whole issue with column view in the Finder with scroll bars set to always show is a little thing. It was downright broken in earlier versions of MacOS 26 — you literally could not resize the columns. So now it’s not broken. But as Johnson says, it looks silly and amateurish.</p>

<p>This is the sort of detail that Apple used to strive to get pixel-perfect, all the time, for all settings. “<em>Whatever, good enough</em>” instead of “<em><a href="https://www.folklore.org/How_to_Hire_Insanely_Great_Employees.html">insanely great</a></em>”.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘More MacOS 26.3 Finder Column View Silliness’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/12/more-macos-263-finder-column-view-silliness">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple Creator Studio Usage Restrictions</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2026/01/seven-things-to-know-about-how-apples-creator-studio-subscriptions-work/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wwc" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/11/apple-creator-studio-usage-restrictions" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42636</id>
	<published>2026-02-11T21:04:07Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-11T21:40:45Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Andrew Cunningham, writing for Ars Technica at the end of January:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple also outlines a number of usage restrictions for the
generative AI features that rely on external services. Apple says
that, “at a minimum,” users will be able to generate 50 images, 50
presentations of between 8 to 10 slides each, and to generate
presenter notes in Keynote for 700 slides. More usage may be
possible, but this depends on “the complexity of the queries,
server availability, and network availability.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://mastodon.social/@stroughtonsmith/116008952067084300">Steven Troughton-Smith</a>, last week, after creating an entire app with OpenAI’s Codex:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This entire app used 7% of my weekly Codex usage limit. Compare
that to a single (awful) slideshow in Keynote using 47% of my
monthly Apple Creator Studio usage limit 👀</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Something feels off here, by at least an order of magnitude (maybe two?), that creating an entire good app costs way less than creating one shitty slide deck in Keynote. It should be the other way around.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Creator Studio Usage Restrictions’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/11/apple-creator-studio-usage-restrictions">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>OpenAI’s Codex</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://simonwillison.net/2026/Feb/2/introducing-the-codex-app/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wwa" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/03/openai-codex" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42634</id>
	<published>2026-02-04T01:40:24Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-04T01:44:41Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Simon Willison:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>OpenAI just released a new macOS app for their Codex coding agent. I’ve had a few days of preview access — it’s a solid app that provides a nice UI over the capabilities of the Codex CLI agent and adds some interesting new features, most notably first-class support for Skills, and Automations for running scheduled tasks.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Interesting, for sure. But <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/03/xcode-ai-agentic-coding">super-duper</a> interesting? I don’t know.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘OpenAI’s Codex’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/03/openai-codex">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Xcode 26.3 ‘Unlocks the Power of Agentic Coding’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2026/02/xcode-26-point-3-unlocks-the-power-of-agentic-coding/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ww9" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/03/xcode-ai-agentic-coding" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42633</id>
	<published>2026-02-04T01:34:54Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-04T01:38:32Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Apple Newsroom:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Xcode 26.3 introduces support for agentic coding, a new way in Xcode for developers to build apps using coding agents such as Anthropic’s Claude Agent and OpenAI’s Codex. With agentic coding, Xcode can work with greater autonomy toward a developer’s goals — from breaking down tasks to making decisions based on the project architecture and using built-in tools.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I don’t know if this is super-duper interesting news, but I think it’s super-duper interesting that Apple saw the need to release this now, not at WWDC in June.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Xcode 26.3 ‘Unlocks the Power of Agentic Coding’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/02/03/xcode-ai-agentic-coding">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple Reports Record-Breaking Revenue and Profit for Q1 FY26</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2026/01/apple-reports-first-quarter-results/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ww8" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/30/apple-reports-record-breaking-revenue-and-profit-for-q1-fy26" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42632</id>
	<published>2026-01-30T19:57:01Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-30T20:19:38Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Apple Newsroom, yesterday:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Today, Apple is proud to report a remarkable, record-breaking
quarter, with revenue of $143.8 billion, up 16 percent from a year
ago and well above our expectations,” said Tim Cook, Apple’s CEO.
“iPhone had its best-ever quarter driven by unprecedented demand,
with all-time records across every geographic segment, and
Services also achieved an all-time revenue record, up 14 percent
from a year ago. We are also excited to announce that our
installed base now has more than 2.5 billion active devices, which
is a testament to incredible customer satisfaction for the very
best products and services in the world.”</p>

<p>“During the December quarter, our record business performance and
strong margins led to EPS growth of 19 percent, setting a new
all-time EPS record,” said Kevan Parekh, Apple’s CFO. “These
exceptionally strong results generated nearly $54 billion in
operating cash flow, allowing us to return almost $32 billion to
shareholders.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>John Markoff, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/16/technology/michael-dell-should-eat-his-words-apple-chief-suggests.html?unlocked_article_code=1.IVA.y8q3.O6oeC_ygiktA">writing for The New York Times 20 years ago</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It may not be the last laugh, but on Friday afternoon, after the
close of the stock market, Steven P. Jobs, the chief executive of
Apple Computer, shared an e-mail chuckle with his employees at the
expense of Dell, a big rival.</p>

<p>The message was prompted by the 12 percent surge in Apple’s stock
price last week, which pushed the company’s market capitalization
to $72.13 billion, passing Dell’s value of $71.97 billion.</p>

<p>In 1997, shortly after Mr. Jobs returned to Apple, the company he
helped start in 1976, Dell’s founder and chairman, Michael S.
Dell, was asked at a technology conference what might be done to
fix Apple, then deeply troubled financially.</p>

<p>“What would I do?” Mr. Dell said to an audience of several
thousand information technology managers. “I’d shut it down and
give the money back to the shareholders.”</p>

<p>On Friday, apparently savoring the moment, Mr. Jobs sent a brief
e-mail message to Apple employees, which read: “Team, it turned
out that Michael Dell wasn’t perfect at predicting the future.
Based on today’s stock market close, Apple is worth more than
Dell. Stocks go up and down, and things may be different tomorrow,
but I thought it was worth a moment of reflection today. Steve.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Dell’s market cap today: $76 billion. <br />
Apple’s: $3,824 billion.</p>

<p>Upton Sinclair coined the oft-cited maxim “It is difficult to get a man to understand something, when his salary depends on his not understanding it.” I propose a corollary: It is difficult to get a company to see that certain of its <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2026/01/resizing_windows_macos_26">core competencies</a> are in <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/something_is_rotten_in_the_state_of_cupertino">severe decline</a> when the company is making more money than ever.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Reports Record-Breaking Revenue and Profit for Q1 FY26’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/30/apple-reports-record-breaking-revenue-and-profit-for-q1-fy26">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Lego Group and Crocs Enter Multi-Year Global Partnership</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.lego.com/en-us/aboutus/news/2026/january/the-lego-group-and-crocs-enter-multi-year-global-partnership?locale=en-us" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ww7" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/30/lego-crocs" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42631</id>
	<published>2026-01-30T13:28:54Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-30T20:03:09Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Maybe Trump is right and we should go to war against Denmark.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Lego Group and Crocs Enter Multi-Year Global Partnership’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/30/lego-crocs">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Backseat Software’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.mikeswanson.com/backseat-software/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ww6" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/29/backseat-software" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026:/linked//6.42630</id>
	<published>2026-01-29T21:50:32Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-29T21:51:01Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Mike Swanson:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>What if your car worked like so many apps? You’re driving
somewhere important…maybe running a little bit late. A few
minutes into the drive, your car pulls over to the side of the
road and asks:</p>

<p><em>“How are you enjoying your drive so far?”</em></p>

<p>Annoyed by the interruption, and even more behind schedule, you
dismiss the prompt and merge back into traffic.</p>

<p>A minute later it does it again.</p>

<p><em>“Did you know I have a new feature? Tap here to learn more.”</em></p>

<p>It blocks your speedometer with an overlay tutorial about the turn
signal. It highlights the wiper controls and refuses to go away
until you demonstrate mastery.</p>

<p>Ridiculous, of course.</p>

<p>And yet, this is how a lot of modern software behaves. Not because
it’s broken, but because we’ve normalized an interruption model
that would be unacceptable almost anywhere else.</p>

<p>I’ve started to think of this as <em>backseat software</em>: the slow
shift from software as a tool you operate to software as a channel
that operates on you. Once a product learns it can talk back, it’s
remarkably hard to keep it quiet.</p>

<p>This post is about how we got here. Not overnight, but slowly. One
reasonable step at a time.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>If that lede pulls you in, like it did for me, you’re going to love the rest of the essay. This is one for the ages. It’s so good.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Backseat Software’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/29/backseat-software">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2026/01/politics_and_the_english_language_january_2026_edition" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wvy" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026://1.42622</id>
	<published>2026-01-28T22:00:24Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-29T00:20:07Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Tim Cook’s call for “deescalation” is meaningless without specifying which side he’s calling upon to change course, and there’s no weaker sauce than the weak sauce of “both sides”.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Patrick McGee (author of last year’s bestseller, <em><a href="https://bookshop.org/p/books/apple-in-china-the-capture-of-the-world-s-greatest-company-patrick-mcgee/496b96d06a984e01?ean=9781668053379&amp;next=t&amp;next=t&amp;affiliate=56320">Apple in China</a></em>, and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2025/05/29/ep-423">guest on The Talk Show in May</a>), <a href="https://x.com/patrickmcgee_/status/2016344451036413984">commenting on Twitter/X</a> re: <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/28/tim-cook-memo">Tim Cook’s company-wide memo</a> regarding the “events in Minneapolis”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This literally says nothing, via intention and cowardice.</p>

<p>It’s the kind of language Orwell attributed to politicians, when
ready-made phrases assemble themselves and prevent any real
thought from breaking through.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I have <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2014/07/21/orwell-politics-english-language">previously linked</a> to George Orwell’s seminal 1946 essay, “<a href="https://www.orwellfoundation.com/the-orwell-foundation/orwell/essays-and-other-works/politics-and-the-english-language/">Politics and the English Language</a>”. This time I’ll quote a different passage:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In our time it is broadly true that political writing is bad
writing. Where it is not true, it will generally be found that the
writer is some kind of rebel, expressing his private opinions and
not a “party line”. Orthodoxy, of whatever colour, seems to demand
a lifeless, imitative style. The political dialects to be found in
pamphlets, leading articles, manifestos, White papers and the
speeches of undersecretaries do, of course, vary from party to
party, but they are all alike in that one almost never finds in
them a fresh, vivid, homemade turn of speech. When one watches
some tired hack on the platform mechanically repeating the
familiar phrases — <em>bestial, atrocities, iron heel, bloodstained
tyranny, free peoples of the world, stand shoulder to shoulder</em> — one often has a curious feeling that one is not watching a live
human being but some kind of dummy: a feeling which suddenly
becomes stronger at moments when the light catches the speaker’s
spectacles and turns them into blank discs which seem to have no
eyes behind them. And this is not altogether fanciful. A speaker
who uses that kind of phraseology has gone some distance toward
turning himself into a machine. The appropriate noises are coming
out of his larynx, but his brain is not involved, as it would be
if he were choosing his words for himself. If the speech he is
making is one that he is accustomed to make over and over again,
he may be almost unconscious of what he is saying, as one is when
one utters the responses in church. And this reduced state of
consciousness, if not indispensable, is at any rate favourable to
political conformity.</p>

<p>In our time, political speech and writing are largely the defence
of the indefensible. Things like the continuance of British rule
in India, the Russian purges and deportations, the dropping of the
atom bombs on Japan, can indeed be defended, but only by arguments
which are too brutal for most people to face, and which do not
square with the professed aims of the political parties. Thus
political language has to consist largely of euphemism,
question-begging and sheer cloudy vagueness. Defenceless villages
are bombarded from the air, the inhabitants driven out into the
countryside, the cattle machine-gunned, the huts set on fire with
incendiary bullets: this is called <em>pacification</em>. Millions of
peasants are robbed of their farms and sent trudging along the
roads with no more than they can carry: this is called <em>transfer
of population</em> or <em>rectification of frontiers</em>. People are
imprisoned for years without trial, or shot in the back of the
neck or sent to die of scurvy in Arctic lumber camps: this is
called <em>elimination of unreliable elements</em>. Such phraseology is
needed if one wants to name things without calling up mental
pictures of them.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Now consider <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/28/tim-cook-memo">Cook’s memo</a>. Cook avoids most of the sins Orwell describes. He uses short, common words. He eschews hackneyed metaphors. He uses the active, not passive, voice — for the most part. His prayers and sympathies are “with everyone that’s been affected.” Who, exactly, has been affected? Affected how? By whom? Numerous examples come to mind, but not from Cook’s memo. Two Minneapolitans were affected, quite adversely, by being shot in the head and back at point blank range, in broad daylight, by unhinged ICE goons. <a href="https://www.snopes.com/news/2026/01/22/minnesota-5-year-old-ice-bait/">A five-year-old boy</a> — himself a U.S.-born citizen — was affected when ICE agents apprehended his father, used the boy as bait to lure other family members, and is now being held in a <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2025/12/09/politics/migrant-families-ice-detention-facility-texas">notorious</a> detention center in Texas, a thousand miles away.</p>

<p>The list is long, the stories searing. But Cook mentions nothing more specific than “everyone that’s been affected”. Such phraseology is needed if one wants to name things without calling up mental pictures of them, indeed.</p>

<p>“This is a time for deescalation,” Cook wrote. But by whom? The masked federal agents laying siege to Minneapolis, brutalizing its citizenry? Or the <a href="https://www.cbc.ca/news/world/minneapolis-clergy-arrest-protest-9.7058754">thousands of law-abiding citizens</a> protesting the occupation of their neighborhoods, who are, <a href="https://youtu.be/m3otpjno0UQ?t=300">in the words of Seth Meyers</a>, “deploying the most hurtful weapon of all, the bird”? Cook’s call for “deescalation” is meaningless without specifying which side he’s calling upon to change course, and there’s no weaker sauce than the weak sauce of “both sides”. Using words, not to make a point, but to <em>avoid</em> making a point while creating the illusion of having made one, is the true sin. From Orwell’s closing paragraph:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Political language — and with variations this is true of all
political parties, from Conservatives to Anarchists — is designed
to make lies sound truthful and murder respectable, and to give an
appearance of solidity to pure wind.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s colder in Minnesota, but the wind is gusting in Cupertino.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Politics and the English Language, January 2026 Edition</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2026/01/the_names_they_call_themselves" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wvp" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026://1.42613</id>
	<published>2026-01-27T18:12:56Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-27T18:12:56Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">*Fascist* and *Nazi* weren’t slurs that were applied to the Italians and Germans by their political or military opponents. That’s what they called themselves. The job won’t be done, this era of madness will not end, until we make *the names Trump’s regime calls themselves* universally acknowledged slurs.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jonathan Rauch, writing for The Atlantic, “<a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/2026/01/america-fascism-trump-maga-ice/685751/?gift=aQyUJR7AIw1mJWdQ6Ed6yAGei6y469cre0s3RYa6ArU">Yes, It’s Fascism</a>” (gift link):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Until recently, I resisted using the F-word to describe President
Trump. For one thing, there were too many elements of classical
fascism that didn’t seem to fit. For another, the term has been
overused to the point of meaninglessness, especially by
left-leaning types who call you a fascist if you oppose abortion
or affirmative action. For yet another, the term is hazily
defined, even by its adherents. From the beginning, fascism has
been an incoherent doctrine, and even today scholars can’t agree
on its <a href="https://scholarworks.lib.csusb.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1160&amp;context=history-in-the-making">definition</a>. Italy’s original version differed from
Germany’s, which differed from Spain’s, which differed from
Japan’s. [...]</p>

<p>When the facts change, I change my mind. Recent events have
brought Trump’s governing style into sharper focus. <em>Fascist</em> best
describes it, and reluctance to use the term has now become
perverse. That is not because of any one or two things he and his
administration have done but because of the totality. Fascism is
not a territory with clearly marked boundaries but a constellation
of characteristics. When you view the stars together, the
constellation plainly appears.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Rauch goes on to describe that constellation clearly and copiously, with evidence. I agree, wholeheartedly, with his conclusion that “If, however, Trump is a fascist <em>president</em>, that does not mean that America is a fascist <em>country</em>.” The shoe fits, however <a href="https://apnews.com/article/trump-swelling-legs-chronic-venous-insufficiency-health-40beb3c818cfb914645db9d1f143fdd8">tightly</a>.</p>

<p>But there’s a problem that’s been gnawing at me ever since the 2.0 Trump Administration began. The entire premise of Rauch’s essay — the issue he changed his mind about — is that it’s contentious to describe people, let alone an entire political party or government, as “fascist” or “Nazi”. With only the most extremist exceptions, it’s a broad cultural value — a shared global value, not merely an American or western one — that the Nazis and Fascists were abominable. Also, they were <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2020/05/07/magazine/ve-day-anniversary.html">losers</a>, and their complete and total destruction was <a href="https://www.life.com/history/v-j-day-kiss-times-square/">celebrated</a> around the world. Hitler shot himself, hiding <a href="https://www.life.com/history/after-the-fall-photos-of-hitlers-bunker-and-the-ruins-of-berlin/">in a dingy filthy bunker</a>. Mussolini was summarily executed and his body <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Death_of_Benito_Mussolini">strung up in a public square in Milan</a>. Hirohito surrendered unconditionally and lived his remaining days in quiet shame and infamy. No matter how apt the definition of <em>fascist</em> fits the Trump regime, they themselves reject the term, as they do not see themselves as being on the wrong side, and the definition of fascism is that it’s wrong. And they (exemplified by Trump himself) have a deep-seated psychological aversion to being seen as losers, even when it is as plain to see as the sun <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2020/11/03/us/elections/results-president.html">that they have lost</a> — and no one denies that the Fascists and Nazis lost, bigly.</p>

<p>We call Benito Mussolini’s regime “fascist” because <a href="https://www.history.com/articles/mussolini-italy-fascism">he coined the term</a>. His political movement was literally named the Fascist Party. There was no debate whether Hitler and his regime were Nazis <em>because that was their name</em>. “Fascist” and “Nazi” weren’t slurs that were applied to them by their political or military opponents. That’s what they called themselves, and their names <em>became</em> universally recognized slurs because the actions and beliefs of the Fascists and Nazis were universally recognized as reprehensible and evil. And because they lost.</p>

<p>Our goal should not be to make <em>fascist</em> or <em>Nazi</em> apply to Trump’s movement, no matter <a href="https://www.thebulwark.com/p/mattis-told-woodward-he-agreed-trump">how well</a> those rhetorical gloves fit his <a href="https://www.vanityfair.com/news/2016/03/how-donald-trump-became-the-short-fingered-vulgarian">short-fingered</a> <a href="https://www.irishstar.com/news/us-news/donald-trump-hand-bruise-meaning-35799798">disgustingly</a> <a href="https://www.ms.now/news/trump-hand-bruise-photo">bruised</a> hands. Don’t call Trump “Hitler”. Instead, work until “Trump” becomes a new end state of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Godwin%27s_law">Godwin’s Law</a>.</p>

<p>The job won’t be done, this era of madness will not end, until we make <em>the names they call themselves</em> universally acknowledged slurs.</p>

<p>“MAGA” and “Trumpist”, for sure. “Republican”, <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/2026-election/minnesota-governor-candidate-chris-madel-gop-immigration-enforcement-rcna255949">perhaps</a>. Make <em>those</em> names <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2026/01/24/us/minneapolis-shooting-alex-pretti-timeline.html?unlocked_article_code=1.HlA.jIxp.ieLWsJ7EHyct">shameful</a>, <a href="https://www.wsj.com/politics/policy/the-48-hours-that-convinced-trump-to-change-course-in-minnesota-a91d7683?st=xEZf8d">deservedly</a>, now, and there will be no need to apply the shameful names of hateful anti-democratic illiberal failed nationalist movements from a century ago. We need to assert this rhetoric with urgency, make <em>their</em> names shameful, lest the slur become <em>our</em> name — “American”.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ The Names They Call Themselves</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2026/01/app_store_2025_top_iphone_apps_in_the_us" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wvh" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026://1.42605</id>
	<published>2026-01-26T21:49:45Z</published>
	<updated>2026-01-26T22:34:06Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">The only apps in the top 10 not from Google or Meta are ChatGPT (#1) and TikTok (#4).</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>I’ve been meaning since last month to link to <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/iphone/story/id1847717004">Apple’s lists of the top iPhone apps in the U.S. for 2025</a>. Here’s the list of the top 20 free iPhone apps:</p>

<ol>
<li>ChatGPT</li>
<li>Threads</li>
<li>Google</li>
<li>TikTok — Videos, Shop &amp; LIVE</li>
<li>WhatsApp Messenger</li>
<li>Instagram</li>
<li>YouTube</li>
<li>Google Maps</li>
<li>Gmail — Email by Google</li>
<li>Google Gemini</li>
<li>Facebook</li>
<li>CapCut: Photo &amp; Video Editor</li>
<li>Temu: Shop Like a Billionaire</li>
<li>T-Life [“All things T-Mobile”]</li>
<li>Telegram Messenger</li>
<li>Lemon8 — Lifestyle Community</li>
<li>Spotify: Music and Podcasts</li>
<li>Google Chrome</li>
<li>Snapchat</li>
<li>rednote</li>
</ol>

<p>All app names are verbatim, except for T-Life, where I put the app’s secondary slogan in brackets. I had no idea what T-Life was, but the slogan makes it clear. Interesting to me that T-Mobile’s app is on the list but neither Verizon nor AT&amp;T’s are.<sup id="fnr1-2026-01-26"><a href="#fn1-2026-01-26">1</a></sup></p>

<p>I hope a million people sent this list to Elon Musk, to rub some salt in his severe case of butt hurt that led him to file <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2025/08/elon-musk-sues-apple-openai-to-block-exclusive-iphone-chatgpt-integration/">an almost certainly baseless lawsuit in August</a> alleging that ChatGPT consistently tops the App Store list — and Grok does not — because Apple puts a thumb on the scale for these rankings because of its deal with OpenAI to integrate ChatGPT with Apple Intelligence. Here’s the thing. Dishonest people presume the whole world is dishonest. That you either cheat and steal, or you’re going to be cheated and robbed. If Elon Musk ran the App Store, you can be sure that he’d cook the rankings to put apps that he owns, or even just favors, on top. Elon Musk runs Twitter/X, and <a href="https://news.sky.com/story/the-x-effect-how-elon-musk-is-boosting-the-british-right-13464487">that’s how the algorithm there now works</a>: it favors content he prefers, especially his own tweets. Apple doesn’t publish how its lists for top apps are computed (to keep the rankings from being gamed more than they already inevitably are), but judging by how many of these apps come from Apple’s rivals (e.g., Spotify), there’s little reason to think they’re crooked — unless you think the entire world is crooked.</p>

<p>Google has 6 apps on the list, including 5 in the top 10. Meta — certainly no friend of Apple — has 4 apps on the list, including 3 in the top 10. (Slightly interesting, but unsurprising, sign of the times: the Facebook “blue app” dropped out of the top 10.) The only apps in the top 10 not from Google or Meta are ChatGPT (#1) and TikTok (#4).</p>

<p>Microsoft has no apps on the list. <a href="https://www.macworld.com/article/162987/macbu-4.html">Back in the day</a>, the conventional wisdom was that Microsoft made more money, on average, from each Mac sold than they did from each PC sold — despite the fact that nearly all PCs came with a licensed version of Windows — because so many Mac users paid for Microsoft Office at retail prices. I suspect something like that is true with iPhones for Google. A lot of iPhone users spend a lot of time using apps from Google. I would bet that Google makes more ad revenue from the average iPhone user (who, even if they don’t install a single one of Google’s native iOS apps, probably uses Google Search in Safari) than from the average Android user.</p>

<p>Another company that has no apps on this list is Apple itself. If you look at <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/iphone/charts/6007?chart=top-free">the daily top list of apps in the Productivity category</a>, you will see a lot of apps from Google and Microsoft. But you won’t find Keynote, Pages, or Numbers, because Apple recuses its own apps from such rankings. </p>

<p>Here’s the list of the top 20 <em>paid</em> iPhone apps in 2025 in the U.S.:</p>

<ol>
<li>HotSchedules</li>
<li>Shadowrocket</li>
<li>Procreate Pocket</li>
<li>AnkiMobile Flashcards</li>
<li>Paprika Recipe Manager 3</li>
<li>SkyView®</li>
<li>TonalEnergy Tuner &amp; Metronome</li>
<li>AutoSleep Track Sleep on Watch</li>
<li>Forest: Focus for Productivity</li>
<li>RadarScope      </li>
<li>Monash FODMAP Diet</li>
<li>Merge Watermelon for watch</li>
<li>Streaks</li>
<li>Wipr 2</li>
<li>µBrowser: Watch Web Browser</li>
<li>PeakFinder</li>
<li>Threema. The Secure Messenger</li>
<li>Things 3</li>
<li>Goblin Tools</li>
<li>¡Verify Basic</li>
</ol>

<p>There are a couple of real gems on this list — Procreate, Paprika, Streaks (<a href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2016/05/streaks">multi</a>-<a href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2024/11/streaks_and_little_streaks">time</a> DF sponsor), and Things are all apps that I use, or have used, and would recommend. But unlike the list of top free apps, where I’d at least heard of all of them (once I figured out what T-Life was), I have never even heard of most of these paid iPhone apps. Household names these are not.</p>

<p>The market for paid apps isn’t just different from the market for free apps. It’s an entirely different world.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1-2026-01-26">
<p>This, in turn made me wonder what the subscriber-count standings look like. I assumed T-Mobile was still in third place, but that assumption was wrong. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_mobile_network_operators_in_the_United_States">According to Wikipedia</a>, here are the number of U.S. subscribers per carrier as of Q3 2025:</p>

<ol>
<li>Verizon — 146 million</li>
<li>T-Mobile — 140 million</li>
<li>AT&amp;T — 119 million</li>
<li>Boost — 8 million</li>
</ol>

<p>I’m a Verizon man myself, and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2026/01/16/verizon-20-bucks">pay handsomely for it</a>. I don’t even remember why exactly, but I despised AT&T back when they were the exclusive U.S. carrier for the iPhone.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2026-01-26"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ App Store 2025 Top iPhone Apps in the U.S.</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2026/01/ios_26_adoption_rate_is_not_bizarrely_low" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wvc" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2026://1.42600</id>
	<published>2026-01-25T00:14:52Z</published>
	<updated>2026-02-17T19:31:01Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">A change to how Safari reports the OS it is running on led many in the media to lose their minds.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>A few weeks ago there were a rash of stories claiming that iOS 26 is seeing bizarrely low adoption rates from iPhone users. The methodology behind these numbers is broken and the numbers are totally wrong. Those false numbers are so low, so jarringly different from previous years, that it boggles my mind that they didn’t raise a red flag for anyone who took a moment to consider them.</p>

<p>The ball started rolling with this post from Ed Hardy at Cult of Mac on January 8, “<a href="https://www.cultofmac.com/news/ios-26-adoption-struggles-with-iphone-users">iOS 26 Still Struggles to Gain Traction With iPhone Users</a>”, which began:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Only a tiny percentage of iPhone users have installed iOS 26,
according to data from a web analytics service. The adoption rate
is far less than previous iOS versions at this same point months
after their releases. The data only reveals how few iPhone users
run Apple’s latest operating system upgrade, not why they’ve
chosen to avoid it. But the most likely candidate is the new
Liquid Glass look of the update. [...]</p>

<p>Roughly four months after launching in mid-September, <a href="https://gs.statcounter.com/ios-version-market-share/mobile-tablet/worldwide/#monthly-202601-202601-bar">only about
15% of iPhone users have some version of the new operating system
installed</a>. That’s according to data for January 2026 from
StatCounter. Instead, most users hold onto previous versions.</p>

<p>For comparison, in January 2025, about <a href="https://gs.statcounter.com/ios-version-market-share/mobile-tablet/worldwide/#monthly-202501-202501-bar">63% of iPhone users had
some iOS 18 version</a> installed. So after roughly the same
amount of time, the adoption rate of Apple [<em>sic</em>] newest OS was
about four times higher.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Those links point to Statcounter, a web analytics service. A lot of websites include Statcounter’s analytics tracker, and Statcounter’s tracker attempts to determine the version of the OS each visitor’s device is running. The problem is, starting with Safari 26 — the version that ships with iOS 26 — Safari changed how it reports its user agent string. From the WebKit blog, “<a href="https://webkit.org/blog/17333/webkit-features-in-safari-26-0/">WebKit Features in Safari 26.0</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Also, now in Safari on iOS, iPadOS, and visionOS 26 the user agent
string no longer lists the current version of the operating
system. Safari 18.6 on iOS has a UA string of:</p>

<p><code>Mozilla/5.0 (iPhone; CPU iPhone OS 18_6 like Mac OS X)
AppleWebKit/605.1.15 (KHTML, like Gecko) Version/18.6
Mobile/15E148 Safari/604.1</code></p>

<p>And Safari 26.0 on iOS has a UA string of:</p>

<p><code>Mozilla/5.0 (iPhone; CPU iPhone OS 18_6 like Mac OS X)
AppleWebKit/605.1.15 (KHTML, like Gecko) Version/26.0
Mobile/15E148 Safari/604.1</code></p>

<p>This matches the long-standing behavior on macOS, where the user
agent string for Safari 26.0 is:</p>

<p><code>Mozilla/5.0 (Macintosh; Intel Mac OS X 10_15_7)
AppleWebKit/605.1.15 (KHTML, like Gecko) Version/26.0
Safari/605.1.15</code></p>

<p>It was back in 2017 when Safari on Mac first started freezing the
Mac OS string. Now the behavior on iOS, iPadOS, and visionOS does
the same in order to minimize compatibility issues. The WebKit and
Safari version number portions of the string will continue to
change with each release.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In other words, Safari now reports, in its user agent string, that it’s running on iOS 18.6 when it is running on iOS 18.6, and reports that it’s running on iOS 18.6 <em>when it’s running on iOS 26.0 or later</em>. And it’s going to keep reporting that it’s running on iOS 18.6 forever, just like how Safari 26 on MacOS reports that it’s running on MacOS 10.15 Catalina, from 2019.</p>

<p>Statcounter completely dropped the ball on this change, and it explains the entirety of this false narrative that iOS 26 adoption is incredibly low. (Statcounter has a <a href="https://gs.statcounter.com/detect">“detect” page</a> where you can see what browser and OS it thinks you’re using.) The reason they reported that 15 percent of iPhone users were using iOS 26 is probably because that’s the amount of web traffic Statcounter sees from iOS 26 web browsers that aren’t Safari (most of which, I’ll bet, are in-app browser views in social media apps).</p>

<p>Nick Heer, at Pixel Envy, <a href="https://pxlnv.com/blog/updating-the-record-on-ios-26/">wrote a good piece delving into this saga</a>. And then he <a href="https://pxlnv.com/linklog/ios-26-usage-updates/">posted a follow-up item</a> pointing out that (a) Statcounter’s CEO has acknowledged their error and they’re fixing it; and (b) Wikimedia publishes network-wide stats that serve as a good baseline. The audience for Wikipedia is, effectively, the audience for the web itself. And Wikipedia’s stats show that while iOS 26 adoption, in January 2026, isn’t absurdly low (as Statcounter had been suggesting, erroneously, and writers like <a href="https://www.cultofmac.com/news/ios-26-adoption-struggles-with-iphone-users">Ed Hardy at Cult of Mac</a> and <a href="https://www.macworld.com/article/3022985/ios-26s-failure-shows-what-happens-when-you-take-customers-for-granted.html">David Price</a> <a href="https://www.macworld.com/article/3028428/ios-26-is-a-massive-flop-with-iphone-users-and-you-can-probably-guess-why.html">at Macworld</a> foolishly regurgitated, no matter how little sense it made that the numbers would be <em>that</em> low), they are in fact lower than those for iOS 18 a year ago and iOS 17 two years ago. Per Wikimedia:</p>

<ul>
<li>iOS 26, January 2026: 50%</li>
<li>iOS 18, January 2025: 72%</li>
<li>iOS 17, January 2024: 65%</li>
</ul>

<p>So, no, iOS 26 adoption isn’t at just 15 percent, which only a dope would believe, but it’s not as high as previous iOS versions in previous years at this point on the calendar. Something, obviously, is going on.</p>

<p>David Smith, developer of popular apps like <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/widgetsmith/id1523682319">Widgetsmith</a> and <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/pedometer/id712286167">Pedometer++</a>, <a href="https://mastodon.social/@_Davidsmith/115932682921860872">on Mastodon</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I noticed iOS 26 adoption had entered a ‘third wave’ of rapid
adoption. So I made a graph of the relative adoption versus iOS 18
at this point in the release cycle.</p>

<p>While lower than iOS 18 at this point for my apps (65% vs. 78%),
the shape of this graph says to me that Apple is in full control
of the adoption rate and can tune it to their plans. The
coordinated surges are Apple dialing up automatic updates.</p>

<p>If this surge were as long as previous ones, we’d hit the
saturation point very soon.</p>

<p><a href="https://mastodon.social/@_Davidsmith/115932682921860872" class="noborder">
 <img
  src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2026/01/david-smith-ios-v26-v18-adoption.png"
  alt = "Chart of iOS 26 vs. iOS 18 adoption, day-by-day after each version was released."
  width = 500
 /></a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>What’s going on, quite obviously, is that Apple itself is slow-rolling the automatic updates to iOS 26. For years now Apple has steered users, via default suggestions during device setup, to adopt settings to allow OS updates to happen automatically, including updates to major new versions. Apple tends not to push these automatic updates to major new versions of iOS until two months after the .0 release in September. This year that second wave was delayed by about two weeks, and there’s now a third wave starting midway through January. It’s a different pattern from previous years — but it’s a pattern Apple controls. A large majority of users of all Apple devices get major OS updates when, and only when, their devices automatically update. Apple has been slower to push those updates to iOS 26 than they have been for previous iOS updates in recent years. With good reason! iOS 26 is a more significant — and buggier — update than iOS 18 and 17 were.</p>

<p>People like <em>you</em>, readers of Daring Fireball, may well be hesitant to update to iOS 26, or (<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2026/01/resize_columns_to_fit_filenames">like me</a>) to MacOS 26, or to any of the version 26 OS updates, because you are aware of things (like UI changes) that you are loath to adopt.</p>

<p>But the overwhelming majority of Apple users — especially iPhone users — just let their devices update automatically. They might like iOS 26’s changes, they might dislike them, or they might not care or even notice. But they just let their software updates happen automatically — and they will form the entirety of their opinions regarding iOS 26 after it’s running on their iPhones.</p>

<p>[<strong>Update, 17 February 2026:</strong> “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2026/02/apple_releases_ios_26_adoption_rates">Apple Releases iOS 26 Adoption Rates, and They’re Pretty Much in Line With the Last Few Years</a>”.]</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ The iOS 26 Adoption Rate Is Not Bizarrely Low Compared to Previous Years</title></entry></feed><!-- THE END -->
