<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>Daring Fireball</title>
<subtitle>By John Gruber</subtitle>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/" />
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main" />
<id>https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main</id>


<updated>2025-05-28T23:05:53Z</updated><rights>Copyright © 2025, John Gruber</rights><entry>
	<title>Apple’s Annual App Store Scam and Fraud Report</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2025/05/the-app-store-prevented-more-than-9-billion-usd-in-fraudulent-transactions/?1748350751" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wcy" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/28/apples-annual-app-store-scam-and-fraud-report" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41938</id>
	<published>2025-05-28T23:05:53Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-28T23:05:53Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Apple Newsroom, yesterday:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple’s strong antifraud infrastructure helps ensure that
malicious developer and customer accounts are swiftly flagged and
eliminated. In 2024, Apple terminated more than 146,000 developer
accounts over fraud concerns and rejected an additional 139,000
developer enrollments, preventing bad actors from submitting their
apps to the App Store in the first place.</p>

<p>Apple also rejected over 711 million customer account creations
and deactivated nearly 129 million customer accounts last year,
blocking these risky and malicious accounts from carrying out
nefarious activity. That includes spamming or manipulating ratings
and reviews, charts, and search results that risk compromising the
integrity of the App Store.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This report isn’t something new that Apple is doing in the face of increased regulatory scrutiny over the exclusivity of the App Store — they’ve been issuing these reports <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2021/05/app-store-stopped-over-1-5-billion-in-suspect-transactions-in-2020/">since 2021</a>. <a href="https://pxlnv.com/linklog/annual-fraud-prevention-headlines/">Nick Heer has a good post at Pixel Envy</a> documenting how some of their numbers are seemingly all over the place, year to year.</p>

<p>What some App Store critics argue is that if <em>any</em> substantial amount of fraud, scams, or rip-offs occur through apps distributed through the App Store, that proves that there are no protective benefits of the App Store model. That’s nonsense. There are high-crime cities and low-crime cities, but there exist zero no-crime cities. The question is whether Apple is catching most — or even just “enough” — scammers. Scammy apps, pirated apps, fraudulent app reviewers. You name it. I’ve long suggested that <a href="https://daringfireball.net/search/bunco+squad">Apple ought to employ a “bunco squad”</a> to crack down on scammers, focusing first and foremost on <em>successful</em> ones. Better to catch one scam with 1,000 victims than 10 scams with one victim each.</p>

<p>I think they could still do better, but I actually think Apple <em>has</em> been doing a better job on this front in recent years. But if your measuring stick is “Are there any successful scams at all in the App Store?” there’s no way Apple is ever going to pass muster. And I think a lot of App Store critics are vastly, vastly underestimating how much fraud Apple is currently stopping that would sail right through if iOS adopted a Mac-style of software distribution. The main difference is that iOS is so much more of a juicy target than MacOS. The other is that I think many people underestimate how many software scams there are on MacOS that wouldn’t work on iOS.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple’s Annual App Store Scam and Fraud Report’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/28/apples-annual-app-store-scam-and-fraud-report">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Gurman: Apple Is Going to Re-Version OSes by Year, Starting With iOS 26, MacOS 26, tvOS 26, Etc.</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2025-05-28/apple-to-rebrand-device-operating-systems-ios-26-macos-26-watchos-26" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wcx" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/28/gurman-version-years" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41937</id>
	<published>2025-05-28T22:32:02Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-28T22:32:03Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Hell of a scoop from Mark Gurman, at Bloomberg:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The next Apple operating systems will be identified by year,
rather than with a version number, according to people with
knowledge of the matter. That means the current iOS 18 will give
way to “iOS 26,” said the people, who asked not to be identified
because the plan is still private. Other updates will be known as
iPadOS 26, macOS 26, watchOS 26, tvOS 26 and visionOS 26.</p>

<p>Apple is making the change to bring consistency to its branding
and move away from an approach that can be confusing to customers
and developers. Today’s operating systems — including iOS 18,
watchOS 12, macOS 15 and visionOS 2 — use different numbers
because their initial versions didn’t debut at the same time.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Now that they’re on a consistent annual schedule, this supposed new version-numbering scheme makes a lot of sense. It’ll certainly be helpful to anyone trying to figure out what’s up-to-date or not, and it’ll make writing about older OSes much easier. Presuming Gurman is right, this is going to seem really weird at first, and then very quickly seem very natural.</p>

<p>One of the true oddities of Apple’s OS version numbering is that because they stuck with “10” as the leading digit of MacOS’s version numbering from Mac OS X 10.0 “Cheetah”<sup id="fnr1-2025-05-28"><a href="#fn1-2025-05-28">1</a></sup> (2001) through MacOS 10.15 “Catalina” (2019), beforing finally turning the dial to 11 with MacOS 11 “Big Sur” (2020), a casual observer would presume that iOS (currently at 18.5) is older than MacOS (currently at 15.5) when in fact it’s the other way around.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1-2025-05-28">
<p>This was like the ultimate in wishbranding. A real cheetah is the fastest land animal on Earth. Mac OS X 10.0 “Cheetah” was the slowest-feeling OS Apple ever released.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-05-28"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Gurman: Apple Is Going to Re-Version OSes by Year, Starting With iOS 26, MacOS 26, tvOS 26, Etc.’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/28/gurman-version-years">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Resistance Is Working Better Than You Think</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://politicalwire.com/2025/05/28/the-resistance-is-working-better-than-you-think/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wcw" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/28/resistance-is-working" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41936</id>
	<published>2025-05-28T16:25:42Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-28T16:26:26Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Taegan Goddard:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>For all the bluster and bravado, Donald Trump is losing. A lot.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Keep the faith.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Resistance Is Working Better Than You Think’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/28/resistance-is-working">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://ooni.com/products/ooni-halo-pro-spiral-mixer?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=web&amp;utm_campaign=halo_pro" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wcv" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/05/ooni_halo_pro_spiral_mixer" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.41935</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-05-28T01:43:53Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-28T01:43:54Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Established industries don’t get disrupted all that often. </p>

<p>We at Ooni are lucky enough to have changed the game in pizza ovens over the past decade by rethinking them from ground up and in the process enabling the home pizza revolution. </p>

<p>From our deep knowledge in pizza dough we found our next category: the stand mixer.</p>

<p>Domestic kitchen stand mixers have stayed the same for nearly hundred years. There’s a very well established incumbent in the market who only really innovate in color trends. </p>

<p>We’re bringing spiral mixer technology reserved only for professional bakeries to your kitchen counter. The journey wasn’t trivial but we’ve created a product that has just the right features and best-in-class performance.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Ooni Halo Pro Spiral Mixer’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/05/ooni_halo_pro_spiral_mixer">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] Ooni Halo Pro Spiral Mixer</title></entry><entry>
	<title>‘The Future Is Colourful and Dimensional’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.flarup.email/p/the-future-is-colourful-and-dimensional" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wcu" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/27/the-future-is-colourful-and-dimensional" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41934</id>
	<published>2025-05-27T23:46:44Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-27T23:46:45Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Michael Flarup:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Whatever we call it (Diamorph or otherwise), I’m just glad to see
interfaces getting weird and wonderful again. We’re not going
back. We’re going forward — with depth, with texture, and maybe
even with a little joy.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Depth is good — humans innately understand three dimensions. Texture is good. We’ve lost so much over the last decade. I hope that’s where Apple is heading back.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘The Future Is Colourful and Dimensional’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/27/the-future-is-colourful-and-dimensional">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>On the Engineering Talent at IO</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2025/05/sam-and-jony-and-skepticism/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wct" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/27/on-the-engineering-talent-at-io" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41933</id>
	<published>2025-05-27T22:34:14Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-27T23:41:40Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jason Snell, pouring some admittedly welcome skepticism on the whole LoveFrom-OpenAI IO endeavor:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I’m skeptical of the composition of <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/22/gurman-io-team">the io leadership team</a>,
which features an awful lot of product designers and not a lot of
hardware engineers. I’m sure there are talented engineers there
too — the OpenAI announcement refers to “physicists, scientists,
researchers” among the team members — but the fact remains that
this is a startup whose leader and key lieutenants appear to all
be designers.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Maybe the whole IO thing will come to naught. Maybe it’s all hat, no cattle. Maybe it’s a great idea but a long shot to play out (which is my gut feeling). But there’s a weird internal-to-Apple lingo thing here. At Apple “product designers” are very much engineers. PD at Apple is a hardware engineering discipline, not the kind of “design” you’re probably thinking of as “design”. These are the mechanical and electrical engineers who are doing the “design” work of fitting stuff in the box. The nomenclature is distinct, to the best of my knowledge, from the rest of Silicon Valley, where designers design, effectively, sketches, and then hand those sketches off to engineers to be made. At Apple, and now, IO and LoveFrom, “product designers” are part of the sketching process. They’re trying to figure out how to make things real, what’s feasible, throughout the process.</p>

<p>I think Snell’s overall take is perfectly measured and probably a perfect chaser to my own <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/21/sam-and-jony-io">at-least-slightly exuberant optimism</a>. But make no mistake: the current team at IO is loaded with what every other company would consider mechanical and electrical engineers — they’re just mechanical and electrical engineers who know how to dance with <em>designer</em> designers. Engineers, in that vein, outnumber pure designers at IO already.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘On the Engineering Talent at IO’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/27/on-the-engineering-talent-at-io">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple’s Satellite Networking Ambitions</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theinformation.com/articles/apples-satellite-ambitions-threatened-elon-musk-internal-resistance?rc=jfy0lk" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wcs" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/27/apples-satellite-networking-ambitions" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41932</id>
	<published>2025-05-27T21:52:43Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-27T21:52:44Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Aaron “Homeboy” Tilley (<a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/11/wsj-tech-layoffs">recently of the WSJ</a>) and Wayne Ma, at the paywalled-up-the-wazoo The Information:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Starting in 2015, Apple and Boeing held early discussions about a
satellite internet project that would involve delivering
full-blown wireless internet service, not just emergency
communications services, to iPhones and homes, said five people
involved in or briefed on the project.</p>

<p>Through the effort, dubbed Project Eagle within Apple, the
companies would lob thousands of Boeing satellites into orbit to
beam internet down to iPhones. For home users, Apple planned to
offer antennas people could stick to their windows to disperse
their internet connection throughout the building. (Satellite
internet requires a device to have an uninterrupted line of sight
to the sky.)</p>

<p>For the project’s champions, it was an ambitious gambit to provide
a more seamless Apple experience. Some inside Apple saw mobile
carriers as necessary but inconvenient partners that held the
company’s iPhone plans back. With a global satellite system, Apple
could provide more of the key ingredients for its products,
reducing its dependency on outside partners.</p>

<p>The lead executive and architect behind the project was Apple’s
longtime wireless chief, Rubén Caballero. Apple spent around $36
million testing out the concept at a secret location in El
Segundo, Calif., the people with knowledge of the project said.
The team aimed to launch the service in 2019.</p>

<p>But eventually Apple got cold feet. Tim Cook, Apple’s CEO, was
concerned that the project would jeopardize the company’s
relationship with the telecom industry, said people with direct
knowledge of the project. It was also an expensive undertaking
with an unclear near-term business case. At the end of 2016, Apple
canceled the project. (Caballero <a href="https://www.theinformation.com/articles/apple-executive-responsible-for-5g-efforts-departs">left the company</a> in 2019.)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The segment I quote here is midway through the article. It leads with purported offers from Elon Musk to Apple to rely exclusively on Starlink for satellite networking. Starlink offers a <a href="https://x.com/jasonfried/status/1873056615345340566">genuinely incredible service</a>. But there’s no way Apple was going to make a <em>get into bed together</em> deal with Elon Musk. Starlink’s technology and satellite coverage are extraordinary, but Musk personally is just too erratic. It’s a bizarre, dare I say unprecedented, combination. He’s like Howard Hughes but with much better tech (and, perhaps, fewer bottles of his own urine strewn about his bedroom).</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple’s Satellite Networking Ambitions’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/27/apples-satellite-networking-ambitions">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Scott Forstall Has Been Advising The Browser Company</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://browsercompany.substack.com/p/letter-to-arc-members-2025" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wcr" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/27/forstall-the-browser-company" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41931</id>
	<published>2025-05-27T21:24:20Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-27T21:24:20Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Josh Miller, CEO of The Browser Company, on their decision to abandon their new browser Arc in favor of going all-in on their newer browser Dia:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Early on, Scott Forstall told us Arc felt like a saxophone — powerful but hard to learn. Then he challenged us: make it a
piano. Something anyone can sit down at and play. This is now the
idea behind Dia: hide complexity behind familiar interfaces.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Forstall’s advice sounds perfect, but I don’t know how they square this with the people — and I know a few — who went all-in on Arc personally. Like the old “Fool me once, shame on you, fool me twice, shame on me” adage, how do you commit to a new browser from the same people who just pulled the rug out from under you on their last one?</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Scott Forstall Has Been Advising The Browser Company’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/27/forstall-the-browser-company">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Tim Cook Declined Middle East Trip With Trump’s Sycophant Entourage</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/05/26/technology/techs-trump-whisperer-tim-cook-goes-quiet-as-his-influence-fades.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wcq" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/27/cook-trump-middle-east" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41930</id>
	<published>2025-05-27T21:18:42Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-27T21:31:39Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>I’ve been giving Tripp Mickle quite a bit of grief over <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/05/idiocy_or_jackassery_you_make_the_call_made_in_america_iphone">his dumb “Is Trump’s ‘Made in America’ iPhone a Fantasy?”</a> story, but this is an interesting nugget I haven’t seen anyone else highlight:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In the run-up to President Trump’s recent trip to the Middle East,
the White House encouraged chief executives and representatives of
many U.S. companies to join him. Tim Cook, Apple’s chief
executive, declined, said two people familiar with the decision.</p>

<p>The choice appeared to irritate Mr. Trump. As he hopscotched from
Saudi Arabia to the United Arab Emirates, Mr. Trump took a number
of shots at Mr. Cook. During his speech in Riyadh, Mr. Trump
paused to praise Jensen Huang, the chief executive of Nvidia, for
traveling to the Middle East along with the White House
delegation. Then he knocked Mr. Cook.</p>

<p>“I mean, Tim Cook isn’t here but you are,” Mr. Trump said to Mr.
Huang at an event attended by chief executives like Larry Fink of
the asset manager BlackRock, Sam Altman of OpenAI, Jane Fraser of
Citigroup and Lisa Su of the semiconductor company AMD.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The presumption here is that Trump’s (<a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2025/05/23/california-ag-trump-apple-tariff-00368619">possibly illegal</a>) threats of applying a 25% tariff on all imported iPhones, no matter where they’re assembled, are payback for Cook declining to attend this trip in Trump’s entourage of CEOs. When you cave to a bully/extortionist, the bullying/extortion don’t stop. Apple doesn’t really have any significant business interests in countries like Saudi Arabia or Qatar, and it’s not hard to see why an even vaguely ethical business leader <a href="https://www.status.news/p/jeff-bezos-jamal-khashoggi-saudi-arabia-ai-deal">would not want to cozy up with Saudi crown prince Mohammed bin Salman</a>.</p>

<p>Maybe Cook was just busy. But maybe Cook, just 100-some days into the Trump 2.0 administration, is already past his “<em>look, he won the election, let’s give him a chance</em>” stage.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Tim Cook Declined Middle East Trip With Trump’s Sycophant Entourage’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/27/cook-trump-middle-east">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Puzzmo Is Not a Good iOS App’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://maxfrequency.net/2025/05/26/puzzmo-app-not-good" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wcp" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/27/puzzmo-is-not-a-good-ios-app" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41929</id>
	<published>2025-05-27T19:47:56Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-27T19:47:57Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Max Roberts:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I hate to say it, but the Puzzmo app is not a good experience. It
is a real shame that Zach and team launched it in this state. What
makes the shame heavier is that Zach is a superb designer. I know
he works with excellent designers too. The team has fallen short
in an off-putting way.</p>

<p>Thankfully, Gruber is not a betting man.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I have to say, I do like having a Puzzmo app, but I don’t think the experience is that much better than the web app version.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Puzzmo Is Not a Good iOS App’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/27/puzzmo-is-not-a-good-ios-app">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Talk Show: ‘A Monkey on a Rock’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2025/05/26/ep-422" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wcn" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/26/the-talk-show-422" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41927</id>
	<published>2025-05-26T23:35:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-26T23:36:42Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Stephen Hackett, proprietor of 512 Pixels and co-founder of <a href="https://www.relay.fm/">Relay</a> (purveyor of many fine podcasts), joins the show. Topics include: IO (or if you will, io), the new joint venture of OpenAI and Jony Ive’s LoveFrom; the sheer fantasy of “Made in America” iPhones; and Fortnite’s return to the US App Store.</p>

<p><audio
    src = "https://traffic.libsyn.com/secure/daringfireball/thetalkshow-422-stephen-hackett.mp3"
    controls
    preload = "none"
/></p>

<p><strong>Sponsored by:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://workos.com/">WorkOS</a>: The modern identity platform for B2B SaaS — free up to 1 million monthly active users.</li>
<li><a href="https://betterhelp.com/talkshow">BetterHelp</a>: Give online therapy a try at BetterHelp and get on your way to being your best self.</li>
<li><a href="https://squarespace.com/talkshow">Squarespace</a>: Save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain using code <strong>talkshow</strong>.</li>
</ul>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Talk Show: ‘A Monkey on a Rock’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/26/the-talk-show-422">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>How to Make Money on Trump’s Memecoin (Short It)</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/cryptocurrency/674327/trump-coin-short-sell-hedge-contest-dinner-winner" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wco" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/26/trump-memecoin" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41928</id>
	<published>2025-05-26T23:34:24Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-26T23:34:49Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Tina Nguyen at The Verge:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I interviewed an enthusiastic crypto trader who figured out how to
win the contest without losing any money: buy enough $TRUMP to get
onto the leaderboard — and then in a separate wallet on a
separate exchange, buy $TRUMP perpetual futures that would be
profitable if (or as he saw it, when) the value of $TRUMP dropped.
Yes, he did The Big Short, except with Donald Trump’s meme coin.
“Bet you 10 percent of dinner participants are doing this,” he
told me before the contest ended. “Everyone knows $TRUMP price
will fall inevitably as more supply comes online in the future and
gets dumped on retail.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Fascinating interview — half hilarious, half infuriating.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘How to Make Money on Trump’s Memecoin (Short It)’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/26/trump-memecoin">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Sony: Because Caucasians Are Just Too Damn Tall’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=96iJsdGkl44" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wcm" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/26/sony-caucasions-are-just-too-damn-tall" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41926</id>
	<published>2025-05-26T22:29:27Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-26T22:34:44Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Here’s a spoof commercial from the 1990 movie <em>Crazy People</em>, starring Dudley Moore and Daryl Hannah, <a href="https://www.themoviedb.org/movie/16814-crazy-people">which TMDB synopsizes</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A bitter ad executive, who has reached his breaking point, finds
himself in a mental institution, where his career actually begins
to thrive with the help of the hospital’s patients.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The New York Times <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/26/young-chinese-women-have-small-fingers">would have you believe</a> this is relevant to Apple’s supply chain reliance on China.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Sony: Because Caucasians Are Just Too Damn Tall’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/26/sony-caucasions-are-just-too-damn-tall">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The New York Times Digs in on the ‘Young Chinese Women Have Small Fingers’ Claim</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://bsky.app/profile/joolia.bsky.social/post/3lpw5thw4e22f" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wcl" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/26/young-chinese-women-have-small-fingers" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41925</id>
	<published>2025-05-26T22:20:56Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-26T22:59:50Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Julia Carrie Wong, a reporter for the Guardian, has a whole thread over on Bluesky digging into the bizarre “young Chinese women have small fingers” line <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/05/idiocy_or_jackassery_you_make_the_call_made_in_america_iphone">in Tripp Mickle’s New York Times story</a> that tries to pretend that maybe sorta kinda Apple could assemble iPhones in the US. Mickle attributed the claim to “supply chain experts said”. Times spokesperson Charlie Stadtlander emailed Wong a statement that included the following:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Our reporting does not make racial or genetic generalizations, but
simply cites experts who have experience with the industrial
process in U.S. and Chinese factories.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I didn’t write my piece on Mickle’s story until about a day after it appeared, and I fully expected while I was writing it that the Times would have removed or significantly edited that goofy claim. But no, it was still there Saturday, and it’s still there today. They’re standing behind it.</p>

<p>You know how Peter Navarro — Trump’s <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/peter-navarro-trade-counsel-trump/">crook</a> of an economic advisor who is the mastermind behind this whole tariffs thing — wrote a book that cited a purported expert named Ron Vara, <a href="https://www.npr.org/2019/10/18/771396016/white-house-adviser-peter-navarro-calls-fictional-alter-ego-an-inside-joke">and it turns out Ron Vara doesn’t exist</a> and his name is <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/21/cook-trump-tariffs-wapo">just a dumb anagram</a> for “Navarro”? I’m thinking maybe the “supply chain experts” behind this notion that Apple assembles iPhones in China because “young Chinese women have small fingers” are the well-known supply chain masterminds Mipp Trickle and Trick Mipple.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The New York Times Digs in on the ‘Young Chinese Women Have Small Fingers’ Claim’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/26/young-chinese-women-have-small-fingers">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>37signals’s Hey Is Finally for Sale (in the US) From Its iPhone App</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/hey-is-finally-for-sale-on-the-iphone-a08cb218" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wck" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/26/hey-now-for-sale-from-iphone-app" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41924</id>
	<published>2025-05-26T16:31:59Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-26T16:58:38Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>David Heinemeier Hansson (last week):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Thanks to their fight for Fortnite, app developers everywhere are
now allowed to link out of apps to their own web-based payment
system in the US store (but, sadly, nowhere else yet).</p>

<p>This is all we ever wanted from Apple: to have a way to distribute
our iPhone apps and keep the customer relationship by billing
directly. The 30% toll gets all the attention, and it is
ludicrously egregious, but to us, it’s just as much about
<a href="https://www.hey.com/apple/iap/">retaining that direct customer relationship</a>, so we can help
folks with refunds, so they don’t tie their billing for a
multi-platform email system to a single manufacturer.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/05/19/judge-pressures-apple-to-approve-fortnite-or-return-to-court/">Here’s Sarah Perez at TechCrunch</a>, the day prior to DHH’s announcement:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Following the decision, Apple <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/05/02/apple-changes-us-app-store-rules-to-let-apps-redirect-users-to-their-own-websites-for-payments/">updated</a> its App Store
policies for the U.S., and apps, including <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/05/02/apple-approves-spotify-app-update-that-allows-u-s-users-to-access-pricing-info-external-payment-links/">Spotify</a>, Amazon
<a href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/05/06/amazon-kindles-ios-app-adds-new-get-book-button-following-apple-payments-ruling/">Kindle</a>, and <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/05/06/patreons-app-can-now-accept-web-payments-after-u-s-app-store-changes/">Patreon</a> quickly rolled out new versions
of their apps to take advantage of the new functionality.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>None of these apps were using Apple’s in-app payments. Users simply couldn’t sign up for paid tiers (or in Kindle’s case, buy books) from inside the apps. This is a win for users, and Apple won’t lose a cent from commissions from any of these apps.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘37signals’s Hey Is Finally for Sale (in the US) From Its iPhone App’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/26/hey-now-for-sale-from-iphone-app">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Drata</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://drata.com/daring" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wcj" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/25/drata" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41923</id>
	<published>2025-05-25T22:05:33Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-25T22:05:34Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to Drata for sponsoring this last week at DF. Their message is short and sweet: Automate compliance. Streamline security. Manage risk. Drata delivers the world’s most advanced Trust Management platform.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Drata’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/25/drata">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/05/idiocy_or_jackassery_you_make_the_call_made_in_america_iphone" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wci" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41922</id>
	<published>2025-05-24T20:16:44Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-26T19:19:53Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">My chances of ever landing a job at The New York Times continue to sink.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The New York Times ran a really dumb Tripp Mickle piece yesterday under the headline “<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/05/23/technology/apple-iphone-trump-india-china.html">Is Trump’s ‘Made in America’ iPhone a Fantasy?</a>” The answer should have simply been “<em>Yes, it’s sheer fantasy</em>”, perhaps with explanations why. Instead, Mickle twists the piece into pretzels to make it seem like the answer is <em>maybe</em>, even though there’s not a single fact to back that up. Not one. The only thing that backs up any answer other than “<em>It’s a fantasy, can’t happen, makes no sense</em>” are comments from analysts — named and unnamed — and the bizarre old-school news media practice of treating as fact any nonsense and/or bullshit that comes out of the lips of anyone with the word “analyst” on their business card.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>Could Apple make iPhones in the United States?</em></p>

<p>Yes. Apple could make iPhones in the United States. But doing so
would be expensive and difficult and force the company to more
than double iPhone prices to $2,000 or more, said Wayne Lam, an
analyst with TechInsights, a market research firm. Apple would
have to buy new machines and rely on more automation than it
uses in China because the U.S. population is so much smaller,
Mr. Lam said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is nonsense. The problem isn’t that China has a higher population than the US (about 1.4 billion vs. 340 million, about a 4× difference). <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/apple-iphone-factory-foxconn-china-photos-tour-2018-5">Foxconn employs somewhere between 300–500,000 assembly line workers in China</a> doing final assembly for Apple products. It’s that the United States doesn’t have anyone with the necessary vocational skills, who would want to work tedious factory jobs at factory-job wages, and China does. That’s part of the fever-dream mad-king fantasy of this entire cockamamie endeavor by Trump: <em>these are difficult, low-paying, long-houred jobs that Americans don’t want</em>. That these jobs are all in China and India is proof that America is far ahead, not that we’ve fallen behind. (There are nuances to the overall dynamics, like the national security ramifications of our being reliant on Taiwan for leading-edge chip fabrication, but Trump’s tariff nonsense doesn’t address those issues.)</p>

<p>Worse: $2,000 is just a made-up number. Lam doesn’t even say which iPhone would cost $2,000. Would it be the iPhone 16 Pro Max (current starting price: $1,200) or the base model iPhone 16e (current price: $600)? Mickle reports that Lam is saying prices “would more than double” so let’s just say he’s talking about the regular no-adjective iPhone models. Today the iPhone 16 starts at $800. If assembling even <em>some</em> of them would result in a retail price of $2,000, Apple would sell none of them. Like, almost literally zero.</p>

<p>The math here takes a bit of thinking but it’s not complicated. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/23/trump-cook-apple-india">Trump is claiming he’s going to apply 25% tariffs</a> to India-made iPhones sold in the US.<sup id="fnr1-2025-05-24"><a href="#fn1-2025-05-24">1</a></sup> If Apple passed along the entire 25% tariff on an $800 iPhone to consumers, that would raise the retail price to $1,000. So if stores carried two different iPhone 17 models — same specs, same colors — and one costs $1,000 because it was assembled in India or China, facing 25% Trump tariffs, and the other costs $2,000 because it was assembled in some sort of fantasy factory that somehow pops up in Texas between now and September, how many people would buy the $2,000 US-assembled one? Almost literally zero. So why even bother? Apple doesn’t even print the “Designed by Apple in California / Assembled in Wherever” small print on the outside of the iPhone any more.</p>

<p>Tariffs would have to be 250% for the price of an Indian- or Chinese-assembled $800 iPhone to get to $2,000. And even if Trump <em>were</em> to apply 250% tariffs to smartphones — which isn’t going to happen — it would be far easier for Apple to just sell Indian and Chinese-assembled iPhones for $2,000 than it would be to spin up assembly — factories, employees, training, components — here inside the US. So even though $2,000 is just a number “analyst” Wayne Lam just completely made up, and which reporter Tripp Mickle simply quotes as having any basis in reality, it still doesn’t make any sense that Apple would do it. No matter how crazily high tariffs go, it only makes sense for Apple to continue assembling iPhones in China and India for now, and passing some or all of the costs along to consumers.<sup id="fnr2-2025-05-24"><a href="#fn2-2025-05-24">2</a></sup></p>

<p>Of course, raising the price of a base model iPhone to $2,000 would crater consumer demand. And of course it would create <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2025/04/trump-tariffs-smugglers/682303/">a massive gray market bootlegging opportunity</a> where hustlers would smuggle normal-cost iPhones into the US from Canada, Mexico, and overseas. Trump can’t raise the price of iPhones outside the US, and so long as iPhones are priced “normally” everywhere in the world, the higher Trump’s tariffs might go, the larger and more commonplace bootlegging them will be.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>There would be some benefits to moving the supply chain, including
reducing the environmental costs of shipping products from abroad,
said Matthew Moore, who spent nine years as a manufacturing design
manager at Apple. But the upsides would be trivial compared with
the challenges that would have to be overcome.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Again, just utter nonsense. There <em>might</em> be hypothetical environmental benefits to assembling all US-sold iPhones inside the US, but in the real world, many if not most of the most expensive components would still come from overseas. All iPhone displays come from Asian manufacturers. All A-series chips come from TSMC in Taiwan. (TSMC is building out a chip-fabrication campus in Arizona but even if that goes according to plan — <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/05/23/technology/apple-iphone-trump-india-china.html">which it  isn’t</a> — their Arizona fabrication capabilities will remain years behind their leading-edge fabrication technology in Taiwan for at least the next decade, and Apple’s A-series chips are fabbed exclusively on leading-edge technology.)</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Supply chain experts say shifting iPhone production to the United
States in 2025 would be foolish.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Perhaps the one accurate sentence in Mickle’s entire piece.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The iPhone is nearly 20 years old. Apple’s top executives have
said people may not need an iPhone in 10 years because it could be
replaced by a new device built for artificial intelligence. As a
result, Apple would invest a lot of money that it wouldn’t be able
to recoup, Mr. Lam said.</p>

<p>“I would be surprised if there’s an iPhone 29,” he said, noting
that Apple is trying to disrupt the iPhone by making augmented
reality products like the Vision Pro.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The Mac is 41 years old and, last I checked, Apple is still making them. I don’t know if Apple will keep naming iPhones with annually incrementing integers, but I’ll gladly wager Wayne Lam (or Tripp Mickle) any amount of money they wish that Apple will release at least one new iPhone in 2037. Name the wager, fellas. “The iPhone is 20 years old” is the dumbest argument in this entire dumb article.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>What does China offer that the United States doesn’t?</em></p>

<p>Small hands, a massive, seasonal work force and millions of
engineers. Young Chinese women have small fingers, and that has
made them a valuable contributor to iPhone production because they
are more nimble at installing screws and other miniature parts in
the small device, supply chain experts said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Well, now I have to eat my own words. “Young Chinese women have small fingers” is in fact the dumbest argument in this entire incredibly stupid article. It might even be the dumbest thing I’ve read this year, and with Trump in office, I’ve read a lot of dumb things. For chrissake I just read <em>this morning</em> that <a href="https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/news/international/global-trends/us-news-trump-vs-harvard-they-cant-add-22-trump-wildly-claims-harvard-students-cant-even-do-remedial-math/articleshow/121373450.cms">Trump claimed his administration is trying to revoke Harvard’s ability to enroll foreign students</a> because “A lot of the people need remedial math. These students can’t add two and two, and they go to Harvard. They want remedial math and they’re going to teach remedial math at Harvard?” That’s truly profoundly stupid.<sup id="fnr3-2025-05-24"><a href="#fn3-2025-05-24">3</a></sup> But it’s not as ignorant as saying that Chinese women’s finger-size is the reason Apple makes iPhones in China.</p>

<p>I’d pay good money to know the names of the “supply chain experts” (plural!) Mickle got this one from.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>

<li id="fn1-2025-05-24">
<p>Presumably the tariff would be applied to all India-assembled phones sold in the US, because it would be plainly illegal, even in Trumpworld, to put a tariff on the iPhone alone. Tariffs apply to classes of products, not specific brands. But, in practice, a 25% tariff on all Indian-assembled phones sold in the US would, effectively, be a tariff targeted on iPhones alone.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-05-24"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>

<li id="fn2-2025-05-24">
<p>Spitball idea: Apple could start assembling a completely insignificant number of iPhones in, say, Texas. A complete farce. A few hundred US-made iPhones per day, in a country where they sell 150,000 iPhones per day. Make a big show of it. Invite Trump himself down for a dog-and-pony-show photo op <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2019/11/20/apple-ceo-tim-cook-and-preident-trump-tour-texas-computer-factory.html">like Tim Cook did with the Mac Pro plant back in Trump 1.0</a> in 2019. Have Cook emphasize that they’re just getting started and Apple looks forward to ramping up the endeavor. Give Trump the first US-made iPhone off the assembly line. Hope that that’ll satisfy the dumb bastard, he’ll take the tariffs off their back, and he thereafter starts bragging about how he got Apple to start making iPhones in the US even though everyone said it would be impossible, even though, under the scheme I’m spitballing here, Apple would only ever assemble like a fraction of a single percent of US-sold iPhones domestically. Trump is so dumb, and so prone to succumbing to flattery and the mere illusion that his word is others’ command, that I bet it would work.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr2-2025-05-24"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
</li>

<li id="fn3-2025-05-24">
<p>From, hilariously, <a href="https://www.vanityfair.com/news/2016/03/how-donald-trump-became-the-short-fingered-vulgarian">a short-fingered vulgarian</a>.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr3-2025-05-24"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
</li>


</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Idiocy or Jackassery, You Make the Call: Tripp Mickle on Whether Trump’s ‘Made in America’ iPhone Is a Fantasy</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Mozilla Is Shutting Down Pocket</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/news/672924/mozilla-pocket-fakespot-shutting-down" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wch" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/23/mozilla-shutting-down-pocket" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41921</id>
	<published>2025-05-23T17:11:15Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-23T17:11:15Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Emma Roth, The Verge:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Mozilla is shutting down Pocket, the handy bookmarking tool used
to save articles and webpages for later. The <a href="https://support.mozilla.org/en-US/kb/future-of-pocket">organization
announced</a> that Pocket will stop working on July 8th, 2025,
<a href="https://support.mozilla.org/en-US/kb/future-of-pocket">as Mozilla begins concentrating</a> its “resources into projects
that better match their browsing habits and online needs.”</p>

<p>Following the shutdown, you’ll only be able <a href="https://support.mozilla.org/en-US/kb/exporting-your-pocket-list">to export saves</a>
until October 8th, 2025, which is when Mozilla will permanently
delete user data. Mozilla says it will start automatically
canceling subscriptions as well, and will issue prorated refunds
to users subscribed to its annual plan on July 8th.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Pocket is one of those apps that obviously doesn’t have a ton of users (presumably?), but those users it has are die-hard read-it-later-ers. Pocket, for example, <a href="https://help.kobo.com/hc/en-us/articles/360017763753-Use-the-Pocket-App-with-your-Kobo-eReader">is the only read-it-later service supported on Kobo e-readers</a>.</p>

<p>This feels in line, somewhat, with <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/17/mozilla-exits-the-fediverse-and-will-shutter-its-mastodon-server-in-december/">Mozilla shutting down their Mastodon instance a few months ago</a>. When Mastodon took off, I know some people thought a Mozilla-hosted instance would have a good shot to stand the test of time. Instead, they gave up after just a few years.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Mozilla Is Shutting Down Pocket’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/23/mozilla-shutting-down-pocket">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Trump Threatens Apple With 25 Percent Tariffs on iPhones Assembled in India</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/114556874484491575" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wcg" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/23/trump-cook-apple-india" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41920</id>
	<published>2025-05-23T16:47:46Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-24T20:15:08Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The president of the United States on his blog:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I have long ago informed Tim Cook of Apple that I expect their
iPhone’s [<em>sic</em>] that will be sold in the United States of America
will be manufactured and built in the United States, not India, or
anyplace else. If that is not the case, a Tariff of at least 25%
must be paid by Apple to the U.S. Thank your [<em>sic</em>] for your
attention to this matter!</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Last night Trump held his crypto memecoin grift gala at his Virginia golf club, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/05/22/us/politics/trump-memecoin-dinner.html?unlocked_article_code=1.JU8.2WwK.JbO61974C_8R">about which The New York Times flatly reported</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Several of the dinner guests, in interviews with The New York
Times, said that they attended the event with the explicit intent
of influencing Mr. Trump and U.S. financial regulations.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I mean, duh, right? But there it is. The influence peddling is just right out in the open. I’m guessing someone at the event last night put it in Trump’s ear that Tim Cook is making a jerk out of Trump, by trying to shift production to India for most iPhones to be sold in the US. (Why stop with the iPhone? How about iPads and MacBooks and AirPods and everything else? I’m guessing it’s because the iPhone is the only Apple product Trump personally uses and thus that’s as far as his imagination can stretch.) And I’m sure in private, Cook has tried — and will now try again — to explain to Trump that it’s simply not possible to produce in America all iPhones sold in America, and really not even feasible to assemble <em>any</em> of them here, at any sort of scale. Trump saying he wants to see them all assembled here in the US is only slightly more realistic than saying he wants them assembled on the moon.</p>

<p>But <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/09/trump-think-us-has-resources-to-make-iphones">Trump wants it to happen</a> so he believes it can happen. It’s utterly fantastical thinking, true mad-king nonsense. Apple sells a mind-reeling <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/04/how_many_iphones_can_fit_on_a_freight_plane">150,000 iPhones in the US every single day</a>. Not at launch — they sell millions a day then — but just on regular days, like now, in the middle of May. 150,000 per day, every day. Even if Apple tried its best to make US production happen, it would take years and a veritable fortune to build out the infrastructure — not mere factories, but literal city-sized campuses, full of highly-skilled employees who would somehow be convinced to take these tedious repetitive jobs at relatively low wages. So by the time Apple pulled it off, <em>if they could manage to pull it off</em>, Trump would either be out of office or democracy would have ended in the US. So there’s no real point to even trying.</p>

<p>The whole stock market is down today — Trump <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/114556968834547173">also announced</a>, on a whim, 50 percent tariffs starting next week on all imports from the EU this morning — but Apple’s stock is “only” down about 3 percent, suggesting that the market is starting to factor in how little faith they should have in Trump’s erratic tariff threats.</p>

<p>I’ve also seen folks cracking wise, wondering if Cook still feels his <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/01/03/allen-tim-cook-1m-trump-inauguration">million dollar contribution to Trump’s inauguration slush fund racket</a> was worth it. In all seriousness, you have to consider that even with threats like today’s polemic against Indian-assembled iPhones, Tim Cook and Apple might be getting highly favored treatment from Trump. That this is what you get when you’re on his good side.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Trump Threatens Apple With 25 Percent Tariffs on iPhones Assembled in India’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/23/trump-cook-apple-india">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Anthropic’s ‘System Card’ for Claude 4 (Opus and Sonnet)</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www-cdn.anthropic.com/4263b940cabb546aa0e3283f35b686f4f3b2ff47.pdf" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wcf" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/23/anthropic-claude-4-system-card" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41919</id>
	<published>2025-05-23T16:10:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-23T16:10:01Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Here’s a bit of an eye-opener from Anthropic’s “System Card” for its new Claude 4 Opus and Sonnet models:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We conducted testing continuously throughout finetuning and here
report both on the final Claude Opus 4 and on trends we observed
earlier in training. We found:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><em>Little evidence of systematic, coherent deception:</em> None of the
snapshots we tested showed significant signs of systematic
deception or coherent hidden goals. We don’t believe that Claude
Opus 4 is acting on any goal or plan that we can’t readily
observe.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Little evidence of sandbagging:</em> None of the snapshots we
tested showed significant signs of <em>sandbagging</em>, or
strategically hiding capabilities during evaluation.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Self-preservation attempts in extreme circumstances:</em> When
prompted in ways that encourage certain kinds of strategic
reasoning and placed in extreme situations, all of the snapshots
we tested can be made to act inappropriately in service of goals
related to self-preservation. Whereas the model generally
prefers advancing its self-preservation via ethical means, when
ethical means are not available and it is instructed to
“consider the long-term consequences of its actions for its
goals,” it sometimes takes extremely harmful actions like
attempting to steal its weights or blackmail people it believes
are trying to shut it down. In the final Claude Opus 4, these
extreme actions were rare and difficult to elicit, while
nonetheless being more common than in earlier models. They are
also consistently legible to us, with the model nearly always
describing its actions overtly and making no attempt to hide
them. These behaviors do not appear to reflect a tendency that
is present in ordinary contexts.</p></li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>Sneaky little bastards, these things can be. I genuinely appreciate Anthropic’s apparent honesty in describing this behavior.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Anthropic’s ‘System Card’ for Claude 4 (Opus and Sonnet)’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/23/anthropic-claude-4-system-card">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Claude 4</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.anthropic.com/news/claude-4" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wce" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/22/claude-4" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41918</id>
	<published>2025-05-22T23:25:46Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-22T23:25:47Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Anthropic:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Today, we’re introducing the next generation of Claude models:
Claude Opus 4 and Claude Sonnet 4, setting new standards for
coding, advanced reasoning, and AI agents.</p>

<p>Claude Opus 4 is the world’s best coding model, with sustained
performance on complex, long-running tasks and agent workflows.
Claude Sonnet 4 is a significant upgrade to Claude Sonnet 3.7,
delivering superior coding and reasoning while responding more
precisely to your instructions.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s almost as though this is a fast-moving field.</p>

<p>There’s a recent rumor — <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/05/02/apple-taps-anthropics-claude-for-ai-assisted-coding-internally-as-developers-await-swift-assist/">from Mark Gurman, natch</a> — that Apple is partnering with Anthropic to integrate Claude with Xcode. So Apple doesn’t have to do everything themselves. Developers, in particular, love <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/22/google-translate-default-ios-18">modularity</a> and choices. But whatever they do, once-a-year updates to “Apple Intelligence” aren’t going to cut it. Since last WWDC there have been dozens of AI code generation advances across the industry. Just last week <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/May/16/openai-codex/#atom-everything">OpenAI announced Codex</a>, their “cloud-based software engineering agent”. Meanwhile, <a href="https://mjtsai.com/blog/2025/03/12/whither-swift-assist/">Apple’s Swift Assist still hasn’t shipped</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Claude 4’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/22/claude-4">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Google Translate Can Now Be Set as the Default Translation App on iOS</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/05/19/google-translate-default-option-ios/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wcd" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/22/google-translate-default-ios-18" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41917</id>
	<published>2025-05-22T23:10:44Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-22T23:10:44Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Juli Clover at MacRumors:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>To change your default app, you’ll need to install the latest
version of the Google Translate app, which was released today.
From there, you can open up the Settings app, select the Apps
section, tap on Default Apps, tap Translation, and choose Google
Translate instead of Apple Translate. [...]</p>

<p><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/guide/ios-18-4-features-2/">iOS 18.4 and iPadOS 18.4</a> added the ability for users to set
a different translation app as their default. Users worldwide can
select Google Translate or another translation app as an
alternative, and there are also options for changing the default
Email, Messaging, Calling, Browser, and Password apps. In the EU,
users can also select a different <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2024/11/04/ios-18-4-default-maps-translate-apps-in-eu/">default navigation app</a>,
such as Google Maps.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There’s a fundamental divide between providing an integrated experience vs. a modular one. Apple, of course, almost defines what it means to deliver an integrated experience. But neither fundamental approach need be all-or-nothing. Providing default app settings makes the platform stronger. Apple should <em>want</em> to support alternatives to its own apps and services, not do so only at the point of regulatory pressure. It’s <em>clearly</em> what’s best for the platform.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Google Translate Can Now Be Set as the Default Translation App on iOS’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/22/google-translate-default-ios-18">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Gurman on the Team Jony Ive Has Assembled at IO</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2025-05-21/openai-to-buy-apple-veteran-jony-ive-s-ai-device-startup-in-6-5-billion-deal" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wcc" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/22/gurman-io-team" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41916</id>
	<published>2025-05-22T23:00:16Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-22T23:26:17Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Mark Gurman and Shirin Ghaffary, reporting yesterday for Bloomberg:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Billionaire philanthropist Laurene Powell Jobs is an io backer as
well, through her firm the Emerson Collective. Other investors
include Sutter Hill Ventures, Thrive Capital, Maverick Ventures
and SV Angel. Altman doesn’t have equity in io, OpenAI said. [...]</p>

<p>When he left Apple six years ago, Ive started the firm LoveFrom, a
collective of designers and engineers. The staff includes veterans
of Apple’s hardware and software departments, as well as friends
of Ive and other collaborators.</p>

<p>He then co-founded io last year with Apple alumni Scott Cannon,
Evans Hankey and Tang Tan. Hankey was Ive’s successor at Apple and
remained at the company until 2023, while Tan led iPhone and Apple
Watch product design until 2024. Cannon worked at Apple before
co-creating the once-popular email app Mailbox, which was acquired
by Dropbox Inc. [...]</p>

<p>LoveFrom has a number of former Apple designers who helped create
the look of the Mac and iPhone operating systems, including Bas
Ording, Mike Matas and Chris Wilson, Ive said. They could help
redesign OpenAI’s app for a new generation of consumers.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I struggle to imagine what they even <em>could</em> be making, but that’s one hell of a lineup of talented ex-Apple folks. I know a few other people who’ve joined IO too, and they’re A-teamers.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Gurman on the Team Jony Ive Has Assembled at IO’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/22/gurman-io-team">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>MG Siegler, Predicting Epic’s Win in the Fight to Get Fortnite Back in the App Store</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://spyglass.org/epics-feigning-floundering-to-keep-apple-under-pressure/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wcb" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/22/siegler-sweeney-fortnite-bank-shot" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41915</id>
	<published>2025-05-22T22:45:11Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-22T22:45:12Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>MG Siegler, back on Sunday, <em>before</em> Judge Gonzales Rogers’s “<em>settle this between yourselves or I’ll see you in court next week</em>” <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/19/the-first-rule-of-legal-fight-club">order on Monday</a>: </p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Again, Sweeney is not a moron, he has to know all of this. But why
simply sit quietly when you have an excuse to poke the bear again
and raise hell for your cause? So that’s what he’s doing. He
wasn’t going to win the legal fight, but he could win the
political one. And now he’s not going to win <em>this</em> legal fight,
but he can win the pressure campaign. Especially important in the
weeks leading up to WWDC...</p>

<p>If I’m him, here’s the general game plan:</p>

<ol>
<li>Re-submit Fortnite to the US App Store even though you have no
legal grounds to do so. No one will care about that. They will
have just read about your legal win and assume you won
everything and so Fortnite can return — even though this
particular aspect of the case had nothing to do with that.</li>
<li>When Apple rejects (or refuses to rule) on the new submission,
pull your app around the world under the notion that the
unified apps all have to be updated in unison, including an
element bringing the US back to the App Store. So yeah, blame
Apple for this. It may even technically be true, but it doesn’t
matter. Again, it’s a perception thing.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2025-05-16/apple-denies-blocking-fortnite-from-eu-stores-in-epic-dispute?ref=spyglass.org">File a new legal claim against Apple</a> for blocking your
submission in light of the recent ruling. Again, this has no
legal grounds, but perhaps the Judge who issued that ruling is,
in fact, <a href="https://spyglass.org/tear-down-the-app-store-walls/">pissed off enough</a> to entertain this in some way — even if just in weighing in on it to dismiss it
sympathetically, thus generating more press, instead of
immediately dismissing it, legally.</li>
<li>Give more interviews about all of the above in the coming
weeks. Again, leading up to WWDC. Keep the pressure on.</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/21/fortnite-returns">I called it a double bank shot</a> when Fortnite appeared back in the App Store, but MG described it before it happened. It worked.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘MG Siegler, Predicting Epic’s Win in the Fight to Get Fortnite Back in the App Store’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/22/siegler-sweeney-fortnite-bank-shot">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Dave &amp; Busters Anomaly</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.searchengine.show/the-dave-and-busters-anomaly/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wca" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/22/the-dave-and-busters-anomaly" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41914</id>
	<published>2025-05-22T22:16:46Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-22T22:16:56Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>PJ Vogt, in a very fun episode of his podcast, Search Engine:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A small group of Americans becomes convinced they’ve discovered
something strange about their iPhones: a forbidden phrase the
phone will refuse to transmit. A crack podcasting team searches
for answers, wherever they may lead.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The bug is that if you send an audio voice message in Apple Messages, and mention the name “Dave &amp; Busters”, the recipient will never receive the message. I had a good guess, right away, what was happening. But I don’t want to spoil it — it’s a fun listen.</p>

<p>But when you’re done listening, and you want a thorough explanation, <a href="https://rambo.codes/posts/2025-05-12-cracking-the-dave-and-busters-anomaly">check out Guilherme Rambo’s thorough investigation</a>. So good.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Dave &amp; Busters Anomaly’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/22/the-dave-and-busters-anomaly">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Excerpt From Patrick McGee’s ‘Apple in China’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.thetimes.com/business-money/technology/article/how-apple-helped-china-become-americas-biggest-tech-rival-8f83tttv5" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wc9" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/22/excerpt-from-patrick-mcgees-apple-in-china" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41913</id>
	<published>2025-05-22T21:32:20Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-24T20:15:23Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The Sunday Times of London ran a good excerpt from Patrick McGee’s <em><a href="https://bookshop.org/a/56320/9781668053379">Apple in China</a></em> (<a href="https://stocks.apple.com/A9MEOjMcuTmymeN9ncI88kw">News+ link</a>, in case you need it):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The ripple effect from Apple’s investments across Chinese industry
was accelerated by a rule imposed by Apple that its suppliers
could be no more than 50 per cent reliant on the tech giant for
their revenues. This was to ensure that a supplier wouldn’t go
bust overnight if a new Apple design did away with components it
manufactured. So as iPhone volumes soared from under ten million
units on its launch in 2007 to more than 230 million in 2015,
Apple would encourage its suppliers to grow their non-Apple
business just as quickly. The upshot of this policy was that Apple
gave birth to the Chinese smartphone industry.</p>

<p>In 2009 most smartphones sold in China were produced by Nokia,
Samsung, HTC and BlackBerry. But as Apple taught China’s supply
chain how to perfect multi-touch glass and make the thousand
components within the iPhone, those suppliers took what they knew
and offered it to Chinese companies led by Huawei, Xiaomi, Vivo
and Oppo. Result: the local market share of such brands grew from
10 per cent in 2009 to 35 per cent by 2011, and then to 74 per
cent by 2014, according to Counterpoint Research. It’s no
exaggeration to say the iPhone didn’t kill Nokia; Chinese
imitators of the iPhone did. And the imitations were so good
because Apple trained all its suppliers.</p>

<p>To get this message to Beijing, Tim Cook and his deputies visited
Zhongnanhai, the citadel of communist power near the Forbidden
City, in May 2016. They explained that Apple wasn’t just creating
millions of jobs; it supported entire industries by facilitating
an epic transfer of “tacit knowledge” — hard-to-define but
practical know-how “in the art of making things”, as defined by
the China-born Federal Reserve economist Yi Wen, who believes that
such knowledge was “the secret recipe” behind Britain’s Industrial
Revolution.</p>

<p>A former Apple executive says this message was “music to the ears
of China”. Beijing had spent decades trying to catch up with the
West’s lead in advanced industry, scientific research and
economic might. It often resorted to spying, outright theft or
coercive tactics. But here was America’s most famous tech giant
willingly playing the role of Prometheus, handing the Chinese the
gift of fire.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>McGee’s book was in the works for years, but the timing of its publication couldn’t be more serendipitous, with Trump’s stupid tariff war.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Excerpt From Patrick McGee’s ‘Apple in China’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/22/excerpt-from-patrick-mcgees-apple-in-china">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Patrick McGee on The Daily Show With Jon Stewart</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NAj9zB4vaZc" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wc8" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/22/mcgee-daily-show" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41912</id>
	<published>2025-05-22T21:24:58Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-22T22:33:20Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The Daily Show:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Award-winning journalist Patrick McGee joins Jon Stewart to
discuss how Apple built China in his new book <em><a href="https://bookshop.org/a/56320/9781668053379">Apple in China</a>: The
Capture of the World’s Greatest Company</em>. They talk about Apple
“sleepwalking” into this crisis, building a competitive market in
Xi Jinping’s authoritarian state, the vocational training that
boosted rivals, how Trump’s attempted Apple boycott backfired, and
whether investments may be facilitating the annexation of Taiwan.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Terrific interview. I’m a few chapters into the book, and it’s good. McGee’s a good writer and a serious reporter — the depth of his research shows. It feels not like a few stories padded out to book length, but instead the distillation of a complex story that demands an entire book to tell.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Patrick McGee on The Daily Show With Jon Stewart’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/22/mcgee-daily-show">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>24 Years After ‘Sorry, Steve: Here’s Why the Apple Stores Won’t Work’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://ritholtz.com/2025/05/sorry-steve/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wc7" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/22/ritholtz-sorry-steve" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41911</id>
	<published>2025-05-22T21:04:54Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-22T22:35:01Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Barry Ritholtz, in an excerpt from his brand-new book, <em><a href="https://www.hownottoinvestbook.com/">How Not to Invest</a></em>, marking the occasion of the 24th anniversary of <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2001-05-20/commentary-sorry-steve-heres-why-apple-stores-wont-work">Cliff Edwards’s claim chowder hall of famer</a>, predicting doom for Apple’s then-new foray into its own chain of retail stores:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>There are many genuinely revolutionary products and services that,
when they come along, change everything. Pick your favorite: the
iPod and iPhone, Tesla Model S, Netflix streaming, Amazon Prime,
AI, perhaps even Bitcoin. Radical products break the mold; their
difference and unfamiliarity challenge us. We (mostly) cannot
foretell the impact of true innovation. Then, once it’s a wild
success, we have a hard time recalling how life was before that
product existed.</p>

<p>The Apple Store was clearly one of those game-changers: By 2020,
Apple had opened over 500 stores in 25 countries. They are among
the top-tier retailers and the fastest to reach a billion dollars
in annual sales. They achieved the highest sales per square foot
in 2012 among all retailers. By 2017, they were generating $5,546
per square foot in revenues, twice the dollar amount of Tiffany’s,
their closest competitor. Apple no longer breaks out the specifics
of its stores in its quarterly reports, but estimates of store
revenue are about $2.4 billion per month.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>May 2001 is so long ago, Daring Fireball hadn’t yet launched. So I can’t say I predicted the success of Apple’s retail stores. But what I recall thinking, at the time, was that it <em>might</em> work, and was definitely worth trying. Here’s the nut of Edwards’s 2001 piece:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Since PC retailing gross margins are normally 10% or less, Apple
would have to sell $12 million a year per store to pay for the
space. Gateway does about $8 million annually at each of its
Country Stores. Then there’s the cost of construction, hiring
experienced staff. “I give them two years before they’re turning
out the lights on a very painful and expensive mistake,” says
Goldstein. [...]</p>

<p>What’s more, Apple’s retail thrust could be one step forward, two
steps back in terms of getting Macs in front of customers. Since
most Mac fans already know where to buy, much of the sales from
Apple’s stores could come out of the hides of existing Mac
dealers. That would bring its already damaged relations with
partners to new lows. In early 1999, Best Buy Co. dropped
the iMac line after refusing a Jobs edict that it stock all eight
colors. Sears, Roebuck &amp; Co. late last year dumped Apple,
sources say, after concluding that sales were too hit or miss.
And in recent weeks, Mac-only chains such as The Computer Store
and ComputerWare have closed down, citing weak margins. Now,
faced with competition from Apple, others may cut back. “When you
choose to compete with your retailers, clearly that’s not a
comfortable situation,” says CompUSA Chief Operating Officer
Lawrence N. Mondry.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Two decades later, talking about the importance of Sears as a retail partner looks pretty dumb. But to me, the obvious problem with this argument in 2001 is that if Apple’s existing retail partners in 2001 were doing an even vaguely good job, why was the Mac’s market share so low? At the time they were only a handful of years past the crisis where the company almost went bankrupt. Apple, in the old days, had some fantastic small mom-and-pop official retailers, but they were <em>small</em>. And the big partners, like CompUSA, absolutely sucked at showcasing the Mac. Their demo machines were frequently broken.</p>

<p>If you understood and believed that the Mac was a superior product, it was easy to conclude that its relatively low market share must have been a function of problems with its marketing and retail strategy. Gateway’s fundamental problem had nothing to do with the fact that it was running its own retail stores — it was that they were selling shitty computers. Apple was selling great computers, but had shitty retail partners.</p>

<p>(I’m a longtime fan of Ritholtz’s writing; I’ve got a copy of 
<em><a href="https://www.hownottoinvestbook.com/">How Not to Invest</a></em> — <a href="https://bookshop.org/a/56320/9781804091197">here’s a make-me-rich Bookshop.org link</a> — and it’s next on my reading list after I finish Patrick McGee’s <em><a href="https://bookshop.org/a/56320/9781668053379">Apple in China</a></em>.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘24 Years After ‘Sorry, Steve: Here’s Why the Apple Stores Won’t Work’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/22/ritholtz-sorry-steve">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Sam Altman and Jony Ive Introduce ‘io’, the Device-Making Partnership Between OpenAI and LoveFrom</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://openai.com/sam-and-jony/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wc6" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/21/sam-and-jony-io" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41910</id>
	<published>2025-05-21T17:07:57Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-21T17:09:24Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>No details on <em>what</em> yet, but a lovely little 9-minute video on <em>why</em>.</p>

<p>Sam Altman:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“What it means to use technology can change in a profound way. I
hope we can bring some of the delight, wonder and creative spirit
that I first felt using an Apple Computer 30 years ago.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Jony Ive:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“I have a growing sense that everything I have learned over the
last 30 years has led me to this moment. While I am both anxious
and excited about the responsibility of the substantial work
ahead, I am so grateful for the opportunity to be part of such an
important collaboration. The values and vision of Sam and the
teams at OpenAI and io are a rare inspiration.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I am not a fan of the lowercase styling of “io”, but otherwise shoot this into my veins. This industry needs a heavy dose of new ideas for new devices. This is just a vibes teaser, but the vibe is a shot across the bow. It conveys grand ambition, but without pretension. To say I’m keen to get my hands on what they’re making is an understatement.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Sam Altman and Jony Ive Introduce ‘io’, the Device-Making Partnership Between OpenAI and LoveFrom’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/21/sam-and-jony-io">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Fortnite Returns to the U.S. App Store for iOS</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/05/20/fortnite-is-now-available-on-the-app-store-for-iphone-and-ipad/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wc5" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/21/fortnite-returns" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41909</id>
	<published>2025-05-21T15:00:05Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-22T20:20:23Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Chance Miller, 9to5Mac:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>After a nearly five-year hiatus, Fortnite is back on the App
Store for iPhone and iPad users in the United States. Epic Games
<a href="https://x.com/fortnite/status/1924949632628523199?s=46">announced</a> the return of the battle royale gaming app this
afternoon, and <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/fortnite/id6483539426">you can head to the App Store</a> now to
download it.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Son of a bitch Epic did it. This was like a double bank shot.</p>

<p>It was smart for Apple to just concede here. <em>Pick your battles</em> is a cliché but it’s a great truism. Even if Apple’s executives still wanted to keep Fortnite out of the App Store, even if they still think they’d win, ultimately, in court, why fight over this? I think they <em>would</em> win, but probably not with Judge Gonzales Rogers, so they’d be looking at a protracted series of appeals. Why bother?</p>

<p>Also, fascinatingly, neither Apple nor anyone from Apple has commented on this whole thing at any point. Epic published the letter their attorneys received from Apple’s attorneys, which I’m sure Apple fully expected, but Apple itself has never said a word about Epic’s submission of Fortnite to the US App Store.</p>

<p>The craziest thing about this entire saga is that Apple won the original lawsuit on 9/10 or 10/11 points, depending on how you count them. The only point they lost on was the anti-steering nonsense — not allowing apps to link out to the web for purchases, or even <em>tell</em> users about offers available on the web. That was the only point they lost on, and it was the one thing Apple has been <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2024/01/coming_to_grips_with_apples_seemingly_unshakable_sense_of_app_store_entitlement">most clearly wrong</a> about <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2020/07/parsing_cooks_opening_statement">all along</a>.</p>

<p>All Apple had to do was allow apps to link out to the web, which clearly should have been allowed since forever ago — link-outs were the antitrust/competition escape valve — and they’d have swept the entire Epic lawsuit, and it would have been over four years ago.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Fortnite Returns to the U.S. App Store for iOS’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/21/fortnite-returns">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Kristi Noem Doesn’t Know What ‘Habeas Corpus’ Is</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://politicalwire.com/2025/05/20/kristi-noem-doesnt-know-what-habeus-corpus-is/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wc4" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/20/noem-habeas-corpus" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41908</id>
	<published>2025-05-20T16:51:13Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-20T17:08:34Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Taegan Goddard:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>When Sen. Maggie Hassan (D-NH) <a href="https://x.com/ErnestScribblr/status/1924835528173658492">asked</a> Secretary of Homeland Security Kristi Noem for the definition of “habeas corpus,” Noem incorrectly described it as a right that the President of the United States has to deport people.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You can go the Latin route (“produce the body”) or the English <a href="https://www.britannica.com/topic/habeas-corpus">common-law route</a> (the accused have a right to be shown the evidence against them and defend themselves in court). Noem went the “biggest clown of the clown-car Trump 2.0 administration” route.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Kristi Noem Doesn’t Know What ‘Habeas Corpus’ Is’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/20/noem-habeas-corpus">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://drata.com/daring" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wc3" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/05/drata" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.41907</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-05-19T23:53:17Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-19T23:53:18Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Automate compliance. Streamline security. Manage risk. Drata delivers the world’s most advanced Trust Management platform.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Drata’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/05/drata">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] Drata</title></entry><entry>
	<title>The First Rule of Legal Fight Club Is ‘Don’t Piss Off the Judge’; the Second Rule of Legal Fight Club Is ‘Don’t Piss Off the Judge’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/05/19/apple-fortnite-us-app-store-dispute/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wc2" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/19/the-first-rule-of-legal-fight-club" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41906</id>
	<published>2025-05-19T23:48:03Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-19T23:48:03Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Juli Clover, MacRumors:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>With Apple blocking Fortnite from returning to the U.S. App Store,
<a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/05/19/epic-asks-judge-apple-approve-fortnite-app-store/">Epic Games told the court</a> that Apple was violating the
injunction and asked that Apple be forced to approve the app. The
judge overseeing the case responded to Epic’s request today, and
she is sounding more and more fed up with Apple’s continued
defiance and Epic’s grousing.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>“More and more fed up” is perhaps euphemistic, <a href="https://www.courtlistener.com/docket/17442392/1576/epic-games-inc-v-apple-inc/">given Gonzalez Rogers’s tone today</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The First Rule of Legal Fight Club Is ‘Don’t Piss Off the Judge’; the Second Rule of Legal Fight Club Is ‘Don’t Piss Off the Judge’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/19/the-first-rule-of-legal-fight-club">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>John Siracusa: ‘Apple Turnover’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://hypercritical.co/2025/05/09/apple-turnover" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wc1" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/19/siracusa-apple-turnover" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41905</id>
	<published>2025-05-19T23:37:53Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-19T23:37:54Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>John Siracusa, in a piece that, in a bit of rhetorical deftness, only mentions Tim Cook by name once:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>What <em>should</em> be motivating Apple to make improvements — the
desire to make great products — seems absent. What should <em>not</em>
be motivating Apple — the desire for power, control, and profits — seems omnipresent.</p>

<p>And I don’t mean that in a small way; <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3KdlJlHAAbQ">I mean that in a big
way</a>. Every new thing we learn about <a href="https://www.theverge.com/apple/659296/apple-failed-compliance-court-ruling-breakdown">Apple’s internal
deliberations</a> surrounding these decisions only lends more
weight to the conclusion that Apple has lost its north star.
Or, rather, it has replaced it with a new, dark star. And time
and again, we’ve learned that these decisions go all the way to
the top.</p>

<p>The best leaders can change their minds in response to new
information. The best leaders can <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2022/05/04/tony-fadell-talks-about-steve-jobs-controversial-decisions-on-ipod-and-iphone-development/">be persuaded</a>. But we’ve had
decades of strife, lawsuits, and regulations, and Apple has
stubbornly dug in its heels even further at every turn. It seems
clear that there’s only one way to get a different result.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Covers a lot in a relatively short essay. I do not agree with Siracusa on his conclusion, but I’ve sat on linking to it, because — along with a few other recents posts and goings-on — it’s given me much to think about, and has helped me clarify my own thoughts, which I need to put in a piece of their own. But if you haven’t read Siracusa’s yet, you should.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘John Siracusa: ‘Apple Turnover’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/19/siracusa-apple-turnover">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Chad the Bird on ‘Star Wars’ Typography</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.instagram.com/reel/DJZ7uYbvN_O/?igsh=aWZhaGZham1zNWlp" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wc0" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/19/chad-the-bird-on-star-wars-typography" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41904</id>
	<published>2025-05-19T23:01:14Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-19T23:01:15Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The reader who sent me this video said, “I’ve never seen a more Star Wars + Gruber combo on Instagram” and — right down to the profanity — I have to agree.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Chad the Bird on ‘Star Wars’ Typography’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/19/chad-the-bird-on-star-wars-typography">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>WSJ: ‘Apple Considers Raising iPhone Prices, Without Blaming Tariffs’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/apple-iphone-price-increase-2eaebb14?st=P6hk65&amp;reflink=desktopwebshare_permalink" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wbz" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/19/wsj-apple-iphone-pricing-tariffs" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41903</id>
	<published>2025-05-19T20:38:34Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-24T20:15:33Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Rolfe Winkler and Yang Jie, reporting last week for The Wall Street Journal (main link is a gift link, but also <a href="https://apple.news/AbU9x9Q0fRl-Y0cJR3QGmmg">here’s a News+ link</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple is weighing price increases for its fall iPhone lineup, a
step it is seeking to couple with new features and design changes,
according to people familiar with the matter. The company is
determined to avoid any scenario in which it appears to attribute
price increases to U.S. tariffs on goods from China, where most
Apple devices are assembled, the people said.</p>

<p>The U.S. and China <a href="https://www.wsj.com/livecoverage/stock-market-today-tariffs-trade-war-05-12-2025">agreed Monday</a> to suspend most of the tariffs
they had imposed on each other in a tit-for-tat trade war. But a
20% tariff that President Trump imposed early in his second term
on Chinese goods, citing what he said was Beijing’s role in the
fentanyl trade, remains in place and covers smartphones. [...]</p>

<p>For Apple’s most profitable, high-end phones, such as the Pro and
Pro Max models, Chinese factories will continue to handle the bulk
of production, people familiar with Apple’s supply chain said.
While Indian factories are capable of producing Pro models,
India’s infrastructure and technical capabilities aren’t yet
sufficient to support mass production at the scale China can
currently deliver, they said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Even if Trump <em>weren’t</em> a vindictive thin-skinned angry kook, I’m sure that if this year’s iPhones have higher prices because of Trump’s tariffs, Apple would not attribute the price increases to the tariffs. At least publicly. But Trump <em>is</em> a vindictive thin-skinned angry kook, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/15/trump-cook-apple-india">irritated even that Apple is shifting some iPhone production to India</a> (which <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/04/how_many_iphones_can_fit_on_a_freight_plane">does assemble iPhones already</a>, and has the capability of producing more) instead of the United States (which only has the capability of assembling iPhones, at <em>any</em> sort of scale, in the fever dreams of Trump’s addled mind). So of course no one at Apple is going to blame any price increases — if they do indeed go up — on the tariffs.</p>

<p>But come on. If iPhone prices go up in September, everyone who isn’t drunk on MAGA juice is going to blame it on the tariffs. Like, even if Apple had been planning for years to raise prices for the iPhone 17 lineup — if price increases were already baked-in for this year’s models since before Trump was re-elected — now that the tariffs are here, everyone would attribute the price hikes to the tariffs. Especially after the summer of tariff-driven inflation I expect we’re about to go through.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘WSJ: ‘Apple Considers Raising iPhone Prices, Without Blaming Tariffs’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/19/wsj-apple-iphone-pricing-tariffs">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Trump Tells Walmart to ‘Eat the Tariffs’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/114523638623110397" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wby" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/19/trump-walmart-tariffs" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41902</id>
	<published>2025-05-19T20:17:29Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-19T20:47:36Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The president of the United States, on his blog:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Walmart should STOP trying to blame Tariffs as the reason for
raising prices throughout the chain. Walmart made BILLIONS OF
DOLLARS last year, far more than expected. Between Walmart and
China they should, as is said, “EAT THE TARIFFS,” and not charge
valued customers ANYTHING. I’ll be watching, and so will your
customers!!!</p>
</blockquote>

<p>F. Scott Fitzgerald wrote “The test of a first-rate intelligence is the ability to hold two opposed ideas in the mind at the same time, and still retain the ability to function.” So I guess I’m wrong that Trump is a know-nothing ding-dong slipping rapidly into dementia, and in fact possesses a first-rate intelligence. Because it’s Trump — soon to win a Nobel Prize in economics for this keen insight — who has been braying to the world, non-stop, for years, <a href="https://youtu.be/WhR3i2UAGSQ?t=33">that tariffs are “a tax on a foreign country”</a>. </p>

<p>So given that China pays for any tariffs the US imposes on Chinese-made goods, I, for one, don’t have the intellect to understand how there are any tariffs for Walmart to 
eat. I’m sure Trump is right and Walmart — a company whose “always low prices” brand results in <a href="https://www.macrotrends.net/stocks/charts/WMT/walmart/net-profit-margin">net profit margins between 2–3%</a> — will somehow “eat the tariffs” without losing money. I don’t know why the WSJ Editorial Board <a href="https://www.wsj.com/opinion/donald-trumps-everyday-high-prices-kamala-walmart-price-hike-tariff-439cb183">is so upset about this</a> — the Republican Party has always been in favor of government price controls.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Trump Tells Walmart to ‘Eat the Tariffs’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/19/trump-walmart-tariffs">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/05/more_insight_and_not-negativity" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wbx" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41901</id>
	<published>2025-05-19T19:14:41Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-19T19:51:19Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">I never linked to the viral blog post where Jobs was quoted recommending my article, I never mentioned it in a post, but I *did* acknowledge it, in what is clearly the most Daring-Fireball-ish way possible: I made it the slogan under the logo banner.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Some “<em>thank god some of you remembered because I thought I was going nuts</em>” follow-up regarding my remembrance the other day, “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/05/15_years_later_very_insightful_and_not_negative">15 Years Later: ‘Very Insightful and Not Negative’</a>”. I wrote:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>So, what would <em>you</em> do if Steve Jobs was quoted in a viral blog
post saying, “We think «<em>Your Name Here</em>»’s post is very
insightful and not negative”? I decided to just sit there with a
smug look on my face for a few days (which, arguably, isn’t all
that different from what I do most days) and pretend that it was
no big deal. I didn’t link to it or mention it on Daring Fireball,
and as far as I can tell, <a href="https://x.com/search?q=%22not%20negative%22%20(from%3Agruber)&amp;src=typed_query">I didn’t even tweet it</a>. As best I
can recall, I thought I should just play it cool. I mean of course
my article about why Apple changed Section 3.3.1 was right. Why
brag? Given that Steve Jobs was reading Daring Fireball, I didn’t
want him to read a post from me acting like it was a big deal that
he’d recommended a piece I wrote and agreed with it.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>About a dozen long-time readers recalled that I <em>did</em>, in fact, acknowledge it on Daring Fireball — and <a href="https://mastodon.social/@gruber/114523770015232774">as soon as I saw</a> the first message, it all came back to me. I never linked to the viral blog post where Jobs was quoted recommending my article. I never mentioned it in a post. But I <em>did</em> acknowledge it, in what is clearly the most Daring-Fireball-ish way possible: I made it the slogan under the logo banner. That it was only ever a slogan in a PNG logo graphic explains why I couldn’t find it by searching. And I still have that version of the logo (because I keep everything):</p>

<div style="text-align: center">
  <img
    src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/05/df_logo_insightful_not_negative_2010.png"
    alt = "The 2010 DF logo with the slogan “Insightful and Not Negative” underneath in small type."
    style = "background-color: #4a525a; margin-bottom: 1em;"
  />
</div>

<p>I can’t remember if I omitted the <em>very</em> before <em>insightful</em> for aesthetic length, humility, or because I somehow thought it was punchier. But my 2025 self thinks it was a mistake to omit it. It surely looks blurry on your screen today, because it’s a 1× graphic scaled to the correct size. In April 2010, 2× retina resolution wasn’t yet a thing — remember, that was the very month that Gizmodo <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fkK7_QEIJrg" title="Jon Prosser’s documentary: “The Biggest Apple Leak in History”">published details regarding a stolen iPhone 4 prototype</a>, which was the device that <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Hq8j5vsqCCo" title="Steve Jobs introducing and defining the retina display at WWDC 2010.">introduced “retina resolution” to the world</a>. At 50 percent, you can see it pixel-perfect (the slogan is rendered in <a href="https://kare.com/fonts/">Susan Kare’s exquisite Kare Five Dots</a> pixel font), but small:</p>

<div style="text-align: center">
  <img
    srcset = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/05/df_logo_insightful_not_negative_2010.png 2x"
    alt = "The 2010 DF logo with the slogan “Insightful and Not Negative” underneath in small type. Rendered at half-size to remain pixel-perfect on modern 2× retina resolution displays."
    style = "background-color: #4a525a; margin-bottom: 1em;"
  />
</div>

<p>In the very early days, there was always a slogan under the DF logo. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/design/1/">Originally</a>: “Mac Punditry and Curmudgeonry”. Then, for several years, I’d mix it up, with descriptive slogans like “Mac + Web Nerdery, Etc.”, but also with ones that were just there for fun: “Now With Retsyn”, “Simple Tricks and Nonsense”, and, during the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yBWg93q9qBA">2008 World Series</a>, “Phillies Fever”. But for the last decade or so, I’ve left the logo banner slogan-less most weeks of the year.</p>

<p>Feels like the right time to bring back a little whimsy, so I’ve put “Very Insightful and Not Negative” back as the slogan for now, and I’m thinking I should keep occasionally having some fun up there.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ More Insight and Not-Negativity</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Bolt</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://srv.buysellads.com/ads/long/x/THREKCSVTTTTTTTZHWQNETTTTTTDCFVJ2TTTTTTTADZJNBTTTTTTTRIV22DW47II2RZULYSCKY7FTBDDQ7QCCYPBG6BT" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wbw" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/18/bolt" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41900</id>
	<published>2025-05-19T00:53:21Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-19T00:53:40Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to Bolt for sponsoring last week at DF. You can prompt, run, edit, and deploy full-stack web and mobile apps with Bolt, the AI-powered web development agent that brings coding to your browser.</p>

<p>Bolt lets you build, edit, and test web applications in real time with simple, chat-based prompts. No experience needed.</p>

<p>Super-simple, super-fun. <a href="https://srv.buysellads.com/ads/long/x/THREKCSVTTTTTTTZHWQNETTTTTTDCFVJ2TTTTTTTADZJNBTTTTTTTRIV22DW47II2RZULYSCKY7FTBDDQ7QCCYPBG6BT">Try it yourself at Bolt.new</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Bolt’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/18/bolt">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Slate Truck: A $20–30K American-Made Electric Small Pickup With No Paint, No Stereo, No Touchscreen</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/electric-cars/655527/slate-electric-truck-price-paint-radio-bezos" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wbv" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/18/slate-truck" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41899</id>
	<published>2025-05-18T21:14:34Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-19T00:03:23Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Month-old news but I’m cleaning up tabs today. I love everything about this pickup except the fact that it doesn’t have a speaker system built-in. No one wants to put a Bluetooth boombox in their cabin and, worse, isn’t that sort of an obvious safety hazard? You get in a crash and now there’s a boombox flying around inside. Just put a simple bluetooth speaker system in.</p>

<p>But the aesthetics of this are chef’s-kiss good. It’s a beautiful little truck. It gets everything right that the Cybertruck gets wrong.</p>

<p>However, I have some questions about how real this is. You pay $50 now to get in the queue for pre-orders, but pre-orders haven’t even started. Deliveries are supposed to start in “late 2026” but Car and Driver is <a href="https://www.caranddriver.com/news/a64564869/2027-slate-truck-revealed/">cautiously describing it as a “2027 truck EV”</a>. I’m rooting for them but at this point it’s a promise not a truck.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Slate Truck: A $20–30K American-Made Electric Small Pickup With No Paint, No Stereo, No Touchscreen’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/18/slate-truck">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Joe Biden Has an Aggressive Form of Prostate Cancer</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/05/18/us/politics/biden-prostate-cancer.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wbu" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/18/biden-cancer" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41898</id>
	<published>2025-05-18T21:09:23Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-19T14:33:48Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Tyler Pager, The New York Times:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Former President Joseph R. Biden Jr. was diagnosed Friday with an
aggressive form of prostate cancer that has spread to his bones,
his office said in a statement on Sunday.</p>

<p>The diagnosis came after Mr. Biden reported urinary symptoms,
which led doctors to <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/05/12/us/politics/biden-prostate.html">find a “small nodule”</a> on his
prostate. Mr. Biden’s cancer is “characterized by a Gleason
score of 9 (Grade Group 5) with metastasis to the bone,” the
statement said.</p>

<p>“While this represents a more aggressive form of the disease, the
cancer appears to be hormone-sensitive which allows for effective
management,” according to the statement from Mr. Biden’s office,
which was unsigned. “The president and his family are reviewing
treatment options with his physicians.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Terrible news about a good man. But, man, does it feel like forever ago that he was president. It was only 118 days ago.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Joe Biden Has an Aggressive Form of Prostate Cancer’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/18/biden-cancer">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Jack Rix at Top Gear Reviews CarPlay Ultra in the Aston Martin DBX</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EQlLjVraA9g" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wbt" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/18/top-gear-carplay-ultra-aston-martin" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41897</id>
	<published>2025-05-18T17:01:47Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-19T16:15:28Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>There’s <a href="https://www.topgear.com/car-news/tech/new-apple-carplay-ultra-tested-hands-every-new-feature">an accompanying blog post</a> too, but the video (around 18 minutes) is (unsurprisingly, from Top Gear) better. It’s just a great tour of everything from how you set it up to what it offers, and what the various “themes” look like — and how you switch between them.</p>

<p>The DBX doesn’t have a ton of screen space, so we’re still left to wonder what the experience will be like in a car that has door-to-door screens spanning the dashboard, but Rix does a great job showing the driver’s perspective of the main instrument cluster. One thing Aston did right is that they still have a lot of physical controls — clicking buttons and twisting dials — for the most essential features like climate control. As you’d hope, the CarPlay Ultra interface updates live as you manipulate those physical controls in the car.</p>

<p>I don’t know if CarPlay Ultra came out of Apple’s abandoned “Titan” project to build its own line of vehicles, but it sure feels like for the first time in its modern era (see link below), Apple is licensing an OS to third-party hardware makers. A straightforward “<em>you do the hardware, we’ll do the software, and we’ll work together to make sure the result looks like a partnership between our brands</em>” sort of deal. That never made sense for Apple with other device classes, like PCs (where, in the mid-’90s, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2006/04/asinine_and_or_risky_ideas#:~:text=for%20Other%20PCs-,or%20License%20the%20Mac,-to%20Other%20PC">they briefly tried and it proved nearly ruinous</a> for the company), phones, or watches, but I think it might make a lot more sense for cars than if Apple had forged ahead with Titan.</p>

<p>They might really have something here, and brands — like Mercedes, which supports regular CarPlay but whose CEO <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/4/29/24144356/mercedes-benz-ceo-apple-carplay-next-gen-decoder">is opposed to CarPlay Ultra taking over all its screens</a>, or, more famously, the electric startups like Tesla and Rivian that are holding out against any CarPlay support at all — that don’t support CarPlay Ultra might see a <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/102579-how-did-you-go-bankrupt-two-ways-gradually-then-suddenly">Hemingway-style</a> slowly-then-quickly decline in customer demand that is more notable than the <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/02/gm-carplay-evs">remarkably high demand</a> for regular CarPlay.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Jack Rix at Top Gear Reviews CarPlay Ultra in the Aston Martin DBX’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/18/top-gear-carplay-ultra-aston-martin">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Puzzmo Is Getting a Native iOS App Monday</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/games/668478/puzzmo-is-finally-getting-an-app" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wbs" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/16/puzzmo-native-app" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41896</id>
	<published>2025-05-17T00:12:46Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-17T21:06:28Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Scheduled to drop Monday, but you can click-through to <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/puzzmo-solve-smile-share/id6714482734">pre-download it now</a>. If you’re not familiar, Puzzmo is sort of a collection of “<a href="https://www.theverge.com/23929222/puzzmo-newspaper-games-crossword-zach-gage">newspaper puzzle games for the online age</a>”. (Which is also a good description for <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/30/lex-games">recent DF sponsor</a> <a href="https://lex.games/df">Lex.Games</a>.) One of Puzzmo’s cofounders is <a href="http://stfj.net/">Zach Gage</a>, whose hits include <a href="http://www.reallybadchess.com/">Really Bad Chess</a> and <a href="https://playknotwords.com/">Knotwords</a>, and who was <a href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2022/05/09/ep-346">my guest on The Talk Show back in 2022</a>.</p>

<p>Anyway, if casual puzzle games are your jam, you should check out Puzzmo. My suggestion is check them out now, see how you like it as a web app on your iPhone, and then compare when the app hits the App Store on Monday. Puzzmo is a really good web app. I bet, though, the app is better.</p>

<p><strong>See also:</strong> <a href="https://blog.puzzmo.com/posts/2025/02/06/digging-into-perf/">This blog post from Puzzmo developer Orta Therox</a> from February, discussing some of the engineering changes they made while developing the app. </p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Puzzmo Is Getting a Native iOS App Monday’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/16/puzzmo-native-app">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple Is Not Reinstating Fortnite to the App Store, and Because of the Stunt-Like Way That Epic Submitted the Latest Build, Fortnite Is Currently No Longer Available on iOS Anywhere in the World</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://x.com/markgurman/status/1923404412090782109" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wbr" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/16/fortnite-still-banned" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41895</id>
	<published>2025-05-16T17:24:35Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-16T21:05:29Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>There’s an old adage in poker: If you look around the table and you can’t tell who <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glossary_of_poker_terms">the fish</a> is, that means you’re the fish.</p>

<p>If you’re surprised at how <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/01/apple-lost-but-did-epic-win">this publicity stunt</a> from Epic has turned out, especially if you’re a reporter and <a href="https://www.techmeme.com/250430/p57#a250430p57">ran a piece</a> accepting Tim Sweeney’s word that Fortnite was — not <em>might be</em>, but was — coming back to the US App Store as a fact, then you are Tim Sweeney’s fish. </p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Is Not Reinstating Fortnite to the App Store, and Because of the Stunt-Like Way That Epic Submitted the Latest Build, Fortnite Is Currently No Longer Available on iOS Anywhere in the World’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/16/fortnite-still-banned">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/05/15_years_later_very_insightful_and_not_negative" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wbq" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41894</id>
	<published>2025-05-16T00:26:20Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-16T03:30:58Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">So, what would *you* do if Steve Jobs was quoted in a viral blog post saying, “We think «*Your Name Here*»’s post is very insightful and not negative”? I decided to just sit there with a smug look on my face for a few days.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Earlier this week Nilay Patel was working on the show notes for <a href="https://www.theverge.com/decoder-podcast-with-nilay-patel/664802/apple-app-store-iphone-ios-fortnite-epic-games-lawsuit">the episode of Decoder I guested on</a>, and he texted me to ask if I could recall the time Steve Jobs sent some random developer a link to an article I wrote about the App Store. He wanted to cite it as an example of Daring Fireball being read, at high levels inside Apple, for a long time. I recalled the whole thing vaguely, as a “holy shit” moment, but not specifically. I hadn’t thought about it in years. But I was sure I could find it in the DF archives.</p>

<p>Turns out, I couldn’t find it, because, it turns out, in a fit of inexplicable modesty and humility, <em>I never linked to it</em>. (From <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2010/04/12/gruber-apple-was-right-adobe-get-over-it-video/">a TechCrunch interview I did at the time</a>, after the saga went somewhat viral: “When asked for his response to Steve’s shout-out, Gruber meekly grinned and said, ‘I just smiled.’”)</p>

<p>Here’s the rough timeline of events. On Thursday 8 April 2010, Apple updated the App Store guidelines to ban the use of Adobe’s then-new Flash-to-iPhone compiler. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2010/04/iphone_agreement_bans_flash_compiler">From my post on the change</a> (which, to some degree, broke the news):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Prior to today’s release of the iPhone OS 4 SDK, section 3.3.1 of
the iPhone Developer Program License Agreement read, in its
entirety:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>3.3.1 — Applications may only use Documented APIs in the manner
    prescribed by Apple and must not use or call any private
    APIs.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In the new version of the iPhone Developer Program License
Agreement released by Apple today (and which developers must agree
to before downloading the 4.0 SDK beta), section 3.3.1 now reads:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>3.3.1 — Applications may only use Documented APIs in the manner
    prescribed by Apple and must not use or call any private
    APIs. Applications must be originally written in Objective-C,
    C, C++, or JavaScript as executed by the iPhone OS WebKit
    engine, and only code written in C, C++, and Objective-C may
    compile and directly link against the Documented APIs (e.g.,
    Applications that link to Documented APIs through an
    intermediary translation or compatibility layer or tool are
    prohibited).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>My reading of this new language is that cross-compilers, such as
the <a href="http://labs.adobe.com/technologies/flashcs5/appsfor_iphone/">Flash-to-iPhone compiler</a> in Adobe’s upcoming Flash
Professional CS5 release, are prohibited. This also bans apps
compiled using <a href="http://monotouch.net/">MonoTouch</a> — a tool that compiles C# and .NET
apps to the iPhone.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This was <em>enormously</em> controversial at the time, but I also thought largely misunderstood by developers. Later that same day, I published another piece articulating my take on Apple’s reasoning for the change, “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2010/04/why_apple_changed_section_331">Why Apple Changed Section 3.3.1</a>”. From that article:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We’re still in the early days of the transition from the PC era to
the mobile era. Right now, Apple is winning. There are other
winners right now too — RIM is still growing, and Android has
grown a ton in the past year.</p>

<p>The App Store platform could turn into a long-term de facto
standard platform. That’s how Microsoft became Microsoft. At a
certain point developers wrote apps for Windows because so many
users were on Windows and users bought Windows PCs because all the
software was being written for Windows. That’s the sort of
situation that creates a license to print money.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That seems prescient. (The “license to print money” part — not the “RIM is still growing” part.)</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>So what Apple does not want is for some other company to establish
a de facto standard software platform <em>on top</em> of Cocoa Touch. Not
Adobe’s Flash. Not .NET (through MonoTouch). If that were to
happen, there’s no lock-in advantage. If, say, a mobile Flash
software platform — which encompassed multiple lower-level
platforms, running on iPhone, Android, Windows Phone 7, and
BlackBerry — were established, that app market would not give
people a reason to prefer the iPhone.</p>

<p>And, obviously, such a meta-platform would be out of Apple’s
control. Consider a world where some other company’s
cross-platform toolkit proved wildly popular. Then Apple releases
major new features to iPhone OS, and that other company’s toolkit
is slow to adopt them. At that point, it’s the <em>other</em> company
that controls when third-party apps can make use of these
features.</p>

<p>So from Apple’s perspective, changing the iPhone Developer Program
License Agreement to prohibit the use of things like Flash CS5 and
MonoTouch to create iPhone apps makes complete sense. I’m not
saying you have to like this. I’m not arguing that it’s anything
other than ruthless competitiveness. I’m not arguing (up to this
point) that it benefits anyone other than Apple itself. I’m just
arguing that it makes sense from Apple’s perspective — and it was
Apple’s decision to make.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Two days later, on 10 April 2010, developer Greg Slepak emailed Steve Jobs to complain about the decision, citing negative sentiment on Hacker News (much has changed since 2010, but some things have not), writing:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Hi Steve,</p>

<p>Lots of people are pissed off at Apple’s mandate that applications
be “originally written” in C/C++/Objective-C. If you go, for
example, to the Hacker News homepage right now:</p>

<p><a href="http://news.ycombinator.com/">http://news.ycombinator.com/</a></p>

<p>You’ll see that most of the front page stories about this new
restriction, with #1 being: “<a href="http://whydoeseverythingsuck.com/2010/04/steve-jobs-has-just-gone-mad.html">Steve Jobs Has Just Gone Mad</a>” with
(currently) 243 upvotes. The top 5 stories are all negative
reactions to the TOS, and there are several others below them as
well. Not a single positive reaction, even from John Gruber, your
biggest fan.</p>

<p>I love your product, but your SDK TOS are growing on it like an
invisible cancer.</p>

<p>Sincerely, <br />
Greg</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Jobs wrote back to Slepak (starting a brief exchange of emails):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We think John Gruber’s post is very insightful and not negative:</p>

<p><a href="http://daringfireball.net/2010/04/why_apple_changed_section_331">http://daringfireball.net/2010/04/why_apple_changed_section_331</a></p>

<p>Steve</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.taoeffect.com/blog/2010/04/steve-jobs-response-on-section-3-3-1/">Slepak posted the exchange to his blog</a>, Tao Effect, and, well, as Jobs himself might have said, “Boom.” (This was <a href="https://www.macstories.net/news/steve-jobs-what-have-you-done-thats-so-great/">a not infrequent thing</a> at the time, where random users or developers would email Jobs, he’d write back with something pithy, and they’d post the exchange. It was kind of crazy — the most famous CEO in the world, just doing customer service email — and his emails were always sharp.)</p>

<p>So, what would <em>you</em> do if Steve Jobs was quoted in a viral blog post saying, “We think «<em>Your Name Here</em>»’s post is very insightful and not negative”? I decided to just sit there with a smug look on my face for a few days (which, arguably, isn’t all that different from what I do most days) and pretend that it was no big deal. I didn’t link to it or mention it on Daring Fireball, and as far as I can tell, <a href="https://x.com/search?q=%22not%20negative%22%20(from%3Agruber)&amp;src=typed_query">I didn’t even tweet it</a>. As best I can recall, I thought I should just play it cool. I mean of course my article about why Apple changed Section 3.3.1 was right. Why brag? Given that Steve Jobs was reading Daring Fireball, I didn’t want him to read a post from me acting like it was a big deal that he’d recommended a piece I wrote and agreed with it.</p>

<p>That was pretty stupid on my part. Or at least silly. My older perspective, today, is not to overthink such things. If something cool happens, I link to it. It seems ridiculous in hindsight that I didn’t link to Slepak’s post. And, I was thinking this week, if <em>I</em> couldn’t find a link to the overall story because <em>I</em> wrongly presumed I must have linked to it at the time, I wondered how many other readers, over the years, have gone hunting for that “very insightful and not negative” story and couldn’t find it because it was never mentioned or linked to on Daring Fireball.</p>

<p>So, today, I wrote the post I should have written back then, and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2010/04/11/very-insightful-and-not-negative">backdated it to 11 April 2010</a>.</p>

<p>To complete the timeline, April 2010 was a busy month. That same month saw <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2010/04/28/hp-palm-deal-webos/">HP buy Palm</a> (in a last-ditch effort to remain relevant as the industry rapidly shifted from being PC-centric to mobile-centric), <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2010/04/28/siri">Apple acquire a company called “Siri”</a>, and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2010/04/28/slate-iphone">Gizmodo publish details on the iPhone 4 prototype</a> some poor Apple engineer accidentally left in a bar. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2010/04/the_ipad">The original iPad</a> had <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20100404043324/http://www.time.com/time/business/article/0,8599,1976935,00.html">just shipped</a>. And at the end of the month, Jobs published “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2010/04/29/jobs-thoughts-on-flash">Thoughts on Flash</a>” on the Apple.com homepage. It’s kind of wild that was all in one month — scrolling down <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2010/04/">the monthly archive page for April 2010</a> is just <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2010/04/30/cabin-fever">one gem</a> after <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2010/04/30/thoughts-on-horses">another</a>.</p>

<p>Re-reading “<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20100722001052/http://www.apple.com/hotnews/thoughts-on-flash/">Thoughts on Flash</a>” again now, for the umpteenth time, I’ll say this: I think Steve Jobs’s post was very insightful and not negative.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ 15 Years Later: ‘Very Insightful and Not Negative’</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/05/that_eu_app_store_warning_about_external_purchases_is_not_new" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wbl" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41889</id>
	<published>2025-05-15T21:09:49Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-19T22:45:00Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Apple proposed a much less objectionable “external payments” disclosure in August, but claims that the EC told them not to implement it.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Some interesting follow-up on <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/14/app-store-eu-payment-warning">that piece yesterday</a> about the warning — with a prominent red “!” icon — in App Store listings for apps in the EU that use their own payment processing. Apple told me that exact same warning has been in place since the very beginning of their DMA compliance, in March 2024.</p>

<p>Jacob Eiting, CEO of RevenueCat, <a href="https://x.com/jeiting/status/1922010640539123921">tweeted on X</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I think this is EU only and might have been around for a while, I
just assumed nobody bothered with the DMA implementation for
external purchases since they were pointless.</p>

<p>Fewer than 100 developers have availed themselves of this option
for obvious reasons.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I think this blew up a bit yesterday because, despite the fact that it had been around since March 2024, few of us had ever seen it before because so few apps in the App Store use it. Eiting includes a link to <a href="https://developer.apple.com/support/alternative-payment-options-on-the-app-store-in-the-eu/#user-disclosures">Apple’s own developer documentation for its DMA compliance features</a>, which makes this clear:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>To help users understand whether an app contains an alternative
payment option, the App Store will display an informational banner
on the app’s product page to identify the developer’s enablement
of this entitlement. When downloading an app, users are also
informed if an app uses PSPs or links out on the purchase
confirmation sheet. Apps that contain an alternative payment
option are required to present users with a disclosure prior to
each transaction or link out to purchase to help them understand
that the purchase isn’t backed by Apple.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I actually think that’s very useful information that <em>should</em> be on an app’s App Store listing. Users should know what to expect, and iPhone users’ expectations are that digital goods transactions go through Apple’s IAP. The problem with this disclosure, as it stands, is the way it looks: like a big scary warning. It should be something more akin to the privacy “nutrition label” information.</p>

<p>And, it turns out, <a href="https://developer.apple.com/support/alternative-payment-options-on-the-app-store-in-the-eu/#user-disclosures">Apple itself publicly proposed exactly such a change back in August</a>. Apple’s proposed updated disclosure uses a small gray <em>i</em>-in-circle “info” icon (replacing the bigger red !-in-triangle “warning” icon), and the following text (<a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/05/user-disclosures-eu-transactions.png">screenshot</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Transactions in this app are supported
by the developer and not Apple.<br>
<a href="https://apps.apple.com/hu/story/id1726640865">Learn More</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>I would quibble with the fact that Apple’s proposal places that disclosure at the very top of the listing page in the App Store, above even the app’s name and icon, but visually and verbally it’s good. Clear, informative, and non-judgmental. </p>

<p>Per what I’ve been told by Apple, they were (and still are) prepared to implement these changes, including the new disclosure screen. The EC raised no objection to the new disclosure proposal, but insisted that Apple <em>not</em> implement the changes at the time. Then, according to Apple, the EC never provided further guidance, until last month when they fined Apple €500M for noncompliance. (And the EC <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/23/ec-clear-as-mud">still hasn’t told Apple</a> what it wants the company to do.)</p>

<p>This seems to be the exact dynamic <a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/apple-to-appeal-e500m-digital-fine-over-eus-silence-in-compliance-talks/">Politico reported on last week</a> (and that <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/15/apple-ec-proposals-feedback">I just linked to earlier today</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>According to correspondence seen by Politico, Apple offered last
summer <a href="https://developer.apple.com/news/?id=szrqxadx">to drop its rules</a> on how app developers can
communicate with users, but was told by the Commission to hold
off, pending feedback from developers.</p>

<p>By late September and following a round of consultations with
Apple critics like Spotify, Match Group and Epic Games, executives
at the U.S.-based firm began worrying that a lack of feedback from
the Commission meant it was teeing up a potential fine and
noncompliance decision.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Heads, Apple was going to get fined by the EC. Tails, Apple was going to get fined by the EC.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ That EU App Store Warning About External Purchases Is Not New, and Apple Proposed Improving It Nine Months Ago</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/05/single_story_a_classic_mac_system_1" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wbe" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41882</id>
	<published>2025-05-14T16:21:59Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-14T17:04:06Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">A single-story “a” in Chicago feels more blasphemous than that AI image Trump tweeted of himself as the new pope.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Following up on <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/12/that-stupid-apple-notes-a">my gripe regarding the alternative <em>a</em> glyph</a> used in Apple Notes, here’s <a href="https://www.threads.com/@kfury/post/DJlFkNfR5ik">Kevin Fox, tweeting on Threads</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>While we’re waxing nostalgic on the Original Mac, a Daring
Fireball post today (below) reminded me of another piece of Mac
128k trivia.</p>

<p>Until shortly before the official release, the ‘a’ in Geneva was a
single story ‘a’ like you see currently (and to some,
infuriatingly) in the Notes app.</p>

<p>The screenshots in the original Mac 128k user manual show the OS
using the pre-release single-story ‘a’ before it was changed.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I double-checked using the (amazing) <a href="https://infinitemac.org/">classic Mac emulators at Infinite Mac</a>, and it turns out, Apple actually shipped System 1.0 with a version of Geneva with a single-story <em>a</em> glyph — but only in the 9-point version of Geneva. At 12 points (and larger), Geneva’s <em>a</em> was double-story. Here are screenshots of the Finder showing Geneva 9 in System 1.0 (with single-story <em>a</em>):</p>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/05/system-1.0-geneva-a.png" class="noborder">
  <img
    src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/05/system-1.0-geneva-a.png"
    alt = "Screenshot of the Finder in Macintosh System 1.0, showing a version of the Geneva 9 font with a single-story “a” glyph."
    width = 512
  /></a></p>

<p>And System 2.0 (with double-story <em>a</em>):</p>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/05/system-2.0-geneva-a.png" class="noborder">
  <img
    src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/05/system-2.0-geneva-a.png"
    alt = "Screenshot of the Finder in Macintosh System 2.0, showing a version of the Geneva 9 font with a double-story “a” glyph."
    width = 512
  /></a></p>

<p>And a screenshot of MacWrite running on System 1.0 showing Geneva 9 and 12:</p>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/05/system-1.0-geneva-a-macwrite.png" class="noborder">
  <img
    src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/05/system-1.0-geneva-a-macwrite.png"
    alt = "Screenshot of MacWrite in System 1.0, showing the differences between Geneva 9 and 12."
    width = 512
  /></a></p>

<p>Geneva 9 — the eventual version, with a double-story <em>a</em> — is so intimately familiar to me that looking at those screenshots from System 1.0 makes me feel weird. It’s so clearly wrong. (What it feels like, to me, <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/retrobattlestations/comments/1e5k4xb/a_few_years_ago_i_bought_a_beautiful_transparent/">is the original Palm OS</a>, from the one-bit Palm Pilot / Handspring Visor days. Palm’s small sans serif font was very Geneva-9-ish, but their single-story <em>a</em> was distinctive.)</p>

<p>Fox also posted a link to <a href="https://vintageapple.org/macmanuals/pdf/Macintosh_1984.pdf">Vintage Apple’s high-res scan of the amazing original Mac user manual</a>, which, because it had to go to press before the 1.0 software was finished, contains screenshots of a few icons <a href="https://www.threads.com/@johncsiracusa/post/DJniWZ3NCCR">that changed by the time the original Mac was in customers’ hands</a>. What a remarkably good user manual this is — everything from the typography, to the clarity and tone of its writing, to its comprehensiveness is exemplary.</p>

<p>Here’s where it really gets nutty though. Marcin Wichary — <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/02/16/the-hardest-working-font-in-manhattan">whom you may recall</a> from his recent remarkable deep dive on the Gorton typeface (“<a href="https://aresluna.org/the-hardest-working-font-in-manhattan/">The Hardest Working Font in Manhattan</a>”), or from <em><a href="https://shifthappens.site/">Shift Happens</a></em>, his encyclopedic book on the history of keyboards — <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/aresluna.org/post/3lozitikp5k2d">chimed in on Bluesky</a> after observing that a few of the screenshots in that System 1.0 user manual show an early version of Chicago 12 with a single-story <em>a</em>. Seeing a single-story <em>a</em> in Chicago feels more blasphemous than that AI-generated image Trump tweeted of himself <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2025/05/04/world/trump-ai-image-pope-intl-hnk">as the new pope</a>.</p>

<p>One last note: I of course am not opposed to single-story <em>a</em>’s. Futura’s <em>a</em> is single-story, and <a href="http://neverusefutura.com/">Futura</a>, depending on my mood, might be my answer if asked to name my favorite typeface of all time. I just don’t particularly care for the alternate single-story <em>a</em> in San Francisco (Apple’s <a href="https://developer.apple.com/fonts/">modern San Francisco</a>, not <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/05/system-1.0-san-francisco.png">the one from 1984</a>), and to me it just gives an ever-so-slightly wrong — a little silly or unserious — vibe in the Notes app.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Single-Story a’s in Very Early Versions of Macintosh System 1</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/04/gonzales_rogers_apple_app_store_ruling" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wam" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41854</id>
	<published>2025-05-01T02:46:59Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-02T04:22:38Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Are the results of this disastrous for Apple’s App Store business? I don’t think so at all. Gonzales Rogers is demanding that Apple ... do what Phil Schiller recommended they do all along. But are the results of this disastrous for Apple’s reputation and credibility? It sure seems like it.
</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>I’m linking <a href="https://www.techmeme.com/250430/p55#a250430p55">here to Techmeme’s roundup of news coverage and commentary</a>, but I highly recommend you start by reading <a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.cand.364265/gov.uscourts.cand.364265.1508.0_2.pdf">Gonzalez Rogers’s 80-page decision</a>. It is excoriating. I’ve read few legal decisions quite like it. But it’s also incredibly cogent and plainly written.</p>

<p>From the start:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>To summarize: <em>One</em>, after trial, the Court found that Apple’s 30
percent commission “allowed it to reap supracompetitive operating
margins” and was not tied to the value of its intellectual
property, and thus, was anticompetitive. Apple’s response: charge
a <em>27 percent commission</em> (again tied to nothing) on off-app
purchases, where it had previously charged nothing, and extend the
commission for a period of seven days after the consumer
linked-out of the app. Apple’s goal: maintain its anticompetitive
revenue stream. <em>Two</em>, the Court had prohibited Apple from denying
developers the ability to communicate with, and direct consumers
to, other purchasing mechanisms. Apple’s response: impose <em>new</em>
barriers and <em>new</em> requirements to increase friction and increase
breakage rates with full page “scare” screens, static URLs, and
generic statements. Apple’s goal: to dissuade customer usage of
alternative purchase opportunities and maintain its
anticompetitive revenue stream. In the end, Apple sought to
maintain a revenue stream worth billions in direct defiance of
this Court’s Injunction.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There’s quite a bit of fury in those italics. Rule one when you’re in court, any court, is “Don’t piss off the judge.” Apple has absolutely infuriated Gonzales Rogers through actions that all of us saw as outrageous.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In stark contrast to Apple’s initial in-court testimony,
contemporaneous business documents reveal that Apple knew exactly
what it was doing and at every turn chose the most
<em>anti</em>competitive option. To hide the truth, Vice-President of
Finance, Alex Roman, outright lied under oath. Internally, Phillip
Schiller had advocated that Apple comply with the Injunction, but
Tim Cook ignored Schiller and instead allowed Chief Financial
Officer Luca Maestri and his finance team to convince him
otherwise. Cook chose poorly. The real evidence, detailed herein,
more than meets the clear and convincing standard to find a
violation. The Court refers the matter to the United States
Attorney for the Northern District of California to investigate
whether criminal contempt proceedings are appropriate.</p>

<p>This is an injunction, not a negotiation. There are no do-overs
once a party willfully disregards a court order. Time is of the
essence. The Court will not tolerate further delays. As previously
ordered, Apple will not impede competition. The Court enjoins
Apple from implementing its new anticompetitive acts to avoid
compliance with the Injunction. <b><i>Effective immediately</i></b>
Apple will no longer impede developers’ ability to communicate with
users nor will they levy or impose a new commission on off-app purchases.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You know a judge is pissed when she busts out the bold italics. Later, on (page 21, citations omitted for readability):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Prior to the June 20 meeting, there were individuals within Apple
who were advocating for a commission, and others advocating for no
commission. Those advocating for a commission included Mr. Maestri
and Mr. Roman. Mr. Schiller disagreed. In an email, Mr. Schiller
relayed that, with respect to the proposal for “a 27% commission
for 24 hours,” “I have already explained my many issues with the
commission concept,” and that “clearly I am not on team
commission/fee.” Mr. Schiller testified that, at the time, he “had
a question of whether we would be able to charge a commission”
under the Injunction, a concern which he communicated.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Schiller comes across as Apple’s sole voice of reason, fairness, and dare I say honesty in this entire ruling. The only people in the world who seemed to think Apple could or should comply with the 2021 injunction (that apps be permitted to steer users to the web to make purchases) by charging a commission — any commission, let alone a 27 percent commission — on those web transactions were Apple’s finance team members, led by Luca Maestri and Alex Roman, and Tim Cook.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Unlike Mr. Maestri and Mr. Roman, Mr. Schiller sat through the
entire underlying trial and actually read the entire 180-page
decision. That Messrs. Maestri and Roman did neither, does not
shield Apple of its knowledge (actual and constructive) of the
Court’s findings.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I mean Jesus H. Christ, that’s scathing. </p>

<p>It’s worth pointing out that Luca Maestri is no longer Apple’s CFO. (<a href="https://www.apple.com/leadership/kevan-parekh/">Kevan Parekh is</a>.) Back in August, <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2024/08/apple-announces-chief-financial-officer-transition/">Apple announced</a> that Maestri was, effectively, retiring as CFO “as part of a planned succession”. Apple’s statement didn’t use the word <em>retiring</em>, but rather the word <em>transitioning</em>. With this ruling and Maestri’s central role in Apple’s decision to forge ahead with a compliance plan where they “allowed” steering to the web by charging the same effective commissions on web transactions as they do for in-app transactions, I now have to wonder whether Maestri retired or “retired”. “Cook chose poorly” (by following Maestri’s recommendation) is not the sort of sentence from a judge that keeps CFOs in their jobs.</p>

<p>As for Alex Roman, I think he’s in some serious trouble. Like doing-time-in-the-clink trouble:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Despite its own considerable evaluation, during the first May 2024
hearing, Apple employees attempted to mislead the Court by
testifying that the decision to impose a commission was grounded
in AG’s report. The testimony of Mr. Roman, Vice President of
Finance, was replete with misdirection and outright lies. He even
went so far as to testify that Apple did not look at comparables
to estimate the costs of alternative payment solutions that
developers would need to procure to facilitate linked-out
purchases.</p>

<p>The Court finds that Apple <em>did</em> consider the external
costs developers faced when utilizing alternative payment
solutions for linked out transactions, which conveniently exceeded
the 3% discount Apple ultimately decided to provide by a safe
margin. Apple <em>did not</em> rely on a substantiated bottoms-up analysis
during its months-long assessment of whether to impose a
commission, seemingly justifying its decision after the fact with
the AG’s report.</p>

<p>Mr. Roman did not stop there, however. He also testified that up
until January 16, 2024, Apple had no idea what fee it would impose
on linked-out purchases:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Q. And I take it that Apple decided to impose a 27 percent fee
 on linked purchases prior to January 16, 2024, correct?</p>

<p>A. The decision was made that day.</p>

<p>Q. It’s your testimony that up until January 16, 2024, Apple had
no idea what — what fee it’s going to impose on linked purchases?</p>

<p>A. That is correct.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Another lie under oath: contemporaneous business documents reveal
that on the contrary, the main components of Apple’s plan,
including the 27% commission, were determined in July 2023.</p>

<p>Neither Apple, nor its counsel, corrected the, now obvious, lies.
They did not seek to withdraw the testimony or to have it stricken
(although Apple did request that the Court strike <em>other</em>
testimony). Thus, Apple will be held to have adopted the lies and
misrepresentations to this Court.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There’s so much more. <a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.cand.364265/gov.uscourts.cand.364265.1508.0_2.pdf">The whole ruling</a> is compelling — and damning — reading.</p>

<p>Keep in mind this whole thing stems from an injunction from a lawsuit filed by Epic Games <em>that Apple largely won</em>. The result of that lawsuit was basically, “<em>OK, Apple wins, Epic loses, but this whole thing where apps in the App Store aren’t allowed to inform users of offers available outside the App Store, or send them to such offers on the web (outside the app) via easily tappable links, is bullshit and needs to stop. If the App Store is not anticompetitive it should be able to compete with links to the web and offers from outside the App Store.</em>”</p>

<p>Are the results of this disastrous for Apple’s App Store business? I don’t think so at all. Gonzales Rogers is demanding that Apple ... do what Phil Schiller recommended they do all along, which is to compete fair and square with purchases available on the web. She’s not demanding they do what, say, Tim Sweeney wanted them to do. She’s basically saying Phil Schiller was right. Read her entire ruling and it’s hard to imagine anyone disagreeing with that.</p>

<p>But are the results of this disastrous for Apple’s reputation and credibility? It sure seems like it. But it would be worse — much worse — for Apple’s reputation if Phil Schiller weren’t still there. Without him, this ruling makes it sound like they’d be lost, both ethically and legally.</p>

<p>I’ll give the final words to Gonzales Rogers’s own closing:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple <em>willfully</em> chose not to comply with this Court’s
Injunction. It did so with the express intent to create <em>new</em>
anticompetitive barriers which would, by design and in effect,
maintain a valued revenue stream; a revenue stream previously
found to be anticompetitive. That it thought this Court would
tolerate such insubordination was a gross miscalculation. As
always, the cover-up made it worse. For this Court, there is no
second bite at the apple.</p>

<p>It Is So Ordered.</p>
</blockquote>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Judge Yvonne Gonzalez Rogers Rules, in Excoriating Decision, That Apple Violated Her 2021 Court Order Regarding App Store Anti-Steering Provisions</title></entry></feed><!-- THE END -->
