<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>Daring Fireball</title>
<subtitle>By John Gruber</subtitle>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/" />
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main" />
<id>https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main</id>


<updated>2025-03-21T19:45:35Z</updated><rights>Copyright © 2025, John Gruber</rights><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/keyboard_maestro_hack_of_the_week_dont_paste_images" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/w74" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41728</id>
	<published>2025-03-21T19:37:49Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-21T19:42:50Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">I keep meaning to write more about Keyboard Maestro, and so I’m just going to start documenting all the little use cases I find for it. Here’s one from today.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My number one tip for becoming a Mac power user is to get into <a href="https://www.keyboardmaestro.com/main/">Keyboard Maestro</a>. Using Keyboard Maestro feels like gaining superpowers. I keep meaning to write more about Keyboard Maestro, and so I’m just going to start documenting all the little use cases I find for it. Here’s one from today.</p>

<p>I use <a href="https://redsweater.com/marsedit/">MarsEdit</a> to publish at least 99 percent of the posts on this site. (The other 1 percent are posts I create on my phone, using the web interface for Movable Type.) I use MarsEdit <em>a lot</em>. About once a week or so, I accidentally try to paste text in MarsEdit when I think I have text on my clipboard, but it’s actually an image. When you paste an image in MarsEdit, it’s not like pasting into Mail or Notes or TextEdit, where the image just goes into the text. So MarsEdit, trying to be helpful, opens its <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/03/marsedit-upload-utility.png">Upload Utility window</a> — which, if I were using WordPress or some other CMS, might allow to me upload the image to my server for referencing from the HTML of the blog post. That’s not how my system works, and not how I want it to work, so every time this happens I have to close the Upload Utility window. And every time, I try to do this by hitting the Esc key on my keyboard. But the Upload Utility window isn’t a dialog box with a Cancel button that would be triggered by Esc. It’s a regular window. So after hitting the Esc key, which doesn’t do anything in this context, I then remember, once again, that I need to hit ⌘W instead. (I think I don’t naturally think to hit ⌘W because my instincts tell me ⌘W would try to close the blog window I’m writing in.)</p>

<p>Today it happened again, and finally the notion occurred to me that I could fix this with Keyboard Maestro. My first thought was that I could create a macro that <em>would</em> close the frontmost window in MarsEdit if, and only if, the frontmost window was named “Upload Utility”. A second later it occurred to me that I could probably do better than that, and prevent the Upload Utility window from opening in the first place if I ever try to paste an image in MarsEdit.</p>

<p>I was right. This wasn’t just super easy to create in Keyboard Maestro, it was super quick. I’ve spent 10× more time writing about this macro here than I did creating it. I think that’s why I so seldom write about my little hacks in Keyboard Maestro — they not only save me time and eliminate annoyances once they’re created, but they’re so easy to create that I just get back to whatever I was previously doing after making a new one.</p>

<p>First, I have a group (think: folders) in Keyboard Maestro for every app for which I’ve created app-specific macros. You just create a new group and set it to only be available when one (or more) specific applications are active. Inside my group for MarsEdit, I created a new macro named “Don’t Paste Images”.</p>

<p>It’s triggered by the hot key sequence ⌘V. That means every single time I paste in MarsEdit, this macro will run. Keyboard Maestro is so frigging fast that I’ll never notice. (Keyboard Maestro macros execute so fast that in some scenarios, you have to add steps to pause for, say, 0.2 seconds to keep the macro from getting ahead of the user interface it’s manipulating.)</p>

<p>The macro executes a simple <a href="https://wiki.keyboardmaestro.com/action/If_Then_Else">if-then-else action</a> with the following pseudocode logic:</p>

<pre><code>if the System Clipboard has an image
    play a sound
else
    simulate the keystroke ⌘V
</code></pre>

<p>That’s the whole thing. And it worked perfectly the first time I tried it. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/03/km-dont-paste-images-marsedit.png">Here’s a screenshot of my macro</a>.</p>

<p>So if <em>I</em> type ⌘V in MarsEdit, and the clipboard contains an image, I just hear a beep. (I could just default to the system beep, but I chose the standard MacOS “Bottle” sound just for this macro — I sort of want to know that it’s <em>this</em> macro keeping me from pasting whatever text I wrongly thought was on my clipboard, so I want a distinctive sound to play.) Nothing gets pasted, so MarsEdit’s Upload Utility window doesn’t appear.</p>

<p>If the clipboard <em>doesn’t</em> contain an image, then Keyboard Maestro simulates a ⌘V shortcut and that gets passed to MarsEdit, and from my perspective as a user, it’s just like a normal paste of the text I expected. I have a few macros that work like this, where the macro is trigged by an application’s own keyboard shortcut, and the macro will (if certain conditions are met) pass through the same simulated keyboard shortcut to the application. When I first tried this, many years ago, I was half worried that it would trigger an infinite loop, where the simulated keystroke from the Keyboard Maestro macro would re-trigger the macro. I was wrong to worry — Keyboard Maestro is too clever for that.</p>

<p>The best part is, while writing this very blog post, the macro saved me from seeing that cursed Upload Utility window once more, because I had the screenshot of the macro on my clipboard, when I thought I had copied the URL for it on my server.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Keyboard Maestro Hack of the Week: Don’t Paste Images</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Matthew Belloni on the ‘Apple TV+ Experiment’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://puck.news/how-long-can-the-apple-tv-plus-experiment-sputter-on/?sharer=167184&amp;token=1ff8c319cdac678ace91127c99abfc96" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w73" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/21/belloni-apple-tv" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41727</id>
	<published>2025-03-21T18:01:48Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-21T19:45:35Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Matthew Belloni has a very good take on Apple TV+ at Puck (that’s a gift link that should get you through their paywall — but which requires you creating a free account, sorry):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>All of which fed into the self-centered fears of my lunch date.
What, if anything, does the current state of Apple mean for its
entertainment business? After all, more than five years into the
Apple TV+ experiment, it’s never been entirely clear what C.E.O.
Tim Cook and services chief Eddy Cue are up to in Hollywood.
Certainly not making money, at least not in the traditional sense.
The Information
<a href="https://www.theinformation.com/articles/apple-streaming-losses-top-1-billion-year?rc=1m8jsa">reported</a>
today that Apple lost $1 billion on Apple TV+ last year, following
a Bloomberg
<a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/newsletters/2024-07-21/apple-tries-to-rein-in-hollywood-spending-after-years-of-losses">report</a>
that more than $20 billion has been shoveled into making original
shows and movies since 2019. That’s not nothing, even for a
company worth $3 trillion.</p>

<p>The “loss” number is a bit misleading, of course, considering
Apple has always said that a key goal is to leverage Leo DiCaprio
and Reese Witherspoon to thicken its brand halo and the device
“ecosystem,” ultimately boosting its other businesses. But still…
for all its billions, Apple TV+ has accumulated only about 45
million subscribers worldwide, according to today’s Information
report and other estimates.</p>

<p>That’s far less than Disney+, Max, and Paramount+, all of which
launched around the same time. Those rival services are attached
to legacy studios with rich libraries, but they’re not attached to
a company with $65 billion in cash on hand and a device in the
pockets of 1 billion people that also delivers bundle-friendly
music, news, and games. Apple declined to confirm or comment on
any numbers, but a source there suggested the subscriber number is
higher than 45 million and that the global nature of the sub base
is being undercounted by U.S.-oriented research firms. Maybe. The
company reveals zero performance data beyond B.S. “biggest weekend
ever!” press releases that the trades accept without skepticism
and producers like Ben Stiller and David Ellison post with
“blessed” emojis on their social media. No one outside the company
really knows how the Apple TV+ business is performing.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>One interesting nugget is <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/03/puck-apple-tv+-signups.png">this chart</a>, which suggests that subscriptions to TV+ have boomed since Apple and Amazon <a href="https://www.aboutamazon.com/news/entertainment/apple-tv-shows-amazon-prime-video-subscription">worked out a deal to sell TV+ subscriptions</a> through Amazon Channels in Prime Video at the end of last year. That deal has, seemingly, moved the needle. Another interesting nugget is that TV+ seems to suffer from a higher churn rate than other streaming services. Said Belloni’s Puck colleague Julia Alexander, “Fewer than 35 percent of all subscribers keep the service for longer than six months.”</p>

<p>That’s kind of crazy. I’d think TV+ would have <em>less</em> churn, not more, than the industry average — that the Apple TV+ audience is small but loyal. Perhaps this is the unsurprising side effect of Apple giving away 3-month trials when you purchase new devices. But I also truly wonder if TV+ subscriptions are the hardest for industry groups to measure, because so many people who do subscribe watch through tvOS (or, on their phones, on iOS) where everything is private. Belloni hints at this, and says little birdies at Apple told him the TV+ subscriber base is larger than they’re getting credit for.</p>

<p>And how do you count <a href="https://www.apple.com/apple-one/">Apple One</a> subscribers toward TV+’s subscriber base? My vague theory about Cue and Cook’s thinking about getting into this business has been about making it one leg among several on the stool of reasons to subscribe to Apple One. That Apple will take subscribers who are <em>only</em> subscribed to TV+, or only subscribed to TV+ and Apple Music, but what they really want is to get people to subscribe to Apple One, which because it includes iCloud storage, almost certainly has very little churn.</p>

<p>Belloni closes thus:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple wouldn’t be the first tech powerhouse to dabble in
professionally produced content only to retreat. [...] Neither
Cook nor Cue has suggested anything like that, and Apple, in just
over five years, has become a reliable partner and a high-quality
buyer for Hollywood shows and movies. In some ways, it’s
remarkable how fast Apple TV+ became part of the entertainment
community. Whether that lasts is the question.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Here’s where I will point out that Apple isn’t like other tech companies. Apple isn’t a <em>move fast and break things</em> company. They’re a <em>measure twice, cut once</em> company. When they commit to something, they tend to stay committed. And they’re very, very good at playing long games that require patience, especially when entering new markets. Look at Apple Pay. 10 years ago, it was <a href="https://finance.yahoo.com/news/apple-pay-showing-signs-could-214558347.html">widely panned</a> as <a href="https://www.cultofmac.com/news/apple-pay-was-a-massive-flop-on-black-friday">a flop</a> after a slow first year. Now it’s everywhere.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Matthew Belloni on the ‘Apple TV+ Experiment’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/21/belloni-apple-tv">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Is Apple’s Spending on TV+ Content a ‘Loss’ or a ‘Cost’?</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://deadline.com/2025/03/apple-appletv-annual-streaming-losses-1236345490/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w72" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/21/apple-tv-spend-loss-or-cost" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41726</id>
	<published>2025-03-21T16:18:07Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-21T18:28:48Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jill Goldsmith, Deadline:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple is losing more than $1 billion a year on streamer Apple TV+,
according to a report in the Information that cited two people
familiar with the matter. The tech giant has spent over $5 billion
a year on content since launching Apple TV+ in 2019 but trimmed
that by about $500 million last year, <a href="https://www.theinformation.com/articles/apple-streaming-losses-top-1-billion-year">the report said</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The headline on Wayne Ma’s report at The Information set the framework: “<a href="https://www.theinformation.com/articles/apple-streaming-losses-top-1-billion-year">Apple Streaming Losses Top $1 Billion a Year</a>” — the story got picked up widely, and almost everyone who did framed it in terms of <em>losing</em> or a <em>loss</em>. But is it a <em>loss</em> when Apple expected the business to be unprofitable for a decade or more? <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2025/03/apple-tv-reportedly-loses-1-billion-a-year-and-thats-okay-for-now/">From Scharon Harding’s paraphrasing at Ars Technica</a> of Ma’s paywalled report:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple TV+ being Apple’s only service not turning a profit isn’t
<em>good</em>, but it’s also expected. Like other streaming services,
Apple TV+ wasn’t expected to be profitable until years after its
launch. An Apple TV+ employee that The Information said reviewed
the streaming service’s business plan said Apple TV+ is expected
to lose $15 billion to $20 billion during its first 10 years.</p>

<p>For comparison, Disney’s direct-to-consumer streaming business had
operating losses <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/carolinereid/2025/02/08/disneys-streaming-unit-loses-three-times-more-money-than-disneyland-paris/">of $11.4 billion</a> between the launch of
Disney+ in fall 2020 and April 2024. Disney’s streaming business
became profitable for the first time in its fiscal quarter ending
on June 29, 2024.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The above two paragraphs of essential context are buried 13 paragraphs down. If Apple expected TV+ to operate in the red, to the tune of $15–20 billion over its first decade, and halfway through that decade (<a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2019/09/apple-tv-launches-november-1-featuring-originals-from-the-worlds-greatest-storytellers/">TV+ debuted</a> in November 2019) it operated in the red to the tune of $1 billion for the year — doesn’t that mean costs are exactly in line with their expectations?</p>

<p>The insinuation here is that Apple’s pissing this money away and doesn’t know what they’re doing. Maybe they are! But if so it was exactly Eddy Cue and Tim Cook’s strategy to piss this money away. If Apple had expected TV+ to be profitable or break-even in 2024, then a $1 billion operating loss would be a story. But as it stands it’s just a cost. How much did Apple “lose” on electricity bills last year?</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Is Apple’s Spending on TV+ Content a ‘Loss’ or a ‘Cost’?’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/21/apple-tv-spend-loss-or-cost">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>iOS 18 Software Updates Keep Re-Enabling Apple Intelligence for Users Who Had Turned It Off</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/03/11/ios-18-3-2-apple-intelligence-auto-on/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w71" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/21/ios-18-updates-reenable-apple-intelligence" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41725</id>
	<published>2025-03-21T15:11:46Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-21T18:07:45Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Juli Clover, writing for MacRumors last week:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>With new iOS software updates, Apple has been automatically
turning Apple Intelligence on again even for users who have
disabled it, a decision that has become increasingly frustrating
for those that don’t want to use Apple Intelligence .</p>

<p>After installing iOS 18.3.2, iPhone users have noticed that Apple
Intelligence is <a href="https://forums.macrumors.com/threads/apple-releases-ios-18-3-2-with-bug-fixes.2452817/post-33793315">automatically turned on</a>, regardless of
whether it was turned off prior to the update being installed.
There is an Apple Intelligence splash screen that comes up after
updating, and there is no option other than tapping “Continue,”
which turns on Apple Intelligence .</p>

<p>If you’ve updated to iOS 18.3.2 and do not want Apple Intelligence
enabled, you will need to go the Settings app, tap on Apple
Intelligence, and then toggle it off. When Apple Intelligence is
enabled, it <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/how-to/save-up-to-21gb-storage-disable-apple-intelligence/">consumes up to 7GB</a> of storage space for local
AI models, which is an inconvenience when storage space is
limited.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’d been seeing complaints about this, including from some friends who are developers and/or had previously worked on iOS as engineers at Apple. A bunch of regular DF readers have written to complain about it too. I wouldn’t call it a deluge, but I’ve gotten an unusual number of complaints about this. (And at CNet, <a href="https://www.cnet.com/tech/services-and-software/did-apple-intelligence-turn-on-again-after-the-last-ios-18-update-how-to-turn-it-off/">Jeff Carlson reports the same thing happening with MacOS 15.3.2</a>.)</p>

<p>I hadn’t experienced it personally because I have Apple Intelligence enabled on my iPhone. But my year-old iPhone 15 Pro was still running iOS 18.2. So I disabled Apple Intelligence on that phone, then updated it to 18.3.2. When it finished, Apple Intelligence was re-enabled. I also tried this on my iPhone 16e review unit, which was still running iOS 18.3.1 (albeit a version of 18.3.1 with a unique build number for the 16e). I turned Apple Intelligence off, upgraded to 18.3.2, and on that iPhone, Apple Intelligence remained off after the software upgrade completed.</p>

<p>So I don’t know if this is a bug that only affects some iPhones, or a deliberate growth hacking decision from Apple to keep turning this back on for people who have explicitly turned it off. But it’s definitely happening.</p>

<p>And while the 7 GB of storage space required for the model is a legitimate technical reason to turn it off, I think (judging from my email from DF readers) the main reason people disable Apple Intelligence is that they don’t like it, don’t trust it, and to some degree object to it. It could take up no additional storage space at all and they’d still want it disabled on their devices, and they are fucking angry that Apple’s own software updates keep turning it back on. Put aside the quality or utility of Apple Intelligence as it stands today, and there are people who object to the whole thing on principle or, I don’t know, just vibes alone. Feelings are strong about this. Turning it back on <em>automatically</em>, after a user had turned it off <em>manually</em>, leads those users to correctly <em>distrust</em> Apple Intelligence specifically and Apple in general.</p>

<p>If it’s a bug, it’s a bug that makes Apple look like a bunch of gross shysters. If it’s not a bug, it means Apple is a bunch of gross shysters. I’d wager on bug — especially after seeing it not happen on my 16e review unit. I’m thinking it’s something where it’s supposed to be enabled by default, once, for people who’ve never explicitly turned Apple Intelligence on or off previously, but that for some devices where it <em>has</em> been turned off explicitly, somehow the software update is mistaking it for the setting never having been touched. Apple needs to get it together on this one.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘iOS 18 Software Updates Keep Re-Enabling Apple Intelligence for Users Who Had Turned It Off’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/21/ios-18-updates-reenable-apple-intelligence">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple Sued for False Advertising Over Apple Intelligence</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.axios.com/2025/03/20/apple-suit-false-advertising-ai-intelligence" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w70" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/21/apple-sued-for-false-advertising-over-apple-intelligence" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41724</id>
	<published>2025-03-21T14:29:25Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-21T14:42:50Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Ina Fried, reporting for Axios:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The suit, filed Wednesday in U.S. District Court in San Jose,
seeks class action status and unspecified financial damages on
behalf of those who purchased Apple Intelligence-capable iPhones
and other devices.</p>

<p>“Apple’s advertisements saturated the internet, television, and
other airwaves to cultivate a clear and reasonable consumer
expectation that these transformative features would be available
upon the iPhone’s release,” the suit reads. “This drove
unprecedented excitement in the market, even for Apple, as the
company knew it would, and as part of Apple’s ongoing effort to
convince consumers to upgrade at a premium price and to
distinguish itself from competitors deemed to be winning the
AI-arms race.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Most of these class action lawsuits are bullshit, but it’s hard to argue with the basic premise of this one.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Sued for False Advertising Over Apple Intelligence’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/21/apple-sued-for-false-advertising-over-apple-intelligence">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Seneca</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.norbauer.co/pages/the-seneca" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w6z" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/20/the-seneca" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41723</id>
	<published>2025-03-21T00:03:51Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-21T00:24:29Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>This is beautiful and crazy, and no, I’m not going to buy one, but damn I’m tempted and I’d sure like to try one. I’m glad it exists.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Seneca’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/20/the-seneca">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Gurman: Tim Cook Has Put Mike Rockwell in Charge of Siri, Reporting to Craig Federighi</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2025-03-20/apple-vision-pro-chief-mike-rockwell-named-siri-head-giannandrea-keeps-ai-role" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w6y" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/20/gurman-rockwell-siri" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41722</id>
	<published>2025-03-20T16:26:42Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-20T22:52:36Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Mark Gurman, with a blockbuster scoop for Bloomberg:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple Inc. is undergoing a rare shake-up of its executive ranks,
aiming to get its artificial intelligence efforts back on track
after months of delays and stumbles, according to people familiar
with the situation.</p>

<p>Chief Executive Officer Tim Cook has lost confidence in the
ability of AI head John Giannandrea to execute on product
development, so he’s moving over another top executive to help:
Vision Pro creator Mike Rockwell. In a new role, Rockwell will be
in charge of the Siri virtual assistant, according to the people,
who asked not to be identified because the moves haven’t been
announced.</p>

<p>Rockwell will report to software chief Craig Federighi, removing
Siri completely from Giannandrea’s command. Apple is poised to
announce the changes to employees this week. The iPhone maker’s
senior leaders — a group known as the Top 100 — just met at a
secretive, annual offsite gathering to discuss the future of the
company. Its AI efforts were a key talking point at the summit,
Bloomberg News has reported. [...]</p>
</blockquote>

<p>My quick take on this is that it’s a turf battle that Craig Federighi just won. It’s not just putting a new executive in charge of Siri, it’s moving Siri under Federighi’s group.</p>

<p>How Gurman got this scoop before Apple had announced the changes — even internally — is rather unbelievable. It’s not “Bloomberg” that got this scoop. It’s Mark Gurman. And trust me, Apple PR did not leak this to him deliberately. I’m sure they’re now accelerating an announcement, at least internally, framing it on their own terms. I can only guess that Gurman hinted at his sourcing in the passage above: Tim Cook must have announced these changes at the Top 100 retreat this week, and at least two of those attendees leaked the news to Gurman. Unprecedented.</p>

<p>Also:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Rockwell is currently the vice president in charge of the Vision
Products Group, or VPG, the division that developed Apple’s
headset. As part of the changes, he’ll be leaving that team and
handing the reins to Paul Meade, an executive who has run hardware
engineering for the Vision Pro under Rockwell.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I don’t find it surprising at all that Rockwell was given this task.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Giannandrea will remain at the company, even with Rockwell taking
over Siri. An abrupt departure would signal publicly that the AI
efforts have been tumultuous — something Apple is reluctant to
acknowledge. Giannandrea’s other responsibilities include
oversight of research, testing and technologies related to AI. The
company also has a team reporting to Giannandrea investigating
robotics.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This I find a little surprising. But maybe I shouldn’t. I don’t buy Gurman’s argument that dismissing Giannandrea would “signal publicly that the AI efforts have been tumultuous”. Apple <em>already</em> signaled that publicly <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/apple_is_delaying_the_more_personalized_siri_apple_intelligence_features">when they announced</a> that all of the ambitious features for Siri and Apple Intelligence that were promised for <em>this</em> year’s OS cycle would be postponed until <em>next</em> year’s OS cycle. That’s public tumult. But I mean, you can see for yourself that Apple’s AI efforts have been “tumultuous” by asking Siri on your iPhone, right now, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/hey-siri-what-month-is-it">what month it is</a>.</p>

<p>What Apple needs to signal is that they don’t expect to deliver a significantly better Siri without making significant changes to the team behind Siri.</p>

<p>But maybe the answer is as simple as that Giannandrea is good at leading and managing teams doing advanced research that is abstracted from product. So move the products out of his division and into Federighi’s, and put someone who knows how to ship directly in charge of Siri. Leave Giannandrea in charge of a division focused on research and technology. Attention has moved on from “machine learning” to LLMs, but Apple’s machine learning game has gotten very good.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Gurman: Tim Cook Has Put Mike Rockwell in Charge of Siri, Reporting to Craig Federighi’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/20/gurman-rockwell-siri">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>HealthKit as a Model for an Open Semantic Index From Apple</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/apple-needs-to-get-out-of-the-way-with-ai" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w6x" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/20/healthkit-as-a-model-for-an-open-semantic-index-from-apple" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41721</id>
	<published>2025-03-20T14:08:11Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-20T22:48:41Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Here’s an update I just appended to my post yesterday, after linking to <a href="https://shapeof.com/archives/2025/3/how_apple_could_help_developers_with_ai_and_llms.html">Gus Mueller’s suggestion</a> that Apple open up a semantic index to third-party AI apps:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>HealthKit already works a lot like what Mueller is suggesting here
(for, say, “SemanticKit”). With explicit user permission — that
can be revoked at any time — third party apps can both read from
and write to your Health data. Apple does a lot of that itself,
both through Apple Watch and from the various activity-related
things an iPhone can track, but third-party apps and devices are
welcome participants, in a private, easily-understood way.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Nobody is suggesting Apple should give up on AI. Quite the opposite. They really need to go from being <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/hey-siri-what-month-is-it">a joke</a> to being good at it, fast. But there’s no reason at all they should build out a strategy that relies on Apple doing all of it themselves, and Apple users relying solely on Apple’s own AI. Do it like Health — a model that has proven to be:</p>

<ul>
<li>profitable (for Apple itself, selling devices like Watches);</li>
<li>popular (with users, who actually use it, understand it, and like it);</li>
<li>private;</li>
<li>and open to third-party developers, device makers, and medical service providers.</li>
</ul>

<p>(<a href="https://mastodon.social/@williamw/114191747428238280">Thanks to Bill Welense</a> for the suggestion.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘HealthKit as a Model for an Open Semantic Index From Apple’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/20/healthkit-as-a-model-for-an-open-semantic-index-from-apple">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The M1 MacBook Air Lives on at Walmart, Now Just $650</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.walmart.com/ip/Apple-MacBook-Air-13-3-inch-Laptop-Silver-M1-Chip-8GB-RAM-256GB-storage/715596133" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w6w" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/20/walmart-macbook-air" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41720</id>
	<published>2025-03-20T13:53:04Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-20T22:47:01Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Last March, when Apple introduced the then new M3 MacBook Airs, they moved the base model 13-inch M2 MacBook Air into the magic $999 spot in their own lineup, replacing the M1 MacBook Air. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2024/03/15/macbook-air-walmart">But mid-March it was announced that Walmart would begin selling the M1 MacBook Air</a> — in one tech-spec configuration (8 GB RAM, 256 SSD), but three colors (gold, silver, space gray) for just $700.</p>

<p>This year <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/05/apple-announces-with-little-surprise-m4-macbook-airs">Apple replaced the entire lineup of MacBook Airs that it sells itself with M4-based models</a>, including the $999 starting-price model. Online, <a href="https://www.walmart.com/search?q=macbook">Walmart sells a handful of MacBook models now</a>, at, per Walmart’s brand, slightly lower prices than Apple itself. But the one and only MacBook they seem to stock in their retail stores is the classic wedge-shaped M1 MacBook Air — now down to $650.</p>

<p>It’s over four years old now, and yes, 8 GB RAM and 256 GB of storage are meager, but it’s almost certainly the best new laptop you can buy for that price. Assuming Apple thinks this partnership is a success, eventually they’ll have to replace this with a more recent MacBook Air. But I suspect the main reason it’s still the M1 Air (and hasn’t been replaced by, say, the M2 Air) is not about the specs or performance, per se, but rather simply how it looks. It looks like an older MacBook. Walmart might not get an updated MacBook with a more-recent-than-M1 chip until Apple refreshes the industrial design on its current MacBook Airs.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The M1 MacBook Air Lives on at Walmart, Now Just $650’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/20/walmart-macbook-air">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Hey Siri, What Month Is It?’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.reddit.com/r/iphone/comments/1jehkpm/apple_intelligence_this_apple_intelligence_that/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w6v" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/hey-siri-what-month-is-it" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41719</id>
	<published>2025-03-19T23:49:43Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-20T13:30:59Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Whole Reddit thread examining this simple question: “What month is it?” and Siri’s “I’m sorry, I don’t understand” response (which I just reproduced on my iPhone 16 Pro running iOS 18.4b4). One guy changed the question to “What month is it currently?” and got the answer “It is 2025.”</p>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> Ask Siri (with Apple Intelligence™) “ChatGPT, what month is it?” and, though you’ll have to wait a few extra seconds, you’ll get the right answer each time. Perhaps the current month is “<a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2024/06/introducing-apple-intelligence-for-iphone-ipad-and-mac/">broad world knowledge</a>” and Siri shouldn’t even attempt to answer such a complex question on its own?</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Hey Siri, What Month Is It?’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/hey-siri-what-month-is-it">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple Intelligence Is Coming to iOS in the EU in April</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2025/02/apple-intelligence-expands-to-more-languages-and-regions-in-april/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w6u" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/apple-intelligence-is-coming-to-ios-in-the-eu-in-april" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41718</id>
	<published>2025-03-19T23:24:47Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-19T23:42:02Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>News from Apple that I let slip by a few weeks ago, but that seems apt again <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/eu-apple-interop-requirements">today</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple Intelligence, the personal intelligence system that delivers
helpful and relevant intelligence, will soon be available in more
languages, including French, German, Italian, Portuguese (Brazil),
Spanish, Japanese, Korean, and Chinese (simplified) — as well as
localized English for Singapore and India.</p>

<p>These new languages will be accessible in nearly all regions
around the world with the release of iOS 18.4, iPadOS 18.4, and
macOS Sequoia 15.4 in April, and developers can start to test
these releases today.</p>

<p>With the upcoming software updates, iPhone and iPad users in the
EU will have access to Apple Intelligence features for the first
time, and Apple Intelligence will expand to a new platform in U.S.
English with Apple Vision Pro — helping users communicate,
collaborate, and express themselves in entirely new ways.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Given that Apple Intelligence <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/01/siri_is_super_dumb_and_getting_dumber">isn’t exactly setting the world on fire</a>, I think in the grand scheme of things, it’ll wind up being filed away under “<em>Oh yeah, remember that?</em>” that the EU got it 4-5 months after it debuted. (Clean Up in Photos is often great, and I genuinely enjoy notification summaries and miss them now that they’re disabled for news apps; the rest I don’t use, and the most ambitious aspects of Apple Intelligence are (<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/something_is_rotten_in_the_state_of_cupertino">you may have heard</a>) <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/apple_is_delaying_the_more_personalized_siri_apple_intelligence_features">delayed for everyone</a>, not just the EU.)</p>

<p>Apple was concerned that the EU’s hardline interpretation of the DMA was such that the European Commission considered it a violation of the DMA that Apple Intelligence wasn’t an interchangeable component. Like the way the EC forced Apple to open up iOS to alternative app marketplaces — <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2024/06/eu_reaping_what_it_sows">there was uncertainty</a> whether they’d demand the same for system-integrated AI. And if that’s what the EC had demanded, they simply wouldn’t have gotten system-integrated AI for years. But I’m not sure how to square up <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/eu-apple-interop-requirements">today’s decisions</a> — requiring Apple to enable third-party alternatives to system-level features like AirPlay and AirDrop — with an interpretation that the EU will be fine with Apple Intelligence only offering Apple’s own AI (along with Apple’s approved partners, like OpenAI). </p>

<p>I think the regime change at the European Commission has changed things to some degree, but quietly. Former competition chief Margrethe Vestager was a firebrand. Back in June last year, after Apple had announced that Apple Intelligence would be delayed indefinitely in the EU for iOS, <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2024/06/28/withholding-apple-intelligence-from-eu/">she made clear that <em>she</em> thought it was anti-competitive</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“I find that very interesting that they say we will now deploy AI
where we’re not obliged to enable competition. I think that is
that is the most sort of stunning open declaration that they know
100% that this is another way of disabling competition where they
have a stronghold already.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>But Vestager is gone, and until today we hadn’t heard a whit about DMA compliance from her successor, Teresa Ribera. In September, when the proceedings that resulted in today’s decisions opened, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2024/09/20/ec-apple-specification-proceedings">I wrote</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Also worth noting: Margrethe Vestager is on her way out, <a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/teresa-ribera-brussels-ursula-von-der-leyen-europe/">about to
be replaced</a> by <a href="https://www.ft.com/content/ad2db1a7-69e8-4369-9cf1-cc4896df4cc7">Spanish socialist Teresa
Ribera</a>, a career climate expert (which, possibly, might
give her an affinity for Apple, far and away the most
<a href="https://www.apple.com/environment/">climate-friendly</a> large tech company) with no
experience in competition law. To me that makes Ribera an odd
choice for the competition chief job, but apparently that makes
sense in the EU. It remains unclear to me whether Ribera supports
Vestager’s crusade against the DMA’s designated “gatekeepers”. If
she doesn’t, is this all for naught?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Until today, that remained an open question. Now it appears the Commission’s crusading course is unchanged — it’s just no longer accompanied by inflammatory commentary from the commissioners in charge.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Intelligence Is Coming to iOS in the EU in April’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/apple-intelligence-is-coming-to-ios-in-the-eu-in-april">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>EU Adopts New ‘Interoperability’ Requirements for Apple Under DMA</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://ec.europa.eu/commission/presscorner/detail/en/ip_25_816" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w6t" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/eu-apple-interop-requirements" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41717</id>
	<published>2025-03-19T23:06:52Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-20T19:03:47Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The European Commission, today:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Today, the European Commission adopted two decisions under the
Digital Markets Act (DMA) specifying the measures that Apple has
to take to comply with certain aspects of its interoperability
obligation. [...]</p>

<p>The first set of measures concerns nine iOS connectivity features,
predominantly used for connected devices such as smartwatches,
headphones or TVs. The measures will grant device manufacturers
and app developers improved access to iPhone features that
interact with such devices (e.g. displaying notifications on
smartwatches), faster data transfers (e.g. peer-to-peer Wi-Fi
connections, and near-field communication) and easier device
set-up (e.g. pairing).</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/03/19/apple-says-eu-interoperability-requirements-enables-unfettered-access-to-the-iphone-risks-customer-security-and-privacy/">Benjamin Mayo, reporting for 9to5Mac</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In a statement to 9to5Mac, Apple firmly rebuked the EU decision
announced today about specific interoperability requirements the
company must implement over the coming months.</p>

<p>Apple said “Today’s decisions wrap us in red tape, slowing down
Apple’s ability to innovate for users in Europe and forcing us
to give away our new features for free to companies who don’t
have to play by the same rules. It’s bad for our products and
for our European users. We will continue to work with the
European Commission to help them understand our concerns on
behalf of our users”.</p>

<p>In regards to customer privacy, Apple is especially concerned with
the requirements surrounding opening up access to the iOS
notification system. The company indicated these measures would
allow companies to suck up all user notifications in an
unencrypted form to their servers, sidestepping all privacy
protections Apple typically enforces.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>My interpretation of the adopted decision is that the EU is requiring Apple to treat iOS like a PC operating system, like MacOS or Windows, where users can install third-party software that runs, unfettered, in the background.</p>

<p>Apple’s statement makes clear their staunch opposition to these decisions. But at least at a superficial level, the European Commission’s tenor has changed. The quotes from the Commission executives (Teresa Ribera, who replaced firebrand Margrethe Vestager as competition chief, and Henna Virkkunen) are anodyne. Nothing of the vituperativeness of the quotes from Vestager and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2024/09/16/breton-resigns">Thierry Breton</a> in years past. But the decisions themselves make clear that the EU isn’t backing down from its general position of seeing itself as the rightful decision-maker for how iOS should function and be engineered, and that Apple’s core competitive asset — making devices that work better together than those from other companies — isn’t legal under the DMA.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘EU Adopts New ‘Interoperability’ Requirements for Apple Under DMA’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/eu-apple-interop-requirements">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Sebastiaan de With’s iPhone 16e Camera Review: ‘The Essentials’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.lux.camera/iphone-16e-camera-review-the-essentials/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w6s" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/de-with-16e-camera" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41716</id>
	<published>2025-03-19T21:53:15Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-19T22:07:21Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Sebastiaan de With:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You can speculate what the ‘e’ in ‘16e’ stands for, but in my head
it stands for ‘essential’. Some things that I consider
particularly essential to the iPhone are all there: fantastic
build quality, an OLED screen, iOS and all its apps, and Face ID.
It even has satellite connectivity. Some other things I also
consider essential are not here: MagSafe is very missed, for
instance, but also multiple cameras. It would be reasonable to look at
Apple’s Camera app, then, and see what comprises the ‘essential’
iPhone camera experience according to Apple.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Sebastiaan de With’s iPhone 16e Camera Review: ‘The Essentials’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/de-with-16e-camera">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple Silicon Is Groundbreaking for AI</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://x.com/alexocheema/status/1899735281781411907?s=42" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w6r" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/apple-silicon-is-groundbreaking-for-ai" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41715</id>
	<published>2025-03-19T20:44:22Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-19T20:48:19Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Alex Cheema is the founder of <a href="https://exolabs.net/">EXO Labs</a>, an AI company focused on “AI you can trust with your data” by making systems that run locally, on computers you own and control. Apple <a href="https://x.com/alexocheema/status/1899604613135028716">provided him with two M3 Ultra Mac Studios</a>, each maxed out with 512 GB of unified memory. Within a day, he had them linked together by Thunderbolt 5 and had the <em>full</em> DeepSeek R1 model running on his desk.</p>

<p>Sure, that’s over $20,000 of computing hardware. But to my knowledge there is no other way in the world to run the full DeepSeek R1 model for even <em>close</em> to $20,000, let alone doing it on your desk rather than a data center. It’s an exclusive advantage, made possible by Apple Silicon’s general performance and the breakthrough of Apple’s <a href="https://developer.apple.com/videos/play/wwdc2020/10686/">unified memory architecture</a>, which lets the GPU cores access the same RAM as the CPU cores.</p>

<p>Apple has tremendous technical advantages to offer in AI. But they’re marketing Genmojis of hot dogs carrying briefcases.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Silicon Is Groundbreaking for AI’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/apple-silicon-is-groundbreaking-for-ai">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Apple Needs to Get Out of the Way With AI’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://shapeof.com/archives/2025/3/apple_needs_to_get_out_of_the_way_with_ai.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w6q" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/apple-needs-to-get-out-of-the-way-with-ai" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41714</id>
	<published>2025-03-19T20:16:55Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-20T14:00:20Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Gus Mueller:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A week or so ago I was grousing to some friends that Apple needs
to open up things on the Mac so other LLMs can step in where Siri
is failing. In theory we (developers) could do this today, but I
would love to see a blessed system where Apple provided APIs to
other LLM providers.</p>

<p>Are there security concerns? Yes, of course there are, there
always will be. But I would like the choice.</p>

<p>The crux of the issue in my mind is this: Apple has a lot of good
ideas, but they don’t have a monopoly on them. I would like some
other folks to come in and try their ideas out. I would like
things to advance at the pace of the industry, and not Apple’s.
Maybe with a blessed system in place, Apple could watch and see
how people use LLMs and other generative models (instead of giving
us Genmoji that look like something Fisher-Price would make). And
maybe open up the existing Apple-only models to developers. There
are locally installed image processing models that I would love to
take advantage of in my apps.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The analogy I used, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/10/yours-truly-guesting-on-upgrade-with-jason-snell">talking with Jason Snell during my guest stint on Upgrade last week</a>, was to the heyday of desktop publishing. The Mac was <em>the</em> platform for graphic design because it was the best platform for using design apps. Fonts worked better and looked better on the Mac. Printing worked better from Macs. Peripherals worked better. The apps themselves looked better on the Mac than they did on Windows. The Mac had taste and designers (hopefully) have taste. Graphic designers could understand how their machines worked, and maintain them themselves, in a way they couldn’t with PCs. </p>

<p>But Apple didn’t make any of the actual apps. Companies like Adobe and Macromedia and Aldus did. Independent small developers made niche extensions for use inside apps like Photoshop, FreeHand, and QuarkXPress. When a new app came along like InDesign — which quickly ate Quark’s lunch — the Mac remained the dominant platform to use.</p>

<p>Making a great platform where <em>other developers</em> can innovate is one of Apple’s core strengths. Apple got even <em>better</em> at it once Mac OS X hit its stride in the 2000s — the Cocoa APIs really did empower outside developers to make world-class apps providing experiences that couldn’t be matched on other platforms like Windows or Linux. Then it happened again, with a much bigger audience, with iOS. What desktop publishing was to the Mac in the 1990s, social media was to the iPhone in the 2010s. Apple didn’t make the apps — they made the best platform to use those apps.</p>

<p>Apple should be laser focused on doing this for AI now. Where I quibble with Mueller is that I don’t want Apple to get out of the way. I want Apple to pave the roads to create the way. Apple doesn’t have to make the cars (<a href="https://www.npr.org/2024/02/27/1234315814/apple-cancels-electric-car">literally</a>) — just pave the best roads. Make the Mac <em>the</em> best platform for outside developers to create innovative AI systems and experiences. Make iOS <em>the</em> best consumer device to use AI apps from any outside developer. Work on APIs and frameworks for the AI age. No company has ever been better than Apple at designing and delivering those sort of APIs. Lean into that. It’s as useful, relevant, and profitable an institutional strength (and set of values) today as ever.</p>

<p>In a follow-up post, <a href="https://shapeof.com/archives/2025/3/how_apple_could_help_developers_with_ai_and_llms.html">Mueller shows he’s thinking like I’m thinking</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>But off the top of my head, here’s one idea that I think could
really help and reap benefits for both Apple and developers.</p>

<p>Build a semantic index (SI), and allow apps to access it via
permissions given similar to what we do for Address Book or
Photos.</p>

<p>Maybe even make the permissions to the SI a bit more fine-grained
than you normally would for other personal databases. Historical
GPS locations? Scraping contents of the screen over time? Indexed
contents of document folder(s)? Make these options for what goes
into the SI.</p>

<p>And of course, the same would be true for building the SI. As a
user, I’d love to be able to say “sure, capture what’s on the
screen and scrape the text out of that, but nope - you better not
track where I’ve been over time”.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>HealthKit already works a lot like what Mueller is suggesting here (for, say, “SemanticKit”). With explicit user permission — that can be revoked at any time — third party apps can both read from and write to your Health data. Apple does a lot of that itself, both through Apple Watch and from the various activity-related things an iPhone can track, but third-party apps and devices are welcome participants, in a private, easily-understood way.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Apple Needs to Get Out of the Way With AI’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/apple-needs-to-get-out-of-the-way-with-ai">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘A Delightful and Simple User Experience’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2025/03/roku-says-unpopular-autoplay-ads-are-just-a-test/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w6p" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/roku-delightful-and-simple" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41713</id>
	<published>2025-03-19T19:54:15Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-19T20:01:42Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Scharon Harding, writing for Ars Technica:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Reports of Roku customers seeing video ads automatically play
before they could view the OS’ home screen started appearing
online this week. A Reddit user, for example, <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Roku/comments/1jcuibl/question_about_ads/">posted</a>
yesterday: “I just turned on my Roku and got an ... ad for a
movie, before I got to the regular Roku home screen.” Multiple
apparent users reported seeing an ad for the movie <em>Moana 2</em>.
The ads have a close option, but some users appear to have not
seen it.</p>

<p>When reached for comment, a Roku spokesperson shared a company
statement that confirms that the autoplaying ads are expected
behavior but not a permanent part of Roku OS currently. Instead,
Roku claimed, it was just trying the ad capability out. [...]</p>

<p>“Our recent test is just the latest example, as we explore new
ways to showcase brands and programming while still providing a
delightful and simple user experience.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>What I’d find delightful and simple is disconnecting my Roku box and throwing it out the window.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘A Delightful and Simple User Experience’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/roku-delightful-and-simple">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Two New PebbleOS Watches</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://ericmigi.com/blog/introducing-two-new-pebbleos-watches" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w6o" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/repebble-watches" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41712</id>
	<published>2025-03-19T19:42:45Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-19T21:12:15Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Eric Migicovsky:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We’re excited to announce two new smartwatches that run open
source PebbleOS and are compatible with thousands of your beloved
Pebble apps.</p>

<ul>
<li>Core 2 Duo has an ultra crisp black and white display,
polycarbonate frame, costs $149 and starts shipping in July.</li>
<li>Core Time 2 has a larger 64-colour display, metal frame, costs
$225 and starts shipping in December.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>My advice would have been to return with just one watch. Make a decision: color or monochrome. I’d sort of lean toward black-and-white, to differentiate it from Apple Watch and other high-end smartwatches. They’re never going to out-color Apple on display quality, so why not go the other way and lean in on black-and-white utility and contrast?</p>

<p>I would also suggest that <a href="https://ericmigi.com/blog/apple-restricts-pebble-from-being-awesome-with-iphones">whining about the fact that iOS doesn’t allow third-party devices</a> the sort of integration that Apple Watch offers isn’t the path forward. Instead of arguing that “Apple restricts Pebble from being awesome with iPhones”, lean into the ways that Pebble can be awesome because it isn’t an Apple Watch. 30-day battery life is awesome. I don’t think Apple Watch will ever offer that. Being able to run whatever apps — including watch faces — that you want on your own Pebble watch is awesome, and I know Apple Watch will never offer that. Lean into what Pebble watches <em>can</em> do that Apple Watches can’t. If the experience as a Pebble owner can be a lot better paired with an Android phone than an iPhone, lean into that. Show how much better it is on Android than iOS. Compete.</p>

<p>If you can’t show how much better Pebble is when paired to an Android device (which they couldn’t do 10 years ago), then what’s the point?</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Two New PebbleOS Watches’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/repebble-watches">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Did TikTok Swing the Election to Trump?</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://politicalwire.com/2025/03/19/did-tiktok-swing-the-election-to-trump/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w6n" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/did-tiktok-swing-the-election-to-trump" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41711</id>
	<published>2025-03-19T19:22:53Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-19T19:22:54Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Taegan Goddard, writing at Political Wire regarding <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/03/18/opinion/ezra-klein-podcast-david-shor.html">pollster David Shor’s appearance on Ezra Klein’s podcast</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>His surveys indicate a clear causal relationship: People who
relied on TikTok for news were much more likely to swing toward
Trump than those who got their information from TV. His most
striking data point:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>When you zoom in on people who get their news from TikTok but
don’t care very much about politics, this group is eight
percentage points more Republican than they were four years ago — which is a lot.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>What remains unclear is why this shift happened. Was TikTok’s
parent company, ByteDance, subtly adjusting its algorithm to
undermine Democrats? Or was the platform simply reflecting broader
anti-incumbent sentiment? Shor concedes:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You could tell a story that maybe just anti-incumbent stuff is
going to do really well on TikTok, and Democrats are going to do
great now. I don’t really know. But I think that, for whatever
reason, this major shift really helped Republicans.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It used to be that getting your message out required persuading
reporters, editors, and gatekeepers — people trained to vet and
verify information.</p>

<p>Now anyone can make a short video, and if it’s compelling enough,
it spreads like wildfire — except that it may be following a path
predetermined by TikTok’s algorithms.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I worry that the liberal/left response to this will be to declare, with exasperation, that people shouldn’t be getting their news or forming their political opinions by what they see on TikTok. You need to meet people where they are, and craft messages for the media they consume.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Did TikTok Swing the Election to Trump?’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/did-tiktok-swing-the-election-to-trump">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>On Apple Exclaves</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://randomaugustine.medium.com/on-apple-exclaves-d683a2c37194" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w6m" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/on-apple-exclaves" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41710</id>
	<published>2025-03-19T19:05:08Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-19T20:02:23Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Random Augustine has written a splendidly nerdy but very approachable overview of the evolution of Apple’s XNU kernel over the last decade:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>2017 — Page Protection Layer</em></p>

<p>With the release of the iPhone 8 and iPhone X containing the A11
processor, Apple introduced a security feature known as the Page
Protection Layer (PPL). This hardware+software feature isolated a
small part of the kernel and gave it privileges to modify memory
page tables — critical structures that manage memory access. The
rest of the kernel lost the ability to directly modify these page
tables. The PPL’s limited attack surface ensured that bypasses
were infamously rare. While PPL added a layer of protection, it
was only partly effective as the rest of the kernel still held
most privileges required to compromise data without modifying
page tables.</p>

<p><em>2021–2023 — Secure Page Table Monitor</em></p>

<p>Following PPL, the release of the iPhone 13 containing the A15
processor introduced new functionality utilised in iOS 17: the
Secure Page Table Monitor (SPTM). This replaced and improved upon
the PPL by securing additional memory functions and dividing them
into subsystems, further isolating small kernel components.
Validation of code signatures, confirming that all code had been
signed by Apple was also isolated.</p>

<p>Around this time, oblique references to exclaves began to surface
in XNU source code. These exclaves were speculated to be the
subsystems managed by SPTM. Then 2024 happened…</p>

<p><em>2024 — Exclaves: A major addition to XNU</em></p>

<p>With the release of XNU source code supporting M4 and A18 based
systems (such as the iPhone 16), the curtain was partly pulled
back on exclaves. (Exclaves are not active on prior processors).</p>

<p>It is now clear that exclaves are part of a much larger redesign
of XNU’s security model.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I am reminded of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Gall_(author)">Gall’s Law</a>: </p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A complex system that works is invariably found to have evolved
from a simple system that worked. A complex system designed from
scratch never works and cannot be patched up to make it work. You
have to start over with a working simple system.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>(I also suspect that Siri — today’s Siri at least — might be a canonical example of “a complex system designed from scratch”. But that’s a different topic.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘On Apple Exclaves’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/on-apple-exclaves">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Firefox Users on iOS Have Doubled in France and Germany, From a Very Small Number to a Slightly Less Small Number</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://pxlnv.com/linklog/firefox-france-germany/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w6l" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/firefox-ios-doubling-france-and-germany" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41709</id>
	<published>2025-03-19T18:44:37Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-19T19:47:13Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Nick Heer:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>They are impressive, but my interpretation of statistics like
these is that one often finds percentages used like this when
neither actual number is very large. Nevertheless, <a href="https://www.reuters.com/technology/eus-new-tech-laws-are-working-small-browsers-gain-market-share-2024-04-10/">another
indication</a> that browser choice screens can have a positive
effect for smaller browsers and, conversely, also a reminder of
the <a href="https://pxlnv.com/linklog/ios-eu-changes-default-apps/">power of defaults</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Saying the daily users have doubled isn’t very meaningful when they don’t state the baseline. It’s a bit of <a href="https://x.com/jsnell/status/481863414180896769">a Bezos chart</a>. And what’s the proof that this growth is from happy users — users who, upon seeing the DMA browser choice screen on their iPhones, realized only then that they wanted to switch to Firefox? Surely <em>some</em> number of users who switched to Firefox via the choice screen did so by mistake, because they were confused.</p>

<p>The best case scenario is that this growth for Firefox (and presumably for <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2024/09/the_ios_continental_drift_widens">other alternate browsers that qualified for the EU choice screens</a>) means that alternative browsers have gone from a tiny usage share to a twice-as-large-but-still-tiny share, and that most of the growth comes from happy users. I see no proof, though, that the growth hasn’t at least significantly come from confused users who now wonder what happened to Safari. And either way, the DMA’s mandatory choice screen has, thus far, been relatively ineffective overall.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Firefox Users on iOS Have Doubled in France and Germany, From a Very Small Number to a Slightly Less Small Number’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/firefox-ios-doubling-france-and-germany">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Beyerdynamic DT 770 Pro: Closed Studio Headphones</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://north-america.beyerdynamic.com/p/dt-770-pro" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w6k" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/beyerdynamic-dt-770-pro" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41708</id>
	<published>2025-03-19T18:22:19Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-19T18:22:19Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Ten years ago I bought a pair of Beyerdynamic DT 770 Pro headphones for use while podcasting. My product research was rigorous and exhaustive: I asked Marco Arment which headphones I should buy, he said these, so I bought them. They’re offered in three impedance variants: 32, 80, and 250 ohms. Beyerdynamics describes 80 ohms as the best “allrounder” choice, and that’s what Marco told me to get.</p>

<p>I’ve since worn them to record at least 275 episodes of The Talk Show (I think <a href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2015/07/29/ep-127">this episode</a> was the first) and nearly all of the five-years-and-counting run of Dithering. They sound great, but more importantly, they’re super comfortable. I can wear them for 3+ hours and my ears don’t feel too bad at all. They’re also built to last. Just about everything on mine still looks fairly new, despite my having worn them for something approaching 1,000 hours. No cracking on the cable and the padding on the headband looks new. The one part that <em>didn’t</em> look new were the velour ear pads. Last week I ordered <a href="https://north-america.beyerdynamic.com/p/edt-770-v">replacements from Beyerdynamics for $40</a>; they arrived earlier this week and I swapped the old pads for new today.</p>

<p>When I bought my headphones in 2015, they cost $250. Today the price is down to just $170, either <a href="https://north-america.beyerdynamic.com/p/dt-770-pro">direct from Beyerdynamic</a> or <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0016MNAAI?tag=df-amzn-20">from Amazon</a> (that’s a make-me-rich affiliate link). I am not an audiophile, and I literally only use mine for podcasting. But I’ve spent quite a lot time podcasting with them over the last decade. I’ll bet I’m still using the same pair (with another set of fresh ear pads) 10 years from now.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Beyerdynamic DT 770 Pro: Closed Studio Headphones’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/beyerdynamic-dt-770-pro">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://workos.com/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/w6j" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/03/workos_scalable_secure_authent_1" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.41707</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-03-19T14:39:18Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-19T14:39:19Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Modern authentication should be seamless and secure.  WorkOS makes it easy to integrate features like MFA, SSO, and RBAC.</p>

<p>Whether you’re replacing passwords, stopping fraud, or adding enterprise auth, WorkOS can help you build frictionless auth that scales. </p>

<p>Future-proof your authentication stack with the identity layer trusted by OpenAI, Cursor, Perplexity, and Vercel.  </p>

<p>Upgrade your auth today. </p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘WorkOS: Scalable, Secure Authentication’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/03/workos_scalable_secure_authent_1">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] WorkOS: Scalable, Secure Authentication</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Hyperspace 1.1</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://hypercritical.co/hyperspace/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w6i" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/18/hyperspace" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41706</id>
	<published>2025-03-18T23:03:41Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-19T02:56:46Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>New (well, newish) Mac app from John Siracusa:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/hyperspace-reclaim-disk-space/id6739505345?mt=12">Hyperspace</a> searches for files with identical contents within
one or more folders. If it finds any, it can then reclaim the disk
space taken by all but one of the identical files — <em>without
removing any of the files!</em></p>

<p>You can <a href="https://hypercritical.co/hyperspace/#how-it-works">learn more</a> about how this is done, if you’re
interested, but the short version is that Hyperspace uses a
standard feature of the macOS file system: space-saving clones.
The Finder does the same thing when you duplicate a file.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I love everything about this app. I love the name — it “works” in like at least three ways. I love that it’s right up Siracusa’s alley. I love that Siracusa has talked about it, at wonderful length, on ATP and <a href="https://hypercritical.co/2025/02/25/hyperspace">expounded upon it on his blog</a>. I love that the premise sounds a little crazy but the explanation makes all the sense in the world. I love that this small, laser-focused utility is fully and splendidly documented. I love the way it looks. It’s got a great icon. I mean <em>of course</em> it would, but still, let’s celebrate how fun this is.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Hyperspace 1.1’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/18/hyperspace">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Saturday Night Live’s Cue Cards</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3djg59JUrmc" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w6h" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/18/snl-cue-cards" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41705</id>
	<published>2025-03-18T16:46:35Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-18T17:00:17Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Not new, but new to me, is this delightful 7-minute short with a behind-the-scenes look at SNL’s cue card team, led by longtime main cue card guy Wally Feresten. Sometimes you just can’t beat analog.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Saturday Night Live’s Cue Cards’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/18/snl-cue-cards">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Chris Ware on Richard Scarry and the Art of Children’s Literature</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://yalereview.org/article/chris-ware-richard-scarry" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w6g" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/18/chris-ware-on-richard-scarry" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41704</id>
	<published>2025-03-18T16:34:33Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-18T16:58:59Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>As a kid I loved Richard Scarry’s books. As an adult I loved (and love) Chris Ware’s graphic novels. As a parent I loved reading Scarry’s books, again, with my son. So of course this essay from Ware, commemorating <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Richard-Scarrys-Cars-Trucks-Things/dp/0593706307?tag=df-amzn-20">the 50th anniversary edition of Scarry’s <em>Cars and Trucks and Things That Go</em></a>, hit hard for me. Bet it will for you too.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Chris Ware on Richard Scarry and the Art of Children’s Literature’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/18/chris-ware-on-richard-scarry">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Om Malik on Apple Intelligence: ‘FUD, Dud, or Both’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://om.co/2025/03/13/apple-intelligence-fud-dud-or-both/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w6f" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/17/malik-fud-dud-or-both" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41703</id>
	<published>2025-03-18T00:47:20Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-19T20:54:23Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Om Malik:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I have my own explanation, something my readers are familiar with,
and it is the most obvious one. Just as Google is trapped in the
10-blue-link prison, which prevents it from doing something
radical, Apple has its own golden handcuffs. It’s a company
weighed down by its market capitalization and what stock market
expects from it.</p>

<p>They lack the moral authority of Steve Jobs to defy the markets,
streamline their product lineup, and focus the company. Instead,
they do what a complex business often does: they do more. Could
they have done a better job with iPadOS? Should Vision Pro receive
more attention?</p>

<p>The answer to all those is yes. Apple has become a complex entity
that can’t seem to ever have enough resources to provide the real
Apple experience. What you get is “good enough.” And most of the
time, I think it is enough — because what others have on the
market is worse. They know how to build great hardware; it’s the
software where they falter. In the case of Apple Intelligence,
they have been caught short because others’ AI products, even when
flawed, are significantly better than Apple’s own offerings.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Hardware inherently keeps a company honest in a way that software doesn’t. Hardware either works or it doesn’t. The only way to “upgrade” hardware is via installing newer software, or by taking the hardware apart and replacing physical components. It’s hard to think of a company, in any field, whose software is “better” than its hardware. Maybe Nintendo? But even with Nintendo, I’d say it’s more like their software is as good as their hardware. Also, an interesting thought that popped into my head reading Malik’s post just now: part of what makes Vision Pro so fascinating is that the software is better than the hardware. The hardware for immersive VR is so early-days that even the industry state-of-the-art — which is Vision Pro — stinks compared to where it’s going to be in even just five years. The 1984 Macintosh was a shitty computer with a 9-inch one-bit display, no hard drive, and an absurdly meager 128 kilobytes of RAM. But the software was amazing!</p>

<p>But the bigger, better point Malik makes is that “good enough” is enough to make Apple’s software seem ahead of its competition. I tried to make this point all the way back in 2007 with “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2007/11/apple_needs_a_nikon">Apple Needs a Nikon</a>”, and I think the problem is worse now than it was then. No other company is even vaguely in Apple’s league. But Apple <em>is</em> sliding toward mediocrity on the software side. It’s very open for debate how far they’ve slipped. I, for one, would argue that they haven’t slipped far, and with an honest reckoning — especially with regard to everything related to Siri and AI — they can nip this in the bud. <em>You</em> might argue that they’ve slipped tremendously across the board. But what I don’t think is arguable is that their competition remains below Apple’s league. That’s what gives credence to the voices in Cupertino who are arguing that everything’s fine. Apple’s the only team in the top tier for UI design.</p>

<p>The best thing that could happen to Apple would be for Google to ship an Android Pixel experience that actually makes iPhone owners insanely jealous. Google is incapable of doing that through UI design. They’re incapable of catching up to Apple on hardware. But maybe on the AI front they can do it. Apple needs a rival.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Om Malik on Apple Intelligence: ‘FUD, Dud, or Both’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/17/malik-fud-dud-or-both">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Tesla’s Share Price Has Been Suspect Since Like Forever</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.ft.com/content/9cc311b7-676b-4539-a682-b3533a76b0fc" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w6e" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/17/tesla-suspect" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41702</id>
	<published>2025-03-17T23:10:22Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-17T23:10:23Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Tesla’s share price has been having a <a href="https://stocks.apple.com/Am3FIcwVVSzeUAKbtyv3F1g">hard time of it</a> lately. The stock has lost about half its value since its all-time high back in December, and, since Musk took office alongside Donald Trump in January, <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/03/07/tesla-shares-declined-every-week-since-elon-musk-went-to-washington.html">dropped for 7 consecutive weeks</a>, rebounding only ever-so-slightly last week, after Musk got the president of the United States to turn the White House lawn into a cheesy Tesla (<a href="https://www.instagram.com/thedailyshow/reel/DHHQ7xxBHgk/">sorry, <em>Tesler</em></a>) dealership. Tesla stock dropped another 5 percent today, on a day when the overall market was slightly up.</p>

<p>I bookmarked <a href="https://www.ft.com/content/9cc311b7-676b-4539-a682-b3533a76b0fc">this Bryce Elder column at the Financial Times</a> back on January 31, and now seems like a good time to link to it:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The usual explanation for when Tesla trading resembles a Pump.fun
shitcoin is: “because Elon talks a lot”. Here’s JPMorgan analyst
Ryan Brinkman to expand on the theme:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It’s not clear to us why Tesla shares traded as much as +5%
higher in the aftermarket Wednesday, although we have some
leading theories. Perhaps it was management’s statement that it
had identified an achievable path to becoming worth more than the
world’s five most valuable companies taken together (i.e., more
than the $14.8 trillion combined market capitalizations of Apple,
Microsoft, NVIDIA, Amazon, &amp; Alphabet). Or maybe it was
management’s belief that just one of its products has by itself
the potential to generate “north of $10 trillion in revenue”. It
may have even related to management guidance for 2026 (no
financial targets were provided, but it was said to be “epic”)
and for 2027 and 2028 (“ridiculously good”).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Brinkman, who has a long-standing “underweight” rating on Tesla,
is beginning to sound a bit exasperated:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>[T]he company’s financial performance and Bloomberg consensus for
   revenue, margin, earnings, and cash flow all keep coming down,
   but analyst price targets and the company’s share price keep
   going up. For instance, Tesla has missed Bloomberg consensus
   EBIT in 9 of the past 10 quarters by an average of -16.3%.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Consistently missing estimates is one thing. What Tesla has been
doing is consistently missing <em>lowered</em> estimates. [...]</p>

<p>Tesla’s biggest asset is hyperbole. The more extreme the
hyperbole, the more valuable it gets. Maybe after-hours market
participants understand the dynamics better than Tesla bears, so
are primed to park fundamentals and trade on vibes. Or maybe
something else entirely is going on.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Sounds a lot like the other guy at the White House Auto Mall.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Tesla’s Share Price Has Been Suspect Since Like Forever’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/17/tesla-suspect">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Michael Tsai’s Roundup of Links and Commentary on My ‘Something Is Rotten’ Piece Last Week</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mjtsai.com/blog/2025/03/13/rotten/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w6d" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/17/tsai-rotten" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41701</id>
	<published>2025-03-17T20:37:43Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-17T20:37:44Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>I’ve been commenting and expanding upon some of the commentary my piece prompted, and I have a few more coming, but it’s good to have Tsai collect a comprehensive overview.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Michael Tsai’s Roundup of Links and Commentary on My ‘Something Is Rotten’ Piece Last Week’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/17/tsai-rotten">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Ray Maker on the Heart Rate Sensor of the Beats PowerBeats 2 Pro</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.dcrainmaker.com/2025/02/apple-beats-powerbeats-2-pro-sports-fitness-heart-rate-in-depth-review.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w6c" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/17/maker-powerbeats-pro-2-heartrate-sensor" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41700</id>
	<published>2025-03-17T20:13:06Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-18T16:18:35Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Ray Maker, writing at DC Rainmaker:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This would not only be the first time Apple has created a
non-watch heart rate sensor, but even more notably, the first time
the company has enabled heart rate broadcasting over existing
Bluetooth heart rate standards.</p>

<p>The question then becomes: Is it accurate?</p>

<p>Unfortunately, it turns out, that was not the question I should
have started with. The real question to start with is: Is the
heart rate function (accuracy aside), even usable? A lot of hours
later, I have answers to both of those questions. And trust me,
it’s a very mixed bag.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The answer:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It’s clear that any movement (even on a stationary bike) quickly
leads to either dropouts or inaccurate heart rate. And outdoors
running, it’s even worse. Ultimately, I don’t see any value in the
heart rate sensor in this product, because it’s simply not good
enough to be useful, even for casual use.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So maybe this feature is <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/17/chance-miller-reviews-the-beats-powerbeats-pro-2"><em>not</em> soon coming</a> to AirPods? I think there’s <a href="https://mastodon.social/@_Davidsmith/114105204080909252">a good argument to be made</a> that these are better than no heart rate monitor at all but also not nearly as good as an Apple Watch or dedicated device.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Ray Maker on the Heart Rate Sensor of the Beats PowerBeats 2 Pro’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/17/maker-powerbeats-pro-2-heartrate-sensor">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Chance Miller Reviews the Beats Powerbeats Pro 2</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/02/11/powerbeats-pro-2-review/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w6a" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/17/chance-miller-reviews-the-beats-powerbeats-pro-2" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41698</id>
	<published>2025-03-17T20:00:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-18T01:50:37Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>I’m a month late linking to it, but Chance Miller wrote a terrific review for 9to5Mac:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The last several releases from Beats, such as <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2023/05/17/beats-studio-buds-plus-review/">the Studio Buds
Plus</a> and <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2024/04/30/beats-solo-4-hands-on-the-most-iconic-beats-headphones-just-got-better/">Solo 4 headphones</a>, have been powered by a
custom Beats chip rather than an Apple-designed chip like what’s
used in AirPods. For Beats, this has enabled better cross-platform
support for Android users, but it’s also come at the cost of
several popular features for Apple fans. For example, the Studio
Buds Plus lack support for automatic in-ear detection, iCloud
pairing, automatic device switching, personalized spatial audio,
and more.</p>

<p>With the Powerbeats Pro 2, Beats has gone back to its roots and
opted for an Apple-designed chip. The Powerbeats Pro 2 are powered
by Apple’s H2 chip, the same chip used by the latest-generation
AirPods Pro 2 and AirPods 4. This means you get the full suite of
Apple-focused audio features.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The degree of shared engineering between Apple’s teams and Beats’s has always seemed odd to me. Sometimes it seems like Beats really is an independent subsidiary, focused on cross-platform headphones, and other times it feels like they’re making Apple products under a different brand label. The sweet spot seems to be about where they landed with these Powerbeats 2.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>All of the aforementioned features and improvements make
Powerbeats Pro 2 an incredibly compelling product, but Beats has
one more thing: Powerbeats Pro 2 feature built-in heart rate
monitoring.</p>

<p>Each Powerbeats Pro 2 earbud has a built-in heart rate monitor
comprised of four components. First, there’s an LED sensor that
emits green LED light at a rate of over 100 pulses per second.
This light is emitted through the skin and hits your red blood
cells. The photodiode then receives the reflected light from the
red blood cells that is modulated by the red blood flow. There’s
an optical lens that helps direct and separate the transmitted and
received light, along with an accelerometer to ensure accuracy and
consistency in data collection.</p>

<p>Beats adds that the Powerbeats Pro 2’s heart rate sensor
technology is derived from Apple’s work on the Apple Watch.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s weird, but cool, that Beats has delivered in-ear heartbeat monitoring before Apple’s own AirPods have. But now it seems like a lock that this will be a feature in AirPods Pro 3, right?</p>

<p>What I always want in a review I read — and what I try to provide to readers through my own reviews — is a sense of whether a product is for me. Powerbeats Pro 2 aren’t for me — and I know it, because Miller’s review describes them so well. But they seem like a terrific product that a <em>lot</em> of people would prefer to AirPods Pro.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Chance Miller Reviews the Beats Powerbeats Pro 2’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/17/chance-miller-reviews-the-beats-powerbeats-pro-2">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Michael Gartenberg on the Lessons Apple Learned (and Hopefully Has Not Forgotten) From MobileMe</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://x.com/Gartenberg/status/1900589068003491963" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w6b" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/17/gartenberg-apple-mobileme" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41699</id>
	<published>2025-03-17T19:35:55Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-17T19:50:37Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Sebastiaan de With, on X, linking to my “Something Is Rotten” piece last week:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Ex-MobileMe team here. This was a brutal time.</p>

<p>It was so bad that when he presented iCloud onstage, Steve said “I
know what you’re thinking: why should I trust them? They’re the
ones who gave us MobileMe!”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Michael Gartenberg (who worked at Apple in product marketing for a few years at the tail end of the Jobs era), responded (across <a href="https://x.com/gartenberg/status/1900588567375540671">two</a> <a href="https://x.com/Gartenberg/status/1900589068003491963">tweets</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>When I was at Apple and Apple University was still around there
was a whole course on MobileMe and how it was possible that things
ended up the way they did. Fascinating to hear all the backstory.</p>

<p>One of the lessons of the Apple University course was much of the
MobileMe debacle was directly because Jobs didn’t care about it.
He was too preoccupied with the newest iPhone at the time. He
didn’t even introduce the product, a lot of the stuff crossed his
desk that he ignored.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Twitter-like social posts enforce brevity, but I suspect Gartenberg would agree that it wasn’t that Jobs didn’t care about MobileMe at all. It was that he didn’t think he had to care enough to devote his personal attention to it. Yes, Apple should offer web-based functionality for some online fundamentals (email, calendar, contacts...) and, more importantly, Apple should provide over-the-air Internet sync for that data between customers’ devices. And it should just work, in the way that a hard drive “just works” without Steve Jobs paying close attention to the current state of Apple’s file system team. But then it turned out MobileMe didn’t “just work”, and Jobs decided that he needed to pay laser-focused attention to starting over and building what we now know as iCloud (which is really quite good, very reliable, and I’d say long ago surpassed the “it just works” threshold). <a href="https://apple.fandom.com/wiki/Worldwide_Developers_Conference_2011">Steve Jobs’s final keynote</a> — at WWDC 2011 — was largely focused on the announcement of iCloud.</p>

<p>Who’s got that role inside Apple today — someone with high standards, good taste, and clout within the company — for Siri and Apple Intelligence? Someone who is going to say <em>We didn’t care enough about this, but now we need to, and will.</em></p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Michael Gartenberg on the Lessons Apple Learned (and Hopefully Has Not Forgotten) From MobileMe’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/17/gartenberg-apple-mobileme">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Going National: The Drexel Microcomputing Project’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1E9NsaSYWbY" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w69" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/17/going-national-the-drexel-microcomputing-project" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41697</id>
	<published>2025-03-17T17:48:31Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-17T18:28:40Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>From Drexel’s YouTube channel:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>But far less recognized is that Drexel made the very bold decision
of committing all students to purchase a previously unreleased and
untested computer from Apple. This was, of course, the Macintosh
(introduced in January 1984), which was unlike any previous
computer. Drexel’s commitment to the Mac was also of great benefit
to Apple, helping to legitimize this brand-new platform, which
helped make the Mac a successful product that continues to thrive
in education 40 years later.</p>

<p>This entire initiative, called the Drexel Microcomputer Project,
was captured in a 1-hour documentary filmed by David Jones, Dean
of the Pennoni Honors College from 2008 to 2014. The film
premiered at Drexel in 1985.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I was very fortunate not only to know Dave Jones (who <a href="https://drexel.edu/news/archive/2018/October/Sad-News-on-the-Passing-of-Former-Dean-Dave-Jones">died in 2018</a>) but to have him as a professor for several film criticism courses (one on westerns, and another on the works of Alfred Hitchcock). I was a computer science major, not a film major, but Jones didn’t care. He was also familiar with — dare I say, a fan of — my column in <a href="https://www.thetriangle.org/">The Triangle</a>, Drexel’s student newspaper. He took me to lunch my senior year and encouraged me to pursue writing as a career. He was a great teacher: thoughtful, kind, insightful, open-minded, and deeply knowledgeable.</p>

<p>I saw a screening of <em>Going National</em> back in 2011, and sat on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0-vCnurOBf8">a panel discussion with Jones to talk about it</a>. It’s a good documentary, and he really captured the feel of Drexel’s campus at the time. It is a very <em>’80s</em> movie. It was gratifying that I got to tell him, then, that his advice to me back in 1996 had worked out pretty well.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Going National: The Drexel Microcomputing Project’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/17/going-national-the-drexel-microcomputing-project">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘40 Years Ago, Drexel Made Computer — and Apple — History’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://drexel.edu/news/archive/2024/March/drexel-apple-40th-anniversary-macintosh-1984" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w68" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/17/drexel-macintosh-40-years" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41696</id>
	<published>2025-03-17T17:25:10Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-17T19:49:48Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Alissa Falcone, in a good piece looking back at (my alma mater) Drexel University’s groundbreaking deal with Apple 40 years ago to provide deeply discounted Macintoshes to all students, and integrate them throughout the campus and curriculums:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Drexel was prepared to buy IBM computers — and had equipped its
computer centers with IBMs for decades — but the cost came to
more than $1,000 per unit. IBM’s young competitor Apple, on the
other hand, was willing to give discounts, provided the University
agreed to secret negotiations and discreet showings of its newest,
unreleased personal computer.</p>

<p>Bruce Eisenstein, PhD, Arthur J. Rowland Professor of Electrical
and Computer Engineering in the College of Engineering, was the
head of the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering at
the time, and had been the founding faculty adviser for the Drexel
Computer Society started in 1972. He was Drexel’s choice to meet
with an Apple representative to see the future Macintosh, which
had never-before-seen properties like a mouse, icons on a screen
and different fonts. This new Apple product was more powerful and
easier to use than earlier personal computers; novices could
supposedly master it in 30 minutes (without the need to memorize
and type coded commands). And Apple agreed on the $1,000 price tag
for a model that sold to the public for $2,495.</p>

<p>“I went back to the selection committee and I said, ‘Listen, you
have to forget the IBM. This new computer from Apple is the one
you have to get. They are going to make it available to us for a
thousand dollars — that’s all inclusive.’ And the first question
was ‘Is it compatible with the IBM computer?’ Well, no. Was there
software for it? No. Were there any programs for it, like a word
processor? Not yet. So the committee justifiably kept saying,
well, what’s the name of this? What’s it like? I couldn’t tell
them. I had to say you just gotta trust me on this. So they took a
vote and unanimously voted to adopt the unknown computer that
turned out to be the Macintosh,” Eisenstein recalled in <em>Building
Drexel: The University and Its City, 1891-2016</em>.</p>

<p>Drexel chose the untested Macintosh even knowing that Apple
wouldn’t announce it to the public until January 1984 and that the
computers wouldn’t be ready until March, almost halfway through
that momentous academic year.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I never had the pleasure of meeting Eisenstein, but I’d sure like to thank him for his prescience. By the time I got to Drexel in 1991 the Mac was infused throughout campus.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘40 Years Ago, Drexel Made Computer — and Apple — History’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/17/drexel-macintosh-40-years">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>My 2015 Interview With ‘Becoming Steve Jobs’ Authors Brent Schlender and Rick Tetzeli</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/brent-schlender-rick-tetzeli/id980487310?mt=2" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w67" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/17/my-interview-with-schlender-and-tetzeli" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41695</id>
	<published>2025-03-17T16:32:24Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-17T17:04:08Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Ten years ago I played two small roles in the release of the aforelinked <em>Becoming Steve Jobs</em>. First, I got to <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2015/03/02/becoming-steve-jobs">announce the book</a> here at Daring Fireball, after having been sent an advance copy a few weeks earlier. My praise for the book then was glowing, but in hindsight, I think I undersold just how good — and how essential — it is. At the time of its launch, the book remained in the shadow of Walter Isaacson’s Jobs biography. Ten years later, I refer back to <em>Becoming Steve Jobs</em> regularly; Isaacson’s book almost never.</p>

<p>Second, the SoHo Apple Store in New York hosted a “Meet the Authors” event, and I had the pleasure of playing host for the interview. <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/brent-schlender-rick-tetzeli/id980487310?mt=2">It’s still available</a>, both as video and audio. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2015/03/27/schlender-tetzeli-interview">And as I wrote at the time</a>, “I’m kind of proud that it got flagged as ‘explicit’ — but that was Bill Gates’s fault.”</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘My 2015 Interview With ‘Becoming Steve Jobs’ Authors Brent Schlender and Rick Tetzeli’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/17/my-interview-with-schlender-and-tetzeli">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Original ‘Something’s Rotten in Cupertino’ — Brent Schlender’s 1997 Story for Fortune</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://money.cnn.com/magazines/fortune/fortune_archive/1997/03/03/222710/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w66" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/17/the-og-somethings-rotten-in-cupertino" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41694</id>
	<published>2025-03-17T16:22:58Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-18T15:43:40Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>During Friday’s episode of Dithering — <a href="https://dithering.passport.online/member/episode/being-real-points">a free listen</a> — Ben Thompson reminded me that my headline reference last week, alluding to the well-known line from <em>Hamlet</em>, had been used, to great effect, once before. Brent Schlender wrote a crackerjack piece for Fortune in March 1997 under the <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/something_is_rotten_in_the_state_of_cupertino">slightly-different-than-mine</a> headline “Something’s Rotten in Cupertino”.</p>

<p>I should make very clear that I didn’t mean to allude to Schlender’s piece with mine. We both just riffed on the same idiom from Shakespeare. In my case, I’m writing about <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/something_is_rotten_in_the_state_of_cupertino">one initiative that’s gone awry</a> inside a very successful, well-functioning Apple. The timeframe for Schlender’s piece, on the other hand, was the most precarious and dysfunctional period in the history of Apple. Then-CEO Gil Amelio had just announced the acquisition of NeXT in December 1996. By June, most of the board would be replaced, Amelio fired, and Steve Jobs would return as an “advisor”, and, by the end of 1997, as “interim CEO”. Schlender was all over what was really going on:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>At Apple’s headquarters in Cupertino, California, a power play is
in progress that calls into question who’s really running the
company and that may very well put Apple in play once again. So
thick is this plot that it reaches into the homes of some of the
most powerful CEOs in Silicon Valley. The delicious irony is that
what triggered the soap opera is a move Amelio hopes is his
masterstroke: Apple’s $400-million acquisition of Next, and the
advisory services of Steve Jobs that come bundled with it.</p>

<p>Amelio’s big deal is beginning to look more like a Next takeover
of Apple. Never mind that Next Software was a boutique with
revenues that would amount to less than a rounding error to Apple.
Jobs, the Svengali of Silicon Valley, may have outdone himself
this time: Not only did he collect $100 million and 1.5 million
shares of Apple stock for his stake in Next, but his fingerprints
are all over Amelio’s latest reorganization plan and product
strategy — even though Jobs doesn’t have an operational role or
even a board seat.</p>

<p>To the Machiavellian eye, it looks as if Jobs, despite the lure of
Hollywood — lately he has been overseeing Pixar, maker of <em>Toy
Story</em> and other computer-animated films — might be scheming to
take over Apple for himself. If anyone doubts he could do it, all
you have to do is ask his best friend, Oracle CEO Larry Ellison,
the richest man in Silicon Valley. Says he: “Steve’s the only one
who can save Apple.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We all know today this is exactly how it played out. But in March 1997 none of it was obvious at all. It really wasn’t even clear whether Apple would still exist as an independent company by the end of the year. Just extraordinary reporting and storytelling by Schlender.</p>

<p>Go ahead and re-read Schlender’s 1997 Fortune piece, which we should be thankful remains online at all, but which has been mangled, formatting-wise, by whatever series of CMS transitions have kept it online for 28 years. But if you want the best version of this saga, get yourself a copy of <em>Becoming Steve Jobs</em>, the 2015 biography Schlender co-authored with Rick Tetzeli. I just re-read chapter 8 over the weekend — the chapter covering Jobs’s momentous 1997 (in addition to the Apple-NeXT reunification, that was also the year he hammered out an aggressive new deal with Disney for five post-<em>Toy Story</em> feature films) — and it’s just <em>so good</em>. If you don’t already have a copy of <em>Becoming Steve Jobs</em>, get it <a href="https://amzn.to/4kwfeKC">at Amazon</a> or <a href="https://bookshop.org/p/books/becoming-steve-jobs-the-evolution-of-a-reckless-upstart-into-a-visionary-leader-brent-schlender/8629764?ean=9780385347426&amp;next=t">from Bookshop.org</a> or <a href="https://books.apple.com/us/book/becoming-steve-jobs/id936502684">Apple Books</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Original ‘Something’s Rotten in Cupertino’ — Brent Schlender’s 1997 Story for Fortune’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/17/the-og-somethings-rotten-in-cupertino">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Dithering: ‘Being Real Points’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://dithering.passport.online/member/episode/being-real-points" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w65" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/16/dithering-being-real-points" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41693</id>
	<published>2025-03-17T00:38:26Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-19T19:19:40Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/03/dithering-cover-mar-2025.png" class="noborder">
  <img
    src   = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/03/dithering-cover-mar-2025.png"
    alt   = "The March 2025 cover art for Dithering, showing a man, high atop a cityscape, precariously crossing a high wire."
    width = 525
  /></a></p>

<p>A new feature in our membership CMS (<a href="https://passport.online/">Passport</a> — check it out) lets us make individual episodes of Dithering free for everyone to listen to (on the web). I can’t think of a better way to first use this new capability than to open up Friday’s episode, recapping my “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/something_is_rotten_in_the_state_of_cupertino">Something Is Rotten in the State of Cupertino</a>” article, and the resonance with which it hit. Even the cover art — selected weeks ago — captures how I’ve felt this week.</p>

<p>Give it a listen. <a href="https://dithering.fm/">Subscribe if you enjoy it</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Dithering: ‘Being Real Points’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/16/dithering-being-real-points">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/a_postscript_on_the_singular_nature_of_mark_gurmans_reporting" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/w64" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41692</id>
	<published>2025-03-16T14:26:24Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-17T14:38:43Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">But I’d feel a lot better about our collective conventional wisdom regarding the nature of this particular all-hands Siri meeting if it had leaked to, and been reported on, by more than one reporter at more than one publication.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/14/all-hands-siri-team-meeting-leaks-to-bloomberg">My post Friday</a> commenting (read: <em>wise-cracking</em>) on Mark Gurman’s explosive report on an all-hands Siri team meeting at Apple was begging for a bit of meta commentary on the reporting itself. But I’ve been doing so much of that regarding Gurman lately that I thought it best to hold it for a postscript. Here’s that postscript.</p>

<p>Both of these things are true:</p>

<ul>
<li>Mark Gurman is a singular reporter in the Apple media sphere. He publishes an extraordinary number of exclusives, both regarding leaks of upcoming products, and leaks <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2025-03-14/apple-s-siri-chief-calls-ai-delays-ugly-and-embarrassing-promises-fixes">like this Siri team meeting</a>.</li>
<li>Gurman <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2021/09/14/prosser-flat-edge-watch">often</a> <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/05/gurman-c1-modem-ipad">gets</a> <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/05/gurman-ipads">things</a> wrong, and when he does, he never acknowledges those mistakes, let alone corrects them. He also tries to take credit for having called things <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/05/your-source-for-scoops">he completely missed</a>. He’s not an oracle but presents himself as one. And he writes for a publication, Bloomberg, that shares his insistence on never acknowledging let alone correcting mistakes, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2021/02/12/bloomberg-big-con">even massive ones</a>. What gives me such joy pointing out his boners isn’t that he made them in the first place but that he refuses to acknowledge they happened, presenting an air of infallibility with a provably fallible track record.</li>
</ul>

<p>In short, I <a href="https://sixcolors.com/member/2025/03/the-pinata-of-apple-rumors/">do actually suspect</a> — but can claim zero sources familiar with the matter to confirm — that Gurman hangs his toilet paper in an improper underhand fashion.</p>

<p>So let’s just examine how extraordinary and singular Gurman’s Friday report was. Nobody else reported on this meeting. <a href="https://www.techmeme.com/250314/p18#a250314p18">Every other article about it</a> — including mine — was commenting on Gurman’s exclusive report about the meeting. I’ve not seen one other report even confirming the meeting took place, let alone describing it in detail, replete with copious quotes from Siri senior director Robby Walker, who, according to Gurman, led the meeting. Not one. I’m not pointing that out to cast suspicion that the meeting did not take place or that Gurman’s report cast it inaccurately or that his direct quotations were not, in fact, direct quotations. I’m pointing out just how singular and extraordinary Mark Gurman is in this sphere. If it wasn’t for Gurman’s report we, outside Apple (and probably outside the Siri team inside Apple) wouldn’t even know the meeting occurred.</p>

<p>How did Gurman not only get the scoop on this meeting, but copious direct quotes from Walker’s remarks to the team? Well, it was “according to people with knowledge of the matter, who asked not to be identified because the gathering was private”. In other words, more than one member of the Siri team, and at least one of which either recorded the meeting surreptitiously and slipped the recording to Gurman, or at least one of whom takes notes at the pace and accuracy of a court stenographer. Either way, these sources — plural — surely knew how the meeting would make Apple look if it were to leak.</p>

<p>I’ve long made my opinions about Bloomberg’s institutional journalistic credibility  well known. But I don’t think they’re bereft of credibility — it’s the fact that they are deservedly well-regarded that makes their refusal to ever admit their own glaring mistakes so notable. When a Gurman reports says “people” that means “more than one” and, I believe, he must be able to confirm to his editors that he got this information from more than one source. If he’s reporting direct quotes, I think that means he’s heard a recording. That’s extraordinary.</p>

<p>But I’d feel a lot better about our collective conventional wisdom regarding the nature of this particular all-hands Siri meeting if it had leaked to, and been reported on by, more than one reporter at more than one publication.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ A Postscript on the Singular Nature of Mark Gurman’s Reporting</title></entry><entry>
	<title>WorkOS: Scalable, Secure Authentication</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://workos.com/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w5y" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/15/workos" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41686</id>
	<published>2025-03-16T00:30:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-16T00:30:59Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to WorkOS for sponsoring this week at DF. Modern authentication should be seamless and secure.  WorkOS makes it easy to integrate features like MFA, SSO, and RBAC.</p>

<p>Whether you’re replacing passwords, stopping fraud, or adding enterprise auth, WorkOS can help you build frictionless auth that scales. Future-proof your authentication stack with the identity layer trusted by OpenAI, Cursor, Perplexity, and Vercel. Upgrade your auth today.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘WorkOS: Scalable, Secure Authentication’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/15/workos">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>How to Generate a Report of Apple Intelligence Requests Sent to Private Cloud Compute</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://support.apple.com/guide/iphone/apple-intelligence-and-privacy-iphe3f499e0e/ios" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w63" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/15/how-to-generate-a-report-of-apple-intelligence-requests-sent-to-private-cloud-compute" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41691</id>
	<published>2025-03-16T00:29:41Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-17T19:12:44Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>From Apple’s support documentation:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You can generate a report of requests your iPhone has sent to
Private Cloud Compute.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Go to Settings, then tap Privacy &amp; Security.</p></li>
<li><p>Tap Apple Intelligence Report, then choose a report duration
for the last 15 minutes (default) or last 7 days. Choose off to
disable the report.</p>

<p><em>Note</em>: The report may be empty if there haven’t been any
  Private Cloud Compute requests since you changed the
  duration.</p></li>
<li><p>Tap Export Activity, choose a place to store the file, then tap
Export.</p>

<p>The report is saved as a file named
  Apple_Intelligence_Report.json.</p></li>
<li><p>Open the file with a text reader.</p></li>
</ol>
</blockquote>

<p>These are the iOS instructions, but they’re exactly the same on MacOS 15 Sequoia. My first generated report was empty for the last 7 days, and it was empty again even after running the Writing Tools Proofread function on the text of my 4,000-word “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/something_is_rotten_in_the_state_of_cupertino">Something Is Rotten in the State of Cupertino</a>” article from this week. But when I ran the Writing Tools Summarize feature on the same text, I wound up with a long entry that was sent to Private Cloud Compute. So, at the moment, Summarize seems like a good way to invoke Private Cloud Compute, even from a relatively powerful Mac.</p>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/03/something-is-rotten-in-cupertino-apple-intelligence-summary.text">Here’s the summary Apple Intelligence generated</a>. I have to say: it’s pretty good. It’s completely petty but also completely <em>me</em> to notice and object to the way it uses two spaces after periods — and worse, only <em>some</em> of the time. Also, the sentence “This raises concerns about the company’s ability to maintain its position as a leader in AI innovation” is, let’s say, off the mark.</p>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> <a href="https://eclecticlight.co/2024/10/29/check-writing-tools-using-air/">Howard Oakley wrote a post</a> with a brief overview of the structure and contents of these reports back on October 29.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘How to Generate a Report of Apple Intelligence Requests Sent to Private Cloud Compute’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/15/how-to-generate-a-report-of-apple-intelligence-requests-sent-to-private-cloud-compute">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>New RCS Spec From GSM Association Adds E2EE; Both Apple and Google to Support It</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/news/629620/apple-iphone-e2ee-encryption-rcs-messaging-android" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w62" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/15/rcs-e2ee-apple-google" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41690</id>
	<published>2025-03-15T22:08:35Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-16T18:41:42Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jess Weatherbed, reporting for The Verge:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>iPhone and Android users will be able to exchange end-to-end
encrypted (E2EE) RCS messages in the near future thanks to newly
updated RCS specifications. <a href="https://www.gsma.com/newsroom/article/rcs-encryption-a-leap-towards-secure-and-interoperable-messaging/">The GSM Association announced</a> that the
latest RCS standard includes E2EE based on the Messaging Layer
Security (MLS) protocol, enabling interoperable encryption between
different platform providers for the first time. [...]</p>

<p>“End-to-end encryption is a powerful privacy and security
technology that iMessage has supported since the beginning, and
now we are pleased to have helped lead a cross industry effort to
bring end-to-end encryption to the RCS Universal Profile published
by the GSMA,” said Apple spokesperson Shane Bauer. “We will add
support for end-to-end encrypted RCS messages to iOS, iPadOS,
macOS, and watchOS in future software updates.” [...]</p>

<p>“We’ve always been committed to providing a secure messaging
experience, and Google Messages users have had end-to-end
encrypted (E2EE) RCS messaging for years,” Google spokesperson Ed
Fernandez told The Verge. “We’re excited to have this updated
specification from GSMA and work as quickly as possible with the
mobile ecosystem to implement and extend this important user
protection to cross-platform RCS messaging.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is nothing but good news. But it’s wrong to frame this along Google’s lines, that they’ve been there waiting for Apple to support E2EE for RCS. They’ve been <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2024/02/eu_rcs_imessage">waiting for Apple to support RCS <em>at all</em></a>, yes, and Google has also implemented their own <em>proprietary</em> E2EE layer for RCS. But until now, there was no E2EE specification in the open RCS spec. Now there is. That’s why it’s not just Android ↔︎ iOS RCS messaging that wasn’t able to use E2EE, but even Android ↔︎ Android, unless both devices were using Google’s own Messages app.</p>

<p>I have also noticed recently that Google Messages and Apple Messages now do a pretty good job of supporting each other’s tapbacks. And that hasn’t done anything to really change the green/blue messaging dynamic. Both things are true: RCS makes cross-platform messaging way better <em>and</em> iMessage remains vastly superior to RCS.</p>

<p>What I’m most interested about with Apple’s implementation of RCS encryption is how they’ll indicate it visually in chats. It’s not going to be with blue bubbles. Blue means “iMessage”, not “encrypted” — it just happens to be that iMessage started as a protocol based on end-to-end encryption. There’s no such thing as a non-encrypted iMessage — it’s part of the protocol, and always has been. But what happens when new/updated Android phones support the new RCS encryption spec, and older devices don’t? A lock icon for the encrypted chats? If it were up to me, iOS would drop support for non-encrypted RCS — iOS should use RCS with E2EE for every device that supports it, and fall back to dumb old no-encryption-at-all SMS for all devices that do not.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘New RCS Spec From GSM Association Adds E2EE; Both Apple and Google to Support It’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/15/rcs-e2ee-apple-google">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple Did Demo Swift Assist at WWDC Last Year, and Has Shown It, Under NDA, Since Then</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macstories.net/news/a-look-at-code-completion-and-swift-assist-coming-in-xcode-16/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w61" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/15/swift-assist-voorhees" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41689</id>
	<published>2025-03-15T18:54:01Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-16T00:31:53Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>In <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/13/whither-swift-assist">an item earlier this week</a> observing that Swift Assist, the most ambitious Xcode-related Apple Intelligence feature shown at WWDC last year, not only hasn’t yet shipped but still is not in beta, I wondered whether Apple actually demoed it live last year. John Voorhees, writing for MacStories from WWDC last June, reports that they did:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Earlier today, I got the very first live demo of Swift Assist, one
of the many <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2024/06/apple-empowers-developers-and-fuels-innovation-with-new-tools-and-resources/">developer tools introduced today</a> by Apple. I
also saw code completion in action. It was an impressive demo, and
although the tools seem like magic and will undoubtedly be
valuable to developers, they do have their limitations, which are
worth exploring. [...]</p>

<p>The code completion demo also included a live demo of Swift
Assist. Unlike code completion, Swift Assist requires an Internet
connection because requests are sent to the cloud. As a result, it
takes several seconds for Swift Assist to return results. The
delay was noticeable compared to the speed of code completion, but
it wasn’t a painfully long wait either.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I heard this week from a third-party developer who was invited to Apple for a one-day hands-on session with Swift Assist late last year. Swift Assist was definitely working, but seemingly not working too well. From that source: “The UI is very much complete (just like Siri), but the results the LLM produces were not very good. It could make very basic demo apps with a prompt like ‘make an app that takes the NASA satellite JSON and shows the current satellites traveling overhead right now’, but not too much more than that. It fell apart on more complex tasks.”</p>

<p>I remember the remote-inference-only aspect of the Swift Assist presentation from my Xcode briefing at WWDC: that because of its complexity, Swift Assist would not execute locally and would only run via Private Cloud Compute. My own notes on this from WWDC were mostly related to the privacy and security implications. That developers should feel safe using Swift Assist even with confidential code and projects because Private Cloud Compute would be guaranteed private. I also remember thinking, at the time, that I should be more skeptical about Apple’s claims about Apple Intelligence features that would execute locally, on-device, rather than the ones that would execute remotely, via Private Cloud Compute, because the way almost all “AI” features from other companies over the previous two years worked was entirely in the cloud. Apple’s statements that Apple Intelligence will perform much inference locally, on-device, seemed like the stretch goal.</p>

<p>But now in March 2025 I’m beginning to think it’s the other way around. What features and aspects of Apple Intelligence run in Private Cloud Compute, today, in March 2025? Do any? I’ve been poking around for a few days and I don’t have any answers. Is Private Cloud Compute running in production yet? How would we know? If you know, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/contact/">let me know</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/15/how-to-generate-a-report-of-apple-intelligence-requests-sent-to-private-cloud-compute">How to Generate a Report of Apple Intelligence Requests Sent to Private Cloud Compute</a>”.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Did Demo Swift Assist at WWDC Last Year, and Has Shown It, Under NDA, Since Then’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/15/swift-assist-voorhees">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Imagine How Powerful Meta Might Be Today If Their PR Wasn’t Run by Sycophantic Morons</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.businessinsider.com/meta-book-mark-zuckerberg-defense-drawing-more-attention-2025-3" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w60" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/15/meta-tries-to-squash-book" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41688</id>
	<published>2025-03-15T18:33:34Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-15T18:33:34Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Katie Notopoulos, writing at Business Insider (<a href="https://apple.news/AKBVv40CYTPea6iXqh-wl-A">Apple News+ link</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It’s possible that this strident defense is backfiring — creating
a “<a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/gina-rinehart-portrait-australia-national-gallery-lesson-in-streisand-effect-2024-5">Streisand Effect</a>” that’s publicizing the book even more.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Notopoulos isn’t one to pull punches or hedge, normally, but there’s no question that Meta has Streisand Effected the hell out of <a href="https://amzn.to/4hGWXHH">Wynn-Williams’s <em>Careless People</em></a>. I’m on my way to buy a copy this afternoon and I hadn’t even heard of its existence a day ago.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Sarah Wynn-Williams worked at Facebook from 2011 to 2017 — and
her <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/mark-zuckerberg-board-game-careless-people-sarah-wynn-williams-2025-3">book, “Careless People</a>,” details what she said were a
bunch of bad things the company did. It also contains allegations
that Joel Kaplan — who is now Meta’s chief global affairs officer — sexually harassed her. (Meta said this week that Kaplan had
been cleared of the harassment allegations in 2017 after it
investigated Wynn-Williams’ complaint.)</p>

<p>The book was released with hardly any pre-publishing fanfare: It
was announced by its publisher, Flatiron Books, an imprint of
Macmillan, only a few days before it came out Tuesday. That’s an
unusually short timeline.</p>

<p>Meta’s reaction has been emphatic and multi-pronged. The company
created a <a href="https://about.fb.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/Sarah-Wynn-Williams-New-Book-Of-Old-News.pdf">page on its website</a> that detailed a series of
the claims in the book. It said some of these — like claims
about its ambitions in China or its alleged failure to act in
Myanmar — have already been reported in the news media as far
back as 2017 and have been acknowledged by the company publicly.
The company lists seven “new” claims from the book and then
offers links to past coverage and company responses — calling
the claims “old news.”</p>

<p>Meta’s strongest move was on Wednesday when it won <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/meta-legal-win-bars-former-exec-promoting-book-careless-people-2025-3">a ruling in
arbitration</a> that said Wynn-Williams could no longer promote
the book because of a non-disparagement clause in a contract she
signed as an employee. The ruling was granted on an emergency
basis and is temporary pending the completion of the full
arbitration process, The Washington Post <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/style/2025/03/13/careless-people-facebook-meta-arbitration/">reported</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>“<em>Read the book that Meta not only doesn’t want you to read, but wants to prevent its author from even talking about</em>” is a hell of a marketing angle. What an own goal.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Imagine How Powerful Meta Might Be Today If Their PR Wasn’t Run by Sycophantic Morons’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/15/meta-tries-to-squash-book">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Ted Lasso’ Renewed for a Fourth Season</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.hollywoodreporter.com/tv/tv-news/ted-lasso-renewed-season-4-apple-tv-1236163347/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w5z" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/15/lasso-season-4" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41687</id>
	<published>2025-03-15T18:06:06Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-15T18:06:07Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Rick Porter, The Hollywood Reporter:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>After more than a year of speculation, Apple TV+ has ordered a
fourth season of its Emmy-winning comedy Ted Lasso. The pickup
comes after co-creator and star Jason Sudeikis closed a deal to
reprise his role as the title character, the manager of the
fictional AFC Richmond soccer club in London.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I dig <em>Ted Lasso</em> but this is like 0.1 percent as interesting as <strong>When are we going to get <em>Severance</em> season 3?! Gimme gimme gimme.</strong> And we haven’t even gotten to next week’s season 2 finale yet.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Ted Lasso’ Renewed for a Fourth Season’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/15/lasso-season-4">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/something_is_rotten_in_the_state_of_cupertino" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/w5q" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41678</id>
	<published>2025-03-12T23:37:14Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-18T16:05:51Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Who decided these personalized Siri features should go in the WWDC keynote, with a promise they’d arrive in the coming year, when, at the time, they were in such an unfinished state they could not be demoed to the media even in a controlled environment? Three months later, who decided Apple should double down and advertise these features in a TV commercial, and promote them as a selling point of the iPhone 16 lineup?</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>In the two decades I’ve been in this racket, I’ve never been angrier at myself for missing a story than I am about Apple’s <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/apple_is_delaying_the_more_personalized_siri_apple_intelligence_features">announcement on Friday</a> that the “more personalized Siri” features of Apple Intelligence, scheduled to appear between now and WWDC, would be delayed until “the coming year”.</p>

<p>I should have my head examined. </p>

<p>This announcement dropped as a surprise, and certainly took me by surprise to some extent, but it was all there from the start. I should have been pointing out red flags starting back at WWDC last year, and I am embarrassed and sorry that I didn’t see what should have been very clear to me from the start.</p>

<p>How I missed this is twofold. First, I’d been lulled into complacency by Apple’s track record of consistently shipping pre-announced products and features. Their record in that regard wasn’t perfect, but the exceptions tended to be around the edges. (Nobody was particularly clamoring for Apple to make a multi-device inductive charging mat, so it never generated too much controversy <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/apple_is_delaying_the_more_personalized_siri_apple_intelligence_features#fn1-2025-03-07">when AirPower turned out to be a complete bust</a>.) Second, I was foolishly distracted by the “Apple Intelligence” brand umbrella. It’s a fine idea for Apple to brand its AI features under an umbrella term like that, similar to how a bunch of disparate features that allow different Apple devices to interoperate are under the “<a href="https://www.apple.com/macos/continuity/">Continuity</a>” umbrella. But there’s no such thing, technically speaking, as “Continuity”. It’s not like there’s an Xcode project inside Apple named Continuity.xcodeproj, and all the code that supports everything from AirDrop to Sidecar to iPhone Mirroring to clipboard sharing is all implemented in the same framework of code. It’s a marketing term, but a useful one — it helps Apple explain the features, and helps users understand them.</p>

<p>The same goes for “Apple Intelligence”. It doesn’t exist as a single thing or project. It’s a marketing term for a collection of features, apps, and services. Putting it all under a single obvious, easily remembered — and <a href="https://www.creativebloq.com/design/print-design-publishing/apples-new-billboard-ads-are-um-not-great">easily promoted</a> — name makes it easier for users to understand that Apple is launching a new initiative. It also makes it easier for Apple to just say “<em>These are the devices that qualify for all of these features, and other devices — older ones, less expensive ones — get none of them.</em>”</p>

<p>Let’s say Apple were to quietly abandon the dumb Image Playground app next year. It just disappears from iOS 19 and MacOS 16. That would just be Apple eliminating a silly app that almost no one uses or should use. That wouldn’t be a setback or rollback of “Apple Intelligence”. I would actually argue that axing Image Playground would improve Apple Intelligence; its mere existence greatly lowers the expectations for how good the whole thing is.<sup id="fnr1-2025-03-12"><a href="#fn1-2025-03-12">1</a></sup></p>

<p>What I mean by that is that it was clear to me from the WWDC keynote onward that some of the features and aspects of Apple Intelligence were more ambitious than others. Some were downright trivial; others were proposing to redefine how we will do our jobs and interact with our most-used devices. That was clear. But yet somehow I didn’t focus on it. Apple itself strongly hinted that the various features in Apple Intelligence wouldn’t all ship at the same time. What they didn’t spell out, but anyone could intuit, was that the more trivial features would ship first, and the more ambitious features later. That’s where the red flags should have been obvious to me.</p>

<p>In broad strokes, there are four stages of “doneness” or “realness” to features announced by any company:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Features that the company’s own product representatives will demo, themselves, in front of the media. Smaller, more personal demonstrations are more credible than on-stage demos. But the stakes for demo fail are higher in an auditorium full of observers.</p></li>
<li><p>Features that the company will allow members of the media (or other invited outside observers and experts) to try themselves, for a limited time, under the company’s supervision and guidance. Vision Pro demos were like this at WWDC 2023. A bunch of us got to use pre-release hardware and in-progress software for 30 minutes. It wasn’t like free range “Do whatever you want” — it was a guided tour. But we were the ones actually using the product. Apple allowed hands-on demos for a handful of media (not me) at Macworld Expo <a href="https://www.macworld.com/article/186251/ihnatkoiphone.html">back in 2007 with prototype original iPhones</a> — some of the “apps” were just screenshots, but most of the iPhone actually worked.</p></li>
<li><p>Features that are released as beta software for developers, enthusiasts, and the media to use on their own devices, without limitation or supervision.</p></li>
<li><p>Features that actually ship to regular users, and hardware that regular users can just go out and buy.</p></li>
</ol>

<p>As of today — March 2025 — every feature in Apple Intelligence <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/02/26/this-is-every-apple-intelligence-feature-thats-available-now/">that has actually shipped</a> was at level 1 back at WWDC. After the keynote, dozens of us in the press were invited to a series of small-group briefings where we got to watch Apple reps demo features like Writing Tools, Photos Clean Up, Genmoji, and more. We got to see predictive code completion in Xcode. What has shipped, as of today, they were able to show, in some functional state, in June.</p>

<p>For example, there was a demo involving a draft email message on an iPad, and the Apple rep used Writing Tools to make it “more friendly”. I was in a group of just four or five other members of the media, watching this. As usual, we were encouraged to interrupt with questions. Knowing that LLMs are non-deterministic, I asked whether, as the Apple rep was performing this same demo for each successive group of media members, the “more friendly” result was exactly the same each time. He laughed and said no — that while the results are very similar each time, and he hopes they continue to be (hence the laughing), there were subtle differences <em>sometimes</em> between different runs of the same demo. As I recall, he even used Undo to go back to the original message text, invoked Writing Tools to make it “more friendly” again, and we could see that a few of the word choices were slightly different. That answered both my explicit question and my implicit one: Writing Tools generates non-deterministic results, and, more importantly, what we were watching really was a live demo.</p>

<p>We didn’t get to try any of the Apple Intelligence features ourselves. There was no Apple Intelligence “hands on”. But we did see a bunch of features demoed, live, by Apple folks. In my above hierarchy of realness, they were all at level 1.</p>

<p>But we didn’t see <em>all</em> aspects of Apple Intelligence demoed. None of the “more personalized Siri” features, the ones that Apple, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/apple_is_delaying_the_more_personalized_siri_apple_intelligence_features">in its own statement announcing their postponement</a>, described as having “more awareness of your personal context, as well as the ability to take action for you within and across your apps”. Those features encompass three main things:</p>

<ul>
<li>“Personal context” — Knowing details and information about you from a “semantic index”, built from the contents of your email, messages, files, contacts, and more. In theory, eventually, all the information on your device that you wish to share with Siri will be in this semantic index. If you can look it up on your device, Siri will be able to look it up on your device.</li>
<li>“Onscreen awareness” — Giving Siri awareness of whatever is displayed on your screen. <a href="https://www.apple.com/apple-intelligence/">Apple’s own example usage</a>: “If a friend texts you their new address, you can say ‘Add this address to their contact card,’ and Siri will take care of it.”</li>
<li><p>“In-app actions” — Giving Siri the ability, through the App Intents framework, to do things in and across apps that <em>you</em> can do, the old fashioned way (yourself) in and across apps. Again, here’s Apple’s own example usage:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You can make a request like “Send the email I drafted to April and
Lilly” and Siri knows which email you’re referencing and which app
it’s in. And Siri can take actions across apps, so after you ask
Siri to enhance a photo for you by saying “Make this photo pop,”
you can ask Siri to drop it in a specific note in the Notes app — without lifting a finger.</p>
</blockquote></li>
</ul>

<p>There were no demonstrations of <em>any</em> of that. Those features were all at level 0 on my hierarchy. That level is called vaporware. They were features Apple <em>said</em> existed, which they <em>claimed</em> would be shipping in the next year, and which they <em>portrayed</em>, to great effect, in the signature “Siri, when is my mom’s flight landing?” segment of the WWDC keynote itself, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/live/RXeOiIDNNek?t=4934">starting around the 1h:22m mark</a>. Apple was either unwilling or unable to demonstrate those features in action back in June, even with Apple product marketing reps performing the demos from a prepared script using prepared devices.</p>

<p>This shouldn’t have just raised a concern in my head. It should have set off blinding red flashing lights and deafening klaxon alarms.</p>

<p>Even the very engineers working on a project never know exactly how long something is going to take to complete. An outsider observing a scripted demo of incomplete software knows far less (than the engineers) just how much more work it needs. But you can make a rough judgment. And that’s where my aforementioned hierarchy of realness comes into play. Even outsiders can judge how close a public beta (stage 3) feels to readiness. A feature or product that Apple will allow the press to play with, hands-on (stage 2) is further along than a feature or product that Apple is only willing to demonstrate themselves (stage 1).</p>

<p>But a feature or product that Apple is unwilling to demonstrate, at all, is unknowable. Is it mostly working, and close to, but not quite, demonstratable? Is it only kinda sorta working — partially functional, but far from being complete? Fully functional but prone to crashing — or in the case of AI, prone to hallucinations and falsehoods? Or is it complete fiction, just an idea at this point?</p>

<p>What Apple showed regarding the upcoming “personalized Siri” at WWDC was <em>not</em> a demo. It was a concept video. Concept videos are bullshit, and a sign of a company in disarray, if not crisis. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2011/11/companies_that_publish_concept_videos">The Apple that commissioned the futuristic “Knowledge Navigator” concept video</a> in 1987 was the Apple that was on a course to near-bankruptcy a decade later. Modern Apple — the post-NeXT-reunification Apple of the last quarter century — does not publish concept videos. They only demonstrate actual working products and features.</p>

<p>Until WWDC last year, that is.</p>

<p>My deeply misguided mental framework for “Apple Intelligence” last year at WWDC was something like this: <em>Some of these features are further along than others, and Apple is showing us those features in action first, and they will surely be the features that ship first over the course of the next year. The other features must be coming to demonstratable status soon.</em> But the mental framework I should have used was more like this: <em>Some of these features are merely table stakes for generative AI in 2024, but others are ambitious, groundbreaking, and, given their access to personal data, potentially dangerous. Apple is only showing us the table-stakes features, and isn’t demonstrating any of the ambitious, groundbreaking, risky features.</em></p>

<p>It gets worse. Come September, Apple held its annual big event at Apple Park to unveil the iPhone 16 lineup. Apple Intelligence features were highlighted in the announcement. Members of the media from around the world were gathered. That was a new opportunity, three months after WWDC, for Apple to demonstrate — or even better, offer hands-on access to the press to try themselves — the new personalized Siri features. They did not. No demos, at all. But they did promote them, once again, in the event keynote.<sup id="fnr2-2025-03-12"><a href="#fn2-2025-03-12">2</a></sup></p>

<p>But yet while Apple still wouldn’t demonstrate these features in person, they did commission and broadcast a TV commercial showing these purported features in action, presenting them as a reason to purchase a new iPhone — <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/08/apple-pulls-bella-ramsey-ad-that-promoted-vaporware-personalized-siri-feature">a commercial they pulled, without comment, from YouTube this week</a>.</p>

<p>Last week’s announcement — “It’s going to take us longer than we thought to deliver on these features and we anticipate rolling them out in the coming year” — was, if you think about it, another opportunity to demonstrate the current state of these features. Rather than simply issue a statement to the media, they could have invited select members of the press to Apple Park, or Apple’s offices in New York, or even just remotely over a WebEx conference call, and demonstrated the current state of these features live, on an actual device. That didn’t happen. If these features exist in any sort of working state at all, no one outside Apple has vouched for their existence, let alone for their quality.</p>

<h2>Duke Nukem Intelligence</h2>

<p>Why did Apple show these personalized Siri features at WWDC last year, and promise their arrival during the first year of Apple Intelligence? Why, for that matter, do they now claim to “anticipate rolling them out in the coming year” if they still currently do not exist in demonstratable form? (If they <em>do</em> exist today in demonstratable form, they should, you know, <em>demonstrate them</em>.)</p>

<p>I’m not trying to be obtuse here. It’s obvious why some executives at Apple might have <em>hoped</em> they could promote features like these at WWDC last year. Generative AI is the biggest thing to happen in the computer industry since previous breakthroughs this century like mobile (starting with the iPhone, followed by Android), social media (Meta), and cloud computing (Microsoft, Google, and Amazon). Nobody knows where it’s going but wherever it’s heading, it’s going to be big, important, and perhaps profitable. Wall Street certainly noticed. And prior to WWDC last year, Apple wasn’t in the game. They needed to pitch their AI story. And a story that involved nothing but table-stakes AI features isn’t nearly as compelling a story as one that involves innovative, breakthrough, ambitious personal features.</p>

<p>But while there’s an obvious appeal to Apple pitching the most compelling, most ambitious AI story possible, the only thing that was essential was telling a story that was true. If the truth was that Apple only had features ready to ship in the coming year that were table stakes compared to the rest of the industry, that’s the story they needed to tell. Put as good a spin on it as possible, but them’s the breaks when you’re late to the game.</p>

<p>The fiasco here is not that Apple is late on AI. It’s also not that they had to announce an embarrassing delay on promised features last week. Those are problems, not fiascos, and problems happen. They’re inevitable. Leaders prove their mettle and create their legacies not by how they deal with successes but by how they deal with — how they acknowledge, understand, adapt, and solve — problems. The fiasco is that Apple pitched a story that wasn’t true, one that <em>some</em> people within the company surely understood wasn’t true, and they set a course based on that. </p>

<p>The Apple of the Jobs exile years — the Sculley / Spindler / Amelio Apple of 1987–1997 — promoted all sorts of amazing concepts that were no more real than the dinosaurs of <em>Jurassic Park</em>, and promised all sorts of hardware and (especially) software that never saw the light of day. Promoting what you <em>hope</em> to be able to someday ship is way easier and more exciting than promoting what you <em>know</em> is actually ready to ship. However close to financial bankruptcy Apple was when Steve Jobs returned as CEO after the NeXT reunification, the company was already completely bankrupt of credibility. Apple today is the most profitable and financially successful company in the history of the world. Everyone notices such success, and the corresponding accumulation of great wealth. Less noticed, but to my mind the more impressive achievement, is that over the last three decades, the company <em>also</em> accumulated an abundant reserve of credibility. When Apple showed a feature, you could bank on that feature being real. When they said something was set to ship in the coming year, it would ship in the coming year. In the worst case, maybe that “year” would have to be stretched to 13 or 14 months. You can stretch the truth and maintain credibility, but you can’t maintain credibility with bullshit. And the “more personalized Siri” features, it turns out, were bullshit.</p>

<p>Keynote by keynote, product by product, feature by feature, year after year after year, Apple went from a company that you couldn’t believe would even remain solvent, to, by far, the most credible company in tech. Apple remains at no risk of financial bankruptcy (and in fact remains the most profitable company in the world). But their credibility is now damaged. Careers will end before Apple might ever return to the level of “if they say it, you can believe it” credibility the company had earned at the start of June 2024.</p>

<p><em>Damaged</em> is arguably too passive. It was <em>squandered</em>. This didn’t happen to Apple. Decision makers within the company did it.</p>

<p><em>Who</em> decided these features should go in the WWDC keynote, with a promise they’d arrive in the coming year, when, at the time, they were in such an unfinished state they could not be demoed to the media even in a controlled environment? Three months later, who decided Apple should double down and advertise these features in a TV commercial, and promote them as a selling point of the iPhone 16 lineup — not just any products, but the very crown jewels of the company and the envy of the entire industry — when those features still remained in such an unfinished or perhaps even downright non-functional state that they <em>still</em> could not be demoed to the press? Not just couldn’t be shipped as beta software. Not just couldn’t be used by members of the press in a hands-on experience, but could not even be shown to work by Apple employees on Apple-controlled devices in an Apple-controlled environment? But yet they advertised them in a commercial for the iPhone 16, when it turns out they won’t ship, in the best case scenario, until months after the iPhone 17 lineup is unveiled?</p>

<p>When that whole campaign of commercials appeared, I — along with many other observers — was distracted by the fact that <em>none</em> of the features in Apple Intelligence had yet shipped. It’s highly unusual, and arguably ill-considered, for Apple to advertise <em>any</em> features that haven’t yet shipped. But one of those commercials was not at all like the others. The other commercials featured Apple Intelligence features that were close to shipping. We know today they were close to shipping because they were either in the iOS 18.1 betas already, in September, or would soon appear in developer betas for iOS 18.2 and 18.3. Right now, today, they’ve all actually shipped and are in the hands of iPhone 16 users. But the “Siri, what’s the name of the guy I had a meeting with a couple of months ago at Cafe Grenel?” commercial was entirely based on a feature Apple still has never even demonstrated.</p>

<p>Who said “<em>Sure, let’s promise this</em>” and then “<em>Sure, let’s advertise it</em>”? And who said “<em>Are you crazy, this isn’t ready, this doesn’t work, we can’t promote this now?</em>” And most important, who made the call which side to listen to? Presumably, that person was Tim Cook.</p>

<p>Even with everything Apple overpromised (if not outright lied about) at the WWDC keynote, the initial takeaway from WWDC from the news media was wrongly focused on their partnership with OpenAI. The conventional wisdom coming out of the keynote was that Apple had just announced something called “Apple Intelligence” but it was powered by ChatGPT, when in fact, the story Apple told was that they — Apple — had built an entire system called Apple Intelligence, entirely powered by Apple’s own AI technology, and that it spanned from on-device execution all the way to a new Private Cloud Compute infrastructure they not only owned but are powering with their own custom-designed server hardware based on Apple Silicon chips. And that on top of all that, as a proverbial cherry on top, Apple <em>also</em> was adding an optional integration layer with ChatGPT.</p>

<p>So, yes, given that the news media gave credit for Apple’s own actual announced achievements to OpenAI, Apple surely would have been given even <em>less</em> credit had they not announced the “more personalized Siri” features. It’s easy to imagine someone in the executive ranks arguing “<em>We need to show something that only Apple can do.</em>” But it turns out they announced something Apple <em>couldn’t</em> do. And now they look so out of their depth, so in over their heads, that not only are they years behind the state-of-the-art in AI, but they don’t even know <em>what</em> they can ship or <em>when</em>. Their headline features from nine months ago not only haven’t shipped but still haven’t even been demonstrated, which I, for one, now presume means they <em>can’t</em> be demonstrated <em>because they don’t work</em>.</p>

<h2>‘So Why the Fuck Doesn’t It Do That?’</h2>

<p>In May 2011, <a href="https://fortune.com/article/inside-apple/">Fortune published an extraordinary look inside Apple by Adam Lashinsky</a>, at what we now know to be the peak, and (alas) end, of the Steve Jobs era. The piece opens thus:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple doesn’t often fail, and when it does, it isn’t a pretty
sight at 1 Infinite Loop. In the summer of 2008, when Apple
launched the first version of its iPhone that worked on
third-generation mobile networks, it also debuted MobileMe, an
e-mail system that was supposed to provide the seamless
synchronization features that corporate users love about their
BlackBerry smartphones. MobileMe was a dud. Users complained about
lost e-mails, and syncing was spotty at best. Though reviewers
gushed over the new iPhone, they panned the MobileMe service.</p>

<p>Steve Jobs doesn’t tolerate duds. Shortly after the launch event,
he summoned the MobileMe team, gathering them in the Town Hall
auditorium in Building 4 of Apple’s campus, the venue the company
uses for intimate product unveilings for journalists. According to
a participant in the meeting, Jobs walked in, clad in his
trademark black mock turtleneck and blue jeans, clasped his hands
together, and asked a simple question:</p>

<p>“Can anyone tell me what MobileMe is supposed to do?” Having
received a satisfactory answer, he continued, “So why the fuck
doesn’t it do that?”</p>

<p>For the next half-hour Jobs berated the group. “You’ve tarnished
Apple’s reputation,” he told them. “You should hate each other for
having let each other down.” The public humiliation particularly
infuriated Jobs. Walt Mossberg, the influential Wall Street
Journal gadget columnist, had panned MobileMe. “Mossberg, our
friend, is no longer writing good things about us,” Jobs said. On
the spot, Jobs named a new executive to run the group.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Tim Cook should have already held a meeting like that to address and rectify this Siri and Apple Intelligence debacle. If such a meeting hasn’t yet occurred or doesn’t happen soon, then, I fear, that’s all she wrote. The ride is over. When mediocrity, excuses, and bullshit take root, they take over. A culture of excellence, accountability, and integrity cannot abide the acceptance of any of those things, and will quickly collapse upon itself with the acceptance of all three.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>

<li id="fn1-2025-03-12">
<p>Image Playground would make a ton of sense not as a consumer-facing app, but as an example project for developers. Long ago, Apple <a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/archive/samplecode/TextEdit/Introduction/Intro.html">used to share the source code for TextEdit</a> as an example project for Mac developers. (TextEdit is actually a low-key great application, though. It’s genuinely useful, reliable, and understandable.) <a href="https://developer.apple.com/sample-code/wwdc/2024/">Apple shares tons of sample code at WWDC each year</a>. Image Playground would be a great sample project. The silly app icon even looks like something from a WWDC sample project. What Image Playground is <em>not</em> is a credible useful generative AI tool. Yet Apple keeps talking about it — and showing it off in new hardware demonstrations — like it’s something they should be proud of and that anyone might credibly use for real-world work or even personal purposes. Image Playground does exemplify just how state-of-the-art the generative AI features are in Apple Intelligence, but not in the way Apple seems to think.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-03-12"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>

<li id="fn2-2025-03-12">
<p>Skip to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/live/uarNiSl_uh4?t=3184">the 53-minute mark of Apple’s September “It’s Glowtime” event</a> introducing the iPhones 16, and it’s Craig Federighi who says the following:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>“Siri will be able to tap into your personal context to help you in ways that are unique to you. Like pulling up the recommendation for the TV show that your brother sent you last month. And Siri will gain onscreen awareness. So when your friend texts you about a new album, you’ll be able to simply say, ‘Play that.’ And then you’ll be able to take hundreds of new actions in your apps, like updating a friend’s contact card with his new address, or adding a set of photos to a specific album. With Siri’s personal context understanding and action capabilities, you’ll be able to simply say, ‘Send Erica the photos from Saturday’s barbecue’, and Siri will dig up the photos and send them right off.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That’s about 40 seconds of keynote time I bet Federighi regrets — and that I suspect <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/03/09/siri-apple-intelligence-ios-18-development-went-wrong/">he was skeptical about</a> including. It’s telling though, that unlike WWDC, Apple didn’t <em>show</em> those features or spend even a full minute talking about at the iPhone 16 event — despite the fact that, ostensibly, those features should have been three months closer to shipping than they were in June. Federighi’s title is SVP of software, and Apple Intelligence and Siri are “software”, but John Giannandrea (SVP of machine learning and
AI strategy) is Federighi’s peer, not subordinate, <a href="https://www.apple.com/leadership/">on the org chart</a> — both report directly to Tim Cook — and is responsible for Siri and Apple Intelligence. Why it was Federighi, not Giannandrea, pitching those features in the iPhone 16 event keynote almost certainly comes down to Federighi’s presentation skills and stage presence, not responsibility for the features themselves. But who’s going on camera to pitch these features and promise their future availability the next time?&nbsp;<a href="#fnr2-2025-03-12"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
</li>

</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Something Is Rotten in the State of Cupertino</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/new_ui_look_ios_would_be_a_huge_deal" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/w5l" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41673</id>
	<published>2025-03-11T22:33:03Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-12T14:23:06Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">You either have taste or you don’t, and most people don’t, at least for judging something new and unfamiliar.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/03/11/a-totally-new-look-for-ios-19-will-likely-have-a-bigger-impact-than-new-siri/">Ben Lovejoy, writing at 9to5Mac</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Our editor-in-chief Chance Miller wryly commented that a radical
new look would serve as a great way to distract from the
ever-slowing progress on the new Siri. But in truth, I think many
more Apple users will be wowed by a new look than would ever care
about Siri.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>If that’s the way it works out — with a new visual look drawing attention from lackluster progress on the AI front — surely the timing will be coincidental, but some accidents are happy accidents, as Bob Ross used to say.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Sure, the new look introduced with iOS 7 was a massively
controversial one, and many thought that then Apple design chief
Jony Ive should never have been allowed anywhere near the software
side of the business. But love it or hate it, you certainly
couldn’t ignore it.</p>

<p>The same will be true of a new 3D look, which might even include
some (much more modern) skeuomorphic elements. Probably as many
will hate it as love it when it’s first introduced, as that seems
to be true of any significant change made by the company, but it
will likely make more of a bang than any improvement to Siri the
company may introduce, then or later.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There should be no question that all of what Lovejoy is saying here is true. If Apple launches an all-new systemwide UI theme for iOS 19, something even half as radical a change as iOS 7’s theme was, it will be the <em>only</em> thing most users notice or opine about. Humans are fundamentally visual creatures and we notice visual changes. And, most humans are resistant to change. A lot of people simply dislike change, even changes for the better. (Honestly, I think that’s what the iOS 18 Photos complaints are about. Complaints about change itself.)</p>

<p>Part of what makes Apple <em>Apple</em> is that the company is (or at least should be) led by people who both have great taste and trust their own instincts. No one’s taste is perfect. Even Steve Jobs pushed through a <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2013/05/08/siracusa-ive">few</a> <a href="https://www.cultofmac.com/apple-history/flower-power-imac-blue-dalmatian">clunkers</a>. But if you have great taste and confidence, you’ll do what your gut says is right.</p>

<p>When a company only pushes out changes that avoid controversy, it leads to paralysis. Then stagnation. Earlier today, <a href="https://social.panic.com/@cabel/114144740571928406">Cabel Sasser wrote</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>One of my strongest early developer memories was being in the “UI
Feedback Forum” at WWDC after they introduced Aqua. Think of a
live Q&amp;A, but developers giving notes to a team of Apple
engineers.</p>

<p>To these veteran Mac coders, the reaction to Aqua was universally
negative. People were actively very angry. It’s a waste! It’s
ugly! It’s confusing! How could you. It went on and on, and I was
surprised because Aqua looked cool and fun to me.</p>

<p>After that WWDC, they never did another Feedback Forum.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s true. What a lot of Mac users wanted was a Mac OS X that looked like Mac OS 9.<sup id="fnr1-2025-03-11"><a href="#fn1-2025-03-11">1</a></sup> The Aqua look and feel was definitely polarizing. And Apple dialed back its most exuberant details with each subsequent Mac OS X update — less transparency, subtler pinstripes (pinstripes!), etc. But iOS 7 was equally polarizing, and its excesses also got dialed back (or perhaps better, said, dialed back up) with each successive iOS release — a little more depth, some subtle hints of texture.</p>

<p>Either Apple is <em>never</em> going to ship an altogether new UI theme, or they’ll ship one and a large number of people will declare it utter garbage and proof that Apple has completely lost its way. Maybe it <em>will</em> be garbage and proof that Apple has lost its way! Or, maybe it will actually prove to be a great new look that starts a decade-long industry-wide trend that all other companies will soon follow — which is what happened with Aqua’s 3D “lickability”, and happened again with iOS 7’s austere flattening. But either way, you won’t be able to judge it by asking for a show of hands from the general population <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/02/fox_new_scorebug_graphic_design">when it’s unveiled</a>. You either have taste or you don’t, and most people don’t, at least when judging something new and unfamiliar.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1-2025-03-11">
<p>Which is actually <a href="https://www.macintoshrepository.org/1449-mac-os-x-server-1-x-rhapsody-">what 1999’s Mac OS X Server 1.0 looked like</a>. It really was the best-looking version of the classic Platinum UI theme Apple ever released.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-03-11"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ A New System-Wide UI Look for iOS — Let Alone MacOS, Too — Would Be a Huge Deal</title></entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://workos.com/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/w5f" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/03/workos_scalable_secure_authent" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.41667</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-03-11T15:07:27Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-15T17:06:36Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Modern authentication should be seamless and secure.  WorkOS makes it easy to integrate features like MFA, SSO, and RBAC.</p>

<p>Whether you’re replacing passwords, stopping fraud, or adding enterprise auth, WorkOS can help you build frictionless auth that scales. </p>

<p>Future-proof your authentication stack with the identity layer trusted by OpenAI, Cursor, Perplexity, and Vercel.  </p>

<p>Upgrade your auth today. </p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘WorkOS: Scalable, Secure Authentication’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/03/workos_scalable_secure_authent">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] WorkOS: Scalable, Secure Authentication</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/apple_is_delaying_the_more_personalized_siri_apple_intelligence_features" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/w54" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41656</id>
	<published>2025-03-07T16:32:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-12T23:28:33Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">This announcement is disappointing, but unsurprising. If it’s Apple’s general policy not to ship a product before it’s ready, that applies tenfold for a product involving LLM access to deeply private on-device information.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Here’s a statement I got this morning from Apple spokeswoman Jacqueline Roy, verbatim:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Siri helps our users find what they need and get things done
quickly, and in just the past six months, we’ve made Siri more
conversational, introduced new features like type to Siri and
product knowledge, and added an integration with ChatGPT. We’ve
also been working on a more personalized Siri, giving it more
awareness of your personal context, as well as the ability to take
action for you within and across your apps. It’s going to take us
longer than we thought to deliver on these features and we
anticipate rolling them out in the coming year.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is a Friday sort of <em>wah-waaah</em> sad-trombone news drop, but it’s good that Apple is getting on top of it, and setting expectations accurately.</p>

<p>Reading between the lines, and based on my PhD-level fluency in Cupertino-ese, what Apple is saying here is that these “more personalized Siri” features are being punted from this year’s OS cycle to next year’s: to iOS 19 and MacOS 16. Apple’s <em>years</em> in this context aren’t calendar years, but Apple’s OS product years. Those years effectively start at WWDC. The problem, from Apple’s perspective, messaging-wise, is that they don’t talk about future products. They haven’t officially acknowledged there is going to be an iOS 19 or MacOS 16. They haven’t even yet announced that there’s going to be a WWDC 2025. But they do want to set expectations accurately, especially for a feature as high profile — from Apple’s own marketing push — as Apple Intelligence. So here we are.</p>

<p>It was already pretty obvious these features weren’t coming in iOS 18.4/MacOS 15.4, because they’re not in the developer betas that are already out. And if these features were coming in iOS 18.5/MacOS 15.5, or even iOS 18.6/MacOS 15.6, Apple wouldn’t have felt the need to issue this “It’s going to take us longer than we thought...” statement today. Delivering the “more personalized Siri” in iOS 18.5 or even 18.6 would have been delivering them on the originally announced schedule — the “coming year” that began with WWDC 2024. That would have been the tail end of that “year”, but within it. But Apple, being limited to the self-imposed opaque verbiage of Cupertino-ese, isn’t going to spell that out. But trust me, you can bank on it: what they’re announcing today is that these features are coming in iOS 19/MacOS 16.</p>

<p>Siri <em>has</em> improved in several useful, but iterative, ways under the Apple Intelligence umbrella in this year’s OS cycle (iOS/iPadOS 18 + MacOS 15 Sequoia), but the big “more personalized Siri” that was shown at WWDC last June is the Siri-related Apple Intelligence stuff that people are, justifiably, most excited about. This is the “<a href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/appintents/integrating-actions-with-siri-and-apple-intelligence">App Intents</a>” stuff — the features requiring Siri to have access to and, effectively, <em>understanding of</em> your personal information, in your apps, stored privately on your devices. These are the most helpful-sounding, most practical, most futuristic features of Apple Intelligence. And they’re the sort of features Apple is almost uniquely positioned to offer, alongside only Google, as the provider of a mobile platform and device ecosystem.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2024/06/introducing-apple-intelligence-for-iphone-ipad-and-mac/">From Apple’s own announcement</a>, after the WWDC keynote:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Siri will be able to deliver intelligence that’s tailored to the
user and their on-device information. For example, a user can say,
“Play that podcast that Jamie recommended,” and Siri will locate
and play the episode, without the user having to remember whether
it was mentioned in a text or an email. Or they could ask, “When
is Mom’s flight landing?” and Siri will find the flight details
and cross-reference them with real-time flight tracking to give an
arrival time.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>“When is Mom’s flight landing?” is easily understood, by we humans, and a really good example of the sort of Siri interaction that would be obviously useful. But you can also pretty easily see how complex it is on Apple’s side. Siri has long been able to do the “Mom” thing. Your spouse, your kids — you’ve long able to tell Siri to call or text those people by nickname like that. But getting your mom’s flight information out of your email (which I think was the premise of this demo in the WWDC keynote — that the flight info was stored in a message in Mail) or from text messages, and then knowing how to check for current flight status information for <em>that</em> flight, is something far beyond the ken of current Siri. Getting the information requires access to your most personal information — your own email and messages. Getting the <em>correct</em> information from your messages requires the common sense of understanding that you’re obviously asking about some sort of <em>current</em> trip your mom is taking, not, say, an email she sent you about a flight back in 2019, or one from 2022, or even one from December last year. The Siri we currently know <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/01/siri_is_super_dumb_and_getting_dumber">lacks that sort of common sense</a>. And then lastly, after getting the correct flight from your email, performing this task requires Siri to have the agency to go look up the current status of that particular flight — and get it right <em>every time</em> it provides an answer.</p>

<p>If Siri answers, “Your mom’s flight is arriving at 4:30 this afternoon, and it’s currently showing an on-time arrival,” you really want that information to be correct if you’ve promised to pick her up at the airport. You’ll be annoyed if you drive to the airport and it turns out she’s not actually landing until 7:30. And you’ll be in <em>real</em> trouble if she’s landing at 1:30 and you show up three hours later, having banked on Siri’s answer being accurate.</p>

<hr />

<p>It’s very unusual, to say the least, for Apple to announce a product delay.<sup id="fnr1-2025-03-07"><a href="#fn1-2025-03-07">1</a></sup> The white iPhone 4 was supposed to debut alongside the black one in June 2010, but, bizarrely, was delayed several times (<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2010/10/anthropomorphized_white_iphone_4">which I had fun with</a> more than <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/apple-writer-john-gruber-that-white-iphone-i-tweeted-about-was-a-toy-2010-11">once</a>) and wound up not shipping <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2011/04/27/jobs-schiller">until the end of April the next year</a>, 10 months late. The original AirPods were announced alongside the iPhones 7 in September 2016, and were supposed to ship in October. They wound up being delayed until December. Apple’s statement in October 2016, regarding the AirPods being delayed, <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2016/10/26/apple-delays-airpod-rollout-dont-expect-them-in-october/">as given to Matthew Panzarino at TechCrunch</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The early response to AirPods has been incredible. We don’t
believe in shipping a product before it’s ready, and we need a
little more time before AirPods are ready for our customers.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is exactly why Apple hews to an almost religious policy of not announcing products before they’re ready. When they <em>do</em> make exceptions — when they lapse, as it were, as cited above (<a href="#fn1-2025-03-07">and below</a>) — they often regret it. You can’t break a promise you never made, and you can’t miss a ship date you never announced. Even with talented teams and realistic managers, there’s often a long span between how long you expect a project to take and how long it actually winds up taking. Engineering schedules often slip even with predictable technologies, and the non-deterministic nature of LLMs makes their future inherently unpredictable.</p>

<p>Most of Apple Intelligence has felt like Apple has pushed it out a year ahead of the company’s usual level of baked-ness. I’ve held all year long that if the entire industry — along with Wall Street — weren’t in the midst of a generative-AI/LLM mania, that “Apple Intelligence” wouldn’t have been announced until this year’s WWDC, not last year’s. Today’s announcement is disappointing, but to me utterly unsurprising. The Siri integration with personal data through App Intents has never felt like something that was going to be ready for real customer usage in this year’s OS cycle. And if it’s Apple’s general policy not to ship a product before it’s ready, that applies tenfold for a product involving LLM access to deeply private on-device information. It’s better to ship late, but ready, than to ship something unfinished or unreliable to hit a promised deadline. And with something like next-generation Siri, I’d say that’s downright essential. Apple can take the bad publicity today’s announcement is engendering; they cannot afford to squander the trust of their users.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1-2025-03-07">
<p>The granddaddy of modern-era Apple product delays, of course, is <a href="https://daringfireball.net/search/airpower">AirPower</a> — the multi-device (iPhones, Apple Watch, AirPods) charging device that Apple pre-announced in September 2017, alongside the iPhone X and iPhone 8. When announced, Apple said AirPower would ship in “2018”. It wound up never shipping, but the plug wasn’t officially pulled (so to speak) <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2019/03/29/airpower-canceled">until 29 March 2019</a>, an absurd 18 months after it was announced.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-03-07"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Apple Is Delaying the ‘More Personalized Siri’ Apple Intelligence Features</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/abc_shuts_down_fivethirtyeight" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/w50" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41652</id>
	<published>2025-03-06T16:12:37Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-07T00:06:25Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">From the perspective of a company the size of Disney, it would cost veritable pennies to keep FiveThirtyEight’s website around forever. What a disgrace.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Oliver Darcy, reporting at Status (paywalled, alas), <a href="https://www.status.news/p/abc-news-layoffs">on the sudden demise of FiveThirtyEight</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>On Wednesday morning, shortly after sending an all-staff memo
announcing layoffs at ABC News, network president Almin
Karamehmedovic joined a virtual meeting with the FiveThirtyEight
team. The 15 staffers at the political analysis site owned by ABC
News had learned the previous evening — via a Wall Street Journal
report — that they were being let go. Now, they were hearing it
from Karamehmedovic himself.</p>

<p>But Karamehmedovic, like other managers carrying out mass layoffs
at ABC News that day, had little to say about it. I’m told he
appeared to be reading from a script as he delivered the
devastating news. He offered no explanation for why the
Disney-owned network had decided to shutter FiveThirtyEight, which
it acquired in 2018 along with data whiz and then-editor Nate
Silver. He took no questions. He simply thanked the employees for
their work, told them a human resources staffer would follow up,
and ended the meeting. The entire affair, I’m told, lasted about
15 minutes. Soon after, employees had their access to ABC News’
systems shut off and the FiveThirtyEight website was <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/538">pulled
offline</a>. Just like that, it was over.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Business is business, and layoffs and closures are never anything but traumatic. But there’s a right way to do things and a wrong way. And one of the wrong ways is having the staff find out they’re all fired by <a href="https://www.wsj.com/business/media/disney-to-cut-nearly-6-staff-across-abc-news-disney-entertainment-networks-8af04b40">reading it from The Wall Street Journal</a>. This guy Karamehmedovic sounds like a real Grade-A dickhead.</p>

<p>And what is the deal with these companies that just unceremoniously pull the plug on websites when they close them? Why not keep the FiveThirtyEight site up and running — at least for a while, if not in perpetuity? It costs practically nothing to run a server for a static/archived website. I don’t get it. It betrays a profound level of disrespect for the work that the site hosted. It’s ABC’s business if they want to close FiveThirtyEight as an ongoing concern, but the years of work deserves to remain online, both out of respect for the people who made it <em>and</em> for the audience that might still want to refer to it. Disney didn’t burn the movies from now-closed subsidiary studios like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Touchstone_Pictures">Touchstone Pictures</a>.</p>

<p>There’s a vast gulf between the old world of print and the new world of online publishing. The difference is profound, but largely overlooked, because it’s human nature to just adapt to the nature of different forms of media and quickly accept current media forms as “normal”. With print, issues were largely ephemeral to the audience. You’d get a newspaper every day, and magazines every week or month, and you’d throw them out after you’d finished reading them. If you wanted to look back at what the paper had published about something a year, a month, or even just a few days ago, you were out of luck, in terms of being able to just look it up on the spot. Librarians did the yeoman’s work of archiving newspapers and magazines to microfilm, so nothing was truly gone or forgotten, but it was an enormous hassle to access microfilm archives. You pretty much had to know the dates of the issues you wanted to see, and you had to do the “searching” with your eyeballs, page by page. The ability of anyone, today, to just instantly access week-, month-, year-, and even decades-old stories is a breathtaking advantage of web publications. And for the last 15 years or so, we’ve had the ability to do this from little machines we all carry in our pockets everywhere we go. It’s truly remarkable.</p>

<p>But the standard behavior when closing a web publication is to just pull the plug. When the whole company goes under, that’s one thing. But when there’s a parent company, especially a thriving one, there’s no justification for pulling the plug other than spiteful disregard for the work. From the perspective of a company the size of Disney, it would cost veritable pennies to keep FiveThirtyEight’s website around forever. What a disgrace.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ ABC Shuts Down FiveThirtyEight, and Pulls the Plug on Its Website</title></entry></feed><!-- THE END -->
