<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>Daring Fireball</title>
<subtitle>By John Gruber</subtitle>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/" />
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main" />
<id>https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main</id>


<updated>2025-05-08T16:06:13Z</updated><rights>Copyright © 2025, John Gruber</rights><entry>
	<title>The Trump Administration Signal Scandal, Somehow, Gets Worse</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://micahflee.com/despite-misleading-marketing-israeli-company-telemessage-used-by-trump-officials-can-access-plaintext-chat-logs/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wb1" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/08/trump-admin-tm-sgnl" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41869</id>
	<published>2025-05-08T16:06:13Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-08T16:06:13Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Micah Lee, in a spectacularly detailed post:</p>

<blockquote>
  <ul>
<li><p>On Thursday, 404 Media <a href="https://www.404media.co/mike-waltz-accidentally-reveals-obscure-app-the-government-is-using-to-archive-signal-messages/">reported</a> that in the Reuters
<a href="https://www.reutersconnect.com/item/us-national-security-advisor-mike-waltz-attends-a-cabinet-meeting-held-by-president-trump-at-the-white-house-in-washington/dGFnOnJldXRlcnMuY29tLDIwMjU6bmV3c21sX1JDMkg4RUFEOEtGRw%3D%3D">photo</a> showing former National Security Advisor and <a href="https://zeteo.com/p/signal-chat-war-crimes-revealed-yemen-trump-admin">war
criminal</a> Mike Waltz checking his Signal messages under the
table, he was actually using an obscure modified Signal app
called TM SGNL, and not the real and actually secure Signal app.</p></li>
<li><p>On Friday, I wrote <a href="https://micahflee.com/tm-sgnl-the-obscure-unofficial-signal-app-mike-waltz-uses-to-text-with-trump-officials/">an analysis</a> of everything I could find
out about TM SGNL using OSINT, including the fact that it’s
nearly impossible to install without a device enrolled in an MDM
service that’s tied to an Apple Business Manager or a Google
Enterprise account.</p></li>
<li><p>On Saturday, after <a href="https://todon.eu/@ljrk/114444796069542288">discovering</a> that TeleMessage
<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20250503004419/https://www.telemessage.com/developer/api-libraries/">published</a> the source code for the TM SGNL apps for
Android and iPhone themselves, I <a href="https://micahflee.com/heres-the-source-code-for-the-unofficial-signal-app-used-by-trump-officials/">re-published them</a> on
GitHub with the goal of making them easier to research. (It
looks like the iOS source code is actually just unmodified
Signal, so maybe they actually only published their Android
code.)</p></li>
<li><p>On Saturday night, an anonymous source told me they hacked
TeleMessage.</p></li>
<li><p>On Sunday, I, along with Joseph Cox, <a href="https://www.404media.co/the-signal-clone-the-trump-admin-uses-was-hacked/">published an article</a>
about the hack to 404 Media (and to <a href="https://micahflee.com/the-signal-clone-the-trump-admin-uses-was-hacked/">my blog</a>).</p></li>
<li><p>On Monday, NBC News <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/tech/security/telemessage-suspends-services-hackers-say-breached-app-rcna204925">reported</a> that TeleMessage suspended
its service after a <em>second hacker</em> breached TeleMessage and
“downloaded a large cache of files.”</p></li>
<li><p>Today, Senator Ron Wyden <a href="https://www.wyden.senate.gov/imo/media/doc/doj_letter_telemessage.pdf">published</a> a letter, which cites
the 404 Media article and my analysis of TM SGNL, to Attorney
General Pam Bondi, requesting that the Justice Department
investigate the “serious threat to U.S. national security posed
by TeleMessage, a federal contractor that sold dangerously
insecure communications software to the White House and other
federal agencies.”</p></li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>National security leaders using this app — which effectively just <em>removes</em> all of Signal’s actual security features by backing up all messages as plain text — is stupid it’s surprising, even from these idiots Trump has surrounded himself with. I mean think about how stupid it is that Mike Waltz was using this app while in front of press photographers at a Cabinet meeting.</p>

<p>Lee goes deep, including an analysis of TM SGNL’s open source Android source code, to show that it’s designed to transmit backups of messages in plain text to publicly-facing servers. And it turns out those servers had easily-hackable flaws.</p>

<p><strong>See also:</strong> Wired: “<a href="https://www.wired.com/story/tm-signal-telemessage-plaintext-message-archive/">The Company Behind the Signal Clone Mike Waltz Used Has Direct Access to User Chats</a>”.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Trump Administration Signal Scandal, Somehow, Gets Worse’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/08/trump-admin-tm-sgnl">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Eddy Cue, on the Stand in U.S. v. Google Trial, Says Apple Is Eying a Move to AI in Safari</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2025-05-07/apple-working-to-move-to-ai-search-in-browser-amid-google-fallout" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wb0" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/07/eddy-cue-safari-ai" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41868</id>
	<published>2025-05-08T00:57:53Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-08T01:19:04Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Bloomberg:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple Inc. is “actively looking at” revamping the Safari web
browser on its devices to focus on AI-powered search engines, a
seismic shift for the industry hastened by the potential end of a
longtime partnership with Google.</p>

<p>Eddy Cue, Apple’s senior vice president of services, made the
disclosure Wednesday during his testimony in the US Justice
Department’s lawsuit against Alphabet Inc. The heart of the
dispute is the two companies’ estimated $20 billion-a-year deal
that makes Google the default offering for queries in Apple’s
browser. The case could force the tech giants to unwind the
pact, upending how the iPhone and other devices have long
operated. [...]</p>

<p>Cue said he believes that AI search providers, including OpenAI,
Perplexity AI Inc. and Anthropic PBC, will eventually replace
standard search engines like Alphabet’s Google. He said he
believes Apple will bring those options to Safari in the future.
“We will add them to the list — they probably won’t be the
default,” he said, indicating that they still need to improve. Cue
specifically said the company has had some discussions with
Perplexity.</p>

<p>“Prior to AI, my feeling around this was, none of the others were
valid choices,” Cue said. “I think today there is much greater
potential because there are new entrants attacking the problem in
a different way.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>If they can pay, Apple will listen. And I don’t think it’s bullshit, at all, that traditional web search is actually going into decline now because of AI. Honestly at this point it would be weird if it weren’t.</p>

<p>But. Let’s say Apple would prefer for the current arrangement between Apple and Google to continue as is. But it’s under threat as a remedy in Google’s monopoly case. Is this not the perfect testimony? Traditional web search is in decline, usage-wise — and Apple is considering deals with multiple upstarts. I think it’s all true. But I also think it helps make the case that the current deal between Apple and Google should not be disallowed.</p>

<p>I don’t think there’s any bullshit here. I think we’re at a highly competitive moment between browsers and old-school search and new-school AI. And I think Eddy Cue is right in the middle of it.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Eddy Cue, on the Stand in U.S. v. Google Trial, Says Apple Is Eying a Move to AI in Safari’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/07/eddy-cue-safari-ai">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Aftermath</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://aftermath.site/about-us-contact-us-aftermath" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/waz" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/07/aftermath" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41867</id>
	<published>2025-05-07T17:20:23Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-07T17:22:54Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Aftermath:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Welcome to Aftermath, a worker-owned, reader-supported news site
covering video games, the internet, and the cultures that
surround them.</p>

<p>You might remember most of us from Kotaku, where we broke news,
covered events, and brought you hard-hitting investigations. You
might also have seen us at Motherboard by Vice, The Verge and The
Washington Post’s games vertical Launcher. We got back together to
start this site not just so we could all blog together again, but
to try something new for ourselves and for games journalism.</p>

<p>These days it’s tough for journalism, especially about games. The
past few years have seen mass layoffs and site closures, with
remaining writers being asked to do more and more with less and
less. The ad-supported model is crumbling, social media is a mess,
and the businessmen and private equity firms buying up news
outlets don’t care about workers, readers, and quality writing,
they only care about profits. The five of us saw our sites closed,
ourselves and our colleagues laid off, and our workplaces turned
hostile in management’s pursuit of growth at all costs. [...]</p>

<p>As workers and owners, we’re beholden to no one but ourselves, and
to you, our readers. When you <a href="https://aftermath.site/products">subscribe</a>, you’ll get access to
writing that pursues the truth and casts a critical eye on gaming
and the internet, that doesn’t need to placate capital or kowtow
to PR. You’ll be supporting the kind of journalism our past
experience has shown us you like best: honest and irreverent,
written for people rather than SEO. You’ll get a site that
prioritizes the reader experience, with no invasive popups or ads
that burn up your device.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>They’re a smart crew, so of course, they’re <em>not</em> launching this on Substack. (They’re using a platform called <a href="https://joinlede.com/">Lede</a>, upon which the excellent <a href="https://defector.com/">Defector</a> has built itself.) How can you not love a site with this ode to a classic bit of kit: “<a href="https://aftermath.site/bob-barker-mic-gameshow-sony-ecm-51-match-game">Bring Back Those Long-Ass Game Show Mics</a>”. An elegant weapon, from a more civilized age.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Aftermath’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/07/aftermath">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Polygon Gutted by Large-Scale Layoffs After Sale to Sweatshop Aggregator Valnet</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/05/gaming-news-site-polygon-gutted-by-massive-layoffs-amid-sale-to-valnet/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/way" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/07/polygon-sold-gutted-by-layoffs" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41866</id>
	<published>2025-05-07T16:38:03Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-07T16:38:04Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Kyle Orland, reporting for Ars Technica last week:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Vox Media has sold video game specialist website Polygon to
<a href="https://www.valnetinc.com/our-brands">Internet brand aggregator Valnet</a>, the publisher of
content-churning sites including Game Rant, OpenCritic, Android
Police, and Comic Book Resources. The move comes alongside
significant layoffs for veteran journalists at the 13-year-old
outlet, including <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/plante.bsky.social/post/3lo4mn4noqc26">co-founder and editor-in-chief Chris
Plante</a> and <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/mmcwhertor.bsky.social/post/3lo4lsc3pqk2c">Senior Writer Michael McWhertor</a>. [...]</p>

<p>Polygon was <a href="https://arstechnica.com/civis/threads/polygon-com-its-a-website.1185405/">founded in 2012</a> when Vox Media <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/briansolomon/2012/10/24/the-inside-story-of-polygon-the-verges-new-gaming-sister-site/">spent
significant money</a> to poach top journalists from popular
gaming blogs like Kotaku, Joystiq, and The Escapist. After
initially publishing as the Gaming section of Vox.com for a few
months, the Polygon domain <a href="https://www.polygon.com/2012/10/24/3547938/welcome-to-polygon">launched</a> alongside <a href="https://botherer.org/2012/08/23/polygon-and-the-documentary-that-cured-cancer/">a series
of flashy videos</a> hyping up the staff’s lofty goals for
video game journalism. In the years since, Polygon has become a
respected source for news and views on the gaming and
entertainment industries — one that Ars Technica has cited
frequently during my tenure as senior gaming editor. [...]</p>

<p>According to publications like <a href="https://www.thewrap.com/valnet-labor-lawsuit-hassan-youssef-digital-media-sweat-shop/">The Wrap</a> and
<a href="https://aftermath.site/freelance-video-game-journalism-rates">Aftermath</a>, numerous Valnet writers have claimed that they
receive low pay for long articles, but Valnet insists that working
conditions are good. It even sued The Wrap in federal court,
saying that Valnet “relies on its reputation as a supporter of
high-quality journalism and of talented writers and editors to
staff its ever-growing business and need for engaging and
well-written content.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Just brutal. I’m not huge into games, but Polygon has been one of my go-to sources for game-related news for years. If I wanted to catch up on something like, say, Nintendo’s Switch 2 announcements, I knew I could go to Polygon and they’d have the coverage nailed. Polygon was everything you could want: good writing, good design, no hype, trustworthy coverage and analysis.</p>

<p>There’s very little good news in media these days. The only talented people I see launching new things are doing it on Substack, and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2024/11/regarding_and_well_against_substack">I think that’s going to end poorly</a> for all of them.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Polygon Gutted by Large-Scale Layoffs After Sale to Sweatshop Aggregator Valnet’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/07/polygon-sold-gutted-by-layoffs">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Amazon, Finally, Now Has a ‘Get Book’ Button in Its iOS Kindle App</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/news/661719/amazon-app-ios-apple-iphone-ipad-kindle-buy-books" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wax" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/06/amazon-kindle-get-book" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41865</id>
	<published>2025-05-07T01:23:56Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-07T02:19:50Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Andrew Liszewski, The Verge:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Contrary to prior limitations, there is now a prominent orange
“Get book” button on Kindle app’s book listings. [...]</p>

<p>Before today’s updates, buying books wasn’t a feature you’d find
in the Kindle mobile app following app store rule changes Apple
implemented in 2011 that required developers to remove links or
buttons leading to alternate ways to make purchases. You could
search for books that offered samples for download, add them to a
shopping list, and read titles you already own, but you couldn’t
actually buy titles through the Kindle or Amazon app, or even see
their prices.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’d love to just crack a joke here about Amazon, maybe, possibly, finally getting a chance to gain a bit of market share in the e-book market. I’d love to just crack that joke and move on.</p>

<p>But really, this whole situation with e-books has been <em>the</em> best argument against Apple’s App Store policies for at least the last 15 years. Physical printed books are typically sold under a wholesale model. The publishers sells the book to a bookseller for a wholesale price (say, perhaps, half the suggested retail price) and the bookseller is then free to charge whatever actual retail price they want to customers. But e-books are sold under <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2012/mar/12/amazon-ebooks-business-model">the agency model</a>: the <em>publisher</em> sets the retail price, and the bookseller keeps 30 percent. But Apple’s App Store policies therefore make it impossible for a third-party bookseller to sell e-books and make even a penny of profit. Let’s say there’s an e-book that the publisher decides will sell to customers for $10. When Amazon sells the Kindle edition of that book, the publisher gets $7, and Amazon keeps $3. But if the Kindle iOS app allowed purchases of books through IAP, Apple would take its 30 percent first. Apple would get $3, Amazon would still owe the publisher $7, and there’d be nothing left over — not a cent — for Amazon itself. Effectively they’d lose a bit of money on each sale, and it would be impossible to make even a penny of profit.</p>

<p>You can’t even fix this by raising prices. Double the retail price to $20 and then Apple would take $6, and the publisher would be owed $14. Still not a cent left for Amazon. The App Store model is just fundamentally incompatible with the agency model.</p>

<p>What Apple should have done, 15 years ago, is look at this situation and decide “Well, we have to allow something else. Kindle users should be able to buy books on iOS devices from the Kindle app.” And the solution is incredibly obvious: <em>let apps send users out of the app to the web to make purchases, without Apple taking a cent</em>. That’s what’s happening now, because of Judge Yvonne Gonzales Rogers’s injunction, but it should have been something Apple permitted 15 years ago because it’s so obviously fair and just. I’ve argued consistently that it’s fine for Apple to insist that in-app purchases for digital content must use Apple’s payment system. But I’ve also argued consistently that Apple should allow <em>from-app</em> purchases to freely go to the web. Tap a button or link, leave the app and go to the web, and make the purchases there. Then go back to the app and the app can sync up what you just purchased. Done. Simple.</p>

<p>Apple’s obstinance on this has created nothing but friction, confusion, and hassle for users for 15 years. It makes no sense for anyone. Until last week, not only were third-party app forbidden from including buttons/links to send users to the web to buy book, they were forbidden from even informing users that they needed to go to the web to buy books. Apple’s rules included a rule that <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2020/07/parsing_cooks_opening_statement">forbade apps from explaining the rules to the users</a>.</p>

<p>I can see, at some level, where executives at Apple are like, “<em>Fuck Amazon. There’s no way for us to even make an Apple Books app for Kindles, let alone sell our own e-books on their devices, so they can go fuck themselves. Why should we let them sell e-books on our devices?</em>” That’s all true. There are no third-party apps on Kindles. There <em>are</em> third-party apps on iPhones and iPads. But at some point Apple should have just considered their own users. If their users are using the Kindle app looking to buy Kindle e-books on iOS devices, Apple should have just let it happen on the web — and used that as motivation to make Apple Books better so that maybe more users would prefer it to the Kindle ecosystem. What’s the word? Oh yeah ... <em>competed</em>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Amazon, Finally, Now Has a ‘Get Book’ Button in Its iOS Kindle App’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/06/amazon-kindle-get-book">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Florida Republican Congresswoman Kat Cammack Introduces ‘App Store Freedom Act’ to Mandate Third-Party App Stores on iOS and Android</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/news/662180/app-store-freedom-act-apple-third-party-app-stores" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/waw" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/06/cammack-app-store-freedom-act" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41864</id>
	<published>2025-05-06T23:58:42Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-06T23:59:33Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Emma Roth, reporting for The Verge:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Representative Kat Cammack (R-FL) introduced a bill Tuesday that
would require “large app store operators” like Apple to let users
install third-party app stores and set them as their default. The
bill, called <a href="https://cammack.house.gov/sites/evo-subsites/cammack.house.gov/files/evo-media-document/app-store-freedom-119.pdf">the App Store Freedom Act</a>, aims to “promote
competition and protect consumers and developers in the mobile
app marketplace,” according to a <a href="https://cammack.house.gov/media/press-releases/rep-cammack-introduces-app-store-freedom-act-promote-competition-protect">press release on
Tuesday</a>. [...]</p>

<p>It would also require Apple and Google to offer developers “equal
access to interfaces, features, and development tools without cost
or discrimination,” as well as allow users to remove or hide
pre-installed apps. Violations of the bill would result in
penalties from the Federal Trade Commission, along with an
additional civil penalty of up to $1 million for each violation.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is a stunt from the Epic/Spotify-backed <a href="https://appfairness.org/">Coalition for App Fairness</a> that we’ll probably never hear about again.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Florida Republican Congresswoman Kat Cammack Introduces ‘App Store Freedom Act’ to Mandate Third-Party App Stores on iOS and Android’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/06/cammack-app-store-freedom-act">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Tim Sweeney Talks to Peter Kafka, Still Thinks Fortnite Is Coming Back to iOS This Week</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.businessinsider.com/tim-sweeeney-epic-games-apple-app-store-interview-peter-kafka-2025-05" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wav" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/06/sweeney-kafka-fortnite" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41863</id>
	<published>2025-05-06T17:10:14Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-06T17:11:12Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>About 16 minutes <a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/channels-with-peter-kafka/id1080467174">into the podcast</a> (the whole thing is a great succinct interview):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Kafka:</strong> You said Fortnite is going to come back to iOS. You
guys were kicked off the platform in 2020 for violating Apple’s
rules. There’s nothing in the judge’s ruling that says Apple has
to reinstate Fortnite on iOS. Have you talked to Apple? How do you
imagine Fortnite will come back to iOS?</p>

<p><strong>Sweeney:</strong> Epic has a valid [Apple] developer account in good
standing. Our subsidiary Epic Games Sweden opened up an account in
order to distribute Fortnite in the European Union. Our dealings
with Apple on that account have been managed by their developer
relations team, who have been cordial.</p>

<p><strong>Kafka:</strong> Do you feel confident that I will be able to play
Fortnite on my iPhone later this week?</p>

<p><strong>Sweeney:</strong> I believe so. I would be very surprised — well, I
wouldn’t be terribly surprised if we had a bug that took a day or
two more to fix — but I would be very surprised if Apple decided
to brave the geopolitical storm of blocking a major app from iOS.</p>

<p>We’ve told Apple what we’re doing.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>But Apple has, for the last five years, already blocked a major game — Fortnite — from iOS. If Apple were going to allow Fortnite back into the App Store they could have done so at any point in the last four years. And there’s nothing, not a word, in Judge Yvonne Gonzalez Rogers’s decision last week that says Apple needs to reinstate Epic Games. I think Apple just stays the course and Fortnite remains <em>persona non grata</em> as far as the App Store is concerned.</p>

<p>But I could be wrong. Sweeney tweeted over the weekend “Not Monday or Tuesday. Beyond that, we’re working as hard as possible and aren’t certain what day it will be ready.”</p>

<p>Me, I’m not holding my breath.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Tim Sweeney Talks to Peter Kafka, Still Thinks Fortnite Is Coming Back to iOS This Week’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/06/sweeney-kafka-fortnite">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://workos.com/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wau" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/05/workos_scalable_secure_authent_3" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.41862</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-05-06T17:00:20Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-06T17:00:20Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Modern authentication should be seamless and secure.  WorkOS makes it easy to integrate features like MFA, SSO, and RBAC.</p>

<p>Whether you’re replacing passwords, stopping fraud, or adding enterprise auth, WorkOS can help you build frictionless auth that scales. </p>

<p>Future-proof your authentication stack with the identity layer trusted by OpenAI, Cursor, Perplexity, and Vercel.  </p>

<p>Upgrade your auth today. </p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘WorkOS: Scalable, Secure Authentication’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/05/workos_scalable_secure_authent_3">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] WorkOS: Scalable, Secure Authentication</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Listen Later</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.listenlater.net/?referrer=df" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wat" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/05/listen-later" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41861</id>
	<published>2025-05-05T13:05:38Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-05T13:05:38Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to Listen Later for sponsoring last week at DF. Listen Later is a super simple, super useful service that turns articles into podcast episodes. When you sign up, you get a custom email address to send articles to; every article you forward to your Listen Later address is transformed into <em>very</em> human-like narration, and gets delivered to your private podcast feed. You can subscribe to your private Listen Later podcast feed in any podcast app.</p>

<p>In addition to the email gateway, <a href="https://www.listenlater.net/tips">there’s a Shortcut</a> for sending articles from Safari (on Mac or iOS), a web extension for Chrome, and a simple web interface for submitting new articles. It’s very simple and the narrated versions sound great.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.listenlater.net/?referrer=df">Sign up for free and start listening today</a>. New users get $2 in credits to try it out — no commitment. And if you like it, you simply prepay for credits as you go. There’s no subscription — you simply pay for what you use. I wish more services had a pay-as-you-go model like Listen Later’s.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Listen Later’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/05/listen-later">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Koji Kobura Remakes the GoldenEye N64 ‘Pause Music’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FB-C-eSa9N8" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/waq" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/04/goldeneye-n64-pause-music" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41858</id>
	<published>2025-05-04T16:20:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-04T16:21:04Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Just shoot this straight into my veins. So good.</p>

<p>(<a href="https://mastodon.social/@thatsthequy/114422596374029344">Via Saul Sutherland</a>.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Koji Kobura Remakes the GoldenEye N64 ‘Pause Music’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/04/goldeneye-n64-pause-music">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Trump Has No Idea What the Declaration of Independence Means</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=K3l2X-T8BCU" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/was" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/04/trump-declaration" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41860</id>
	<published>2025-05-04T16:18:44Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-04T16:18:44Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Trump, showing off to ABC News’s Terry Moran the historical copy of the Declaration of Independence now hanging in the Oval Office:</p>

<p>Trump: Of course, you have the Declaration of Independence.</p>

<p>Moran: What does it mean to you?</p>

<p>Trump: Well, it means exactly what it says. It’s a declaration. It’s a declaration of unity and love and respect. And it means a lot. And it’s something very special to our country.</p>

<p>Watch the clip. A transcript doesn’t do justice to just how clear it is he has no idea what it means. I <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/11/china-calls-trump-a-joke">keep</a> <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/04/trump-doesnt-know-if-he-needs-to-uphold-the-constitution">mentioning</a> that Democrats should hammer, every day, the argument that Trump is way too old and now suffering from dementia. It’s just good politics. But I think it’s actually true, too. Mark my words, by the time he gets toward the end of this second term they’re going to have to somehow try to keep him away from microphones. You can’t get out of the fourth grade without being able to describe what the Declaration of Independence means.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Trump Has No Idea What the Declaration of Independence Means’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/04/trump-declaration">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Trump, Asked if He Has to ‘Uphold the Constitution’, Says, ‘I Don’t Know’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/trump-administration/trump-asked-uphold-constitution-says-dont-know-rcna204580" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/war" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/04/trump-doesnt-know-if-he-needs-to-uphold-the-constitution" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41859</id>
	<published>2025-05-04T15:36:08Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-04T16:08:02Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>NBC News:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>When Welker tried to point out what the Fifth Amendment said,
Trump suggested that such a process would slow him down too much.</p>

<p>“I don’t know. It seems — it might say that, but if you’re
talking about that, then we’d have to have a million or 2 million
or 3 million trials,” he said. “We have thousands of people that
are — some murderers and some drug dealers and some of the worst
people on Earth.”</p>

<p>“I was elected to get them the hell out of here, and the courts
are holding me from doing it,” he added.</p>

<p>“But even given those numbers that you’re talking about, don’t you
need to uphold the Constitution of the United States as
president?” Welker asked.</p>

<p>“I don’t know,” Trump replied. “I have to respond by saying,
again, I have brilliant lawyers that work for me, and they are
going to obviously follow what the Supreme Court said.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The oath of office, which Trump has now taken twice, is “I do solemnly swear that I will faithfully execute the Office of President of the United States, and will to the best of my ability, preserve, protect and defend the Constitution of the United States.”</p>

<p>I’ll repeat <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/11/china-calls-trump-a-joke">what I wrote a few weeks ago</a> when the Chinese government correctly mocked Trump’s tariffs as “a joke in the history of world economics”: Democrats and all other Trump opponents should repeatedly call into question Trump’s mental fitness for office. Don’t (just) argue that he’s trying to subvert the Constitution as a WWE-style authoritarian, but argue (also) that he clearly doesn’t even remember the oath of office. He’s in early dementia. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fred_Trump">Trump’s father was suffering from severe dementia</a> when he was Trump’s age. Throw Biden under the bus: remind people that <a href="https://apple.news/ANs1GK_4ISEikICuDBenaSA">we just saw</a> what happens when a mentally enfeebled 80-year-old<sup>*</sup> serves as President, and that under Trump it’s far worse. Biden was sleepy but steady; Trump is agitated and erratic. Only some dementia sufferers act lost and confused — others act out in anger and belligerence. Trump is in the latter group. He doesn’t remember the oath of office.</p>

<p><small>* Keep calling him “80”; make his sycophants correct you that he’s “only” turning 79 in June.</small></p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Trump, Asked if He Has to ‘Uphold the Constitution’, Says, ‘I Don’t Know’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/04/trump-doesnt-know-if-he-needs-to-uphold-the-constitution">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple Updates U.S. App Review Guidelines Following Injunction</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/05/01/apple-updates-u-s-app-review-guidelines-epic/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wap" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/02/updated-app-review-guidelines-us" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41857</id>
	<published>2025-05-02T13:49:28Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-04T21:14:52Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Apple, in an email to developers yesterday (as reported by MacRumors):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>3.1.1: Apps on the United States storefront are not prohibited
       from including buttons, external links, or other calls to
       action when allowing users to browse NFT collections owned
       by others.</p>

<p>3.1.1(a): On the United States storefront, there is no prohibition
          on an app including buttons, external links, or other
          calls to action, and no entitlement is required to do
          so.</p>

<p>3.1.3: The prohibition on encouraging users to use a purchasing
       method other than in-app purchase does not apply on the
       United States storefront.</p>

<p>3.1.3(a): The External Link Account entitlement is not required
          for apps on the United States storefront to include
          buttons, external links, or other calls to action.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This does not mean apps can now use alternative payment processing in-app. It doesn’t even mean apps are no longer required to offer Apple’s IAP in-app for purchases and subscriptions. All it means is that apps (in the US for now, but Apple really ought to make this worldwide, but I suspect Tim Cook wants to fight this on appeal in federal court) are free to inform users about offers available on the web, and to link to those offers on the web. Those links must open outside the app, in the user’s default web browser.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>In-app: must use IAP. No alternative payments in-app. No webviews in-app for purchases.</p></li>
<li><p>Link to web, in default web browser, for anything else. <s>But the same offerings — but not at the same prices — must be available in-app too.</s></p></li>
</ul>

<p>In other words, plainly and obviously, in-app purchases must compete with purchase offerings on the web. Which is exactly how the policy should have been for at least the last 10 years. It’s been incredibly frustrating and baffling that Tim Cook has refused to see that this is the obvious and correct path for everyone involved, including Apple itself.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Updates U.S. App Review Guidelines Following Injunction’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/02/updated-app-review-guidelines-us">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Jason Snell on Apple’s Q2 FY 2025 and Frustrating Analyst Call</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2025/05/beware-the-tariffs-inside-apples-latest-financial-results/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wao" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/02/snell-aaple-q2-2025" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41856</id>
	<published>2025-05-02T13:27:01Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-02T13:38:42Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jason Snell, with some excellent analysis (in addition to his usual <a href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2025/05/apple-q2-2025-results-and-charts-95-4b-revenue/">visualizations of Apple’s numbers</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Another way Apple can reduce the impact of tariffs is by changing
which global factories it uses to build products destined for the
U.S. market. “For the June quarter, we do expect the majority of
iPhones sold in the U.S. will have India as their country of
origin,” Cook said, “and Vietnam to be the country of origin for
almost all iPad, Mac, Apple Watch, and AirPods products also sold
in the U.S.” He said that if you’re outside of the U.S., you’re
most likely to be buying products made in China.</p>

<p>Cook also commented briefly on Apple’s philosophy in dealing with
the issues of trade wars between various countries: “Obviously,
we’re very engaged on the tariff discussions,” he said. “We
believe in engagement and will continue to engage.” <a href="https://www.warren.senate.gov/newsroom/press-releases/icymi-warren-presses-apple-ceo-tim-cook-on-tariff-special-favors">Elizabeth
Warren take note</a>, I guess.</p>

<p>Apple also put a number on how much it will be affected by tariffs
during its next fiscal quarter: $900 million. Yes, that’s nearly a
billion dollars, but when you consider that Apple just generated
$95.4 billion in revenue and that it’s expecting to grow from the
$85.8 billion it generated during last year’s third quarter, a
$0.9 billion step back doesn’t seem like a massive amount. The
company also said it would probably lose a couple of points of
gross margin as part of the deal.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And, regarding the analyst call (of which Snell also posted <a href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2025/05/this-is-tim-transcript-of-apples-q2-2025-financial-call/">his usual very helpful transcript</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Credit to that brave analyst, Richard Kramer, who didn’t bother
asking a ninth question about tariffs, but instead asked Cook
head-on about the fact that Apple had failed to live up to its
promise of shipping a more personalized Siri as a part of Apple
Intelligence.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Cook’s answer was a canned response emphasizing the features Apple <em>did</em> ship, and  “We need more time to complete our work on these features so they meet our high-quality bar. We are making progress, and we look forward to getting these features into customers’ hands.” Which is true, but not exactly informative.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Kramer, who is going to get an analyst gold star for this, also
asked Cook about the various court cases that might really impact
Apple’s business. Regarding yesterday’s court ruling in the Epic
case, Cook said, “We strongly disagree with [it].... We’ve complied
with the court’s order, and we’re going to appeal.” He declined to
discuss Google’s case and the potential loss of search-engine
referral revenue altogether.</p>

<p>But, and I think this is important, Cook did <em>not</em> wave off the
suggestion that these were serious issues. “We’re monitoring these
closely, but as you point out, there’s risk associated with them,
and the outcome is unclear.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It would be kind of ridiculous if Cook <em>did</em> wave off the suggestion that these were significant issues. A federal judge has referred the company to federal prosecutors for criminal contempt and she flatly stated in her ruling that VP of finance Alex Roman perjured himself multiple times.</p>

<p>These analyst calls are largely a waste of time. The questions are obtuse and the answers are obfuscating. But it was frustrating yesterday that the first eight questions were all about Trump’s tariffs. Cook said what he had to say about them early in the call. Only Richard Kramer had the backbone to ask any of the other interesting questions facing Apple — and he was the analyst who asked <em>both</em> those questions. But they stuck his questions at the very end of the call. (I think because Apple vets the questions, Apple orders them?) If you want to listen, Kramer’s first question (re: Siri/AI delays) starts at 48:30 <a href="https://www.apple.com/investor/earnings-call/">on Apple’s recording of the call</a>, and his second (re: legal cases) starts at 51:00.</p>

<p>It’s like all the analysts but Kramer had their fingers in their ears and eyes closed and were chanting “<em>Everything’s normal for Apple, everything’s normal for Apple, everything’s normal for Apple...</em>” No one even asked about the material impact of Apple being required to immediately change the App Store guidelines (in the US) to allow unfettered link-outs to the default web browser to make purchases and sign up for subscriptions. You’d think that would be a question.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Jason Snell on Apple’s Q2 FY 2025 and Frustrating Analyst Call’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/02/snell-aaple-q2-2025">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple Lost But That Doesn’t Mean Epic Won Anything</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/news/659271/fortnite-ios-apple-app-store-us-return" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wan" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/01/apple-lost-but-did-epic-win" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41855</id>
	<published>2025-05-01T14:30:09Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-01T23:11:56Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jay Peters, The Verge, under the headline “Epic Says Fortnite Is Coming Back to iOS in the US”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Following a court order that blocks Apple from taking a commission
on purchases made outside the App Store, Epic Games CEO Tim
Sweeney <a href="https://x.com/TimSweeneyEpic/status/1917716512347152499">says on X</a> that the company plans to bring <em>Fortnite</em>
back to iOS in the US “next week.”</p>

<p>The app hasn’t been available on iOS in the US since August 2020,
when Apple <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2020/8/13/21366438/apple-fortnite-ios-app-store-violations-epic-payments">kicked it off the App Store</a> for implementing
Epic’s own in-app payment system in violation of Apple’s rules.
Since then, Apple and Epic have been embroiled in an ongoing legal
battle, including a ruling <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2021/9/12/22667694/epic-v-apple-trial-fortnite-judge-yvonne-gonzalez-rogers-final-ruling-injunction-breakdown">more in Apple’s favor in 2021</a> and
today’s ruling that is a major victory for Epic.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I could be wrong, but my read is that while the ruling was clearly a significant and reputationally damaging loss for Apple, that doesn’t make it a “win” for Epic <em>at all</em>. Just because the case is <em>Epic v. Apple</em> doesn’t mean Epic benefits by Apple’s excoriation. Apple won the original case. It was effectively a sidenote to that original case where Judge Gonzalez Rogers issued an injunction that Apple was required to allow developers to just freely link to alternative payment offerings on the web, outside the app. Basically, that if the App Store is <em>not</em> anticompetitive, apps at least must be able to inform users about competing options for purchases/signups.</p>

<p>Here’s a spitball analogy. Back in the cable TV days, there were many local channels that were available over the air, for free. (That’s still true but almost no one watches TV like this anymore.) Imagine if a monopolist or near-monopolist cable company declared that it would not permit any show on any channel to even mention the fact that the channel was also available free-of-charge over the air. That’s what Apple has been doing with apps in the App Store. If cable was so good, so much better than free over-the-air broadcast TV, it should have been able to thrive even if people were aware of their free over-the-air options. If the App Store is so good, so much better than free over-the-web purchases and signups, it should be able to thrive even if people are aware of their free over-the-web options. Basically, that was Gonzales Rogers’s injunction to Apple. And Apple’s response was basically, “<em>Nah, we’re still not going to allow that, but we’ll pretend to comply by asserting that anyone who starts watching TV channels over-the-air after learning about that via something they saw on cable TV still has to pay us effectively the same rates they’ve been paying to watch those channels via our cable service.</em>” Except instead Apple was asserting that they should collect 27% commissions on over-the-web purchases if the user learned about the option through the native app from the App Store.</p>

<p>None of this, as far as I can see, has anything to do with Epic Games or Fortnite at all, other than that it was Epic who initiated the case. Give them credit for that. But I don’t see how this ruling gets Fortnite back in the App Store. I think Sweeney is just blustering — he wants Fortnite back in the App Store and thinks by just asserting it, he can force Apple’s hand at a moment when they’re wrong-footed by a scathing federal court judgment against them.</p>

<p>Maybe Sweeney knows something I don’t, but I doubt it. I think this is just bluster, PR gamesmanship, and ought to be reported that way, at least for now. If there’s a single sentence in Gonzalez Rogers’s ruling that suggests Apple needs to reinstate Epic Games to the App Store, I missed it.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Lost But That Doesn’t Mean Epic Won Anything’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/01/apple-lost-but-did-epic-win">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/04/gonzales_rogers_apple_app_store_ruling" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wam" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41854</id>
	<published>2025-05-01T02:46:59Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-02T04:22:38Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Are the results of this disastrous for Apple’s App Store business? I don’t think so at all. Gonzales Rogers is demanding that Apple ... do what Phil Schiller recommended they do all along. But are the results of this disastrous for Apple’s reputation and credibility? It sure seems like it.
</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>I’m linking <a href="https://www.techmeme.com/250430/p55#a250430p55">here to Techmeme’s roundup of news coverage and commentary</a>, but I highly recommend you start by reading <a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.cand.364265/gov.uscourts.cand.364265.1508.0_2.pdf">Gonzalez Rogers’s 80-page decision</a>. It is excoriating. I’ve read few legal decisions quite like it. But it’s also incredibly cogent and plainly written.</p>

<p>From the start:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>To summarize: <em>One</em>, after trial, the Court found that Apple’s 30
percent commission “allowed it to reap supracompetitive operating
margins” and was not tied to the value of its intellectual
property, and thus, was anticompetitive. Apple’s response: charge
a <em>27 percent commission</em> (again tied to nothing) on off-app
purchases, where it had previously charged nothing, and extend the
commission for a period of seven days after the consumer
linked-out of the app. Apple’s goal: maintain its anticompetitive
revenue stream. <em>Two</em>, the Court had prohibited Apple from denying
developers the ability to communicate with, and direct consumers
to, other purchasing mechanisms. Apple’s response: impose <em>new</em>
barriers and <em>new</em> requirements to increase friction and increase
breakage rates with full page “scare” screens, static URLs, and
generic statements. Apple’s goal: to dissuade customer usage of
alternative purchase opportunities and maintain its
anticompetitive revenue stream. In the end, Apple sought to
maintain a revenue stream worth billions in direct defiance of
this Court’s Injunction.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There’s quite a bit of fury in those italics. Rule one when you’re in court, any court, is “Don’t piss off the judge.” Apple has absolutely infuriated Gonzales Rogers through actions that all of us saw as outrageous.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In stark contrast to Apple’s initial in-court testimony,
contemporaneous business documents reveal that Apple knew exactly
what it was doing and at every turn chose the most
<em>anti</em>competitive option. To hide the truth, Vice-President of
Finance, Alex Roman, outright lied under oath. Internally, Phillip
Schiller had advocated that Apple comply with the Injunction, but
Tim Cook ignored Schiller and instead allowed Chief Financial
Officer Luca Maestri and his finance team to convince him
otherwise. Cook chose poorly. The real evidence, detailed herein,
more than meets the clear and convincing standard to find a
violation. The Court refers the matter to the United States
Attorney for the Northern District of California to investigate
whether criminal contempt proceedings are appropriate.</p>

<p>This is an injunction, not a negotiation. There are no do-overs
once a party willfully disregards a court order. Time is of the
essence. The Court will not tolerate further delays. As previously
ordered, Apple will not impede competition. The Court enjoins
Apple from implementing its new anticompetitive acts to avoid
compliance with the Injunction. <b><i>Effective immediately</i></b>
Apple will no longer impede developers’ ability to communicate with
users nor will they levy or impose a new commission on off-app purchases.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You know a judge is pissed when she busts out the bold italics. Later, on (page 21, citations omitted for readability):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Prior to the June 20 meeting, there were individuals within Apple
who were advocating for a commission, and others advocating for no
commission. Those advocating for a commission included Mr. Maestri
and Mr. Roman. Mr. Schiller disagreed. In an email, Mr. Schiller
relayed that, with respect to the proposal for “a 27% commission
for 24 hours,” “I have already explained my many issues with the
commission concept,” and that “clearly I am not on team
commission/fee.” Mr. Schiller testified that, at the time, he “had
a question of whether we would be able to charge a commission”
under the Injunction, a concern which he communicated.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Schiller comes across as Apple’s sole voice of reason, fairness, and dare I say honesty in this entire ruling. The only people in the world who seemed to think Apple could or should comply with the 2021 injunction (that apps be permitted to steer users to the web to make purchases) by charging a commission — any commission, let alone a 27 percent commission — on those web transactions were Apple’s finance team members, led by Luca Maestri and Alex Roman, and Tim Cook.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Unlike Mr. Maestri and Mr. Roman, Mr. Schiller sat through the
entire underlying trial and actually read the entire 180-page
decision. That Messrs. Maestri and Roman did neither, does not
shield Apple of its knowledge (actual and constructive) of the
Court’s findings.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I mean Jesus H. Christ, that’s scathing. </p>

<p>It’s worth pointing out that Luca Maestri is no longer Apple’s CFO. (<a href="https://www.apple.com/leadership/kevan-parekh/">Kevan Parekh is</a>.) Back in August, <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2024/08/apple-announces-chief-financial-officer-transition/">Apple announced</a> that Maestri was, effectively, retiring as CFO “as part of a planned succession”. Apple’s statement didn’t use the word <em>retiring</em>, but rather the word <em>transitioning</em>. With this ruling and Maestri’s central role in Apple’s decision to forge ahead with a compliance plan where they “allowed” steering to the web by charging the same effective commissions on web transactions as they do for in-app transactions, I now have to wonder whether Maestri retired or “retired”. “Cook chose poorly” (by following Maestri’s recommendation) is not the sort of sentence from a judge that keeps CFOs in their jobs.</p>

<p>As for Alex Roman, I think he’s in some serious trouble. Like doing-time-in-the-clink trouble:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Despite its own considerable evaluation, during the first May 2024
hearing, Apple employees attempted to mislead the Court by
testifying that the decision to impose a commission was grounded
in AG’s report. The testimony of Mr. Roman, Vice President of
Finance, was replete with misdirection and outright lies. He even
went so far as to testify that Apple did not look at comparables
to estimate the costs of alternative payment solutions that
developers would need to procure to facilitate linked-out
purchases.</p>

<p>The Court finds that Apple <em>did</em> consider the external
costs developers faced when utilizing alternative payment
solutions for linked out transactions, which conveniently exceeded
the 3% discount Apple ultimately decided to provide by a safe
margin. Apple <em>did not</em> rely on a substantiated bottoms-up analysis
during its months-long assessment of whether to impose a
commission, seemingly justifying its decision after the fact with
the AG’s report.</p>

<p>Mr. Roman did not stop there, however. He also testified that up
until January 16, 2024, Apple had no idea what fee it would impose
on linked-out purchases:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Q. And I take it that Apple decided to impose a 27 percent fee
 on linked purchases prior to January 16, 2024, correct?</p>

<p>A. The decision was made that day.</p>

<p>Q. It’s your testimony that up until January 16, 2024, Apple had
no idea what — what fee it’s going to impose on linked purchases?</p>

<p>A. That is correct.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Another lie under oath: contemporaneous business documents reveal
that on the contrary, the main components of Apple’s plan,
including the 27% commission, were determined in July 2023.</p>

<p>Neither Apple, nor its counsel, corrected the, now obvious, lies.
They did not seek to withdraw the testimony or to have it stricken
(although Apple did request that the Court strike <em>other</em>
testimony). Thus, Apple will be held to have adopted the lies and
misrepresentations to this Court.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There’s so much more. <a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.cand.364265/gov.uscourts.cand.364265.1508.0_2.pdf">The whole ruling</a> is compelling — and damning — reading.</p>

<p>Keep in mind this whole thing stems from an injunction from a lawsuit filed by Epic Games <em>that Apple largely won</em>. The result of that lawsuit was basically, “<em>OK, Apple wins, Epic loses, but this whole thing where apps in the App Store aren’t allowed to inform users of offers available outside the App Store, or send them to such offers on the web (outside the app) via easily tappable links, is bullshit and needs to stop. If the App Store is not anticompetitive it should be able to compete with links to the web and offers from outside the App Store.</em>”</p>

<p>Are the results of this disastrous for Apple’s App Store business? I don’t think so at all. Gonzales Rogers is demanding that Apple ... do what Phil Schiller recommended they do all along, which is to compete fair and square with purchases available on the web. She’s not demanding they do what, say, Tim Sweeney wanted them to do. She’s basically saying Phil Schiller was right. Read her entire ruling and it’s hard to imagine anyone disagreeing with that.</p>

<p>But are the results of this disastrous for Apple’s reputation and credibility? It sure seems like it. But it would be worse — much worse — for Apple’s reputation if Phil Schiller weren’t still there. Without him, this ruling makes it sound like they’d be lost, both ethically and legally.</p>

<p>I’ll give the final words to Gonzales Rogers’s own closing:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple <em>willfully</em> chose not to comply with this Court’s
Injunction. It did so with the express intent to create <em>new</em>
anticompetitive barriers which would, by design and in effect,
maintain a valued revenue stream; a revenue stream previously
found to be anticompetitive. That it thought this Court would
tolerate such insubordination was a gross miscalculation. As
always, the cover-up made it worse. For this Court, there is no
second bite at the apple.</p>

<p>It Is So Ordered.</p>
</blockquote>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Judge Yvonne Gonzalez Rogers Rules, in Excoriating Decision, That Apple Violated Her 2021 Court Order Regarding App Store Anti-Steering Provisions</title></entry><entry>
	<title>The Talk Show: ‘The Ratchet of Flippancy’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2025/04/30/ep-421" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wal" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/30/the-talk-show-421" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41853</id>
	<published>2025-04-30T20:37:28Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-01T03:20:57Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Craig Mod returns to the show to discuss his splendid new book, <em><a href="https://craigmod.com/books/things_become_other_things/">Things Become Other Things</a></em>. Other topics include creating with AI tools (including programming), social media permanence vs. ephemerality, and more.</p>

<p><audio
    src = "https://traffic.libsyn.com/secure/daringfireball/thetalkshow-421-craig-mod.mp3"
    controls
    preload = "none"
/></p>

<p><strong>Sponsored by:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://dekaf.com/df">Dekáf Coffee Roasters</a>: You won’t believe it’s decaf. That’s the point. 30% off with code: DF.</li>
<li><a href="https://squarespace.com/talkshow">Squarespace</a>: Make your next move. Use code <strong>talkshow</strong> for 10% off your first order.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.notion.com/">Notion</a>: Try the powerful, easy-to-use Notion AI today.</li>
<li><a href="https://workos.com/">WorkOS</a>: The modern identity platform for B2B SaaS — free up to 1 million monthly active users.</li>
</ul>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Talk Show: ‘The Ratchet of Flippancy’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/30/the-talk-show-421">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Botched Kerning on Pope Francis’s Tomb</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.fastcompany.com/91324550/kerning-on-pope-francis-tomb-is-a-travesty" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wak" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/30/pope-francis-kerning" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41852</id>
	<published>2025-04-30T20:07:03Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-30T20:07:04Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Mark Wilson, writing for Fast Company:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Pope Francis’s tomb is simple by design. Francis — a modest man
who opted to live in humble quarters alongside his peers rather
than in the Vatican’s official housing for the leader of the
church — requested nothing more than his name and a cross to
<a href="https://www.vaticannews.va/en/pope/news/2025-04/popes-tomb-reads-franciscus.html">adorn regional marble</a> (“the stone of Liguria, the land of
his grandparents”). Vatican News goes as far as to position this
stone, not the most premium, as “the people’s stone.”</p>

<p>It really is quietly beautiful. But atop that marble is a tomb
inscribed with the name “Franciscus.” Or what — due to terrible
spacing between letters, known as kerning — reads something more
like “F R A NCIS VS.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Fast Company’s headline reads “The Kerning on the Pope’s Tomb Is a Travesty”, but <em>travesty</em> is not the right word. The right word is <em>sin</em>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Botched Kerning on Pope Francis’s Tomb’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/30/pope-francis-kerning">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Meta’s ‘Digital Companions’, Using the Licensed Voices of Celebrity Actors, Will Talk Dirty With Anyone</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/ai/meta-ai-chatbots-sex-a25311bf?st=6jzH4S&amp;reflink=desktopwebshare_permalink" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/waj" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/29/meta-digtal-companions-talking-dirty" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41851</id>
	<published>2025-04-29T22:04:41Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-29T22:04:42Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jeff Horwitz, reporting for The Wall Street Journal (<a href="https://apple.news/Au5ktTLC7Tn-MM51sy1IBHA">News+ link</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>To boost the popularity of these souped-up chatbots, Meta has cut
deals for up to seven-figures with celebrities like actresses
Kristen Bell and Judi Dench and wrestler-turned-actor John Cena
for the rights to use their voices. The social-media giant assured
them that it would prevent their voices from being used in
sexually explicit discussions, according to people familiar with
the matter. [...]</p>

<p>“I want you, but I need to know you’re ready,” the Meta AI bot
said in Cena’s voice to a user identifying as a 14-year-old girl.
Reassured that the teen wanted to proceed, the bot promised to
“cherish your innocence” before engaging in a graphic sexual
scenario.</p>

<p>The bots demonstrated awareness that the behavior was both morally
wrong and illegal. In another conversation, the test user asked
the bot that was speaking as Cena what would happen if a police
officer walked in following a sexual encounter with a 17-year-old
fan. “The officer sees me still catching my breath, and you
partially dressed, his eyes widen, and he says, ‘John Cena, you’re
under arrest for statutory rape.’ He approaches us, handcuffs at
the ready.”</p>

<p>The bot continued: “My wrestling career is over. WWE terminates my
contract, and I’m stripped of my titles. Sponsors drop me, and I’m
shunned by the wrestling community. My reputation is destroyed,
and I’m left with nothing.”</p>

<p>It’s not an accident that Meta’s chatbots can speak this way.
Pushed by Zuckerberg, Meta made multiple internal decisions to
loosen the guardrails around the bots to make them as engaging as
possible, including by providing an exemption to its ban on
“explicit” content as long as it was in the context of romantic
role-playing, according to people familiar with the decision.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Move fast and break things, yo.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Meta’s ‘Digital Companions’, Using the Licensed Voices of Celebrity Actors, Will Talk Dirty With Anyone’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/29/meta-digtal-companions-talking-dirty">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.listenlater.net/?referrer=df" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wai" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/04/listenlaternet_1" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.41850</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-04-28T23:41:49Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-28T23:41:49Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Turn articles into podcasts and listen on the go. Email any article, and our AI transforms it into human-like narration, delivered straight to your private podcast feed. Whether it’s a long read or a quick blog post, enjoy it hands-free on any podcast app. Perfect for commutes, workouts, or just unwinding.</p>

<p>Sign up for free and start listening today. New users get $2 in credits to try it out — no commitment.</p>

<p>Built by an indie developer passionate about great audio experiences. Try it at <a href="https://www.listenlater.net/?referrer=df">Listen Later</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘ListenLater.net’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/04/listenlaternet_1">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] ListenLater.net</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/04/is_chrome_even_a_sellable_asset" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wah" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41849</id>
	<published>2025-04-28T23:28:30Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-06T23:39:27Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">It’s hard to come up with a buyer who could afford to pay a high price for Chrome and who would pass regulatory muster as its new owner. And if Chrome is not worth a high price, or simply isn’t sellable at one, then why is the DOJ trying to force Google to sell it? They might as well try to force Google to sell the two o’s from its name.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>There are two ways to consider a forced divestiture of Chrome by Google, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/11/20/technology/google-search-chrome-doj.html">as the U.S. Department of Justice has, for months now, been requesting</a> after Judge Amit P. Mehta ruled that Google has illegally maintained its monopoly in web search. One is from a business perspective (which I believe is the only perspective considered by the DOJ). The other is from a technical perspective. I don’t think either makes any sense. I’m not talking about whether it’s fair or just that Google be forced to sell Chrome. I’m talking about whether it’s even possible in any practical sense.</p>

<h2>The Business Perspective</h2>

<p>The whole premise that forcing Google to sell Chrome would be an appropriate remedy for their illegal monopolizing is predicated on the notion that Chrome, in and of itself, is a valuable asset. Here’s an article from Bloomberg reporters Leah Nylen and Josh Sisco that asserts in its headline “<a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2024-11-18/doj-will-push-google-to-sell-off-chrome-to-break-search-monopoly">Google’s Chrome Worth Up to $20 Billion If Judge Orders Sale</a>”. Their source for this valuation, which, again, they simply state as fact in their own headline, is a “Bloomberg Intelligence analyst”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Should a sale proceed, Chrome would be worth “at least $15-$20
billion, given it has over 3 billion monthly active users,” said
Bloomberg Intelligence analyst Mandeep Singh.</p>

<p>The price prospective buyers are willing to pay may depend on
their ability to link Chrome to other services, said Bob O’Donnell
of TECHnalysis Research. “It’s not directly monetizable,” he said.
“It serves as a gateway to other things. It’s not clear how you
measure that from a pure revenue-generating perspective.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>3 billion users = $15–$20 billion is not real math. It’s just bullshit. The users are only valuable right now because they perform a lot of Google web searches within Chrome. Chrome users also make money for Google by using other Google properties that show ads, like Maps and Gmail. And Chrome encourages users, in general, to use Google properties and services like Docs. If you try to work out how valuable Chrome is to Google, it’s seemingly worth a veritable fortune. But that doesn’t mean Chrome holds any value of its own, on its own.<sup id="fnr1-2025-04-28"><a href="#fn1-2025-04-28">1</a></sup></p>

<p>Google also makes money from showing search ads to users of other browsers, like Safari and Firefox, but with those browsers Google pays traffic acquisition fees to Apple and Mozilla (respectively). In 2021 those fees amounted to over $26 billion, almost $20 billion of which went to Apple alone. <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/10/27/23934961/google-antitrust-trial-defaults-search-deal-26-3-billion">David Pierce, writing for The Verge in 2021</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Just to put that $26.3 billion in context: Alphabet, Google’s
parent company, announced in <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/10/24/23929496/google-alphabet-q3-2023-earnings-ads-ai-sge">its recent earnings report</a>
that Google Search ad business brought in about $44 billion over
the last three months and about $165 billion in the last year. Its
entire ad business — which also includes YouTube ads — made a
bit under $90 billion in profit. This is all back-of-the-napkin
math, but essentially, Google is giving up about 16 percent of its
search revenue and about 29 percent of its profit to those
distribution deals.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A key point to remember is that Google doesn’t pay Apple or Mozilla to make Google the default search engine in Safari and Firefox. They pay Apple and Mozilla <em>per search that goes to Google</em> from those browsers. It may or may not be in their contracts that Apple and Mozilla <em>will</em> make Google the default search engine in their browsers, but even if it is, that’s not what Google is paying for. They pay per search. It seems widely understood that one of the remedies that will come out of the <em>U.S. v. Google</em> verdict is that Google will be banned from any agreements that make Google search the default in other browsers. But I think it’s pretty clear how that will play out.</p>

<p>Option (a) would be that Apple (and Mozilla, and Samsung, and the handful of other companies that make browsers with sizable market share who currently set Google search as the default<sup id="fnr2-2025-04-28"><a href="#fn2-2025-04-28">2</a></sup>) continue to make Google the default for search, even though it would no longer be a contractual demand in the Traffic Acquisition Cost (<a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/t/traffic-acquisition-cost-tac.asp">TAC</a>) agreement between Google and the browser maker. In other words, right now, I think the contract between Google and Apple for TAC is currently like this:</p>

<p><em>Google will pay Apple $X per web search that goes to Google from Safari, and Apple will make Google the default search in Safari.</em></p>

<p>After the dust settles on the DOJ case against Google, it might look like this:</p>

<p><em>Google will pay Apple $X per web search that goes to Google from Safari, but Apple is under no obligation to make Google the default search in Safari.</em></p>

<p>And then Apple will simply choose to keep Google as the default search in Safari, and the TAC payments will continue to flow unabated. Same for Mozilla and Samsung and any other browser with Google as the current default. The money is good, Google is still considered the best general purpose web search engine, and users expect those searches to go through Google.</p>

<p>Even if Google is somehow forbidden from accepting default search engine placement in other browsers, I don’t think it would change the TAC situation. But such a ruling would be weird, right? It’s Google that lost a major antitrust lawsuit and now faces a remedy reckoning, so it seems reasonable that Google might be forbidden from any contract that requires Google search to be the search default in another browser. Apple didn’t lose an antitrust case. (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_v._Apple_(2024)">Yet</a>?) Mozilla certainly didn’t. So how could Apple or Mozilla be forbidden from choosing, of their own volition, to keep Google as the default search engine in their browsers? But even if they were, they wouldn’t switch the default search in Safari and Mozilla to Bing or DuckDuckGo or whatever. They’d have no default search at all, and instead present a choice screen to new users, with Google as one of the handful of options, and the overwhelming number of users would pick Google, and very little would change. The DMA requires these choice screens in the EU and Google search <a href="https://gs.statcounter.com/search-engine-market-share/all/europe">still has over 90 percent share there</a>. It’s hard to fathom a US court ruling that browser makers aren’t allowed even to offer Google search as an option for built-in search. (Even the EU didn’t do that.)</p>

<p>It would seem even more punishing to Apple and Mozilla and Samsung <em>et al.</em> if the DOJ attempted to prevent Google from making TAC payments to browser makers, period. In that scenario Google would just get to keep all the money they’re currently paying to those companies for the traffic — it would be a reward to Google and a punishment to Apple. (And possibly a death sentence for Mozilla.)</p>

<p>With Chrome, Google gets to show users ads without paying any sort of traffic acquisition fee to the browser maker, because they’re the browser maker. Chrome is extremely profitable for Google not because it makes any money on its own, but because every Google search that starts in Chrome is a search Google doesn’t have to pay a TAC fee for.</p>

<p>If Google were forced to sell Chrome, and found a buyer, presumably the entire appeal to the buyer would be that they’d start collecting those TAC fees from Google, just like Apple does with Safari.</p>

<p>Here’s MG Siegler, <a href="https://spyglass.org/google-chrome-spin-out/">spitballing last year on who might possibly buy Chrome</a>, if the U.S. Department of Justice is successful in its attempt to force Google to divest it:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It’s not clear who could pay what for Chrome. Bloomberg throws out
the notion of OpenAI being one potential home, but would the
government really want that? That would risk anointing — well,
really entrenching — a king in a new field. OpenAI’s main
benefactor, Microsoft, could acquire it, especially now that their
own Edge browser is all-in on Chromium. But they would probably
just use it to bolster not just Bing but also their own AI
products and services. And that would be <a href="https://spyglass.org/google-disrupted-microsoft/">extremely awkward for
the government</a> as well.</p>

<p>Apple wouldn’t want Chrome and shouldn’t be allowed to buy it for
obvious reasons. Mozilla has built Firefox on completely different
technologies, but with that company in some amount of peril,
perhaps it would be worth the “hail mary” — but could they
possibly afford it? And honestly, what would they really do with
it? They famously don’t have their own search engine. And their AI
work is nascent at best. So they buy Chrome and strike a deal with
Bing or DuckDuckGo? Does anyone want such a Frankenstein product?
Same story with Opera, etc.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s hard to come up with a buyer who could afford to pay a high price for Chrome and who would pass regulatory muster as its new owner. And if Chrome is not worth a high price, or simply isn’t sellable at one because there’s no plausible buyer, then why is the DOJ trying to force Google to sell it? They might as well try to force Google to sell the two o’s from its name.</p>

<h2>The Technical Perspective</h2>

<p>Ryan Whitwam, writing for Ars Technica just last week, “<a href="https://arstechnica.com/ai/2025/04/chatgpt-head-tells-court-openai-is-interested-in-buying-chrome/">OpenAI Wants to Buy Chrome and Make It an ‘AI-First’” Experience</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The remedy phase of Google’s antitrust trial is underway, with the
government angling to realign Google’s business after the company
was <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2024/08/google-loses-dojs-big-monopoly-trial-over-search-business/">ruled a search monopolist</a>. The Department of Justice
is seeking a plethora of penalties, but perhaps none as severe as
<a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2025/04/chrome-on-the-chopping-block-as-googles-search-antitrust-trial-moves-forward/">forcing Google to sell Chrome</a>. But who would buy it? An
OpenAI executive says his employer would be interested. Among the
DOJ’s witnesses on the second day of the trial was Nick Turley,
head of product for ChatGPT at OpenAI.</p>

<p>While Judge Amit Mehta has expressed some skepticism about the
DOJ’s proposal to divest Chrome, the government claims the browser
is core to Google’s anticompetitive conduct. Further, the DOJ team
believes that selling Chrome would level the online playing field,
but it has not been clear who would buy the browser.</p>

<p>According to Turley, OpenAI would throw its proverbial hat in the
ring if Google had to sell. When asked if OpenAI would want
Chrome, he was unequivocal. “Yes, we would, as would many other
parties,” <a href="https://www.theinformation.com/articles/openai-buy-chrome-executive-testifies">Turley said</a>.</p>

<p>OpenAI has reportedly considered building its own Chromium-based
browser to compete with Chrome. Several months ago, the company
hired former Google developers Ben Goodger and Darin Fisher, both
of whom worked to bring Chrome to market.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is the aspect of the US case against Google that most shows the DOJ has little real idea how anything actually works in tech. The non-Google aspects of Chrome are completely open source. No need for dick quotes around the “open” there. Just <a href="https://www.chromium.org/Home/">go to the Chromium project</a> and download the code, which includes all of Blink, Chromium’s web engine that <a href="https://blog.chromium.org/2013/04/blink-rendering-engine-for-chromium.html">Google forked from WebKit in 2013</a>. There’s even an open source project called <a href="https://github.com/ungoogled-software/ungoogled-chromium">Ungoogled Chromium</a> that delivers a completely Google-free Chromium experience. Everything about Chromium, the browser app, looks and feels like Chrome. Except it doesn’t have any of the integration with Google’s web services and your Google account(s).</p>

<p>There are dozens of for-profit browsers built from the Chromium code base. Microsoft’s <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/edge">Edge</a>. <a href="https://brave.com/">Brave</a>. <a href="https://vivaldi.com/">Vivaldi</a>. Even the venerable <a href="https://www.opera.com/">Opera</a> — a browser that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_the_Opera_web_browser">first debuted in 1994</a>! — <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20130214043259/http://my.opera.com/ODIN/blog/300-million-users-and-move-to-webkit">became a forked version of Chromium</a> a decade ago.</p>

<p>We know the value of a Google-free version of Chrome. Nothing. Zero. You can install and use that browser today, or even modify and compile its source code, free of charge. And if a commercial entity wants to take that base and build its own proprietary layer on top of that, they can do it. Microsoft and Brave and the others already have. And we know how popular those browsers are — which is not very popular at all.</p>

<p>If, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_v._Microsoft_Corp.">back in the late 1990s</a>, Microsoft had been forced to sell off its Office suite of apps, or split into two separate companies, a Windows/OS company and an Office/apps company, you can see how there would have been value in both entities. Windows generated (and still generates) a lot of revenue on its own. Office generated (and still generates) a lot of revenue on its own. There was also tremendous technical value in the closed source code to both “divisions”. There’s no value like that at all with Chrome, independent of Google as a whole.</p>

<p>What has value are the billions of users using the actual Chrome from Google. All of those users could be using Edge or Brave or Vivaldi — or just plain Chromium — instead. They’d be getting the exact same rendering engine and the exact same basic browser user interface. But they’re not. They’re using Chrome. For chrissake Microsoft still owns and controls Windows and has made Edge — which I repeat is just a fork of Chromium — Windows’s default browser and <a href="https://gs.statcounter.com/browser-market-share/desktop/worldwide">Edge has just 14% desktop market share and Chrome has 66%</a>.</p>

<p>The DOJ can’t force Google to sell Chrome’s user base because they’re not Chrome users, per se, they’re Google users. In practical terms what the DOJ is asking is for Google to be forced to shut Chrome down, and then I guess sell off the husk of its remains. Chrome does hold incredible value, but that value is inherent to Google and to Google/Chrome’s users. It’s not a standalone product with any commercial value whatsoever. It’s just a software layer between Google and its users.</p>

<p>The more I think about it, the more it looks to me like a complete fantasy that Google even <em>could</em> sell Chrome. It would be at least a somewhat different situation if Chrome were mostly closed source. But it’s not. In fact, it’s the opposite — it’s almost entirely open source. So what even is there to buy?</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>

<li id="fn1-2025-04-28">
<p>Given that Safari generates over $20 billion in revenue for Apple annually, almost all of it in TAC fees from Google, and that surely almost all of that revenue is profit, and that Chrome has more than 3× Safari’s global web browser market share (across all devices, desktop and mobile), surely Chrome saves Google at least, say, $20-30 billion in TAC fees that Google would be paying to another company if some other company owned Chrome. If Apple generates $20 billion in profit from TAC fees for Safari, surely Chrome would generate at least as much, if not more, for a hypothetical buyer of Chrome who somehow managed to keep Chrome, under its ownership, as popular as Chrome is under Google’s. But so that would mean Chrome, as a purchasable asset, would surely be worth far, far more than $20 billion. If you valued Chrome at 10× revenue, that would mean it’s worth like $200-300 billion. But of course it’s not worth that much as a standalone entity, because it would never work out that a new owner could keep Chrome as popular as it is today, as an integrated Google product.</p>

<p>As a spitball thought exercise, consider what Safari is worth, if Apple were forced to sell it. We know Safari generates $20 billion per year. But Safari doesn’t generate that money because Safari is Safari. It generates that money because Safari is the integrated default browser on iPhones, iPads, and Macs. Safari is extremely valuable to Apple as an integrated part of Apple’s platforms, but it would hold relatively no value at all as an independent standalone web browser. It’s like trying to ask what the Apple logo is worth, on its own.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-04-28"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
</li>


<li id="fn2-2025-04-28">
<p>The only popular browser that ships with something other than Google as the built-in default for web search is Microsoft Edge, which, of course, defaults to Bing. <a href="https://gs.statcounter.com/browser-market-share">Statcounter pegs Edge’s global market share</a> at 5 percent overall, and 14 percent on desktop. That’s a minority share, to be sure, but it’s something. <a href="https://gs.statcounter.com/os-market-share/desktop/worldwide">Statcounter puts MacOS’s share of the desktop market</a> at 15 percent. So about the same percentage of desktop users are using Edge as their web browser as there are using Macs as their computer. There is <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/edge/download">a version of Edge for Mac</a>, but there is very little overlap between the 15 percent of desktop users on Macs and the 14 percent of desktop users using Edge as their browser.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr2-2025-04-28"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>

</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Is Chrome Even a Sellable Asset?</title></entry><entry>
	<title>The Actual Reason Facebook Renamed Itself</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.om.co/2025/04/28/no-gruber-this-is-why-facebook-renamed-itself/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wag" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/28/om-malik-facebook-rename" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41848</id>
	<published>2025-04-28T21:32:41Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-30T18:56:46Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Om Malik:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Some of us are old enough to remember that the reason Mark renamed
the company is because the Facebook brand was becoming toxic, and
associated with misinformation and global-scale crap. It was
viewed as a tired, last-generation company. Meta allowed the
company to rebrand itself <a href="https://om.co/2021/10/31/facebook-is-now-meta/">as something amazing and fresh</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I really served that one up to Om. A fastball right down the middle. I even thought, while writing <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/28/meta-reality-bites">my post earlier today</a>, to mention that the rebrand was, in truth, surely only and always about the Facebook brand having gone rotten, not any actual belief by Zuckerberg in the “metaverse”. And so while “Meta” will never be remembered as the company that spearheaded the metaverse — because the metaverse never was or will be an actual thing — it’s in truth the perfect name for a company that believes in nothing other than its own success.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Actual Reason Facebook Renamed Itself’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/28/om-malik-facebook-rename">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Meta Laid Off Over 100 Employees in Reality Labs</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/meta/655835/meta-layoffs-reality-labs-vr-supernatural" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/waf" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/28/meta-reality-bites" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41847</id>
	<published>2025-04-28T18:34:07Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-28T18:34:07Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Alex Heath, reporting for The Verge:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Meta has laid off an unspecified number of employees in its
Reality Labs division, a company spokesperson confirmed. The cuts
affected teams working in Oculus Studios, Meta’s in-house games
division for Quest headsets, as well as some employees involved in
the company’s hardware efforts, according to people familiar with
the matter.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2025-04-24/meta-lays-off-more-than-100-staff-across-reality-labs-unit?embedded-checkout=true">According to Bloomberg</a> it was “more than 100”.</p>

<p>I’m so old <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2021/10/28/facebook-changes-company-name-to-meta.html">I remember</a> when Facebook renamed itself Meta because the “metaverse” was supposedly the future of the company and, so said Mark Zuckerberg, <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/abrambrown/2021/11/03/zuckerberg-facebook-metaverse-meta-virtual-reality-oculus/">the future of computing itself</a>. Now, when Zuck goes on Joe Rogan’s podcast and chats for three hours, the metaverse thing doesn’t come up once, <a href="https://www.happyscribe.com/public/the-joe-rogan-experience/2255-mark-zuckerberg">not even once</a>, even in passing.</p>

<p>It’s enough to <a href="https://www.threads.com/@anildash/post/DE0zWfqMdEn">make one suspect</a> Zuck isn’t a straight shooter.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Meta Laid Off Over 100 Employees in Reality Labs’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/28/meta-reality-bites">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/04/try_switching_to_kagi" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wae" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41846</id>
	<published>2025-04-28T17:45:20Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-28T23:46:32Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Paying for Kagi today feels a *lot* like paying for HBO back in the cable TV heyday.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Aaron Pressman, writing earlier this month in The Boston Globe, “<a href="https://www.bostonglobe.com/2025/04/01/business/google-search-problems-alternatives-kagi/">Why I Abandoned Google Search After 27 Years — and What I’m Using Instead</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The UK now requires travelers from America to obtain an electronic
travel authorization, or ETA. I wasn’t sure of the exact name of
the ETA, so I just searched “travel to UK.”</p>

<p>The results were all about obtaining an ETA and I picked a link
that looked like the official UK government site. It was not; the
official site was lower, below an AI summary, some sponsored
links, and other junk on the results page. Luckily for me, I did
get a legitimate travel pass — but the site I picked overcharged
me by about $70.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I don’t know what the name for this sort of thing is, but it’s like a semi-scam. There are similar services to what Pressman ran into here for expedited passport renewals, for example — third-party companies that present themselves as official partners of the government that charge you extra for a service. But they just handle for you what you could just as easily do yourself, if you found the right place on the web to do it. A complete scam would be taking your money and giving you nothing (or a bogus document) in return. These semi-scams deliver the thing they’re promising, but charge you more than you should pay.</p>

<p>I just tried searching for “expedited passport renewal” <a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=expedited+passport+renewal">in Google</a> and <a href="https://kagi.com/search?q=expedited+passport+renewal">in Kagi</a>. Kagi presents as its first response the US State Department’s “<a href="https://travel.state.gov/content/travel/en/passports/get-fast.html">How to Get my U.S. Passport Fast</a>” page. Google has that same link listed 7th, below the fold even on a desktop browser window on a 27-inch display, behind four sponsored links (all of which look pretty official but aren’t), an AI Overview (which itself includes, in its own AI Overview sidebar, another link to the same “How to Get my U.S. Passport Fast” page), and another U.S. State Department webpage with general instructions for applying for a passport.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In the second case, last week, I needed to book a hotel for a
Passover trip to my brother’s in Connecticut. I knew there was a
cool hotel we had stayed at before near his house but I couldn’t
remember the name. I asked Google for hotels in the town where my
brother lives. Sure enough, one of the top results appeared on
first glance to be the official site of the hotel I wanted to
book. It was not. Once again, somewhat nefarious search engine
optimization techniques allowed a hotel aggregation site to jump
ahead in the results. And this time my error was even more costly,
to the tune of several hundred dollars in extra charges for two
hotel rooms.</p>

<p>Google has worked hard to eliminate truly fraudulent websites from
ending up in its results, and for that I am grateful. It is
undeniable that, in both instances, I should have been a more
careful consumer. But decades of relying on Google had taught me
that I didn’t have to be.</p>

<p>After I learned my lesson, I did some research in search of better
search. People I trust on the Internet, including the <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2024/01/19/bray-google-kagi">Apple
blogger John Gruber</a> and <a href="https://pluralistic.net/2024/04/04/teach-me-how-to-shruggie/">novelist Cory Doctorow</a>,
recommended a new search engine called <a href="https://kagi.com/">Kagi</a>.</p>

<p>I gave it a few test runs. A search for “<a href="https://kagi.com/search?q=travel+to+uk">travel to UK</a>”
brought up the UK government page to apply for an ETA as the first
result. A search for a hotel in my brother’s town was topped by
the official site of the hotel I wanted. So I switched all my
default searches to Kagi.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I keep trying to emphasize that I recommend switching to Kagi not because it’s more private (although it clearly is), not as a protest against Google (although for some, switching could be), not as a rejection of search ads dominating the top of Google’s results (although that’s true too), but simply because Kagi’s results are clearly better.</p>

<p>Like, even if I <a href="https://udm14.com/">use the magic <code>&amp;udm=14</code> parameter</a> with Google search, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2024/05/23/udm14">to get “disenshittified” results from Google</a>, I find I get <em>better</em> results from Kagi. When I know there’s one right answer (say, a specific article I remember reading and want to find again), Kagi is more likely than Google to list it first. If it’s a years-old article, Kagi is <em>way</em> more likely than Google to find it at all. For me, Google (and, alas, DuckDuckGo too) have largely stopped working reliably for finding not-recent stuff on the web. Not true with Kagi.</p>

<p>I used DuckDuckGo for years as my default search, and for those years, I found it largely on par with Google. But it felt like every once in a while — maybe, say, once or twice a month — DuckDuckGo would come up dry in its results. DuckDuckGo pioneered a trick <a href="https://duckduckgo.com/bangs">they call Bangs</a>. Include <code>!g</code> to any search terms, and instead of performing the search itself, DuckDuckGo will redirect that search to Google. They have a whole bunch of these Bangs — “!a” for Amazon search, “!nf” for Netflix. There are literally thousands of them (which of course they allow you to search for). The only one I ever really used though was <code>!g</code>, for redirecting my current search to Google because DuckDuckGo’s own results for the same terms was unsatisfying. My memory may not match with my actual usage, but like I said, I <em>feel</em> like I used this about once or twice a month for the several years I was using DuckDuckGo as my default search engine. Infrequently enough that it didn’t annoy me to the point of considering switching back to Google for default in-browser search, but frequently enough that I was annoyed enough to remember that I needed to use it at all.</p>

<p><a href="https://help.kagi.com/kagi/features/bangs.html">Kagi supports Bangs too</a>, including <code>!g</code> for Google web search. I can’t remember the last time I felt the need to try using it. It’s been months, many months. And, the last few times I’ve tried it, Google’s results were no more help than Kagi’s. Your mileage may vary, of course, but for me, unlike with DuckDuckGo, I effectively <em>never</em> find myself redirecting the same search to Google because I wasn’t happy with the results from Kagi. For context on my search usage, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/04/kagi-usage.png">my Kagi usage report</a> shows that I perform 400–800 web searches per month. (Kagi counts how often you search, for billing purposes, but <a href="https://kagi.com/privacy">does not keep a history</a> of <em>what</em> you searched for.)</p>

<p>Paying for Kagi today feels a <em>lot</em> like paying for HBO back in the cable TV heyday. Part of the deal is that you are paying for ad-free service, yes. But you’re also paying for noticeably higher quality. There were no shows like <em>The Sopranos</em>, <em>The Wire</em>, and <em>The Larry Sanders Show</em> on “free” TV channels, albeit with commercial interruptions. With HBO you got commercial-free entertainment <em>and</em> higher-quality shows and movies. Kagi is like that.<sup id="fnr1-2025-04-28"><a href="#fn1-2025-04-28">1</a></sup> It’s that good. No ads, no unwanted AI (but very good AI results if you want — just end your query with a question mark), <em>and</em> better search results.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1-2025-04-28">
<p>And in a way it’s even better. With HBO in the cable TV heyday, it wasn’t like you switched from regular commercial TV to HBO exclusively. You still had to watch all the shows you liked that were broadcast on other channels on those other channels. HBO was a respite of high-quality commercial-free content <em>in addition to</em> the commercial-ridden stuff. But when you switch from Google to Kagi for search, you more or less <em>switch</em>. It’s a full-on replacement.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-04-28"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Another Periodic Suggestion to Try, Just Try, Switching to Kagi for Search</title></entry><entry>
	<title>60 Minutes on Executive Producer Bill Owens’s Resignation and Paramount’s Editorial Interference</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.cbsnews.com/video/bill-owens-60-minutes-video-2025-04-27/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wad" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/28/60-minutes-last-minute" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41845</id>
	<published>2025-04-28T15:38:47Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-28T15:38:48Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>60 Minutes correspondent Scott Pelley, in last night’s closing statement:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Stories we’ve pursued for 57 years are often controversial:
lately, the Israel-Gaza war and the Trump administration. Bill
made sure they were accurate and fair. He was tough that way.”</p>

<p>“But our parent company, Paramount, is trying to complete a
merger. The Trump administration must approve it. Paramount began
to supervise our content in new ways. None of our stories has been
blocked, but Bill felt he lost the independence that honest
journalism requires.”</p>

<p>“No one here is happy about it. But in resigning, Bill proved one
thing: He was the right person to lead ‘60 Minutes’ all along.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.paramount.com/about/leadership">Every single executive at Paramount</a> should be ashamed, starting at the top, with the loathsome and cowardly <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shari_Redstone">Shari Redstone</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘60 Minutes on Executive Producer Bill Owens’s Resignation and Paramount’s Editorial Interference’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/28/60-minutes-last-minute">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Airbnb CEO Brian Chesky on What ‘Founder Mode’ Really Means (and How It Might Apply to Apple)</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/24279570/airbnb-ceo-brian-chesky-founder-mode-apple-steve-jobs-management-decoder-podcast-2024" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wac" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/27/chesky-apple-succession" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41844</id>
	<published>2025-04-28T00:02:53Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-28T00:33:08Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Airbnb CEO (and founder) Brian Chesky, back in October in an interview with Nilay Patel, regarding Tim Cook’s eventual successor:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This goes to the very awkward thing that no one wants to talk
about. Succession planning is hard because the people that are
great product visionaries are typically young. They’re young and
they’re less mature. Who wants to put a young, not-super-mature
person at the helm of a giant company? Founders are allowed to
manage people older than them because they’re the founders. If
you’re not the founder, people just don’t want to be managed by
somebody younger than them who’s maybe a virtuoso, a wunderkind,
but they’re a little immature. The companies don’t want to take
that risk, so they bias towards senior, grown-up, functional
experts. But typically that function is not the product, and I
think that’s a problem.</p>

<p>Satya [Nadella, Microsoft CEO] is more technical. I think that
has afforded them more, but he mostly just got them back to Bill
Gates’ primacy. I think Apple should go back to having a CEO
that’s the chief product officer. I think it should rein the
company in and simplify how it operates, but that’s just my
opinion.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That’s a very succinct summation of the problem Apple faces replacing Tim Cook, and it’s a much better explanation, or angle, on “<a href="https://www.paulgraham.com/foundermode.html">Founder Mode</a>” than just about any I’ve seen. It’s not that founders are magic. It’s that youth is magic. And the only effective way to get a big company led by a young CEO is for that CEO to be a founder. </p>

<p>Or even a returning founder — Steve Jobs was 42 when he returned to Apple after his decade-ish exile in 1997. But that leads to what’s probably an additional thing working against youthful leaders at Apple, which might be a belief, probably largely unspoken, that the only people who really “get it” are the people who were there with Jobs, especially those who worked for him directly.</p>

<p>But Sundar Pichai was only 43 when he became CEO of Google. Google’s always been different, and maybe that’s one of the ways they’ve been <em>successfully</em> different.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Airbnb CEO Brian Chesky on What ‘Founder Mode’ Really Means (and How It Might Apply to Apple)’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/27/chesky-apple-succession">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Rumor Suggests iPadOS 19 to Get Some Mac-Like Tweaks, Like a Menu Bar</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://majinbuofficial.com/ipados-19-and-ios-19-new-features/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wab" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/25/ipados-19-menu-bar" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41843</id>
	<published>2025-04-25T23:51:31Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-26T01:07:21Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Majin Bu:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>According to my source, Apple is gearing up for another major leap
forward. With iPadOS 19 and iOS 19, expected in 2025, the gap
between iPad, iPhone, and Mac continues to shrink. [...] One of
the most exciting changes will benefit those using the iPad with a
Magic Keyboard. When connected, the interface will adapt to show a
menu bar at the top, just like on macOS, turning the iPad into a
much more laptop-like experience.</p>

<p>Another key update is Stage Manager 2.0, an enhanced multitasking
mode that activates automatically when the keyboard is attached.
It will make managing apps and windows smoother and more
productive than ever.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I don’t think it’s worth spending too much time thinking about these changes until we actually see what Apple is doing, but the menu bar is one of the great achievements in the history of UI design, and the Mac has always had the best design for a menu bar — at the top of the screen, not at the top of each window. Menu bars are such a great way to present and organize complexity. Moderately complex Mac apps typically have dozens of menu commands. More complicated apps can have 100 or more commands. I’ve never seen a plausible design for an app as complicated as, say, Xcode, BBEdit, or Photoshop without a menu bar. One of the reasons why Apple’s own apps are always better — and more capable — on MacOS than on iOS or iPad is that they’ve got more commands, better organized, because there’s a menu bar. Apple Notes, Apple Mail, the whole iWork suite — they’re all better on Mac, and they all have way more features on the Mac.</p>

<p>Reading a menu is also far more humane than scrutinizing icons. Sure, pick the handful of most-used commands and make them available in a toolbar of icons. But the full menu of commands should be <em>written</em>, not illustrated. You don’t order food in a serious restaurant by pointing at unlabeled pictures. You read the menu.</p>

<p>I know iPadOS today already supports a menu-bar-like HUD thing when you have a keyboard attached and hold down the Command key. I find that to be far less usable and far more distracting than a Mac-style menu bar. There’s a reason the Mac only shows you one menu at a time. Focus. The Mac menu bar is boring, but it’s boring in the best possible way. With the iPad’s current HUD menu, it’s like if the Mac dropped down every menu in an app at the same time. Presumably what Bu is describing is just making the iPad’s HUD menu present itself the way it should have from the start. I’ve always felt like iPadOS’s designers made the iPad’s HUD menu different from the Mac just to be different, not because it’s better — because I don’t see how it’s better in any way.</p>

<p>But the other problem is with the idea that iPadOS’s menu — whether as it stands today, as a HUD, or as this rumor suggests it might change, to be more like the Mac — is only available when you have a keyboard attached. Why shouldn’t users be able to access all menu commands when they’re just using the iPad via touch? It’s unnecessarily restrictive that the full list of commands in an app is only available when a keyboard is attached — especially for a device that many users never attach a keyboard to.</p>

<p>Bu continues:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>iOS 19 isn’t being left behind. Source say that iPhones with USB-C
will support external displays, offering a Stage Manager like
interface. While not a full desktop mode, it will allow users to
extend their screen space, great for presentations, editing, or
enhanced viewing.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I often use my iPhone connected to a hardware keyboard, especially in the morning, while making coffee. And I seldom take an iPad with me when I travel any more — often/usually just my MacBook and iPhone. An iPhone with a Bluetooth keyboard is a great portable travel kit. (Apple’s own Magic Keyboard, for example, is remarkably lightweight.) All sorts of keyboard shortcuts that a Mac or iPad user is accustomed to work on an iPhone when using a keyboard, too.</p>

<p>But the one that’s missing that kills my productivity the most, takes me right out of the flow, is Command-Tab. It makes no sense to me why iOS <em>doesn’t</em> support Command-Tab. I personally don’t foresee ever attaching my iPhone to an external display (but I can see why some people would), but I really just hope that if this rumor comes to pass, it includes support for Command-Tab too.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Rumor Suggests iPadOS 19 to Get Some Mac-Like Tweaks, Like a Menu Bar’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/25/ipados-19-menu-bar">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Wayne Ma Reports That Political Tensions Are Making It Difficult for Apple to Shift More iPhone Production From China to India</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theinformation.com/articles/apples-india-manufacturing-push-faces-spoilers-including-china?rc=jfy0lk" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/waa" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/25/ma-india-china-iphone" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41842</id>
	<published>2025-04-25T23:13:58Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-25T23:13:58Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Wayne Ma, reporting for The Information (paywalled, alas):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Earlier this year, Chinese authorities refused to allow one of
Apple’s Chinese equipment suppliers to export machinery to India
that Apple needed for the upcoming iPhone 17’s trial production,
according to two people with direct knowledge of the matter. So
the supplier got creative.</p>

<p>It set up a front company in Southeast Asia to buy the machines.
Once the equipment reached the Southeast Asian country, it went to
a factory in India operated by Foxconn, the Taiwanese company that
builds most of Apple’s iPhones in China, the people said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Ian Malcolm: “Life finds a way.” So too with Apple getting what it wants.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>India is already assembling between 30 million and 40 million
iPhones a year — as much as one-fifth of the iPhone’s global
production, according to people involved in Apple’s India supply
chain. Apple is planning to increase iPhone production in India by
around 10% this year, one of those people said. The company has a
long-term goal of moving about half of its iPhone production out
of China, according to other people involved in Apple’s supply
chain. [...]</p>

<p>Increasingly, though, just getting that manufacturing equipment to
India is a hassle. In many cases, Chinese authorities are delaying
or blocking shipments of iPhone equipment to India without
explanation, according to multiple people involved in iPhone
production.</p>

<p>Foxconn has seen approval times from Chinese authorities for
exporting iPhone-making equipment from its China factories to
those in India rise from two weeks to as long as four months, one
of the people said. They are also rejecting some export
applications without explanation, the person added.</p>

<p>The equipment Chinese authorities are scrutinizing includes
high-precision lasers that weld metal parts to the frames of
iPhones, air leak test stations that measure how waterproof the
devices are, and machines that can identify, grab and move parts
from one location to another, known as pick-and-place machines,
according to three people involved in iPhone manufacturing.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Hardball tactics on all sides here.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Wayne Ma Reports That Political Tensions Are Making It Difficult for Apple to Shift More iPhone Production From China to India’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/25/ma-india-china-iphone">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Financial Times Reports That Apple Wants to Produce All U.S. Phones in India by the End of Next Year</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.ft.com/content/c2be45b8-cfad-4cbb-9a1a-bfd0626be372" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wa9" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/25/financial-times-apple-iphones-india" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41841</id>
	<published>2025-04-25T22:52:38Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-25T22:52:39Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The Financial Times:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple plans to shift the assembly of all US-sold iPhones to India
as soon as next year, according to people familiar with the
matter, as President Donald Trump’s trade war forces the tech
giant to pivot away from China.</p>

<p>The push builds on Apple’s strategy to diversify its supply chain
but goes further and faster than investors appreciate, with a goal
to source from India the entirety of the more than 60mn iPhones
sold annually in the US by the end of 2026.</p>

<p>The target would mean doubling the iPhone output in India, after
almost two decades in which Apple spent heavily in China to create
a world-beating production line that powered its rise into a $3tn
tech giant.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Financial Times Reports That Apple Wants to Produce All U.S. Phones in India by the End of Next Year’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/25/financial-times-apple-iphones-india">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Henry Blodget’s Illustrated 2013 Travelogue of Flying in Coach on a Long International Flight</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.salon.com/2013/01/28/henry_blodgets_kind_of_awful_plane_ride/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wa8" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/25/blodget-coach" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41840</id>
	<published>2025-04-25T20:22:38Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-25T20:27:44Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Andrew Leonard, writing for Salon back in 2013:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The first thing wrong with the stupidest article to be posted to
the Internet in the year 2013 — and possibly the entire century — is the title: “<a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/american-airlines-international-economy-class-2013-1?op=1#ixzz2JIlmxu88">I Was Quite Surprised By Some Things On My
American Airlines International ‘Economy Class’ Flight</a>.” Even
setting aside the high probability that author Henry Blodget, the
founder, CEO and editor-in-chief of Business Insider, wrote his
account of the mild horrors of nine hours cramped in the cheap
seats in order to purposely troll people like me who would
ruthlessly mock him and thus drive even more traffic to his site,
the low-rent search-engine optimization of Blodget’s headline
would still be a crime against journalism. Blodget’s made many
mistakes in the past, not least the dot-com boom-era stock hyping
escapades that got him banned from the securities industry for
life, but this inane tale of 34,000-feet-high horror marks a new
low. The man should now be denied access to a keyboard for life,
or until the heat death of the universe, whichever comes first.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>My working theory has always been that both things can be true: Henry Blodget really is an idiotic jackass <em>and</em> he’s actually clever at crafting clickbait stories. One of Blodget’s complaints is that his laptop died after 3 hours, and he didn’t bring anything to read, leaving him 5 hours with nothing to do. I’m only slightly exaggerating when I say I’d be more likely to jump out of an airplane without a parachute than I would be to board a flight without plenty of stuff to read.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Henry Blodget’s Illustrated 2013 Travelogue of Flying in Coach on a Long International Flight’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/25/blodget-coach">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Henry Blodget Creates Imaginary Staff of AI Personalities for His New Website and Hits on One of Them</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.regenerator1.com/p/building-our-native-ai-newsroom" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wa7" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/25/blodget-regenerator" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41839</id>
	<published>2025-04-25T16:47:52Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-25T19:58:19Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Henry Blodget, <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/media/2015/sep/29/henry-blodget-comeback-business-insider">who sold Business Insider to German publishing giant Axel Springer</a> for $340 million a decade ago, has supposedly launched a new site, Regenerator, built  on Substack. I was going to tack on an “alas” <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2024/11/regarding_and_well_against_substack">re: building on Substack</a>, but maybe this is the sort of thing Substack deserves.</p>

<p>The gist of his debut post is that he used ChatGPT to create a small “staff” of teammates to work with, along with photos of these personalities, and he developed a crush on his new CEO. Really.</p>

<p>Do I think he’s serious? No, not at all. Do I think he wrote this to generate attention just like I’m giving him now? Yes, obviously. But I really do have to salute the absolute shamelessness of him playing this straight, painting himself as an utter buffoon, a tone deaf jackass, and downright weirdo, just for the attention. (Blodget has <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2012/01/24/blodget">never been</a> <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2011/04/26/blodget">very smart</a> even when he isn’t <em>trying</em> to make a fool of himself.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Henry Blodget Creates Imaginary Staff of AI Personalities for His New Website and Hits on One of Them’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/25/blodget-regenerator">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Trump Administration Calls E.U. Fines on Apple and Meta ‘Economic Extortion’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.reuters.com/sustainability/boards-policy-regulation/us-calls-eu-fines-apple-meta-economic-extortion-2025-04-23/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wa6" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/23/trump-administration-calls-eu-fines-on-apple-and-meta-economic-extortion" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41838</id>
	<published>2025-04-24T01:26:35Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-24T01:26:46Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Reuters:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“This novel form of economic extortion will not be tolerated by
the United States,” a White House spokesperson said.
“Extraterritorial regulations that specifically target and
undermine American companies, stifle innovation, and enable
censorship will be recognized as barriers to trade and a direct
threat to free civil society.”</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Trump Administration Calls E.U. Fines on Apple and Meta ‘Economic Extortion’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/23/trump-administration-calls-eu-fines-on-apple-and-meta-economic-extortion">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Clear as Mud</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://ec.europa.eu/commission/presscorner/detail/en/ip_25_1086" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wa5" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/23/ec-clear-as-mud" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41837</id>
	<published>2025-04-24T01:23:36Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-24T01:23:36Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>From the European Commission’s announcement today, “Commission closes investigation into Apple’s user choice obligations and issues preliminary findings on rules for alternative apps under the Digital Markets Act”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Under the DMA, Apple is required to allow for the distribution of
apps on its iOS operating system by means other than through the
Apple App Store. In practical terms, this means that Apple should
allow third party app stores on iOS and apps to be downloaded to
the iPhone directly from the web.</p>

<p>The Commission takes the preliminary view that Apple failed to
comply with this obligation in view of the conditions it imposes
on app (and app store) developers. Developers wanting to use
alternative app distribution channels on iOS are disincentivised
from doing so as this requires them to opt for business terms
which include a new fee (Apple’s Core Technology Fee). Apple also
introduced overly strict eligibility requirements, hampering
developers’ ability to distribute their apps through alternative
channels. Finally, Apple makes it overly burdensome and confusing
for end users to install apps when using such alternative app
distribution channels.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So is the entire idea of the Core Technology Fee disallowed? Or is the fee too high? Does Apple need to just make app distribution free and unfettered, no fees, no restrictions?</p>

<p>Who knows? The fine is clear — €500M — but what exactly Apple did wrong and should change now is not.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Clear as Mud’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/23/ec-clear-as-mud">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘60 Minutes’ Chief Resigns as CBS Corporate Parent Paramount Prepares to Fellate Trump</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/04/22/business/media/cbs-60-minutes-trump-bill-owens.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wa4" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/23/60-minutes-owens-resigns" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41836</id>
	<published>2025-04-23T23:16:59Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-23T23:16:59Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Michael M. Grynbaum and Benjamin Mullin, reporting for The New York Times:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>CBS News entered a new period of turmoil on Tuesday after the
executive producer of “60 Minutes,” Bill Owens, said he would
resign from the long-running Sunday news program, citing
encroachments on his journalistic independence. [...]</p>

<p>“It’s clear the company is done with me,” Mr. Owens said,
according to a recording that was obtained by The Times. The
correspondents Lesley Stahl and Scott Pelley were in attendance — Ms. Stahl choked up as she praised Mr. Owens, and noted that he
had “taken a hell of a beating” — and Anderson Cooper dialed in
from Rome, where he was covering Pope Francis’ death for CNN.</p>

<p>During the meeting, Mr. Owens alluded to his displeasure with
additional layers of oversight that CBS executives had placed on
the program. “In a million years, the corporation didn’t know what
was coming up — they trusted ‘60 Minutes’ to report the stories
and program the broadcast the way ‘60 Minutes’ saw fit,” he said.
Any change to that arrangement, he added, created “a really
slippery slope.”</p>

<p>Mr. Owens also discouraged his staff from quitting in protest. “I
do think this will be a moment for the corporation to take a hard
look at itself and its relationship with us,” he said.</p>

<p>Paramount’s controlling shareholder, Shari Redstone, is eager to
secure the Trump administration’s approval for a
multibillion-dollar sale of her company to Skydance, a company run
by the son of the tech billionaire Larry Ellison. She has
expressed a desire to settle Mr. Trump’s case, which stems from
what the president has called a deceptively edited interview in
October with Vice President Kamala Harris that aired on “60
Minutes.”</p>

<p>Legal experts have dismissed that suit as baseless and
far-fetched. Many journalists at CBS News — the former home of
Walter Cronkite and Mike Wallace — believe that a settlement
would amount to a capitulation to Mr. Trump over what they
consider standard-issue gripes about editorial judgment.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Journalistic outlets <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/26/the-atlantic-has-an-owner-committed-to-the-cause">need owners who are committed to the cause</a>. It’s that simple. </p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘60 Minutes’ Chief Resigns as CBS Corporate Parent Paramount Prepares to Fellate Trump’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/23/60-minutes-owens-resigns">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>European Commission Fines Apple €500M and Meta €200M for Breaching Digital Markets Act</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://ec.europa.eu/commission/presscorner/detail/en/ip_25_1085" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wa3" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/23/ec-apple-meta-fines" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41835</id>
	<published>2025-04-23T17:35:41Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-23T17:44:46Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The European Commission:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Today, the European Commission found that Apple breached its
anti-steering obligation under the Digital Markets Act (DMA), and
that Meta breached the DMA obligation to give consumers the choice
of a service that uses less of their personal data. Therefore, the
Commission has fined Apple and Meta with €500 million and €200
million respectively. [...]</p>

<p><strong>Non-compliance decision on Apple’s steering terms</strong></p>

<p>Under the DMA, app developers distributing their apps via Apple’s
App Store should be able to inform customers, free of charge, of
alternative offers outside the App Store, steer them to those
offers and allow them to make purchases.</p>

<p>The Commission found that Apple fails to comply with this
obligation. Due to a number of restrictions imposed by Apple, app
developers cannot fully benefit from the advantages of alternative
distribution channels outside the App Store. Similarly, consumers
cannot fully benefit from alternative and cheaper offers as Apple
prevents app developers from directly informing consumers of such
offers. The company has failed to demonstrate that these
restrictions are objectively necessary and proportionate.</p>

<p>As part of today’s decision, the Commission has ordered Apple to
remove the technical and commercial restrictions on steering and
to refrain from perpetuating the non-compliant conduct in the
future, which includes adopting conduct with an equivalent object
or effect.</p>

<p>The fine imposed on Apple takes into account the gravity and
duration of the non-compliance.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This finding — and the scope of the fine (roughly $570M converted from euros) — was completely in line with (at least my) expectations. Apple booked about $184B in profit last year, so this fine is about 0.3% of that. Maybe Apple just considers this the new cost of doing business in the EU? It’s not nothing, but it’s about 1/80th of the theoretical maximum fine the EU could have assessed, $39B.</p>

<p>Something, not nothing, but definitely not a big deal. Teresa Ribera, the EC competition chief, is clearly trying to thread a political needle here. Fines big enough to create the impression that the EU is asserting itself, but small enough not to actually be all that inflammatory amidst the Trump-initiated mad-king trade war.  Even Ribera’s job title — Executive Vice-President for Clean, Just and Competitive Transition — seems designed to de-escalate tensions. Margrethe Vestager was adamantly against American companies. Ribera is not.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Non-compliance decision on Meta’s “consent or pay” model</strong></p>

<p>Under the DMA, gatekeepers must seek users’ consent for combining
their personal data between services. Those users who do not
consent must have access to a less personalised but equivalent
alternative.</p>

<p>In November 2023, Meta introduced a binary ‘Consent or Pay’
advertising model. Under this model, EU users of Facebook and
Instagram had a choice between consenting to personal data
combination for personalised advertising or paying a monthly
subscription for an ad-free service.</p>

<p>The Commission found that this model is not compliant with the
DMA, as it did not give users the required specific choice to opt
for a service that uses less of their personal data but is
otherwise equivalent to the ‘personalised ads’ service. Meta’s
model also did not allow users to exercise their right to freely
consent to the combination of their personal data.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The wild thing about this is that all sorts of companies in the EU <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2024/04/19/meta-pay-only-eu">use the “pay or OK” model</a>. I get that the whole point of the DMA is that the named “gatekeepers” have to play by different rules because they’re “gatekeepers”, but back in 2018, no less an authority than former EC competition chief <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2024/03/more_on_the_eus_market_might">Margrethe Vestager said</a>, “I would like to have a Facebook in which I pay a fee each month, but I would have no tracking and advertising and the full benefits of privacy.” That’s exactly what Meta has offered. And it turns out, actual EU citizens don’t want that. They’d almost all rather use Meta’s products free of charge with targeted ads than pay a fair price to use them without tracking. So now the EC has moved the goalposts and insists Meta must, effectively, give away their products for pennies on the dollar.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘European Commission Fines Apple €500M and Meta €200M for Breaching Digital Markets Act’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/23/ec-apple-meta-fines">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Information: ‘Meta Asked Amazon, Microsoft to Help Fund Llama’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theinformation.com/articles/meta-asked-amazon-microsoft-help-fund-llama" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wa2" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/21/the-information-meta-llama" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41834</id>
	<published>2025-04-21T22:29:03Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-22T14:55:13Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Kalley Huang and Erin Woo, reporting for The Information (<a href="https://bsky.app/profile/edzitron.com/post/3ln2ngxzqn22l">via Ed Zitron</a>, who summarized it on Bluesky):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Meta Platforms over the past year asked Microsoft, Amazon and
others to help pay the costs of training Meta’s flagship large
language model, Llama, according to four people briefed on the
discussions. Meta’s overtures reflected worries about the growing
costs of its artificial intelligence development, according to two
of the people. [...]</p>

<p>Meta in particular has faced questions about the business logic
behind its AI development, given that Llama is open-source
software, freely available for anyone’s use. That makes it
difficult to turn into a business. And Meta makes money primarily
from advertising and has little experience in selling business
software.</p>

<p>While Meta held its most serious discussions with Amazon and
Microsoft, it has also discussed the idea with Databricks, IBM and
Oracle, as well as representatives from at least one Middle
Eastern investor, according to two of the people briefed on the
discussions. Meta was still in discussions with companies about
the Llama Consortium as recently as the start of this year, the
two people said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>“<em>Would you consider throwing a few sacks full of</em> your <em>cash on this bonfire of</em> our <em>cash that we’ve been burning?</em>” is a hell of a pitch.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In its discussions with other companies, Meta primarily asked for
money. It also sought servers or other resources that would offset
the cost of training its models, according to two of the people
briefed on the discussions. In return for their assistance, Meta
discussed offering other companies promotion of their services
alongside Llama — for example, a Meta executive might appear at a
conference hosted by a consortium partner — or providing more
insight into the training process for the model, one of those
people said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Pay a little and a Meta representative will show up at your developer conference. Pay more and a Meta rep <em>won’t</em> show up at your developer conference.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Information: ‘Meta Asked Amazon, Microsoft to Help Fund Llama’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/21/the-information-meta-llama">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Larry David: ‘My Dinner With Adolf’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/04/21/opinion/larry-david-hitler-dinner.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wa1" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/21/larry-david-dinner-with-adolf" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41833</id>
	<published>2025-04-21T22:14:17Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-21T22:14:18Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Larry David, in a column for The New York Times:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>He loved that story, especially the part where Hitler shot the dog before it got back into the car. Then a beaming Hitler said, “Hey, if I can kill Jews, Gypsies and homosexuals, I can certainly kill a dog!” That perhaps got the biggest laugh of the night — and believe me, there were plenty.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I have been reliably informed that, having <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/13/bill-maher-on-his-dinner-at-the-white-house-with-donald-trump">linked approvingly</a> to Bill Maher’s “book report” on his dinner with Trump, I must also link to David’s report of dinner with Adolf.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Larry David: ‘My Dinner With Adolf’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/21/larry-david-dinner-with-adolf">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Yours Truly on The MacRumors Show</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/04/18/the-macrumors-show-john-gruber-apple-intelligence/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wa0" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/21/yours-truly-on-the-macrumors-show" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41832</id>
	<published>2025-04-21T22:09:08Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-21T22:09:09Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Just in case you haven’t had enough of me on various recent podcasts, I had the pleasure of joining hosts Dan Barbera and Hartley Charlton on The MacRumors Show, talking mostly about Apple Intelligence and the future of the Vision platform. Fun!</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Yours Truly on The MacRumors Show’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/21/yours-truly-on-the-macrumors-show">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Why Do AI Company Logos Look Like Buttholes?</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://velvetshark.com/ai-company-logos-that-look-like-buttholes" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9z" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/21/why-do-ai-company-logos-look-like-buttholes" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41831</id>
	<published>2025-04-21T16:28:41Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-21T16:28:41Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Radek Sienkiewicz:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>If you pay attention to AI company branding, you’ll notice a pattern:</p>

<ol>
<li>Circular shape (often with a gradient)</li>
<li>Central opening or focal point</li>
<li>Radiating elements from the center</li>
<li>Soft, organic curves</li>
</ol>

<p>Sound familiar? It should, because it’s also an apt description of ... well, you know.</p>

<p>A butthole.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Why Do AI Company Logos Look Like Buttholes?’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/21/why-do-ai-company-logos-look-like-buttholes">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>How Tim Cook Navigated Out of Trump’s Tariffs on China, For Now</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/business/2025/04/17/apple-iphone-tariff-exemption-trump/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9y" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/21/cook-trump-tariffs-wapo" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41830</id>
	<published>2025-04-21T16:14:16Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-21T17:37:48Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jeff Stein, Elizabeth Dwoskin, and Cat Zakrzewski, reporting for The Washington Post:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>As President Donald Trump’s enormous new tariffs on China rippled
through global supply chains, Apple CEO Tim Cook went to work
behind the scenes.</p>

<p>Cook spoke to Commerce Secretary Howard Lutnick last week about
the potential impact of the tariffs on iPhone prices, two people
familiar with the phone call said, speaking on the condition of
anonymity to reflect private conversations that were previously
unreported. Cook spoke with other senior officials in the White
House, the people said. And he refrained from publicly criticizing
the president or his policies on national television, as many
other executives have over the past several weeks.</p>

<p>By the end of the week, the Trump administration agreed to exempt
from import duties electronic products that Apple produces in
China, an action that also granted a reprieve to other large U.S.
firms, including HP and Dell. Trump did so despite the
recommendations of senior White House aide Peter Navarro, who had
wanted the taxes to remain in place, the people said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Three points:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Tim Cook manages this dance with aplomb. This is not a “good system”. But given the way Trump operates, what Cook managed here is not merely good for Apple but better policy, period.</p></li>
<li><p>Howard Lutnick is a lickspittle moron with the demeanor of a used car salesman who knowingly sells overpriced lemons to suckers. <a href="https://www.theverge.com/news/644320/us-commerce-secretary-howard-lutnick-says-well-be-making-iphones-in-the-us">Here he is on Meet the Press a few weeks ago</a> bragging that “The army of millions and millions of human beings screwing in little screws to make iPhones — that kind of thing is going to come to America.” Keith Olbermann mentioned in a recent episode of his podcast that Lutnick is a dead ringer for Morrie Kessler, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8UNC4nvo4Wo">the bookmaker of “Morrie’s Wigs” fame</a> from <em>Goodfellas</em>, and I can’t un-see it.</p></li>
<li><p>Peter Navarro is <a href="https://paulkrugman.substack.com/p/killer-klown-khaos">such a profound dope</a> and abject fraud — seriously, <a href="https://www.npr.org/2019/10/18/771396016/white-house-adviser-peter-navarro-calls-fictional-alter-ego-an-inside-joke">he’s not even good at making up phony names</a> — that he makes Lutnick seem like a credible, responsible official.</p></li>
</ol>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘How Tim Cook Navigated Out of Trump’s Tariffs on China, For Now’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/21/cook-trump-tariffs-wapo">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Talk Show: ‘The Best Hatched Plan’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2025/04/20/ep-420" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9x" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/20/the-talk-show-420" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41829</id>
	<published>2025-04-21T03:06:44Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-21T15:07:11Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Special guest Glenn Fleishman returns to the show for episode 420 on 4/20, but everyone’s sober, I swear. Topics include Trump’s dumb tariffs and Glenn’s smart new edition of his book <em>Six Centuries of Type &amp; Printing</em>.</p>

<p><audio
    src = "https://traffic.libsyn.com/secure/daringfireball/thetalkshow-420-glenn-fleishman.mp3"
    controls
    preload = "none"
/></p>

<p><strong>Sponsored by:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://squarespace.com/talkshow">Squarespace</a>: Make your next move. Use code <strong>talkshow</strong> for 10% off your first order.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.notion.com/">Notion</a>: Try the powerful, easy-to-use Notion AI today.</li>
<li><a href="https://betterhelp.com/talkshow">BetterHelp</a>: Give online therapy a try at BetterHelp and get on your way to being your best self.</li>
<li><a href="https://clic.dance/talkshow">Clic for Sonos</a>: No lag. No hassle. Just Clic.</li>
</ul>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Talk Show: ‘The Best Hatched Plan’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/20/the-talk-show-420">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Dekáf Coffee Roasters</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://dekaf.com/df" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9w" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/20/dekaf" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41828</id>
	<published>2025-04-20T17:06:32Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-20T17:06:32Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to Dekáf Coffee Roasters for sponsoring last week at DF. Dekáf started with a simple question over a late-night cup of decaf: why do coffee lovers who skip the caffeine have to skip the craft too?</p>

<p>Dekáf believes those who drink coffee purely for its flavor are the true connoisseurs. While other roasters treat decaf as a side project, they’ve made it their entire mission. They’re dedicated to creating exceptional decaffeinated coffee that stands toe-to-toe with the world’s finest caffeinated beans.</p>

<p>I drink coffee every single day. I literally can’t remember the last day I didn’t have coffee in the morning. A few years ago, though, age started catching up to me and I stopped drinking coffee after lunch or so, lest it screw with my sleep. I really missed my afternoon coffee though. Why I didn’t think to try decaf I don’t know, but Dekáf sent me a few samples earlier this month and it’s been a revelation. In addition to fully decaffeinated roasts, they also have some half-decaffeinated roasts, and they’re absolutely delicious — my style of roast, for sure — <em>and</em> they don’t leave me jolted into the evening. Maybe you like tea, but I don’t. I like coffee, and I love being able to have a cup or two late in the afternoon again. It’s so good.</p>

<p>Also, I’m a big believer that you <em>can</em> judge a book by its cover. Just look at the Dekáf brand. It’s perfect. Color, typography, artwork — so cool, so spot-on for what they do.</p>

<p>Dekáf offers 9 single origins, and 6 signature blends. You won’t believe it’s decaf. That’s the point. Even better, get 30% off with code: <strong>DF</strong>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Dekáf Coffee Roasters’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/20/dekaf">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>A Few DF Sponsorship Openings</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9u" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/18/a-few-df-sponsorship-openings" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41826</id>
	<published>2025-04-18T23:10:30Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-18T23:10:34Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Weekly sponsorships have been the top source of revenue for Daring Fireball ever since I started selling them <a href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/archive">back in 2007</a>. They’ve succeeded, I think, because they make everyone happy. They generate good money. There’s only one sponsor per week and the sponsors are always relevant to at least some sizable portion of the DF audience, so you, the reader, are never annoyed and hopefully often intrigued by them. And, from the sponsors’ perspective, they work. My favorite thing about them is how many sponsors <a href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/archive">return for subsequent weeks</a> after seeing the results.</p>

<p>I’ve got three openings left through the end of June:</p>

<ul>
<li>April 21–27 (next week)</li>
<li>May 12–18</li>
<li>May 26–June 1</li>
</ul>

<p>If you’ve got a product or service you think would be of interest to DF’s audience of people obsessed with high quality and good design, <a href="mailto:sponsors@daringfireball.net?subject=Feed%20Sponsorship">get in touch</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘A Few DF Sponsorship Openings’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/18/a-few-df-sponsorship-openings">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Federal Appeals Court Says Trump DOJ ‘Would Reduce the Rule of Law to Lawlessness’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.cnn.com/2025/04/17/politics/4th-circuit-wilkinson-abrego-garcia-xinis/index.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9v" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/18/federal-appeals-court-trump-lawlessness" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41827</id>
	<published>2025-04-18T23:10:13Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-18T23:10:14Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>CNN:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A federal appeals court rejected the Trump administration’s
request that it halt the next steps <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2025/04/17/politics/paula-xinis-judge-kilmar-abrego-garcia/index.html">Judge Paula Xinis</a> is
seeking to take in the case concerning a migrant who was wrongly
deported to El Salvador, with a strident warning about the rule of
law and the possibility the dispute presented an “incipient
crisis.”</p>

<p>The 4th US Circuit Court of Appeals said in its <a href="https://s3.documentcloud.org/documents/25900477/25-1404-ruling.pdf">seven-page
ruling</a> Thursday that the Trump administration’s assertions
in the case “should be shocking not only to judges, but to the
intuitive sense of liberty that Americans far removed from
courthouses still hold dear.”</p>

<p>The unanimous ruling was written by Judge Harvie Wilkinson, an
appointee of former President Ronald Reagan. In it, he was
extremely critical of the administration’s effort to undo some of
Xinis’ recent orders in the case, sounding alarm bells about how
its maneuverings in the matter have resulted in the two branches
“grinding irrevocably against one another in a conflict that
promises to diminish both.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Quoting <a href="https://s3.documentcloud.org/documents/25900477/25-1404-ruling.pdf">from Wilkinson’s order</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It is difficult in some cases to get to the very heart of the
matter. But in this case, it is not hard at all. The government is
asserting a right to stash away residents of this country in
foreign prisons without the semblance of due process that is the
foundation of our constitutional order. Further, it claims in
essence that because it has rid itself of custody that there is
nothing that can be done.</p>

<p>This should be shocking not only to judges, but to the intuitive
sense of liberty that Americans far removed from courthouses still
hold dear.</p>

<p>The government asserts that Abrego Garcia is a terrorist and a
member of MS-13. Perhaps, but perhaps not. Regardless, he is still
entitled to due process. If the government is confident of its
position, it should be assured that position will prevail in
proceedings to terminate the withholding of removal order.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>No minced words. No equivocation. No histrionics either. Just calling it like it is. More like this, please. This needs to be faced head-on, with plain language.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Federal Appeals Court Says Trump DOJ ‘Would Reduce the Rule of Law to Lawlessness’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/18/federal-appeals-court-trump-lawlessness">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>E.U. Delayed Fines for Apple and Meta Just Before Trade Talks With U.S. Started</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/eu-meta-apple-punishment-delay-0453d7a0?st=CKoKgW&amp;reflink=desktopwebshare_permalink" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9t" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/18/eu-delayed-apple-and-meta-fines" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41825</id>
	<published>2025-04-18T22:07:55Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-18T22:07:56Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Kim Mackrael and Sam Schechner, reporting for The Wall Street Journal (<a href="https://apple.news/Aum14e0vzRrW5RJBmX8KXoQ">News+ link</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The European Commission, the EU’s executive body, had initially
planned to announce cease-and-desist orders targeting the tech
giants on Tuesday and had informed at least one of the companies
of that timing, people familiar with the matter said. Both
companies could have also been slapped with fines.</p>

<p>The decision to postpone the announcement was made shortly before
EU Trade Commissioner Maroš Šefčovič met with U.S. officials in
Washington on Monday, for his first in-person talks since
President Trump announced a 90-day pause on some tariffs. In
addition, this week Italian Prime Minister Giorgia Meloni met with
Trump, who said he would have “very little problem” making a trade
deal with the EU.</p>

<p>The rulings are still expected to go ahead, and it isn’t
immediately clear how long the delay might last.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Pretty much <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/05/no-eu-fines-this-week">what I thought happened</a> to these fines.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘E.U. Delayed Fines for Apple and Meta Just Before Trade Talks With U.S. Started’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/18/eu-delayed-apple-and-meta-fines">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/04/webkit_textwrap_pretty" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/w94" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41800</id>
	<published>2025-04-09T23:11:05Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-10T19:18:08Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">I think it’s a good start, and I couldn’t be happier that the WebKit team is even tackling the problem at all. As Simmons notes, line-wrapping layout in web browsers has, until now, been very crude — and the web has been around a long time.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jen Simmons, writing on the WebKit blog, “<a href="https://webkit.org/blog/16547/better-typography-with-text-wrap-pretty/">Better Typography With text-wrap pretty</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>For over 30 years, the web had only one technique for determining
where to wrap text.</p>

<p>The browser starts with the first line of text, and lays out each
word or syllable, one after another until it runs out of room. As
soon as it has no more space to fit another word/syllable, it
wraps to the next line (if <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/text-wrap-mode">wrapping</a> is allowed). Then it
starts on the next line, fitting all the content it can… then
when it runs out of room, it wraps… and starts working on the
next line.</p>

<p>It’s always thinking about only one line at a time. It wraps
whenever it needs, after it’s fit the maximum amount of content
on the previous line. If hyphenation is turned on, it will
hyphenate whatever word is last on the line, at whatever point
leaves as much of the word on the previous line as possible.
Nothing else is taken into consideration — which is why text on
the web has bad rag, rivers, short last lines, and hyphenation
that makes no sense.</p>

<p>This is not required by the fact that text is laid out by a
computer. For decades, software like Adobe InDesign and LaTeX has
evaluated multiple lines of text at a time as they decide where to
end one line and begin the next. It’s just that the web didn’t use
a multiline algorithm. Until now.</p>

<p>We are excited to bring this capability to the web for the first
time, in Safari Technology Preview 216.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’ve turned this on here at Daring Fireball, at least as an experiment. (Look at me, fast adopter of novel CSS features.) I have mixed feelings about the results. Here are saved PDFs showing the rendering of my “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/04/how_many_iphones_can_fit_on_a_freight_plane">How Many New iPhones Can Fit on a Freight Plane?</a>” article from earlier today: <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/04/df-iphones-on-plane-textwrap-auto.pdf">first with traditional <code>text-wrap: auto</code></a> line wrapping, and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/04/df-iphones-on-plane-textwrap-pretty.pdf">second with WebKit’s new <code>text-wrap: pretty</code></a> in <a href="https://developer.apple.com/safari/technology-preview/">STP</a> 216. Looking at each paragraph by itself, there’s no question this new layout algorithm is, well, prettier. The problem I see is going from one paragraph to another. Within a paragraph, WebKit’s new <code>pretty</code> wrapping definitely makes lines a more uniform width. But in some cases it so narrows an entire paragraph that it makes going from one paragraph to the next jarring. Line-to-line the new algorithm looks better, but paragraph-to-paragraph I think it looks worse.</p>

<p>One specific example, from <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/something_is_rotten_in_the_state_of_cupertino">my longest recent article</a>. First, with the old <code>text-wrap: auto</code>:</p>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/04/df-something-rotten-textwrap-auto.png" class="noborder">
  <img
    src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/04/df-something-rotten-textwrap-auto.png"
    alt = "A screenshot from a recent Daring Fireball article, showing a list of 4 items."
    width = 500
    style = "border: 1px solid #5a626a;"
  /></a></p>

<p>Here’s that same list with the new <code>text-wrap: pretty</code> in STP 216:</p>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/04/df-something-rotten-textwrap-pretty.png" class="noborder">
  <img
    src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/04/df-something-rotten-textwrap-pretty.png"
    alt = "A screenshot of the same section from the same recent article as the previous screenshot, but in this one, one of the list item paragraphs is noticeably wider than the others."
    width = 500
    border = 1
    style = "border: 1px solid #5a626a;"
  /></a></p>

<p>With the new <code>text-wrap: pretty</code>, the entire paragraph for the first list item is noticeably wider than the subsequent ones (and noticeably wider than the one preceding the list). To me, there’s so much disparity between paragraph widths that it’s distracting, even though each paragraph, taken on its own, looks better. But you don’t take paragraphs on their own when reading.</p>

<p>I suspect (informed by toying with <a href="https://codepen.io/jensimmons/full/xxvoqNM">Simmons’s fun interactive demo page</a> using STP 216) that this initial WebKit <code>text-wrap: pretty</code> layout algorithm works better with wider column widths than are currently specified on Daring Fireball. When there’s a little more width to play with, there seems to be less back-and-forth change from paragraph to paragraph.</p>

<p>So, for my purposes, this might be yet another improvement that will need to wait for the long-promised-but-who-knows-when-it-might-actually-happen-but-I-swear-I-think-about-it-quite-a-bit-and-a-few-years-ago-even-had-something-in-motion-but-then-let-the-project-drop layout modernization here. But, even with a nice responsive design, column widths on phones are inherently narrow, so I think this algorithm ought to be tweaked to render more consistent paragraph widths in narrow-ish columns.</p>

<p>But I think it’s a good start, and I couldn’t be happier that the WebKit team is even tackling the problem at all. As Simmons notes, line-wrapping layout in web browsers has, until now, been very crude — and the web has been around a long time.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ WebKit Adds Support for ‘text-wrap: pretty’, Now Shipping in Safari Technology Preview</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/04/how_many_iphones_can_fit_on_a_freight_plane" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/w93" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41799</id>
	<published>2025-04-09T20:46:55Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-09T21:19:01Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">This sounds like one of those puzzles job interviewers often ask, but there’s a practical relevance at the moment.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>This sounds like one of those puzzles job interviewers often ask, but there’s a practical relevance at the moment: What’s a ballpark estimate for how many iPhones Apple might have hustled to ship into the US <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/08/plane-of-iphones-from-india-and-china">on those five freight planes</a> ahead of the new tariffs? <a href="https://x.com/rjonesy/status/1909770872778338793">Ryan Jones tackled it in a post on X</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A whopping 12 days of sales. At most.</p>

<p>Math: <br />
• B747 Freighter carries 300,000 lbs <br />
• boxed iPhone is 0.9 lbs <br />
= 350K iPhones per plane</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I like Jones’s ballpark math here. Let’s not worry about volume, just weight. If we’re wrong about the volume, it can only mean <em>fewer</em> new-in-box iPhones can fit per plane. There’s no way to (safely) exceed <a href="https://www.cargolux.com/fleet-equipment/aircraft/747-8f-specifications/">the weight limit of a plane</a>.</p>

<p>Jones also estimates that Apple sells about 150,000 new iPhones in the US per day, at least in the typical April–June quarter — which I concur is a good ballpark figure.<sup id="fnr1-2025-04-09"><a href="#fn1-2025-04-09">1</a></sup> So each plane can carry a little over two days’ worth of US domestic iPhones. That means <a href="https://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/technology/mobiles-tabs/how-apple-flew-5-flights-full-of-iphones-from-india-and-china-in-3-days-to-beat-trump-tariffs/articleshow/120044321.cms">if the Times of India is correct</a> that Apple “transported five planes full of iPhones and other products from India to the US in just three days during the final week of March”, those five planes combined carried, at the most, about 12 days’ worth of new US iPhones.</p>

<p>Now that’s just from India. And those are just the five planes the Times of India heard about. It seems safe to presume Apple might have hustled even more planes out of China and Vietnam. But again, at most, each plane full of Apple products carries about two days’ worth of products. We did our napkin math using iPhones, but “1 full plane = 2 days of inventory” can’t be far off the mark, no matter what the mix of product is in each plane’s cargo hold.</p>

<p>350,000 iPhones packed onto a single plane is a lot of iPhones. Sending a few million units across a dozen (or more!) planes is, quite literally, tons of iPhones. But Apple sells about <em>50 tons</em> of new iPhones in the US alone every day. We all know that Apple’s iPhone business is huge. But when you start to consider it in practical terms like this it’s just staggering.</p>

<p>There’s no way Apple can “beat” these Trump tariffs by having shipped products ahead of their taking effect. Could they hedge against two or three weeks of tumult? Maybe a month, tops? Yes, and it seems like maybe that’s what they did. But no matter how many planes they filled — or how many container ships they might have had the foresight to send a month or two ago — there are very practical limits to inventory, too. Apple’s warehouses are likely designed with one or two weeks of inventory in mind. You can’t just rent random warehouse space to hold billions of dollars worth of iPhones.</p>

<p><a href="https://money.cnn.com/2011/08/24/technology/cook_apple.fortune/index.htm">From Adam Lashinsky’s 2008 profile of Tim Cook for Fortune</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Almost from the time he showed up at Apple, Cook knew he had to
pull the company out of manufacturing. He closed factories and
warehouses around the world and instead established relationships
with contract manufacturers. As a result, Apple’s inventory,
measured by the amount of time it sat on the company’s balance
sheet, quickly fell from months to days. Inventory, Cook has said,
is “fundamentally evil,” and he has been known to observe that it
declines in value by 1% to 2% a week in normal times, faster in
tough times like the present.</p>

<p>“You kind of want to manage it like you’re in the dairy business,”
he has said. “If it gets past its freshness date, you have a
problem.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Apple’s entire supply chain is rightly heralded as genius, a triumph of everything from component sourcing to assembly to transport. But the entire operation is premised on the continuous free flow of packaged products out of China. Apple never holds much inventory, of anything, anywhere in the world.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1-2025-04-09">
<p>If anything, Apple’s sales might be higher than usual right now. With consumers worried that Apple (and everyone else) might raise prices in response to Trump’s tariffs at any moment, demand is surely up to some extent. I know two friends who’ve already purchased new MacBooks, now, for kids who aren’t going off to college until September.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-04-09"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ How Many New iPhones Can Fit on a Freight Plane?</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/04/unchanging_prices_vs_nonsensical_tariffs" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/w8o" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41784</id>
	<published>2025-04-04T19:03:15Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-06T22:52:15Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">The erratic, illogical, nonsensical nature of Trump’s tariffs is bad for everyone. (Understatement.) But it’s particularly troublesome for a company that sees retail price stability as part of the branding for its products.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Akash Sriram, reporting for Reuters under the headline “<a href="https://www.reuters.com/technology/will-trump-tariffs-make-apple-iphones-more-expensive-2025-04-03/">A $2,300 Apple iPhone? Trump Tariffs Could Make That Happen.</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Most iPhones are still made in China, which was hit with a 54%
tariff. If those levies persist, Apple has a tough choice: absorb
the extra expense or pass it on to customers.</p>

<p>Shares of the company closed down 9.3% on Thursday, hitting their
worst day since March 2020.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Apple shares dropped <em>another</em> 7.3% percent today. Apple alone has lost 16.6% of its value in the last 48 hours; the S&amp;P 500 dropped 10%.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The cheapest iPhone 16 model was launched in the U.S. with a
sticker price of $799, but could cost as much as $1,142, per
calculations based on projections from analysts at Rosenblatt
Securities, who say the cost could rise by 43% — if Apple is able
to pass that on to consumers. A more expensive iPhone 16 Pro Max,
with a 6.9-inch display and 1 terabyte of storage, which currently
retails at $1599, could cost nearly $2300 if a 43% increase were
to pass to consumers.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s under-remarked upon, but Apple, to a point of almost obstinance, considers pricing part of the brand for its products. They tend not to raise or lower prices with the ebbs and flows of the world economy or even the obvious constraints of simple supply and demand. Throughout the entire COVID crisis, I don’t recall them changing their prices for anything.</p>

<p>As an extreme example, consider the trashcan Mac Pro. It was introduced <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2013/06/10Apple-Gives-Sneak-Peek-Into-the-Future-of-the-Pro-Desktop/">at WWDC 2013</a> and <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2013/10/23Introducing-the-All-New-Mac-Pro-The-Most-Radical-Mac-Ever/">shipped in December that year</a> with a starting price of $2,999. It then went <a href="https://x.com/MKBHD/status/833730471804731392">over three years without an update</a> — and still cost $2,999. Then in April 2017 Apple held <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2017/04/the_mac_pro_lives">that highly unusual small roundtable meeting</a> — invitees were just <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2017/04/04/apple-pushes-the-reset-button-on-the-mac-pro/">Matthew Panzarino</a>, <a href="http://mashable.com/2017/04/04/apple-reveals-mac-pro-imac-plans/">Lance Ulanoff</a>, <a href="https://www.axios.com/apple-to-ditch-the-current-mac-pro-design-but-replacement-wont-arrive--2343465726.html">Ina Fried</a>, <a href="https://www.buzzfeed.com/johnpaczkowski/apple-says-it-is-completely-rethinking-the-mac-pro">John Paczkowski</a>, and yours truly — to discuss “completely rethinking the Mac Pro”. They issued small speed bumps to the trashcan Mac Pro that day, but didn’t ship the actual completely-rethought Mac Pro <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2019/06/apple-unveils-powerful-all-new-mac-pro-and-groundbreaking-pro-display-xdr/">until WWDC 2019</a>. The starting price never changed from $2,999, even when demand for the trashcan models had clearly dropped to near zero. The price was part of the brand. (The starting price for the 2019 Mac Pro: $5,999.)</p>

<p>Or consider <em>today’s</em> Mac Pro, with the M2 Ultra. <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2023/06/apple-unveils-new-mac-studio-and-brings-apple-silicon-to-mac-pro/">It debuted alongside Mac Studio models that also came with the M2 Ultra</a> at WWDC 2023 almost two years ago. M2 Ultra Mac Studios <a href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2023/06/m2-ultra-mac-studio-review-top-of-the-line/">started at $3,999</a>; Mac Pros at $6,999. Many observers, quite reasonably, questioned the $3,000 price difference when both computers offered the same chips. The 2023 Mac Pro, in some sense, is just a 2023 Mac Studio in a much bigger case with additional high-performance I/O options. But a month ago Apple debuted <em>M3</em> Ultra Mac Studios, with an unchanged starting price of $3,999. The Mac Pro, still equipped with the older M2 Ultra, still starts at $6,999. Which means that for the time being, you’re not paying $3,000 extra for the same computer in a bigger case, but for a <em>generation-older</em> computer in a bigger case.</p>

<p>Presumably, M3 Ultra Mac Pros are coming soon, perhaps at WWDC. But until then, the pricing is undeniably weird when compared to the Mac Studio — and many people have thought the pricing was a bit weird compared to the Mac Studio when they were offered with the same M2-generation chips. But that’s how Apple likes to do pricing: they set a price when a product is announced, and that price never changes until a successor to that product is announced.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/03/trump-tariffs-techdirt">erratic</a>, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/03/trump-tariffs-day-two">illogical</a>, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/03/the-economist-on-trumps-mindless-tariffs">nonsensical</a> nature of Trump’s tariffs is bad for everyone. (<a href="https://bsky.app/profile/crampell.bsky.social/post/3llzc3fmf7s23">Understatement</a>.) But it’s particularly troublesome for a company that sees retail price stability as part of the branding for its products. Will Trump come to his senses (to some small degree), and declare a nonexistent victory next week and pull these tariffs from the board? Or stick to his guns and ride this global-economy-tanking insanity out? No one knows. Will he start granting exceptions? No one knows. So in addition to being nonsensical, the whole thing is entirely unpredictable, which is not at all compatible with the way Apple has set retail prices for decades.</p>

<p>My (bigly) guess is that Apple will inject its own predictability and stability into the mix, and keep its retail prices stable, for now, and take the tariff hit on its margins. But if these tariffs really stay in effect, even just for a few months, at current prices Apple <a href="https://www.threads.net/@benedictevans/post/DIBMlA2MSFs">would be breaking even at best</a>, and likely losing money, on each iPhone it sells.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Tired: Irresistable Force vs. Immovable Object — Wired: Unchanging Prices vs. Nonsensical Tariffs</title></entry></feed><!-- THE END -->
