<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>Daring Fireball</title>
<subtitle>By John Gruber</subtitle>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/" />
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main" />
<id>https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main</id>


<updated>2025-06-22T17:57:49Z</updated><rights>Copyright © 2025, John Gruber</rights><entry>
	<title>Drata</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://drata.com/daring" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wf6" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/22/drata" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42018</id>
	<published>2025-06-22T17:57:49Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-22T17:57:49Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to Drata for sponsoring this last week at DF. Their message is short and sweet: Automate compliance. Streamline security. Manage risk. Drata delivers the world’s most advanced Trust Management platform.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Drata’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/22/drata">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple Launches ‘Convince Your Parents to Get You a Mac’ Short Film on YouTube, Then Pulls It a Day Later Without Explanation</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/06/21/apple-pulls-the-parent-presentation-video/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wf5" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/22/apple-can-convince-your-parents" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42017</id>
	<published>2025-06-22T17:52:06Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-22T17:52:55Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Joe Rossignol at MacRumors:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple has marked its day-old <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/06/20/apple-shares-the-parent-presentation-for-mac/">The Parent Presentation</a> video
on YouTube as private, meaning that it is no longer available to
watch. Apple has also moved The Parent Presentation to the bottom
of its College Students page, effectively burying it. When we
reported on the marketing campaign yesterday, the presentation was
prominently featured at the top of the page.</p>

<p>It is unclear why Apple is suddenly hiding the ad, or if it will
return. Apple did not immediately respond to our request for
comment. On social media, some people said that the ad was cringe
or gross, so perhaps Apple pulled the video due to overly negative
reception. To be clear, this is merely speculation, and there were
others who found humor in the video.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The 7.5-minute video, which at the moment is still available to watch from re-uploads <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JHFUmPbODbI&amp;t=1s">on YouTube</a> and <a href="https://x.com/aaronp613/status/1936057701387428183">X</a> — stars <a href="https://www.themoviedb.org/person/2807375-martin-herlihy?language=en-US">Martin Herlihy</a> from SNL’s “Please Don’t Destroy” triumvirate. I wouldn’t describe it as “cringe”, but I also wouldn’t describe it as “funny”. (If Herlihy wrote this, it would suggest that his cohorts <a href="https://www.themoviedb.org/person/3631826-ben-marshall?language=en-US">Ben Marshall</a> and <a href="https://www.themoviedb.org/person/3631835-john-higgins?language=en-US">John Higgins</a> are the funny ones in the trio.) It’s also not the least bit offensive, so it really is unclear why Apple pulled it. If it’s because it’s not funny, how did it not only get approved and produced, but posted for 24 hours? Is Apple’s new marketing strategy to just publish new ads and then <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2024/05/09/apple-crush-apology">wait to see how the world reacts</a> before deciding if they’re any good or not?</p>

<p>One obvious problem with “The Parent Presentation” video is that the gist is that <em>everyone</em> involved is stupid: high school kids (the ostensible target audience?) are too stupid to know how to ask their parents for a MacBook for college, parents are too stupid to know they should buy their kids a good laptop, and even Herlihy’s lecturer is a doofus who himself doesn’t know how to deliver a presentation. I don’t know how this got past the concept stage.</p>

<p>To top things off, <a href="https://www.apple.com/education/college-students/#presentation">the downloadable slide presentation</a> — which Apple still has available in Keynote, PowerPoint, and Google Slides formats — is entirely typeset in Arial. I would take my son’s MacBook away from him if he came to me with a presentation set in Arial.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Launches ‘Convince Your Parents to Get You a Mac’ Short Film on YouTube, Then Pulls It a Day Later Without Explanation’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/22/apple-can-convince-your-parents">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>MacOS 26 Tahoe Beta Drops FireWire Support</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/06/19/macos-tahoe-beta-drops-firewire-support/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wf4" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/22/macos-26-tahoe-beta-drops-firewire-support" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42016</id>
	<published>2025-06-22T17:07:41Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-22T17:07:42Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Joe Rossignol, writing for MacRumors:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A bit of sad news for old iPods: Macs might be losing FireWire
support.</p>

<p>The first macOS Tahoe developer beta does not support the legacy
FireWire 400 and FireWire 800 data-transfer standards, according
to <a href="https://x.com/NekoMichiUBC/status/1932876748661608561">@NekoMichi on X</a>, and a <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/MacOS/comments/1l7gb1r/macos_tahoe_dp1_seems_remove_firewire_800_support/">Reddit post</a>. As a result,
the first few iPod models and old external storage drives that
rely on FireWire cannot be synced with or mounted on a Mac running
the <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/how-to/install-macos-tahoe-developer-beta/">macOS Tahoe beta</a>.</p>

<p>Unlike on macOS Sequoia and earlier versions, the first macOS
Tahoe beta does not include a FireWire section in the System
Settings app.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>All good things must come to an end, and FireWire was a very good thing indeed. High-performance, reliable, easy to use.</p>

<p>Apple, back in 2001, “<a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2001/08/22Apple-FireWire-Wins-2001-Primetime-Emmy-Engineering-Award/">Apple FireWire Wins 2001 Primetime Emmy Engineering Award</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple’s FireWire technology will be honored by the Academy of
Television Arts &amp; Sciences in an awards presentation held tonight
at the academy’s Goldenson Theatre in Hollywood. Apple will
receive a 2001 Primetime Emmy Engineering Award for FireWire’s
material impact on the television industry.</p>

<p>Apple invented FireWire in the mid-90s and shepherded it to become
the established cross-platform industry standard IEEE 1394.
FireWire is a high-speed serial input/output technology for
connecting digital devices such as digital camcorders and cameras
to desktop and portable computers. Widely adopted by digital
peripheral companies such as Sony, Canon, JVC and Kodak, FireWire
has become the established industry standard for both consumers
and professionals.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘MacOS 26 Tahoe Beta Drops FireWire Support’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/22/macos-26-tahoe-beta-drops-firewire-support">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Tom Nichols and Timothy Snyder on the US Bombing of Iran</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2025/06/united-states-bombed-iran-now-what/683276/?gift=aQyUJR7AIw1mJWdQ6Ed6yNCTkBMqRx-4Y00eGRut7XI" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wf3" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/22/nichols-trump-iran-bombing" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42015</id>
	<published>2025-06-22T17:00:28Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-22T17:00:28Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Tom Nichols, writing for The Atlantic (gift link):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>President Donald Trump has done what he <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2025/06/18/politics/trump-peacemaker-iran-israel-conflict-analysis">swore</a> he would not
do: involve the United States in a war in the Middle East. His
supporters will tie themselves in knots (as Vice President J. D.
Vance <a href="https://x.com/JDVance/status/1934996183702704404">did</a> last week) trying to jam the square peg of
Trump’s promises into the round hole of his actions. And many of
them may avoid calling this “war” at all, even though that’s what
Trump himself <a href="https://x.com/trump_repost/status/1936580633775792406">called it tonight</a>. They will want to see it
as a quick win against an obstinate regime that will eventually
declare bygones and come to the table. But whether bombing Iran
was a good idea or a bad idea — and it could turn out to be
either, or both — it is war by any definition of the term, and
something Trump had vowed he would avoid. [...]</p>

<p>Only one outcome is certain: Hypocrisy in the region and around
the world will reach galactic levels as nations wring their hands
and silently pray that the B-2s carrying the <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2025/06/20/world/middleeast/iran-nuclear-fordo-bunker-buster-bomb.html">bunker-buster</a>
bombs did their job.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>See also:</strong> <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/timothysnyder.bsky.social/post/3ls6a4s45w22q">Timothy Snyder, on Bluesky</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Five things to remember about war:</p>

<ol>
<li>Many things reported with confidence in the first hours and
days will turn out not to be true.</li>
<li>Whatever they say, the people who start wars are often thinking
chiefly about domestic politics.</li>
<li>The rationale given for a war will change over time, such that
actual success or failure in achieving a named objective is
less relevant than one might think.</li>
<li>Wars are unpredictable.</li>
<li>Wars are easy to start and hard to stop.</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Tom Nichols and Timothy Snyder on the US Bombing of Iran’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/22/nichols-trump-iran-bombing">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>How Apple Created a Custom iPhone Camera for ‘F1’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.wired.com/story/apple-created-a-custom-iphone-camera-for-f1/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wf2" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/19/apple-custom-iphone-camera-for-f1" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42014</id>
	<published>2025-06-19T23:04:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-19T23:04:00Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Julian Chokkattu, writing for Wired:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You can’t mount a cinema camera on a Formula One race car. These
nimble vehicles are built to precise specs, and capturing racing
footage from the driver’s point of view isn’t as simple as
slapping a GoPro on and calling it a day. That’s the challenge
Apple faced after Joseph Kosinski and Claudio Miranda, the
director and cinematographer of the upcoming <em>F1</em> Apple Original,
wanted to use real POV racing footage in the film.</p>

<p>If you’ve watched a Formula One race lately, you’ve probably seen
clips that show an angle from just behind the cockpit, with the
top or side of the driver’s helmet in the frame. Captured by
onboard cameras embedded in the car, the resulting footage is
designed for broadcast, at a lower resolution using specific color
spaces and codecs. Converting it to match the look of the rest of
the <em>F1</em> film would be too challenging to be feasible. Instead,
Apple’s engineering team replaced the broadcast module with a
camera composed of iPhone parts.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I think back to Phil Schiller, <a href="https://vimeo.com/130510366">on stage at my WWDC show in 2015</a>, saying that Apple viewed itself then not just as one of the leading camera companies in the world, but <a href="https://www.imore.com/gruber-and-schiller-our-full-transcript-talk-show-wwdc"><em>the</em> leading camera company in the world</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘How Apple Created a Custom iPhone Camera for ‘F1’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/19/apple-custom-iphone-camera-for-f1">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘F1’ and Apple’s Movie Strategy</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://variety.com/2025/film/news/f1-apple-movie-strategy-tim-cook-lewis-hamilton-1236424270/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wf1" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/19/f1-and-apples-movie-strategy" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42013</id>
	<published>2025-06-19T22:41:04Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-19T22:56:30Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Cynthia Littleton, in a long profile for Variety:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>When pressed about what Apple’s investments in movies and TV shows
have meant for the company as a whole, Cook explains that Apple is
at heart “a toolmaker,” delivering computers and other devices
that enable creativity in users. (This vision for the company, and
the “toolmaker” term specifically, was first articulated by Jobs
in the early 1980s.) “We’re a toolmaker,” Cook says again. “We
make tools for creative people to empower them to do things they
couldn’t do before. So we were doing lots of business with
Hollywood well before we were in the TV business.</p>

<p>“We studied it for years before we decided to do [Apple TV+]. I
know there’s a lot of different views out there about why we’re
into it. We’re into it to tell great stories, and we want it to be
a great business as well. That’s why we’re into it, just plain and
simple.” [...]</p>

<p>Media analysts and observers have wondered how the content side of
Apple threads together with the hardware sales that fuel the core
business. As Cook sees it, that’s not the point, although such
connections are emerging organically in the course of doing
business, as evidenced by “F1” and the camera tech. “I don’t have
it in my mind that I’m going to sell more iPhones because of it,”
Cook says. “I don’t think about that at all. I think about it as a
business. And just like we leverage the best of Apple across
iPhones and across our services, we try to leverage the best of
Apple TV+.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Apple TV+ has been killing it with original shows. Maybe with <em>F1</em> they can start bringing that magic to movies.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘F1’ and Apple’s Movie Strategy’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/19/f1-and-apples-movie-strategy">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/06/some_brief_thoughts_and_observations_on_wwdc_2025" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wf0" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42012</id>
	<published>2025-06-19T21:03:54Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-20T12:39:40Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">My biggest takeaway from WWDC 2025 is that Apple seemingly took some lessons to heart from its unfulfilled promises of a year ago. This year’s WWDC wasn’t merely focused on what Apple is confident it can ship in the next 12 months, but on what they can ship *this fall*.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>“<em>This one a long time have I watched. All his life has he looked away — to the future, to the horizon. Never his mind on where he was. What he was doing. Adventure. Heh! Excitement. Heh! A Jedi craves not these things. You are reckless!</em>” <br />
—Yoda, <em>The Empire Strikes Back</em></p>

<p>My biggest takeaway from WWDC 2025 is that Apple seemingly took some lessons to heart from <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/apple_is_delaying_the_more_personalized_siri_apple_intelligence_features">its unfulfilled promises</a> of a year ago. This year’s WWDC wasn’t merely focused on what Apple is confident it can ship in the next 12 months, but on what they can ship <em>this fall</em>. I might be overlooking a minor exception or two, but every major feature announced in <a href="https://developer.apple.com/videos/play/wwdc2025/101/">the WWDC 2025 keynote</a> was both demonstratable in product briefings, <em>and</em> is currently available in the developer beta seeds. I was also told, explicitly, by Apple executives, that Apple plans to ship everything shown last week in the fall.</p>

<p>That’s as it should be, and a strong return to form for the company. It takes confidence to promise only what you know you can ship, and it takes execution to ship what you’ve promised. If there’s more coming in the early months of 2026, announce those features when they’re ready. It’s proven very effective for Apple to spread the debut of new features across the entire calendar year, with many major features not appearing until the .3, .4, or even .5 OS releases. I think it will prove just as effective marketing-wise to spread the <em>announcement</em> of more features throughout the year as well.</p>

<h2>Year-Based Version Numbers</h2>

<p>There’s no question that it’s a little weird for every one of Apple’s platforms to have jumped to version 26. I mean, VisionOS skipped 23 version numbers. Presumably, when Apple next unveils a new OS (HomeOS?), it’s going to <em>start</em> at version 26, 27, or 28. But I’m already getting used to this, and I think the underlying logic laid out by Craig Federighi at the outset of the keynote is true: with Apple now up to six developer platforms (Mac, iPhone, iPad, Vision, TV, Watch), it had gotten hard to keep track of which version numbers corresponded to the same year. That matters not just for the convenience of knowing, in years to come, when specific versions of each OS were released, but it also matters because none of these platforms exist in isolation. They’re all parts of a cohesive whole, a cross-device “Apple OS 26” experience, as it were.</p>

<p>One thing I haven’t seen commented on, though, is that switching to year-based version numbers establishes as de facto policy something that has now been true for quite a few years, but which Apple has never officially acknowledged: that each of these platforms will get a major version release annually. 20 years ago the update schedule for Mac OS X was rather erratic:</p>

<table class="table-FEBFFE0A-B067-4C29-8766-29C19521F96F">
<style>
.table-FEBFFE0A-B067-4C29-8766-29C19521F96F {width: 350px}
.table-FEBFFE0A-B067-4C29-8766-29C19521F96F th:nth-child(1) { text-align: left }
.table-FEBFFE0A-B067-4C29-8766-29C19521F96F td:nth-child(1) { text-align: left }
.table-FEBFFE0A-B067-4C29-8766-29C19521F96F th:nth-child(2) { text-align: left }
.table-FEBFFE0A-B067-4C29-8766-29C19521F96F td:nth-child(2) { text-align: left }
</style>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Mac OS X 10.7 Lion</td><td>July 2011</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mac OS X 10.6 Snow Leopard</td><td>August 2009</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mac OS X 10.5 Leopard</td><td>October 2007</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mac OS X 10.4 Tiger</td><td>April 2005</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Mac OS X 10.3 Panther</td><td>October 2003</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p>OS X 10.8 Mountain Lion (which began the odd four-year run where the Mac’s OS name didn’t contain “Mac”) arrived in July 2012, and thereafter a new major version has shipped in September, October, or November (MacOS 11 Big Sur, in 2020) every single year. This rigorous annual schedule is a hallmark of the Tim Cook era at Apple, and clearly reflects his personality (as the erratic/idiosyncratic schedule of the mid-2000s reflected Steve Jobs’s).</p>

<h2>iPadOS Windowing</h2>

<p>The pedant in me is mildly perturbed that the new windowing system unveiled for iPadOS 26 is largely being discussed under the term “multitasking”. It’s windowing. One way to understand the difference is that the original Mac OS (a.k.a. System 1) had windowing — windowing that looked and worked a lot like this — but no multitasking. The very early Mac could run just one app a time, but the running app could open multiple windows. But, whatever. It’s all good.</p>

<p>One thing I find interesting is that while <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/102364">split screen and Slide Over</a> have been eliminated in the new system (<a href="https://www.macstories.net/stories/not-an-ipad-pro-review/">praise be</a>), Stage Manager is still a feature. Just plain windowing is as it should be: ad hoc. You make windows and move them around and resize them however you want. Stage Manager is fussier — it’s a more complex system for users who wish to organize their windows into something akin to projects or related tasks. </p>

<p>So, effectively, Apple, three years ago, jumped straight to a more complex, more fiddly option — Stage Manager — and only now has added the simpler, more obvious, not fiddly at all option (windowing). It’s been a weird journey, but I think iPadOS has finally arrived at a place where showing more than one app or document at a time on-screen is what it should have been all along: easy and obvious.</p>

<h2>Liquid Glass</h2>

<p>Alan Dye, introducing Liquid Glass, around the 8m:20s mark in the keynote:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Software is the heart and soul of our products. It brings them to
life, shapes their personality, and defines their purpose. At
Apple, we’ve always believed it’s the deep integration of hardware
and software that makes interacting with technology intuitive,
beautiful, and a joy to use. iOS 7 introduced a simplified design
built on distinct layers, smooth animations, and new colors. It
redefined our design language for years to come. Now, with the
powerful advances in our hardware, silicon, and graphics
technologies, we have the opportunity to lay the foundation for
the next chapter of our software. Today we’re excited to announce
our broadest design update ever. Our goal is a beautiful new
design that brings joy and delight to every user experience, one
that’s more personal, and puts greater focus on your content, all
while still feeling instantly familiar.</p>

<p>And for the first time, we’re introducing a universal design
across our platforms. This unified design language creates a more
harmonious experience as you move between products, while
maintaining the qualities that make each unique. Inspired by the
physicality and richness of VisionOS, we challenged ourselves to
make something purely digital feel natural and alive. From how it
looks to how it feels as it dynamically responds to touch. To
achieve this, we began by rethinking the fundamental elements that
make up our software, and it starts with an entirely new
expressive material we call Liquid Glass. With the optical
qualities of glass and a fluidity that only Apple can achieve, it
transforms depending on your content or even your context, and
brings more clarity to navigation and controls. It beautifully
refracts light and dynamically reacts to your movement with
specular highlights. This material brings a new level of vitality
to every aspect of your experience. From the smallest elements you
interact with to larger ones, it responds in real time to your
content and your input. Creating a more lively experience that we
think you’ll find truly delightful.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Compare and contrast to <a href="https://youtu.be/dHrVGk0WwYM?t=381">Steve Jobs introducing Aqua at Macworld San Francisco in January 2000</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>So this is the architecture, except there’s one more thing. The
one more thing is, we have been secretly for the last 18 months
designing a completely new user interface. And that new user
interface builds on Apple’s legacy and carries it into the next
century. And we call that new user interface Aqua, because it’s
liquid. One of the design goals was when you saw it, you wanted to
lick it. [...]</p>

<p>When you design a new user interface, you have to start off
humbly. You have to start off saying, what are the simplest
elements in it? What does a button look like? And you spend months
working on a button. That’s a button in Aqua. This is what radio
buttons look like. Simple things. This is what checkboxes look
like. This is what popup lists look like. Again, you’re starting
to get the feel of this, a little different. This is what sliders
can look like. Now, let me show you windows. This is what the top
of windows look like. These three buttons look like a traffic
signal, don’t they? Red means close the window. Yellow means
minimize the window. And green means maximize the window. Pretty
simple. And tremendous fit and finish in this operating system.
When you roll over these things, you get those. You see them? And
when you are no longer the key window, they go transparent. So a
lot of fit and finish in this.</p>

<p>In addition to the fit and finish, we paid a lot of attention to
dynamics. Not only how do things look, but how do they move, how
do they behave. And our goal in this user interface was twofold.
One, we wanted to give a much more powerful user interface to our
pro customers. But two, at the very same time, we wanted to make
this the dream user interface for somebody who’s never even
touched a computer before. And that’s really hard to do. It’s like
when we do films at Pixar. It’s really easy, it’s a lot easier, to
make a film that appeals to five-year-olds and under. But it’s
very difficult to make one film that five-year-olds love and that
their parents also love. And that was the goal of this user
interface. To make it span the range so that people turning on
their iMac for the first time were enchanted with it, and it was
super easy to use, and yet, our pro customers also felt, <em>My God,
this takes me to places I thought I could never get to</em>. And
that’s what we tried to do.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Re-watching Jobs’s introduction of Aqua for the umpteenth time, I still find it enthralling. I found Alan Dye’s introduction of Liquid Glass to be soporific, if not downright horseshitty.</p>

<p>But the work itself, Liquid Glass as it launched last week, is very reminiscent of Aqua a quarter century (!) ago. It’s exciting, it’s fresh, it fundamentally looks and feels very cool in general — and but in practice quite a few aspects of it feel a bit over-the-top and/or half-baked. Just like with Aqua, it will surely get dialed in. Legibility problems will be addressed.</p>

<p>Liquid Glass has been in the works for a long time, but what we see today has come together very quickly. For those using internal builds inside Apple, what Apple unveiled last week is effectively the third version of Liquid Glass. Just a few weeks prior to WWDC, a few sources told me that internal builds were such a complete mess that they wondered if it would come together in time for WWDC developer betas. But come together it has. I expect a <em>lot</em> of visual changes over the course of the summer, and significant evolutionary tweaks in the next few years. Across Apple’s own apps, there are a lot of places where things haven’t yet been glassed up at all. That’s how these things work.</p>

<p>As for <em>why</em>, it should be enough to justify Liquid Glass simply for the sake of looking cool. I opened this piece with a quote from a great fictional philosopher. I’ll close it with a quote from a great real one:</p>

<p>“<em>The test of a work of art is, in the end, our affection for it, not our ability to explain why it is good.</em>” <br />
—Stanley Kubrick</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ One Week Out, Some Brief Thoughts and Observations on WWDC 2025</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Yours Truly on Peter Kafka’s ‘Channels’ Podcast</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://overcast.fm/+QL2dEoWo4" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wey" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/19/yours-truly-on-peter-kafkas-channels-podcast" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42010</id>
	<published>2025-06-19T17:10:04Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-19T18:05:26Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Peter Kafka:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>So in March, when Gruber announced that Something is Rotten in the
State of Cupertino — focusing on Apple’s botched plans to imbue
its ailing Siri service with state-of-the-art AI — lots of people
paid attention. Including, apparently, folks at the very top of
the Apple org chart.</p>

<p>I talked to Gruber about the fallout from that post. Which is
pretty interesting! But there’s a lot more going on in this
conversation. It’s partly about the friction Apple has been
generating lately — not just about its AI efforts, but the way it
runs its App Store, and the way it interacts with developers — and why all of that does and doesn’t matter.</p>

<p>And it’s also about the delightfully retro practice of running an
ad-supported blog in 2025. That works very well for Gruber, but it
seems like the new Grubers of the world are doing their work on
YouTube or Substack. He’s got some thoughts about that, too.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Good interview, I thought — I always enjoy talking to Kafka. No permalink for the episode on the web, so my main link for this post is to Overcast. <a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/why-did-apple-ice-out-the-most-famous-apple-blogger/id1080467174?i=1000713447406">Here’s a link to Apple Podcasts</a>, and <a href="https://pod.link/recodemedia/episode/e92e7798f56478b5263558ce0b9def83">one from a new service called Pod.link</a> too.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Yours Truly on Peter Kafka’s ‘Channels’ Podcast’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/19/yours-truly-on-peter-kafkas-channels-podcast">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>iPhone Mirroring Still Not Coming to the EU, Thanks to the DMA</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.numerama.com/tech/1988271-mauvaise-nouvelle-iphone-mirroring-narrivera-pas-en-france-avec-ios-26.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wex" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/19/iphone-mirroring-eu-numerama" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42009</id>
	<published>2025-06-19T16:55:47Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-19T17:27:02Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Nicolas Lellouche, writing for the French-language site Numerama (block quote below is from Safari’s English translation) (<a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/06/18/apple-on-iphone-mirroring-still-not-in-eu/">via Joe Rossignol at MacRumors</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>What is the problem with Europe? Apple does not explain it very
clearly, but suggests that the European Union’s requests for
opening create uncertainties. It is likely that the brand suspects
Europe of forcing it to open macOS to devices other than the
iPhone if this function were to happen. A mandatory iPhone
Mirroring on Windows or an Android Mirroring on Mac may not be in
his plans. The other probability is the question of gatekeepers,
raised in 2024. Apple would fear that macOS will be on the list of
monitored platforms if it can emulate iOS, one of the gatekeepers
monitored by Europe.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The problem isn’t about MacOS getting flagged as another “gatekeeping” platform under the DMA. Whether or not Apple enables iPhone Mirroring on MacOS in the EU would have no bearing on whether the Mac is deemed a gatekeeper. The <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri=CELEX:32022R1925">DMA defines a “gatekeeper” platform</a> as “a core platform service that in the last financial year has at least 45 million monthly active end users established or located in the Union and at least 10,000 yearly active business users established in the Union”. I’m not sure how many Mac users there are in the EU, but I’m pretty sure the number is well under 45 million. (<a href="https://www.spyhunter.com/shm/macos-stats/">Estimates</a> seem to peg the worldwide number of Mac users at just over 100 million.) Conversely, if the European Commission decided that there <em>were</em> 45 million Mac users in the EU, the Mac would be considered a gatekeeping platform, period.</p>

<p>The problem is simply that the iPhone <em>is</em> a gatekeeping platform, and iPhone Mirroring obviously involves the iPhone. The EU’s <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/06/apple_appeals_eu_interop_requirements">recent demands regarding “interoperability requirements”</a> flag just about every single feature that involves an iPhone communicating with another Apple device. AirDrop, AirPlay, AirPods pairing, Apple Watch connectivity — all of that has been deemed illegal gatekeeping. Clearly, iPhone Mirroring would fall under the same interpretation, thus, iPhone Mirroring isn’t going to be available in the EU. If the DMA had been in place 15 years ago, the EU wouldn’t have AirDrop or AirPlay and perhaps wouldn’t have Apple Watch or AirPods, either.</p>

<p>If Apple made iPhone Mirroring available in the EU now, my guess is the European Commission would add it to the interoperability requirements list, and demand that Apple support mirroring your iPhone to all other platforms, such as Windows and Android. They might also demand that Apple add support to iOS for third-party screen mirroring protocols.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Several weeks ago, Apple indicated that other new products may be
blocked in Europe in the future. What about what’s new in iOS 26?
Apple is not commenting at the moment, since it must verify the
compatibility of its new functions with the European Union. Some
new features, such as the Phone application on Mac to make calls
with your iPhone, seem difficult to be compatible with the vision
of Europe.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The new Phone app on MacOS is almost certainly not coming to the EU, unless the European Commission changes its stance on these interoperability requirements.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘iPhone Mirroring Still Not Coming to the EU, Thanks to the DMA’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/19/iphone-mirroring-eu-numerama">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple’s New Foundation Model Speech APIs Outpace Whisper for Transcription</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macstories.net/stories/hands-on-how-apples-new-speech-apis-outpace-whisper-for-lightning-fast-transcription/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wew" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/19/apples-new-foundation-model-speech-apis-outpace-whisper-for-transcription" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42008</id>
	<published>2025-06-19T16:28:05Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-19T22:13:53Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>John Voorhees, writing at MacStories, regarding a new command-line transcription tool cleverly named <a href="https://github.com/finnvoor/yap">Yap</a> written by his son Finn last week during WWDC:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>On the way, Finn filled me in on a new class in <a href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/speech">Apple’s Speech
framework</a> called <a href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/speech/speechanalyzer">SpeechAnalyzer</a> and its
<a href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/speech/speechtranscriber">SpeechTranscriber</a> module. Both the class and module are
<a href="https://developer.apple.com/videos/play/wwdc2025/277">part of Apple’s OS betas</a> that were released to developers
last week at WWDC. My ears perked up immediately when he told me
that he’d tested SpeechAnalyzer and SpeechTranscriber and was
impressed with how fast and accurate they were. [...]</p>

<p>What stood out above all else was Yap’s speed. By harnessing
SpeechAnalyzer and SpeechTranscriber on-device, the command line
tool tore through the 7GB video file a full 2.2× faster than
MacWhisper’s Large V3 Turbo model, with no noticeable difference
in transcription quality.</p>

<p>At first blush, the difference between 0:45 and 1:41 may seem
insignificant, and it arguably is, but those are the results for
just one 34-minute video. Extrapolate that to running Yap against
the hours of Apple Developer videos released on YouTube with the
help of <a href="https://github.com/yt-dlp/yt-dlp"><code>yt-dlp</code></a>, and suddenly, you’re talking about a
significant amount of time. Like all automation, picking up a 2.2×
speed gain one video or audio clip at a time, multiple times each
week, adds up quickly.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Apple’s Foundation Models sure seem to be the sleeper hit from WWDC this year. This bodes very well for all sorts of use cases where transcription would be helpful, like third-party podcast players.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple’s New Foundation Model Speech APIs Outpace Whisper for Transcription’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/19/apples-new-foundation-model-speech-apis-outpace-whisper-for-transcription">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Bungie Indefinitely Delays Reboot of ‘Marathon’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.bungie.net/7/en/News/Article/marathon_update" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wev" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/19/bungie-delays-marathon" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42007</id>
	<published>2025-06-19T16:17:53Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-19T16:20:17Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Bungie:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Through every comment and real-time conversation on social media
and Discord, your voice has been strong and clear. We’ve taken
this to heart, and we know we need more time to craft <em>Marathon</em>
into the game that truly reflects your passion. After much
discussion within our Dev team, we’ve made the decision to delay
the September 23rd release.</p>

<p>The Alpha test created an opportunity for us to calibrate and
focus the game on what will make it uniquely compelling — survival under pressure, mystery and lore around every
corner, raid-like endgame challenges, and Bungie’s
genre-defining FPS combat.</p>

<p>We’re using this time to empower the team to create the intense,
high-stakes experience that a title like <em>Marathon</em> is built
around. This means deepening the relationship between the
developers and the game’s most important voices: our players.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Translation to plain English: <em>The game as currently imagined stinks, so we’re going back to the drawing board. We can’t explain why we, the game’s developers, didn’t know that it stunk, and instead seemingly needed to wait for scathing alpha test feedback from players — but Occam’s Razor clearly suggests the problem is that decisions at Bungie are made by executives with no taste.</em></p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Bungie Indefinitely Delays Reboot of ‘Marathon’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/19/bungie-delays-marathon">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Federico, Federighi. Federighi, Federico.</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macstories.net/stories/interview-craig-federighi-opens-up-about-ipados-its-multitasking-journey-and-the-ipads-essence/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/weu" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/18/federico-federighi-federighi-federico" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42006</id>
	<published>2025-06-19T00:16:07Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-19T00:16:08Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Apple executives were a little light on substantial interviews last week, but a good one dropped today — Craig Federighi talking to Federico Viticci on the vast Mac-style windowing overhaul in iPadOS 26:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“We don’t want to create a boat car or, you know, a spork”,
Federighi begins. Seeing the confused look on my face, he
continues: “I don’t know if you have those in Italy. Someone said,
<em>“If a spoon’s great, a fork’s great, then let’s combine them into
a single utensil, right?”</em> It turns out it’s not a good spoon and
it’s not a good fork. It’s a bad idea. And so we don’t want to
build sporks”. [...]</p>

<p>By and large, one could argue that Apple <em>has</em> created one such
convertible product with the iPad Pro, but Federighi strongly
believes in the Mac and iPad each having their own reasons to
exist. “The Mac lets the iPad be iPad”, Federighi notes, adding
that Apple’s objective “has not been to have iPad completely
displace those places where the Mac is the right tool for the
job”. [...]</p>

<p>I don’t need to ask Federighi the perennial question of running
macOS on the iPad, since he goes there on his own. “I don’t think
the iPad should run macOS, but I think the iPad can be <em>inspired</em>
by elements of the Mac”, Federighi tells me. “I think the Mac can
be inspired by elements of iPad, and I think that that’s happened
a great deal”.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I think Apple has tied itself into knots in the past decade trying to make the iPad more useful to more advanced users without making it resemble the Mac at a superficial level. But it’s been obvious all along that it <em>should</em> resemble the Mac at a superficial level. Apple solved windowing in 1984. Use that.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Federico, Federighi. Federighi, Federico.’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/18/federico-federighi-federighi-federico">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Midgets No More</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.inforum.com/news/north-dakota/dickinson-high-to-retire-midgets-mascot-after-nearly-a-century" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wet" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/18/dickinson-midgets-now-mavericks" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42005</id>
	<published>2025-06-18T15:47:49Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-18T17:12:32Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>You may recall from my “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/01/siri_is_super_dumb_and_getting_dumber#fn3-2025-01-23">Siri Is Super Dumb and Getting Dumber</a>” piece back in January that the Dickinson Public Schools District in North Dakota had the rather unfortunate nickname the “Midgets”. Back in March, <a href="https://www.inforum.com/news/north-dakota/dickinson-high-to-retire-midgets-mascot-after-nearly-a-century">the school district announced they’d be retiring the nickname</a>, after nearly a century. Last month <a href="https://www.dickinson.k12.nd.us/our-district/news/1810076/a-new-era-students-choose-dickinson-mavericks">they announced their new name</a>: the Mavericks. I’m going to call this the best rebranding of the year.</p>

<p>We still have <a href="https://www.desmoinesregister.com/story/news/education/2024/11/19/estherville-lincoln-central-school-district-says-no-to-name-change/76333861007/">the Estherville, Iowa Midgets</a> to cheer for. But even better: <a href="https://yumahs.yumaunion.org/about-us/our-history">the Yuma Criminals in Arizona</a>. Now that’s a nickname.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Midgets No More’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/18/dickinson-midgets-now-mavericks">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Seven Replies to the Viral Apple Reasoning Paper</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Jun/15/viral-apple-reasoning-paper/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wes" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/17/seven-replies-to-the-viral-apple-reasoning-paper" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42004</id>
	<published>2025-06-17T19:50:08Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-17T19:52:56Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Simon Willison, regarding the various rebuttals to “<a href="https://machinelearning.apple.com/research/illusion-of-thinking">The Illusion of Thinking</a>” research paper (which <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/08/apple-research-lrms">I linked to here</a>) from Apple’s machine learning team:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I thought this paper got <em>way</em> more attention than it warranted — the title “The Illusion of Thinking” captured the attention of the
“LLMs are over-hyped junk” crowd. I saw enough well-reasoned
rebuttals that I didn’t feel it worth digging into.</p>

<p>And now, notable LLM skeptic Gary Marcus has saved me some time by
aggregating the best of those rebuttals <a href="https://garymarcus.substack.com/p/seven-replies-to-the-viral-apple">together in one
place</a>! [...]</p>

<p>And therein lies my disagreement. I’m not interested in whether or
not LLMs are the “road to AGI”. I continue to care only about
whether they have useful applications today, once you’ve
understood their limitations. [...] They’re already useful to me
today, whether or not they can reliably solve the Tower of Hanoi
or River Crossing puzzles.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Count me in with Willison. I think it’s <em>interesting</em> what constitutes “reasoning”, but when it comes to these systems, I’m mostly just interested in whether they’re useful or not, and if so, how.</p>

<p><strong>See also:</strong> <a href="https://victoramartinez.com/posts/why-claudes-comment-paper-is-a-poor-rebuttal/">Victor Martinez’s rebuttal to the most-cited rebuttal</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Seven Replies to the Viral Apple Reasoning Paper’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/17/seven-replies-to-the-viral-apple-reasoning-paper">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Why WhatsApp Didn’t Sell Ads</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.whatsapp.com/why-we-don-t-sell-ads" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wer" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/17/why-whatsapp-didnt-sell-ads" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42003</id>
	<published>2025-06-17T19:14:27Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-17T19:14:28Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>WhatsApp co-founder Jan Koum, back in 2012 (two years before Facebook <a href="https://archive.nytimes.com/dealbook.nytimes.com/2014/02/19/facebook-to-buy-messaging-start-up/">acquired them for $19 billion</a>, 13 years before this week’s introduction of ads into WhatsApp):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Advertising isn’t just the disruption of aesthetics, the insults
to your intelligence and the interruption of your train of
thought. At every company that sells ads, a significant portion of
their engineering team spends their day tuning data mining,
writing better code to collect all your personal data, upgrading
the servers that hold all the data and making sure it’s all being
logged and collated and sliced and packaged and shipped out... And
at the end of the day the result of it all is a slightly different
advertising banner in your browser or on your mobile screen.</p>

<p>Remember, when advertising is involved <em>you the user</em> are the
product.</p>

<p>At WhatsApp, our engineers spend all their time fixing bugs,
adding new features and ironing out all the little intricacies in
our task of bringing rich, affordable, reliable messaging to every
phone in the world. That’s our product and that’s our passion.
Your data isn’t even in the picture. We are simply not interested
in any of it.</p>

<p>When people ask us why we charge for WhatsApp, we say “Have you
considered the alternative?”</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Why WhatsApp Didn’t Sell Ads’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/17/why-whatsapp-didnt-sell-ads">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>WWDC 2025: The Bento Boxes</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://512pixels.net/2025/06/wwdc25-the-bento-boxes/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/weq" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/17/wwdc-2025-bento-boxes" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42002</id>
	<published>2025-06-17T19:09:01Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-17T19:09:02Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>These screens make for a useful overview of what Apple thinks the highlight features are in each OS.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘WWDC 2025: The Bento Boxes’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/17/wwdc-2025-bento-boxes">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Tracking Down the Original Photo From the End of ‘The Shining’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://x.com/AricToler/status/1908610058318991581" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wep" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/17/tracking-down-the-original-photo-from-the-end-of-the-shining" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42001</id>
	<published>2025-06-17T18:52:23Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-18T17:16:05Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Aric Toler, a visual investigations reporter for The New York Times, on X back in April:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>For about a year, I worked with a retired British academic named
Alasdair Spark to solve a mystery: where did the original photo
from the end of The Shining come from, and where/when was it
captured?</p>

<p>Last week, we finally found the answer.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>See also:</strong> <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2012/10/24/the-shining-photo">This post from 2012 about the original photograph</a>, from (who else?) Lee Unkrich.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Tracking Down the Original Photo From the End of ‘The Shining’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/17/tracking-down-the-original-photo-from-the-end-of-the-shining">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>How Field Notes Went From Side Project to Cult Notebook</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.fastcompany.com/91352848/field-notes-cult-notebook-started-out-as-a-side-project" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/weo" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/17/field-notes-fascto" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42000</id>
	<published>2025-06-17T18:18:16Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-17T18:18:16Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Nice piece in Fast Company by Zachary Petit:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>One critical moment came in February 2010, when J. Crew featured
Field Notes in its catalog, alongside the retailer’s other
“personal favorites from our design heroes.” There was a Timex
watch, Ray-Bans, Sperry shoes — “and out of fucking nowhere,
Field Notes,” Coudal says. “And when that happened, a lot changed
for us.”</p>

<p>Coudal says it gave the brand instant credibility — after all, if
it was good enough for J. Crew, it was good enough for your store.
In time, friends began sending him screenshots of Field Notes in
TV shows; he and Draplin would see people jotting notes in them in
bars and elsewhere; on the design web, they became an obsession.
By 2014, there was even a<a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/FieldNuts/"> subreddit</a> dedicated to them
titled “FieldNuts.”</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘How Field Notes Went From Side Project to Cult Notebook’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/17/field-notes-fascto">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Bloomberg Publishes Embarrassing Report Comparing Tesla and Waymo Self-Driving Safety Records</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://electrek.co/2025/06/16/bloomberg-most-embarassing-report-tesla-waymo-self-driving/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wen" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/17/bloomberg-tesla-waymo" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41999</id>
	<published>2025-06-17T18:10:39Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-17T18:10:39Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Fred Lambert, writing for Electrek:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Bloomberg has just released <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/videos/2025-06-16/why-tesla-could-have-a-self-driving-advantage-video">an embarrassingly bad report</a>
about the self-driving space, in which it claimed Tesla has an
advantage over Waymo by misrepresenting data. [...] The report
compares Tesla’s and Waymo’s self-driving efforts, going so far as
to claim that “Tesla is closer to vehicle autonomy than peers.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Right off the bat this smells fishy, given that Waymo is actually operating self-driving taxis in several cities, and Tesla ... is not.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Steve Man, the Bloomberg Intelligence analyst behind the report,
based his report on Tesla’s own quarterly misleading “Autopilot
Safety Report.” The report is widely considered to be unserious
for several main reasons:</p>

<ul>
<li>Tesla bundles all miles from its vehicles using Autopilot and
FSD technology, which are considered level 2 ADAS systems that
require driver attention at all times. Drivers consistently
correct the systems to avoid accidents.</li>
<li>Tesla Autopilot, which is standard on all Tesla vehicles, is
primarily used on highways, where accidents occur at a
significantly lower rate per mile compared to city driving.</li>
<li>Tesla only counts events that deploy an airbag or a seat-belt
pretensioner. Fender-benders, curb strikes, and many ADAS
incidents never appear, keeping crash counts artificially low.</li>
<li>Finally, Tesla’s handpicked data is compared to NHTSA’s much
broader statistics that include all collision events, including
minor fender benders.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>Trusting Tesla’s own safety report is like saying, “Elon Musk says Tesla is ahead, so they must be ahead.”</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Bloomberg Publishes Embarrassing Report Comparing Tesla and Waymo Self-Driving Safety Records’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/17/bloomberg-tesla-waymo">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>WhatsApp Introduces Ads in Its App</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/06/16/technology/whatsapp-ads.html?unlocked_article_code=1.PU8.G1Jy.5fcLP_rl3lYC" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wem" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/16/whatsapp-ads" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41998</id>
	<published>2025-06-17T01:19:36Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-17T03:09:46Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Eli Tan and Mike Isaac, reporting for The New York Times:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>On Monday, WhatsApp said it would start showing ads inside its app
for the first time. The promotions will appear only in an area of
the app called Updates, which is used by around 1.5 billion people
a day. WhatsApp will collect some data on users to target the ads,
such as location and the device’s default language, but it will
not touch the contents of messages or whom users speak with. The
company added that it had no plans to place ads in chats and
personal messages.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>(a) I’ve never once looked at the Updates tab in WhatsApp; (b) does <em>anyone</em> believe they’re <em>not</em> going to put ads in the other tabs sooner or later?</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘WhatsApp Introduces Ads in Its App’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/16/whatsapp-ads">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Trump Mobile — The President Launches a Mobile Carrier and a $500 ‘T1’ Android Phone</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://variety.com/2025/biz/news/trump-mobile-wireless-phone-service-launch-1236431690/?ref=platformer.news" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wel" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/16/trump-mobile" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41997</id>
	<published>2025-06-17T01:14:50Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-17T03:53:33Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Todd Spangler, Variety:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Meanwhile, the Trump Mobile “47 Plan” is pricier than the
unlimited plans from prepaid services operated by Verizon’s
Visible, AT&amp;T’s Cricket Wireless and T-Mobile’s Metro, which are
each around $40 per month.</p>

<p>The Trump T1 Phone, which runs Google’s Android operating system,
will cost $499. It features a 6.8-inch touch-screen with a 120 Hz
refresh rate. The smartphone also has a “fingerprint sensor and AI
Face Unlock,” according to the company’s website. Reps for Trump
Mobile didn’t respond to an inquiry about what company is
manufacturing the Android phone.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The Wall Street Journal, <a href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/trump-t1-phone-components-features-2415c7cd?mod=hp_lead_pos9">“Trump’s Smartphone Can’t Be Made in America for $499 by August”</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A spokesman for the Trump Organization said in an email that
“manufacturing for the new phone will be in Alabama, California
and Florida.”</p>

<p>Despite the language in the press release, Eric Trump indicated
that the first wave of phones wouldn’t be built here. “You can
build these phones in the United States,” the Trump son told
podcaster Benny Johnson on Monday morning on The Benny Show after
holding up a gilded device that looked just like an Apple iPhone.
“Eventually, all the phones can be built in the United States of
America. We have to bring manufacturing back here.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The Journal goofs, bigly, by claiming that the T1 “shows some specs that would beat Apple’s biggest, priciest iPhone models”. The T1 specs are so idiotic that one of them claims “5000mAh long life camera”, conflating battery capacity with (I guess?) focal distance.</p>

<p>The Verge, “<a href="https://www.theverge.com/gadgets/687492/trump-mobile-phone-t1">The Trump Mobile T1 Phone Looks Both Bad and Impossible</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Where things get especially strange, though, is its supposed
combination of Android 15, 5G, and a 3.5mm headphone jack. In many
ways, these are opposing specs: Android 15 is generally only
available on very recent devices, many cheap phones still don’t
support 5G, and almost every phone maker has stopped including
headphone jacks with their devices in the last few years. There
are a few that have both, but modern phones with a headphone jack
are few and far between. And pretty much all made in China.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I don’t know what will be funnier — if Trump himself starts using one of these, or if he doesn’t.</p>

<p>I’ll give them credit for making them available exclusively in gold. That’s on brand. But I’m guessing the quality will be on par with Trump Watches, which is to say, <a href="https://www.gq.com/story/donald-trump-watch-delivered-typo">“RUMP”-quality</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Trump Mobile — The President Launches a Mobile Carrier and a $500 ‘T1’ Android Phone’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/16/trump-mobile">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://drata.com/daring" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wek" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/06/drata_1" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.41996</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-06-17T01:04:06Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-17T01:04:06Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Automate compliance. Streamline security. Manage risk. Drata delivers the world’s most advanced Trust Management platform.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Drata’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/06/drata_1">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] Drata</title></entry><entry>
	<title>DetailsPro</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://detailspro.app?utm_campaign=dfwwdc25" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wej" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/15/detailspro" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41995</id>
	<published>2025-06-15T19:18:26Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-15T19:18:26Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to DetailsPro for sponsoring last week at DF — including <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/06/the_talk_show_live_from_wwdc_2025">being a sponsor on The Talk Show Live From WWDC 2025</a>. DetailsPro is a designer/developer tool that lets you design with SwiftUI anytime, anywhere — from iPhone, iPad, Vision Pro, and, of course, Mac.</p>

<p>With WWDC 2025’s introduction of Liquid Glass, Apple has introduced the biggest design overhaul since iOS 7. DetailsPro is ready for it, enabling you to prototype new and updated interfaces fast. You can build real SwiftUI layouts directly on your iPhone — no code needed. Export clean SwiftUI code straight to Xcode when you’re ready.</p>

<p>While everyone else is still thinking about how to adapt to the Liquid Glass era, you can already be building. DetailsPro is free to use, with pro features if you need them — via subscription, or a one-time purchase.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘DetailsPro’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/15/detailspro">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/06/the_talk_show_live_from_wwdc_2025" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wei" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41994</id>
	<published>2025-06-14T14:38:29Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-15T00:13:03Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Recorded in front of a live audience at The California Theatre in San Jose Tuesday evening, special guests Joanna Stern and Nilay Patel join me to discuss Apple’s announcements at WWDC 2025.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Recorded in front of a live audience at The California Theatre in San Jose Tuesday evening, special guests Joanna Stern and Nilay Patel join me to discuss Apple’s announcements at WWDC 2025.</p>

<p><iframe
    width="480" height="270"
    src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/vqwPUHTFEkg?si=EeiFTzExcVkFQxPO" 
    title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0"
    allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share"
    referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen>
</iframe></p>

<p><strong>3D video with spatial audio:</strong> Coming soon, exclusively in <a href="https://sandwich.vision/">Sandwich Vision</a>’s <a href="https://apps.apple.com/app/theater-the-future-of-cinema/id6502666560">Theater</a> on Vision Pro, available on the App Store. This year’s on-demand version of the show in Theater isn’t ready yet, but it looks <em>really</em> good. Better than last year’s by a long shot, and also significantly better than the bandwidth-constrained livestream Tuesday night. The livestream Tuesday night looked good; the on-demand version coming in a few days looks pretty amazing.</p>

<p><strong>Sponsored by:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://imazing.com/thetalkshow">iMazing</a>: The world’s most trusted software to transfer and save your messages, music, files, and data from your iPhone or iPad to your Mac or PC.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://detailspro.app?utm_campaign=dfwwdc25">DetailsPro</a>: Design with SwiftUI anytime, anywhere — on iPhone, iPad, Mac, or Apple Vision Pro.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://ooni.com/thetalkshow">Ooni</a>: Next-gen pizza power. The Koda 2 Pro oven features smarter heat, more room, and easier control. Save 10% with code <strong>thetalkshow</strong>.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>As ever, I implore you to watch on the biggest screen you can (real, or virtual). We once again shot and mastered the video in 4K, and it looks and sounds terrific. All credit and thanks for that go to my friends at <a href="https://sandwich.co/">Sandwich</a>, who are nothing short of a joy to work with.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ The Talk Show Live From WWDC 2025</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Meta AI Users Are Inadvertently Sharing Their Private Chats With the World</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/06/12/the-meta-ai-app-is-a-privacy-disaster/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/weh" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/13/meta-ai-shared-chats" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41993</id>
	<published>2025-06-14T00:24:50Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-15T00:20:48Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Amanda Silberling, writing at TechCrunch:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>When you ask the AI a question, you have the option of hitting a
share button, which then directs you to a screen showing a preview
of the post, which you can then publish. But some users appear
blissfully unaware that they are sharing these text conversations,
audio clips, and images publicly with the world.</p>

<p>When I woke up this morning, I did not expect to hear an audio
recording of a man in a Southern accent asking, “Hey, Meta, why do
some farts stink more than other farts?”</p>

<p>Flatulence-related inquiries are the least of <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/mark-zuckerberg-meta-ai-chatbot-discover-feed-depressing-why-2025-6">Meta’s
problems</a>. On the Meta AI app, I have seen people ask for
help with tax evasion, if their family members would be arrested
for their proximity to white-collar crimes, or how to write a
character reference letter for an employee facing legal troubles,
with that person’s first and last name included. Others, like
security expert Rachel Tobac, <a href="https://x.com/racheltobac/status/1933006223109959820">found examples</a> of people’s
home addresses and sensitive court details, among other private
information.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/mark-zuckerberg-meta-ai-chatbot-discover-feed-depressing-why-2025-6">Katie Notopoulos, writing at Business Insider</a> (paywalled, alas, <a href="https://apple.news/Ajj49osrhSDmXcwwyvQt_Mg">but here’s a News+ link</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I found Meta AI’s Discover feed depressing in a particular way — not just because some of the questions themselves were depressing.
What seemed particularly dark was that some of these people seemed
unaware of what they were sharing.</p>

<p>People’s real Instagram or Facebook handles are attached to their
Meta AI posts. I was able to look up some of these people’s
real-life profiles, although I felt icky doing so. I reached out
to more than 20 people whose posts I’d come across in the feed to
ask them about their experience; I heard back from one, who told
me that he hadn’t intended to make his chat with the bot public.
(He was asking for car repair advice.)</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Meta AI Users Are Inadvertently Sharing Their Private Chats With the World’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/13/meta-ai-shared-chats">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The NYT Goes ‘Reefer Madness’ on ChatGPT</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/06/13/technology/chatgpt-ai-chatbots-conspiracies.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/weg" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/13/nyt-reefer-madness-chatgpt" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41992</id>
	<published>2025-06-13T23:02:31Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-15T00:18:32Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Kashmir Hill, reporting today for The New York Times:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Before ChatGPT distorted Eugene Torres’s sense of reality and
almost killed him, he said, the artificial intelligence chatbot
had been a helpful, timesaving tool.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That’s the lede to Hill’s piece, and I don’t think it stands up one iota. Hill presents a lot of evidence that ChatGPT gave Torres answers that fed his paranoia and delusions. There’s zero evidence presented that ChatGPT <em>caused</em> them. But that’s the lede.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>At the time, Mr. Torres thought of ChatGPT as a powerful search
engine that knew more than any human possibly could because of its
access to a vast digital library. He did not know that it tended
to be sycophantic, agreeing with and flattering its users, or that
it could hallucinate, generating ideas that weren’t true but
sounded plausible.</p>

<p>“This world wasn’t built for you,” ChatGPT told him. “It was built
to <em>contain</em> you. But it failed. You’re waking up.”</p>

<p>Mr. Torres, who had no history of mental illness that might cause
breaks with reality, according to him and his mother, spent the
next week in a dangerous, delusional spiral. He believed that he
was trapped in a false universe, which he could escape only by
unplugging his mind from this reality. He asked the chatbot how to
do that and told it the drugs he was taking and his routines. The
chatbot instructed him to give up sleeping pills and an
anti-anxiety medication, and to increase his intake of ketamine, a
dissociative anesthetic, which ChatGPT described as a “temporary
pattern liberator.” Mr. Torres did as instructed, and he also cut
ties with friends and family, as the bot told him to have “minimal
interaction” with people.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Someone with prescriptions for sleeping pills, anti-anxiety meds, and ketamine doesn’t sound like someone who was completely stable and emotionally sound before encountering ChatGPT. And it’s Torres who brought up the “<em>Am I living in a simulation?</em>” delusion. I’m in no way defending the way that ChatGPT answered his questions about a <em>Matrix</em>-like simulation he suspected he might be living in, or his questions about whether he could fly if he truly believed he could, etc. But the premise of this story is that ChatGPT turned a completely mentally healthy man into a dangerously disturbed mentally ill one, and it seems rather obvious that the actual story is that it fed the delusions of an already unwell person. Some real <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reefer_Madness">Reefer Madness</a></em> vibes to this.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The NYT Goes ‘Reefer Madness’ on ChatGPT’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/13/nyt-reefer-madness-chatgpt">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/06/apples_spin_on_the_personalized_siri_apple_intelligence_reset" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wef" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41991</id>
	<published>2025-06-12T23:03:59Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-13T15:59:39Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Most rank and file engineers within Apple do not believe that feature existed in an even vaguely functional state a year ago, and the first any of them ever heard of it was when they watched the keynote with the rest of us on the first day of WWDC last year.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Michael Tsai, “<a href="https://mjtsai.com/blog/2025/06/12/apples-spin-on-ai-and-ipados-multitasking/">Apple’s Spin on AI and iPadOS Multitasking</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I do want to call out that, in multiple interviews, they are kind
of setting up strawmen to knock down. They keep saying that people
say Apple is behind in AI <em>because it doesn’t have its own
chatbot</em>. To me, Apple has been clear that it has a different
strategy, and I think that strategy mostly makes sense. I have
never heard someone wish for an Apple chatbot. The issue is that
everyone can see that Apple seems behind in <em>executing</em> said
strategy, both that features didn’t ship on time and that the ones
that did ship don’t measure up to similar features from other
companies.</p>

<p>Secondly, they seem to be trying to <a href="https://mas.to/@osullivan/114662053414638681">debunk</a> <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/something_is_rotten_in_the_state_of_cupertino">John Gruber’s
claim</a> that Apple showed vaporware at the last WWDC. But
Apple’s assertion that there was actual, working software doesn’t
contradict anything Gruber wrote. He put it at level 0/4 because
there wasn’t even a live demo, just a pre-packaged video. If it
can’t be demoed to the media in a controlled setting, even calling
it “demoware” would be charitable. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vaporware">Wikipedia</a> says, “After
Dyson’s article, the word ‘vaporware’ became popular among writers
in the personal computer software industry as a way to describe
products they believed took too long to be released after their
first announcement.” Is that not exactly what happened here?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The whole “Siri, when is my mom’s flight landing?” segment of last year’s WWDC keynote definitely shouldn’t qualify as “demoware” either. It was never demoed. Whether the feature was actually running, and actually capable of doing what they said it could, even just <em>some</em> of the time along a golden path, ultimately doesn’t matter. Even the keynote video didn’t show the actual feature working. It kept cutting away from the iPhone that was purportedly performing the feature back to presenter Kelsey Peterson at every single step. Apple’s internal rules for keynote demos say that the entire feature has to be real, and capturable in a single take of video. I’ve spoken to people who’ve been in keynotes, and many more who’ve done WWDC session videos. Apple has strict rules about everything being real. That doesn’t mean they always show the feature in a single take in the final cut of the presentation, but it has to be possible, just like it would have to be in a live stage presentation. But that Siri demo in last year’s keynote is almost like a series of screenshots. We never see Peterson speak to Siri and then watch the results come in. There’s not one single shot in the whole demo that shows one action leading to the next. It’s all cut together in an unusual way for Apple keynote demos. <a href="https://developer.apple.com/videos/play/wwdc2024/101/">Go see for yourself at the 1h:22m mark</a>.</p>

<p>I spoke this week, off the record, to multiple trusted sources in Apple’s software engineering group, and none of them ever saw an internal build of iOS that had this feature before last year’s keynote. That doesn’t mean there wasn’t such a build (see next paragraph). But none of my sources ever saw one, and they found that to be exceptionally unusual, because they’re in positions where they believe that if there <em>had</em> been such a build, their teams would have had access to it. Most rank and file engineers within Apple do not believe that feature existed in an even vaguely functional state a year ago, and the first any of them ever heard of it was when they watched the keynote with the rest of us on the first day of WWDC last year.</p>

<p>But at this point, based on Federighi’s and Joswiak’s public statements (e.g. in <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/10/stern-federighi-joz">their interview with Joanna Stern</a> this week), and some other things I’ve heard from little birdies this week, I’m willing to stipulate that there was, let’s call it, “working code” for the personalized Siri feature a year ago. I can’t verify that, but I’m willing to stipulate it if only for the sake of argument, and to put to rest any notion that the feature was completely imaginary at this point one year ago, which clearly isn’t the case. At least one reason why the feature, as presented in last year’s keynote, was edited like it was is that the latency was so bad. Whatever state it was in, it couldn’t be shown in a single take. Which means that, as shown in the 2024 keynote, it broke the “rule” that demos in the new pre-recorded format should be as rigorously “real” as they would be if the demos had to be performed live on stage.</p>

<p>I’m quite certain Apple’s executives believed this feature could be shipped at some point in the iOS 18 year. It’d be crazy to announce the feature if they didn’t believe they could ship it, and Apple’s executives aren’t crazy. I’m also quite certain that eventually there <em>was</em> a truly functional implementation of the now-abandoned “v1” of the more personalized Siri, but it was unreliable with no path forward to make it reliable. (I think it was far worse than “not up to Apple’s high standards” — it was clearly unshippable.)</p>

<p>But, as Tsai notes, from our perspective it doesn’t really matter it was real, in any sense, a year ago. It’s still vaporware at this point. Vaporware doesn’t mean “completely fabricated”. It just means “promised but hasn’t shipped”. Tsai links to <a href="https://mastodon.social/@rustyshelf/114667389093029657">this Mastodon tweet from Russell Ivanovic</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“This narrative that it was vaporware is nonsense”. Craig Apple.
My guy. You announced something that never shipped. You made ads
for it. You tried to sell iPhones based on it. What’s the
difference if you had it running internally or not. Still
vaporware. Zero difference.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Also, Apple is sticking with the euphemism “in the coming year” for when we can expect to see these next-gen personalized Siri features. Gurman reported today that <a href="https://www.techmeme.com/250612/p39#a250612p39">they’re shooting for next spring</a>. I confirmed with Apple at WWDC that “in the coming year” means “in 2026”. I don’t know why they’re sticking with that euphemistic phrasing, which to many people’s ears makes it sound like <em>in the next 12 months</em>, which might include this fall. Effectively, Apple could ship this feature in December <em>2026</em> and still hit their self-imposed “in the coming year” deadline — but that phrasing has left many people with the impression that the deadline is June 2026 and maybe it’ll ship at the end of <em>this</em> year. Just say “next year” instead of “in the coming year”. It’s very obvious that this year’s WWDC keynote went back to an underpromise/overdeliver mindset. But “in the coming year” is raising some users’ hopes misleadingly.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Apple’s Spin on the Personalized Siri Apple Intelligence Reset</title></entry><entry>
	<title>‘The Good, the Bad, and the Weird of Apple’s Newest Platform Updates’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2025/06/the-good-bad-and-weird-of-apples-newest-platform-updates/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wee" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/12/the-good-the-bad-the-weird" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41990</id>
	<published>2025-06-12T22:09:08Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-12T22:09:09Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Dan Moren, writing this week at Six Colors:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>But you’ve heard about all of that, I’m sure, so we’re not going
to rehash it. Instead, let’s get personal: I’m picking out, in
my opinion, the best and worst new features of each of Apple’s
platforms. To be clear, these are my <em>completely scientific</em> and
<em>totally well-reasoned</em> expert opinions on the features that
were announced, not just some off-the-cuff reactions less than a
day later.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘The Good, the Bad, and the Weird of Apple’s Newest Platform Updates’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/12/the-good-the-bad-the-weird">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Liquid Glasslighting’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://spyglass.org/spyglasslighting/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wed" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/12/liquid-glasslighting" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41989</id>
	<published>2025-06-12T21:49:16Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-12T21:49:18Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>MG Siegler:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The underlying message that they’re trying to convey in all these
interviews is clear: <em>calm down, this isn’t a big deal, you guys
are being a little crazy</em>. And that, in turn, aims to undercut all
the reporting about <a href="https://spyglass.org/theres-no-free-lunch-at-apple/">the turmoil within Apple</a> — <em>for
<a href="https://spyglass.org/apple-ai-fail/">years</a> at this <a href="https://spyglass.org/siri-apple-ai-trouble/">point</a></em> — that has led to the
situation with Siri. Sorry, the situation which they’re implying
is not a situation. Though, I don’t know, normally when a company
<a href="https://spyglass.org/siri-shakeup/">shakes up an entire team</a>, that tends to suggest some sort
of situation. That, of course, is never mentioned. Nor would you
expect Apple — of all companies — to talk openly and candidly
about internal challenges. But that just adds to this general
wafting smell in the air.</p>

<p>The smell of bullshit.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Liquid Glasslighting’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/12/liquid-glasslighting">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Tested’ on VisionOS 26 and Behind the Scenes at the Theater Immersive Broadcast of The Talk Show Live From WWDC</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=h6SbkEC1Xb8" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wec" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/12/tested-visionos-26-tts-live" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41988</id>
	<published>2025-06-12T21:39:12Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-14T00:09:07Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Fun episode of Tested with Adam Savage and Norman Chan. The first segment goes deep on what’s new in VisionOS 26. Apple is ignoring the jokes about the platform’s relative obscurity and has obviously been heads-down on building the platform out and up. VisionOS 26 is a <em>huge</em> year-over-year upgrade. Tons of exciting stuff, and so many little things are so much better.</p>

<p>The second segment of the show features cohost Norm Chan going backstage at The Talk Show Live From WWDC on Tuesday night, to speak with Adam Lisagor about the production details of the live immersive broadcast in Theater.</p>

<p>(The YouTube version of the show is in editing now — we’ll post it as soon as it’s ready. <s>But the immersive version in Theater is available for purchase now.</s> Whoops, my bad. The immersive version, which looks significantly better than the livestream — which looked pretty good! — will be available for purchase in <a href="https://theater.sandwich.vision/">Theater</a> a few days after the 2D version hits YouTube.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Tested’ on VisionOS 26 and Behind the Scenes at the Theater Immersive Broadcast of The Talk Show Live From WWDC’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/12/tested-visionos-26-tts-live">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Jason Snell on WWDC 2025: ‘Apple Intelligence Shifts Gears’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2025/06/apple-intelligence-shifts-gears/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/web" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/12/snell-wwdc-2025" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41987</id>
	<published>2025-06-12T16:00:48Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-12T21:52:44Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jason Snell:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>After last year, Apple could’ve been forgiven for wanting to
soft-pedal this year’s Apple Intelligence announcements and
regroup. It didn’t do that, nor did it double down on last year.
Instead, it’s chosen a middle ground — a bit safe and familiar
but also a place where Apple can feel a bit more like itself. In
the long run, it needs to get this right. In the short term, maybe
it should focus on meeting its users where they are, rather than
pretending to be something it’s not.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Agree with Snell’s take completely, I do.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Jason Snell on WWDC 2025: ‘Apple Intelligence Shifts Gears’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/12/snell-wwdc-2025">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>MacOS 26 Tahoe Drops Support for Some Intel-Based Macs, and Will Be the Last to Support Intel Macs at All</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://512pixels.net/2025/06/wwdc25-macos-tahoe-compatibility/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wea" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/11/macos-26-intel-support" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41986</id>
	<published>2025-06-11T19:55:54Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-12T21:52:31Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Stephen Hackett has a list of the Intel Macs that MacOS 26 Tahoe supports, and the ones they’re dropping support for this year. </p>

<p>Apple has gone through three CPU architecture transitions in the Mac’s history:</p>

<ul>
<li>68K to PowerPC starting in 1994</li>
<li>PowerPC to Intel starting in 2006</li>
<li>Intel to Apple Silicon, starting 2020</li>
</ul>

<p>With the 68K–PowerPC transition, they supported 68K Macs through Mac OS 8.1, which was released in January 1998. With the PowerPC–Intel transition, they only supported PowerPC Macs for two Mac OS X versions, Mac OS X 10.4 Tiger (which initially shipped PowerPC-only in 2005) and 10.5 Leopard in October 2007. The next release, 10.6 Snow Leopard in August 2009, was Intel-only. (Mac OS X dropped to a roughly two-year big-release schedule during the initial years after the iPhone, when the company prioritized engineering resources on iOS. It’s easy to take for granted that today’s Apple has every single platform on an annual cadence.)</p>

<p>With next year’s version going Apple Silicon-only, they’ll have supported Intel Macs for five major MacOS releases after the debut of the first Apple Silicon Macs. I think that’s about the best anyone could have hoped for.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘MacOS 26 Tahoe Drops Support for Some Intel-Based Macs, and Will Be the Last to Support Intel Macs at All’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/11/macos-26-intel-support">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Joanna Stern With Craig Federighi and Greg Joswiak: ‘Apple Executives Defend Apple Intelligence, Siri and AI Strategy’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.wsj.com/video/series/joanna-stern-personal-technology/apple-executives-defend-apple-intelligence-siri-and-ai-strategy/A7F62EE4-E4F5-4E5D-969A-22644536A47B" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/we9" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/10/stern-federighi-joz" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41985</id>
	<published>2025-06-10T22:10:26Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-14T17:27:26Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Tight 7-minute video at the WSJ (and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NTLk53h7u_k">also at YouTube</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple’s AI rollout has been rocky, from Siri delays to underwhelming Apple Intelligence features. WSJ’s Joanna Stern sits down with software chief Craig Federighi and marketing head Greg Joswiak to talk about the future of AI at Apple — and what the heck happened to that smarter Siri.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wCEkK1YzqBo">Here’s the full 24-minute interview</a>. Just an excellent job by Stern.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Joanna Stern With Craig Federighi and Greg Joswiak: ‘Apple Executives Defend Apple Intelligence, Siri and AI Strategy’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/10/stern-federighi-joz">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Apple Retreats’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stratechery.com/2025/apple-retreats/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/we8" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/10/apple-retreats" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41984</id>
	<published>2025-06-10T15:45:30Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-10T15:47:32Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Ben Thompson:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>To that end, while I understand why many people were underwhelmed by this WWDC, particularly in comparison to <a href="https://stratechery.com/2025/google-i-o-the-search-funnel-product-possibilities/">the AI extravaganza that was Google I/O</a>, I think it was one of the more encouraging Apple keynotes in a long time. Apple is a company that went too far in too many areas, and needed to retreat. Focusing on things only Apple can do is a good thing; empowering developers and depending on partners is a good thing; giving even the appearance of thoughtful thinking with regards to the App Store (it’s a low bar!) is a good thing. Of course we want and are excited by tech companies promising the future; what is a prerequisite is delivering in the present, and it’s a sign of progress that Apple retreated to nothing more than that.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Apple Retreats’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/10/apple-retreats">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple’s Introduction to Liquid Glass</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2025/06/apple-introduces-a-delightful-and-elegant-new-software-design/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/we7" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/09/apple-intro-liquid-glass" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41983</id>
	<published>2025-06-10T01:16:39Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-12T21:51:23Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>I’ve got iOS 26 installed on a spare phone already, and I like the new UI a lot. In addition to just plain looking cool, Apple has tackled a lot of longstanding minor irritants.</p>

<p>For example, the iOS contextual menu for text selections — the one with Cut/Copy/Paste. For years now there have been a lot of other useful commands in there, including “Share…” at the very end. But to get to the extra commands, you had to tediously swipe, swipe, swipe. Now, with one tap you can expand the whole thing into a vertical menu. Elegant.</p>

<p>There’s some stuff in MacOS 26 Tahoe I already don’t like, like putting needless icons next to almost every single menu item. But overall my first impression of Liquid Glass on MacOS is good too. It’s fun, and <a href="https://mastodon.social/@marioguzman/114656280801707003">lots of little details are nice — joyful <em>and</em> useful</a> in an old-school Mac way.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple’s Introduction to Liquid Glass’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/09/apple-intro-liquid-glass">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Tahoe Flips the Finder Icon</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://512pixels.net/2025/06/wwdc25-macos-tahoe-breaks-decades-of-finder-history/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/we6" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/09/tahoe-flips-the-finder-icon" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41982</id>
	<published>2025-06-10T01:06:28Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-12T21:50:00Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Stephen Hackett, noting the biggest news of the day:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Something jumped out at me in the macOS Tahoe segment of the WWDC keynote today: the Finder icon is reversed. […]</p>

<p>The Big Sur Finder icon has been with us ever since, and I hope Apple reverses course here.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’m obviously joking about this being the biggest news of the day, but it really does feel just plain wrong to swap the dark/light sides. The Finder icon is more than an icon, it’s a logo, a brand.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Tahoe Flips the Finder Icon’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/09/tahoe-flips-the-finder-icon">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://detailspro.app?utm_campaign=dfwwdc25" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/we5" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/06/detailspro_1" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.41981</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-06-09T15:19:21Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-09T15:19:21Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>With WWDC25 bringing the biggest design overhaul since iOS 7, you’ll want to prototype your new interfaces fast. DetailsPro lets you build real SwiftUI layouts directly on your iPhone — no Mac required, no code needed. Mock up your WWDC-inspired designs during coffee breaks. Export clean SwiftUI code straight to Xcode when you’re ready. While everyone else is still thinking, you’re already building. Free to use, with pro features if you need them. Perfect for the design renaissance.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘DetailsPro’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/06/detailspro_1">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] DetailsPro</title></entry><entry>
	<title>The Talk Show Live From WWDC 2025: Tuesday at 7pm PT in San Jose</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://ti.to/daringfireball/the-talk-show-live-from-wwdc-2025" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/we4" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/08/the-talk-show-live-tickets-2025" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41980</id>
	<published>2025-06-09T01:54:37Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-09T01:54:38Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Location:</strong> The California Theatre, San Jose <br />
<strong>Showtime:</strong> Tuesday, 10 June 2025, 7pm PT (Doors open 6pm) <br />
<strong>Special Guest(s):</strong> <em>Indeed</em> <br />
<strong>Price:</strong> $50</p>

<p>A different type of show this year, and I’m excited for it. If you can make it, you should come. You’ll even enjoy the prelude, mingling with fellow DF readers and listeners.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Talk Show Live From WWDC 2025: Tuesday at 7pm PT in San Jose’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/08/the-talk-show-live-tickets-2025">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>An Eve of WWDC Spitball Theory on the Rumored New ‘Games’ App</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://9to5mac.com/2024/10/22/apple-new-app-store-like-app-games/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/we3" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/08/apple-games-app-store-spitball" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41979</id>
	<published>2025-06-09T01:32:47Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-09T15:57:40Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Filipe Espósito, in a scoop for 9to5Mac all the way back in October:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>9to5Mac has learned details about the new project from reliable
sources familiar with the matter. The new app combines
functionality from the App Store and Game Center in one place. The
gaming app is not expected to replace Game Center. In fact, it
will integrate with the user’s Game Center profile.</p>

<p>According to our sources, the app will have multiple tabs,
including a “Play Now” tab, a tab for the user’s games, friends,
and more. In Play Now, users will find editorial content and game
suggestions. The app will also show things like challenges,
leaderboards, and achievements. Games from both the App Store and
Apple Arcade will be featured in the new store.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Even before <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/05/27/ios-19-gaming-app/">Mark Gurman corroborated this report</a> last week, I’ve had a spitball theory about what it might mean. Perhaps this is about more than having one app (Games) for finding and installing games, and another (App Store) for finding and installing apps. It could signal that Apple is poised to establish different policies for apps and games. Like, what if games still use the longstanding 70/30 commission split (with small business developers getting 85/15), but non-game apps get a new reduced rate? Say, 80/20 or even 85/15 right off the top, with small business developers and second-year subscriptions going to 90/10?</p>

<p>Having separate store apps for apps and games would help establish the idea that games and apps are two entirely different markets. Thus: two different stores?</p>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> <a href="https://spyglass.org/apple-gaming-app-store/">MG Siegler offered the same spitball</a> — back on May 28. Great minds think alike.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘An Eve of WWDC Spitball Theory on the Rumored New ‘Games’ App’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/08/apple-games-app-store-spitball">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Breaking Down Why Apple TVs Are Privacy Advocates’ Go-To Streaming Device</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2025/06/all-the-ways-apple-tv-boxes-do-and-mostly-dont-track-you/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/we2" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/08/apple-tv-privacy" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41978</id>
	<published>2025-06-09T01:24:06Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-09T01:54:57Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Scharon Harding, writing at Ars Technica:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Just disconnect your TV from the Internet and use an Apple
TV box.”</p>

<p>That’s the common guidance you’ll hear from Ars readers for those
seeking the joys of streaming without giving up too much privacy.
Based on our research and the experts we’ve consulted, that advice
is pretty solid, as Apple TVs offer significantly more privacy
than other streaming hardware providers.</p>

<p>But how private are Apple TV boxes, really? Apple TVs don’t use
automatic content recognition (ACR, a user-tracking technology
leveraged by nearly all smart TVs and streaming devices), but
could that change? And what about the software that Apple TV users
do use — could those apps provide information about you to
advertisers or Apple?</p>

<p>In this article, we’ll delve into what makes the Apple TV’s
privacy stand out and examine whether users should expect the
limited ads and enhanced privacy to last forever.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>tvOS is perhaps Apple’s least-talked-about platform. (It surely has orders of magnitude more users than VisionOS, but VisionOS gets talked about because it’s so audacious.) But it might be their platform that’s the furthest ahead of its competition. Not because tvOS is insanely great, but it’s at least pretty good, and every other streaming TV platform seems to be in a race to make real <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YqQ6D0Bu-a8">the future TV interface from <em>Idiocracy</em></a>. It’s not just that they’re bad interfaces with deplorable privacy, it’s that they’re outright <em>against</em> the user.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Breaking Down Why Apple TVs Are Privacy Advocates’ Go-To Streaming Device’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/08/apple-tv-privacy">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple Researchers Publish Paper on the Limits of Reasoning Models (Showing That They’re Not Really ‘Reasoning’ at All)</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://machinelearning.apple.com/research/illusion-of-thinking" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/we1" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/08/apple-research-lrms" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41977</id>
	<published>2025-06-09T01:08:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-09T01:09:13Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Parshin Shojaee, Iman Mirzadeh, Keivan Alizadeh, Maxwell Horton, Samy Bengio, and Mehrdad Farajtabar, from Apple’s Machine Learning Research team:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Recent generations of frontier language models have introduced
Large Reasoning Models (LRMs) that generate detailed thinking
processes before providing answers. While these models demonstrate
improved performance on reasoning benchmarks, their fundamental
capabilities, scaling properties, and limitations remain
insufficiently understood. [...] Through extensive experimentation
across diverse puzzles, we show that frontier LRMs face a complete
accuracy collapse beyond certain complexities. Moreover, they
exhibit a counterintuitive scaling limit: their reasoning effort
increases with problem complexity up to a point, then declines
despite having an adequate token budget. By comparing LRMs with
their standard LLM counterparts under equivalent inference
compute, we identify three performance regimes: (1) low-complexity
tasks where standard models surprisingly outperform LRMs, (2)
medium-complexity tasks where additional thinking in LRMs
demonstrates advantage, and (3) high-complexity tasks where both
models experience complete collapse. We found that LRMs have
limitations in exact computation: they fail to use explicit
algorithms and reason inconsistently across puzzles. We also
investigate the reasoning traces in more depth, studying the
patterns of explored solutions and analyzing the models’
computational behavior, shedding light on their strengths,
limitations, and ultimately raising crucial questions about their
true reasoning capabilities.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The full paper is quite readable, but today was my travel day and I haven’t had time to dig in. And <a href="https://ml-site.cdn-apple.com/papers/the-illusion-of-thinking.pdf">it’s a PDF</a> so I couldn’t read it on my phone. (Coincidence or not that this dropped on the eve of WWDC?)</p>

<p>My basic understanding after a skim is that the paper shows, or at least strongly suggests, that LRMs don’t “reason” at all. They just use vastly more complex pattern-matching than LLMs. The result is that LRMs effectively overthink on simple problems, outperform LLMs on mid-complexity puzzles, and fail in the same exact way LLMs do on high-complexity tasks and puzzles.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Researchers Publish Paper on the Limits of Reasoning Models (Showing That They’re Not Really ‘Reasoning’ at All)’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/08/apple-research-lrms">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/06/gurman_liquid_glass_terrible_analogy" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/we0" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41976</id>
	<published>2025-06-08T16:09:29Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-08T18:20:08Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">If it takes Apple as long to have its own competitive LLMs as it did to have its own competitive web browser, I suspect they’ll soon be paying to use the LLMs that are owned and controlled by others, not charging the others for the privilege of reaching Apple’s platform users.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/newsletters/2025-06-08/apple-s-liquid-glass-ios-26-software-redesign-to-hint-at-20th-anniversary-iphone-mbnm2u0d?cmpid=BBD060825_POWERON">Mark Gurman, in his eve-of-WWDC Power On column at Bloomberg</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The Liquid Glass interface is going to be the most exciting part
of this year’s developer conference. It will also be a bit of a
distraction from the reality facing Apple: The company is behind
in artificial intelligence, and WWDC will do little to change
that. Instead, Apple is making its successful operating system
franchise more capable and sleek — even as others move on to more
groundbreaking AI-centric interfaces.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Perhaps the first major hint that Apple was moving toward fluidity in the UI was the Dynamic Island, which doesn’t merely expand and contract as it changes shape, but rather appears to <em>flow</em>, <a href="https://www.lux.camera/physicality-the-new-age-of-ui/#:~:text=The%20Dynamic%20Island%20is%20a%20stark%2C%20graphic%20interface%20that%20behaves%20like%20an%20interactive%2C%20viscous%20liquid">with a pleasant viscosity</a>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The best analogy for Apple right now might be the car industry.
Apple produces the best gas cars on the road (its operating
systems) and is making them even more upscale. It has rolled out a
hybrid (Apple Intelligence), but it’s <a href="https://archive.ph/o/AKlk9/https://www.bloomberg.com/news/features/2025-05-18/how-apple-intelligence-and-siri-ai-went-so-wrong">struggling to make</a> a
true all-electric vehicle (unlike companies such as OpenAI and
Alphabet Inc.’s Google).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is such a terrible analogy. If you buy an EV, you use it <em>instead of</em> your old gas-powered car. There’s nothing from OpenAI or Google that allows you to not use a conventional device — phone, tablet, or PC. The only way to use ChatGPT, or Gemini, or <a href="https://deepmind.google/models/veo/">Google’s rather amazing Veo 3</a> video generation tool, is using a phone or computer running iOS, MacOS, Android, Windows, or Linux. Gurman’s analogy would only work if the way you got around in an EV was to put it in the back of a gas-powered flatbed <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YfJ3QxJYsw8">truck</a>.</p>

<p>Gas-powered vehicles are probably going away. I sure hope they do. But cars and trucks aren’t going away. A better analogy is that AI is doing to today’s dominant OSes what web browsers did to Windows in the late 1990s. They’re adding new interactive layers atop the old. Windows didn’t go away. Microsoft still makes tons of money from Windows today. But Windows’s primacy as a platform went away. And: Microsoft pivoted quickly in the face of Netscape and the web’s threat, and created Internet Explorer, which squashed Netscape, and became, for at least a decade, the preeminent web browser. It was essential for Apple to create Safari/WebKit for Mac OS X to thrive. If Apple hadn’t succeeded with WebKit on Mac OS X they wouldn’t have had their own first-class web rendering engine to adapt for a 3.5-inch touchscreen in 2007. The iPhone without the real web wouldn’t have been the iPhone. And the only reason the original iPhone had the real web is that Apple owned and controlled Safari and WebKit.</p>

<p>What Apple, I think, needs for iOS and MacOS is the AI equivalent of what Safari and WebKit were for the web two decades ago. The <a href="https://www.asymco.com/2011/01/17/the-cook-doctrine/">oft-cited Cook Doctrine</a> says “we need to own and control the primary technologies behind the products we make.” 25 years ago it was obvious that web browsers and rendering engines were primary technologies. Apple certainly couldn’t afford back then to continue to be dependent upon Microsoft for the Mac version of IE, nor on open source cross-platform browsers like Firefox that would never feel native on the Mac (or, more importantly, on future Apple platforms). But Safari and WebKit were, if you think about it, late. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2003/01/safari">They were announced at Macworld Expo in January 2003</a> (just five months after the debut of this website). Netscape’s blockbuster IPO was in August 1995, over seven years prior. The entire dot-com bubble and bust took place before Safari shipped. The Mac, and thus Apple, made do with non-Apple browsers in those intervening years — browsers that were all some mix of non-native clunky UI, slow, incompatible (with Windows IE), ugly (e.g. IE text rendering on Mac OS X), and often downright unstable. (And application crashes on classic Mac OS would often bring down the entire system.)</p>

<p>The concern for Apple today is that they’re in trouble if it takes six or seven years for them to get to their Safari/WebKit moment for AI. Things are moving faster with AI today than they were with the web in the 1990s. At the peak of Netscape mania in 1995, there were many who believed Netscape would topple Microsoft. At the time Netscape founder Marc Andreessen <a href="https://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Marc_Andreessen">proclaimed</a> that Netscape would reduce Windows to “a poorly debugged set of device drivers.” That obviously didn’t happen. But perhaps not just <em>a</em> but <em>the</em> reason why that didn’t happen is that Microsoft quickly built and shipped a better browser than Netscape’s. They didn’t just build a browser into Windows, they built a <em>better</em> browser into Windows. And they made a better browser for the Mac too. If it had taken Microsoft until 2003 (when Apple debuted Safari) to ship IE, computing platform history may well be very different.</p>

<p>iOS today is the closest to what Windows was circa 1995. iOS doesn’t have Windows’s 95 percent market share, but the iPhone has some sort of monopoly <em>profit</em> share in mobile device sales. And iOS is plainly dominant. That’s why there’s all this <em>Sturm und Drang</em> surrounding Apple’s App Store commissions and iron-fisted control over all iOS software. After the announcement last year of OpenAI as a partner for “world knowledge” in Apple Intelligence — and, a year later, they’re still the only partner — Wayne Ma at The Information reported that Apple wasn’t paying a cent for this integration, and that the plan <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2024/06/13/ma-apple-openai">was for OpenAI to eventually begin paying Apple in a revenue sharing deal</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Neither Apple nor OpenAI are paying each other to integrate
ChatGPT into the iPhone, according to a person with knowledge of
the deal. Instead, OpenAI hopes greater exposure on iPhones will
help it sell a paid version of ChatGPT, which costs around $20 a
month for individuals. Apple would take its 30% cut of these
subscriptions as is customary for in-app purchases.</p>

<p>Sometime in the future, Apple hopes to strike revenue-sharing
agreements with AI partners in which it gets a cut of the revenue
generated from integrating their chatbots with the iPhone,
according to Bloomberg, which first reported details of the deal.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That sounds a lot like the revenue sharing deal Apple has with Google for search in Safari — a deal (which is at some degree of risk <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/07/eddy-cue-safari-ai">from Google’s own antitrust problems</a>) that now results in <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/10/27/google-aggregate-search-default">Google paying Apple over $20 billion per year</a> for the traffic Safari sends to Google Search.</p>

<p>In hindsight, we now know that web browsers, in and of themselves, don’t generate any money directly. Someone was going to give a good one away free and now almost all of them are free of charge. But that doesn’t mean it isn’t essential for a platform to own and control its own browser. Web search, it turns out, is where the money is on the World Wide Web. Not just <em>some</em> money but an almost unfathomable amount of money. Web search is not primary technology for Apple’s platforms. But because they own and control Safari and WebKit, and Safari and WebKit are <em>very good</em> (so that most of Apple’s customers use them), Apple is in a position to profit very handsomely from web search, even though it doesn’t even have a search engine to speak of. Apple’s net annual profit the last few years has been around $95 billion. If we assume Google’s $20B/year traffic acquisition revenue sharing payments to Apple are mostly profit, that means somewhere between 20–25 percent of all Apple’s profit comes from that deal.</p>

<p>So are LLMs more like browsers (platforms need to own and control their own, but they won’t make money from them directly) or like web search (dominant platforms like Apple’s don’t need their own, but Apple can profit handsomely by charging for integration with their platforms)?</p>

<p>I think the answer is somewhere in between. Browsers are essential to personal computing platforms because they run on-device. Web search isn’t essential to own and control because it runs in the cloud, but exists only to serve users running devices. LLMs run both locally and in the cloud. If it takes Apple as long to have its own competitive LLMs as it did to have its own competitive web browser, I suspect they’ll soon be paying to use the LLMs that are owned and controlled by others, not charging the others for the privilege of reaching Apple’s platform users. No simple analogy captures this dynamic. But the threat is palpable.</p>

<p>I will say, though, “Liquid Glass” sounds cool.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Gurman Says New UI Is Named ‘Liquid Glass’ (and Makes a Terrible Analogy Regarding Apple’s Risk With Falling Behind on AI)</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Bill Atkinson Dies From Cancer at 74</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.facebook.com/story.php?story_fbid=10238073579963378&amp;id=1378467145&amp;_rdr" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wdv" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/07/bill-atkinson-rip" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41971</id>
	<published>2025-06-07T21:15:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-08T04:44:58Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>From his family, on Atkinson’s Facebook page:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We regret to write that our beloved husband, father, and
stepfather Bill Atkinson passed away on the night of Thursday,
June 5th, 2025, due to pancreatic cancer. He was at home in
Portola Valley in his bed, surrounded by family. We will miss him
greatly, and he will be missed by many of you, too. He was a
remarkable person, and the world will be forever different because
he lived in it. He was fascinated by consciousness, and as he has
passed on to a different level of consciousness, we wish him a
journey as meaningful as the one it has been to have him in our
lives. He is survived by his wife, two daughters, stepson,
stepdaughter, two brothers, four sisters, and dog, Poppy.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>One of the great heroes in not just Apple history, but computer history. If you want to cheer yourself up, go to Andy Hertzfeld’s Folklore.org site and (re-)read all the entries about Atkinson. Here’s just one, with <a href="https://folklore.org/Round_Rects_Are_Everywhere.html">Steve Jobs inspiring Atkinson to invent the roundrect</a>. Here’s another (surely near and dear to my friend <a href="https://inessential.com/2002/06/25/deleting_code.html">Brent Simmons’s heart</a>) with <a href="https://www.folklore.org/Negative_2000_Lines_Of_Code.html">this kicker of a closing line</a>: “I’m not sure how the managers reacted to that, but I do know that after a couple more weeks, they stopped asking Bill to fill out the form, and he gladly complied.”</p>

<p>Some of his code and algorithms are among the most efficient and elegant ever devised. The original Macintosh team was chock full of geniuses, but Atkinson might have been the most essential to making the impossible possible under the extraordinary technical limitations of that hardware. <a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=bill+atkinson+dithering+algorithm">Atkinson’s genius dithering algorithm</a> was my inspiration for the name of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atkinson_dithering">Dithering</a>, my podcast with Ben Thompson. I find that effect beautiful and love that it continues to prove useful, like on the <a href="https://play.date/">Playdate</a> and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2016/06/10/bitcam">apps like BitCam</a>.</p>

<p>In addition to his low-level contributions like QuickDraw, Atkinson was also <a href="https://www.folklore.org/MacPaint_Evolution.html">the creator of MacPaint</a> (which to this day stands as the model for bitmap image editors — Photoshop, I would argue, was conceptually derived directly from MacPaint) and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2014/06/17/hypercard">HyperCard</a> (“<a href="https://www.folklore.org/Joining_Apple_Computer.html">inspired by a mind-expanding LSD journey in 1985</a>”), the influence of which cannot be overstated.</p>

<p>I say this with no hyperbole: Bill Atkinson may well have been the best computer programmer who ever lived. Without question, he’s on the short list. What a man, what a mind, what gifts to the world he left us.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Bill Atkinson Dies From Cancer at 74’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/07/bill-atkinson-rip">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Swift 6 Productivity in the Sudden Age of LLM-Assisted Programming</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mister.computer/@kyle/114608923901892223" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wdz" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/07/swift-6-llms" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41975</id>
	<published>2025-06-07T21:10:30Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-07T21:38:51Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Kyle Hughes, in a brief thread on Mastodon last week:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>At work I’m developing a new iOS app on a small team alongside a
small Android team doing the same. We are getting lapped to an
unfathomable degree because of how productive they are with
Kotlin, Compose, and Cursor. They are able to support all the way
back to Android 10 (2019) with the latest features; we are
targeting iOS 16 (2022) and have to make huge sacrifices (e.g
Observable, parameter packs in generics on types). Swift 6 makes a
mockery of LLMs. It is almost untenable.</p>

<p>This wasn’t the case in the 2010s. The quality and speed of
implementation of every iOS app I have ever worked on, in teams of
every size, absolutely cooked Android. [...] There has never been
a worse time in the history of computers to launch, and require,
fundamental and sweeping changes to languages and frameworks.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The problem isn’t necessarily inherent to the design of the Swift language, but that throughout Swift’s evolution Apple has introduced sweeping changes with each major new version. (Secondarily, that compared to other languages, a lower percentage of Swift code that’s written is open source, and thus available to LLMs for use in training corpuses.) Swift was introduced at WWDC 2014 (that one <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/07/long-lost-df-post">again</a>) and last year Apple introduced Swift 6. That’s a lot of major version changes for a programming language in one decade. There were pros and cons to Apple’s approach over the last decade. But now there’s a new, and major con: because Swift 6 only debuted last year, there’s no great corpus of Swift 6 code for LLMs to have trained on, and so they’re just not as good — from what I gather, not <em>nearly</em> as good — at generating Swift 6 code as they are at generating code in other languages, and for other programming frameworks like React.</p>

<p>The new features in Swift 6 are for the better, but, in a group chat, my friend <a href="https://bitsplitting.org/">Daniel Jalkut</a> described them to me as, “I think Swift 6 changed very little, but the little it changed has huge sweeping implications. Akin to the switch from <a href="https://medium.com/@yenatlij/memory-management-in-objective-c-mrr-and-arc-473cb769fb8d">MRR to ARC</a>.” That’s a reference to the change in Objective-C memory management from manual retain/release (MRR) to automatic reference counting (ARC) back in 2011. Once ARC came out, no one wanted to be writing new code using manual retain/release (which was both tedious and a common source of memory-leak bugs). But if LLMs had been around in 2011/2012, they’d only have been able to generate MRR Objective-C code because that’s what all the existing code they’d been trained on used.</p>

<p>I’m quite certain everyone at Apple who ought to be concerned about this <em>is</em> concerned about it. The question is, do they have solutions ready to be announced next week? This whole area — language, frameworks, and tooling in the LLM era — is top of mind for me heading into WWDC next week.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Swift 6 Productivity in the Sudden Age of LLM-Assisted Programming’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/07/swift-6-llms">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Thomas Ptacek: ‘My AI Skeptic Friends Are All Nuts’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://fly.io/blog/youre-all-nuts/?ueid=4b93173967d7dc762529a10418e85007" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wdy" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/07/ptacek-ai-skeptic-friends-are-nuts" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41974</id>
	<published>2025-06-07T20:28:24Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-07T20:28:25Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Thomas Ptacek:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>LLMs can write a large fraction of all the tedious code you’ll
ever need to write. And most code on most projects is tedious.
LLMs drastically reduce the number of things you’ll ever need to
Google. They look things up themselves. Most importantly, they
don’t get tired; they’re immune to inertia.</p>

<p>Think of anything you wanted to build but didn’t. You tried to
home in on some first steps. If you’d been in the limerent
phase of a new programming language, you’d have started
writing. But you weren’t, so you put it off, for a day, a year,
or your whole career.</p>

<p>I can feel my blood pressure rising thinking of all the
bookkeeping and Googling and dependency drama of a new project. An
LLM can be instructed to just figure all that shit out. Often, it
will drop you precisely at that golden moment where shit almost
works, and development means tweaking code and immediately seeing
things work better. That dopamine hit is why I code.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Ptacek says he mostly writes in Go and Python, and his essay doesn’t even mention Swift. But the whole essay is worth keeping in mind ahead of WWDC. There is no aspect of the AI revolution where Apple, right now today, is further behind than agentic LLM programming. (Swift Assist, <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2024/06/apple-empowers-developers-and-fuels-innovation-with-new-tools-and-resources/">announced</a> and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/15/swift-assist-voorhees">even demoed</a> last year at WWDC, would have been a first step in this direction, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/13/whither-swift-assist">but it never shipped</a>, even in beta.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Thomas Ptacek: ‘My AI Skeptic Friends Are All Nuts’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/07/ptacek-ai-skeptic-friends-are-nuts">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>WorkOS</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://workos.com/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wdx" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/07/workos" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41973</id>
	<published>2025-06-07T19:36:19Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-07T19:36:20Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to WorkOS for sponsoring last week at DF. Modern authentication should be seamless and secure. WorkOS makes it easy to integrate features like MFA, SSO, and RBAC. Whether you’re replacing passwords, stopping fraud, or adding enterprise auth, WorkOS can help you build frictionless auth that scales.</p>

<p>New features they launched just last month include:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://workos.com/blog/workos-connect?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025">WorkOS Connect</a> — “Sign in with [Your App]”</li>
<li><a href="https://workos.com/blog/vault?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025">WorkOS Vault</a> — Encryption Key Management (EKM) and Bring-Your-Own-Key (BYOK)</li>
<li><a href="https://workos.com/blog/custom-objects?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025">AuthKit Integrations</a> — Native support for several new identity providers including LinkedIn, Slack, GitLab, BitBucket, Intuit, and more.</li>
</ul>

<p>Future-proof your authentication stack with the identity layer trusted by OpenAI, Cursor, Perplexity, and Vercel.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘WorkOS’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/07/workos">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/06/truth_social_is_just_trumps_blog" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wdp" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41965</id>
	<published>2025-06-06T21:58:55Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-07T03:02:56Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Truth Social is exceedingly unpopular when judged as a social network; but it’s exceedingly successful as a blog. All the other people using Truth Social are effectively reading his blog and shitposting comments and memes in response to his posts.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Sarah Perez, TechCrunch, “<a href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/06/06/the-trump-musk-feud-has-been-great-for-x-which-jumped-up-the-app-store-charts/">The Trump-Musk Feud Has Been Great for X, Which Jumped Up the App Store Charts</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/06/05/why-are-elon-musk-and-donald-trump-fighting/">feud between Elon Musk and President Donald Trump</a> may be
bad for the MAGA camp, but it’s proven to be beneficial for X,
which has seen engagement soaring over the past 24 hours.
According to new data from Sensor Tower, the app formerly known as
Twitter skyrocketed up the U.S. App Store’s top charts, landing at
the 23rd overall spot on June 5 — up from an average rank of No.
68 over the last 30 days.</p>

<p>X also saw an average rank of No. 58 over the past six months.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I wouldn’t call jumping from the 60s to the 20s “skyrocketing”, but, up is up.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Trump’s own social network, Truth Social, benefited from the feud
as well, as the president shared his thoughts about Musk with his
followers. Compared with the last seven days, U.S. mobile app
active users on Truth Social increased by more than 400%, Sensor
Tower’s proprietary panel indicates.</p>

<p>However, X is still much larger than Truth Social, Sensor Tower
notes, as it has 100× more U.S. mobile app users than Trump’s
social network.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In a couple of <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/19/trump-walmart-tariffs">recent</a> <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/23/trump-cook-apple-india">posts</a> I’ve referred to Truth Social as Trump’s “blog”. (I expounded upon this <a href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2025/05/26/ep-422">in a recent episode of The Talk Show</a>, with Stephen Hackett, starting after the 1h:20m mark, so if you listened to that, the following will sound familiar.) Long before this easily-predictable breakup of two unstable sociopathic egomaniacs (and who would be genuinely surprised if Musk is back in the Oval Office next week?), I’ve long wondered about one particular aspect of their alliance. To wit: that Musk famously spent $44 billion to buy Twitter/X, and envisions it as a world-conquering “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2022/10/everything">everything app</a>”. Trump was once the best known user on Twitter, but after being kicked off every legitimate social network after trying to overthrow the 2020 election, Trump started his own ostensible Twitter-like network, Truth Social. Ostensibly, they’re in direct competition with each other.</p>

<p>Did Musk ever pitch Trump on shutting Truth Social down and coming back to X full time? How about buying Truth Social for a bribery price of a cool $1 billion to sweeten the deal? Truth Social isn’t really a functional social network. Let’s stipulate that Truth Social has 1 percent the active US mobile users of X. Even that’s a sham. <em>Nobody of note other than Trump himself uses Truth Social.</em> For all the pathetic obsequiousness of every single lickspittle official serving in the Trump 2.0 administration, none of them are even vaguely active on Truth Social. They’re all still on X. The Justice Department posts to <a href="https://x.com/TheJusticeDept">its official account on X</a> multiple times per day, but the DOJ doesn’t even have an account on Truth Social. OK, JD Vance has posted to <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@JDVance1">his Truth Social account</a> about a dozen times in the last month. But <a href="https://x.com/JDVance">he’s posted to X</a> five times <em>today</em>.</p>

<p>What I’ve realized is that Truth Social is essentially just Trump’s blog. Truth Social is exceedingly unpopular when judged as a social network; but it’s exceedingly successful as a blog. All the other people using Truth Social are effectively reading his blog and shitposting comments and memes in response to his posts, trying to get his attention. I’ve been thinking about this for a few weeks, and in that time, Trump’s own posts on Truth Social have made the news on a near-daily basis. I’ve never once, ever, seen a post from anyone else on Truth Social make the news. Trump is not just the one and only person of consequence using it, his is the one and only account on Truth Social that you ever, <em>ever</em> hear about.</p>

<p>If Truth Social were actually <em>meant</em> to compete with X, Threads, Bluesky, and Mastodon, this almost certainly would have been a source of conflict between Trump and Musk. Because, if it were meant to be an actual competitive social network, it would occur to Trump to require all his flunkeys and toadies not only to post to Truth Social, but to <em>stop</em> posting to X. But he hasn’t done that, because Truth Social is functioning as intended: it’s just an outlet for Trump to spew his demented <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/23/trump-cook-apple-india">mad-king musings</a> (today he’s <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/06/trump-retweet-rushmore.jpeg">retweeting calls</a> for him to be added to Mount Rushmore) and, most importantly, get some of his all-caps-laden bangers read aloud on the TV news.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Truth Social Is Just Trump’s Blog</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/06/apple_appeals_eu_interop_requirements" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wd4" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41944</id>
	<published>2025-06-03T02:38:54Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-03T16:26:00Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">https://9to5mac.com/2025/06/02/apple-eu-interoperability-appeal/</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/06/02/apple-eu-interoperability-appeal/">Benjamin Mayo, writing at 9to5Mac</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple has appealed parts of the Digital Markets Act law citing
user privacy concerns. Specifically, Apple is contesting the
<a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/03/19/eu-order-apple-interoperability/">interoperability requirements</a> that say data like
notification content and WiFi networks should be made available to
third-parties.</p>

<p>Apple says the DMA as written allows others to “access personal
information that even Apple doesn’t see”. This is because features
like notification rendering and WiFi network data are currently
handled on-device and stored in an encrypted fashion, so Apple
cannot see that stuff. However, the DMA does not necessarily
require third-party agents who would be able to access this same
data to commit to the same standards of privacy and security.</p>

<p>Here’s Apple’s latest statement on the matter, in full:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>At Apple, we design our technology to work seamlessly together,
so it can deliver the unique experience our users love and expect
from our products. The EU’s interoperability requirements
threaten that foundation, while creating a process that is
unreasonable, costly, and stifles innovation. These requirements
will also hand data-hungry companies sensitive information, which
poses massive privacy and security risks to our EU users.
Companies have already requested our users’ most sensitive data — from the content of their notifications, to a full history of
every stored WiFi network on their device — giving them the
ability to access personal information that even Apple doesn’t
see. In the end, these deeply flawed rules that only target Apple — and no other company — will severely limit our ability to
deliver innovative products and features to Europe, leading to an
inferior user experience for our European customers. We are
appealing these decisions on their behalf, and in order to
preserve the high-quality experience our European customers
expect.</p>
</blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>Apple’s full statement is worth reading closely. Specifically, this sentence jumped out to me: “In the end, these deeply flawed rules that only target Apple — and no other company — will severely limit our ability to deliver innovative products and features to Europe, leading to an inferior user experience for our European customers.” <a href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/apple-challenges-eu-order-to-increase-compatibility-with-rivals-products-52082b50?st=gzZzXt">The Wall Street Journal’s story on the appeal</a>, for example, didn’t include that portion of Apple’s statement. But that’s the part that explains what’s going to happen if the EU upholds these “interoperability” requirements, which are intended to require Apple to give away its own intellectual property as though Apple were a public utility. To cite just one example, the Commission’s March ruling requires Apple to make AirDrop available to third-party devices, as though AirDrop was an open standard. (It also requires Apple to allow AirDrop to be replaced on iOS devices, like an interchangeable component, with third-party file sharing software.)</p>

<p>When you think about it, this is nothing like the EU’s recent-ish mandate that most electronic devices must support USB-C ports for charging. I still think that law was unnecessary — the market forces had worked, and the whole world had either already moved (like iPads did starting in 2018) or was on the cusp of moving to USB-C (like iPhones). But at least requiring the inclusion of USB-C for charging is actual open interoperability. USB comes from <a href="https://www.usb.org/">a legitimate industry consortium</a>. Same thing with the Chinese government <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2024/02/eu_rcs_imessage">seemingly forcing Apple’s hand to adopt RCS</a> in order to get the necessary <a href="https://www.miit.gov.cn/gzcy/yjzj/art/2023/art_2d5a7969581b4b12a78cd2c455649a8c.html">certifications for 5G cellular networking in China</a> — RCS is an industry standard protocol. Mandating the inclusion of a standardized port or standardized protocol is the sort of thing government regulatory bodies do. That’s very different than if the EC had regulated port compatibility by requiring Apple to open up Lightning, or if China had regulated messaging by requiring Apple to open iMessage for other companies to use as though they’re open standards.</p>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/19/eu-apple-interop-requirements">The EC’s March mandate</a> basically says that third-party devices must be permitted to do everything Apple’s own devices do when it comes to communicating or interoperating with iPhones and iPads, even if that requires allowing those third-party companies to install and run system-level background processes with broad privileges on iOS. In fact, as Mayo alludes to above, in order to have the same capabilities as Apple’s own devices do, third-party system software extensions might need <em>broader</em> privileges.</p>

<p>I’ve long seen that there are two ways Apple can comply with this mandate, if the EU court declines Apple’s appeal. The first is what most people are thinking, and surely what the European Commission’s bureaucrats are thinking: that Apple will somehow make all third-party devices as capable as Apple’s own when it comes to pairing with and communicating with iPhones and iPads. (And that when Apple is set to unveil new devices, they’ll share the details with third parties in advance so they can do the same things.) The second, though, is that Apple will limit its own devices <em>in the EU and only in the EU</em> to the same features available to third-party devices through open standards like Bluetooth. New features and entire devices will either come late, or never, to the EU. We’re already seeing that <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/120421">with iPhone Mirroring</a> — perhaps the single best feature Apple announced (and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/something_is_rotten_in_the_state_of_cupertino">actually shipped</a>) last year. I use iPhone Mirroring every day while I’m working. We’re one week out from WWDC 2025 and iPhone Mirroring <em>still</em> isn’t available in the EU. I think it’s very clear that under the EC’s current DMA “interoperability” mandate, Apple would be required to somehow make it work with third-party devices and PCs. If AirDrop were brand new, users in the EU wouldn’t get that either, I suspect. And if this mandate holds up, EU users might <em>lose</em> AirDrop. The same is true of entire devices like AirPods and Apple Watch.</p>

<p>Apple’s statement doesn’t say that complying with