<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>Daring Fireball</title>
<subtitle>By John Gruber</subtitle>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/" />
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main" />
<id>https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main</id>


<updated>2025-05-20T17:08:34Z</updated><rights>Copyright © 2025, John Gruber</rights><entry>
	<title>Kristi Noem Doesn’t Know What ‘Habeas Corpus’ Is</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://politicalwire.com/2025/05/20/kristi-noem-doesnt-know-what-habeus-corpus-is/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wc4" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/20/noem-habeas-corpus" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41908</id>
	<published>2025-05-20T16:51:13Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-20T17:08:34Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Taegan Goddard:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>When Sen. Maggie Hassan (D-NH) <a href="https://x.com/ErnestScribblr/status/1924835528173658492">asked</a> Secretary of Homeland Security Kristi Noem for the definition of “habeas corpus,” Noem incorrectly described it as a right that the President of the United States has to deport people.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You can go the Latin route (“produce the body”) or the English <a href="https://www.britannica.com/topic/habeas-corpus">common-law route</a> (the accused have a right to be shown the evidence against them and defend themselves in court). Noem went the “biggest clown of the clown-car Trump 2.0 administration” route.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Kristi Noem Doesn’t Know What ‘Habeas Corpus’ Is’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/20/noem-habeas-corpus">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://drata.com/daring" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wc3" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/05/drata" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.41907</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-05-19T23:53:17Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-19T23:53:18Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Automate compliance. Streamline security. Manage risk. Drata delivers the world’s most advanced Trust Management platform.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Drata’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/05/drata">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] Drata</title></entry><entry>
	<title>The First Rule of Legal Fight Club Is ‘Don’t Piss Off the Judge’; the Second Rule of Legal Fight Club Is ‘Don’t Piss Off the Judge’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/05/19/apple-fortnite-us-app-store-dispute/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wc2" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/19/the-first-rule-of-legal-fight-club" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41906</id>
	<published>2025-05-19T23:48:03Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-19T23:48:03Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Juli Clover, MacRumors:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>With Apple blocking Fortnite from returning to the U.S. App Store,
<a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/05/19/epic-asks-judge-apple-approve-fortnite-app-store/">Epic Games told the court</a> that Apple was violating the
injunction and asked that Apple be forced to approve the app. The
judge overseeing the case responded to Epic’s request today, and
she is sounding more and more fed up with Apple’s continued
defiance and Epic’s grousing.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>“More and more fed up” is perhaps euphemistic, <a href="https://www.courtlistener.com/docket/17442392/1576/epic-games-inc-v-apple-inc/">given Gonzalez Rogers’s tone today</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The First Rule of Legal Fight Club Is ‘Don’t Piss Off the Judge’; the Second Rule of Legal Fight Club Is ‘Don’t Piss Off the Judge’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/19/the-first-rule-of-legal-fight-club">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>John Siracusa: ‘Apple Turnover’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://hypercritical.co/2025/05/09/apple-turnover" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wc1" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/19/siracusa-apple-turnover" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41905</id>
	<published>2025-05-19T23:37:53Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-19T23:37:54Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>John Siracusa, in a piece that, in a bit of rhetorical deftness, only mentions Tim Cook by name once:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>What <em>should</em> be motivating Apple to make improvements — the
desire to make great products — seems absent. What should <em>not</em>
be motivating Apple — the desire for power, control, and profits — seems omnipresent.</p>

<p>And I don’t mean that in a small way; <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3KdlJlHAAbQ">I mean that in a big
way</a>. Every new thing we learn about <a href="https://www.theverge.com/apple/659296/apple-failed-compliance-court-ruling-breakdown">Apple’s internal
deliberations</a> surrounding these decisions only lends more
weight to the conclusion that Apple has lost its north star.
Or, rather, it has replaced it with a new, dark star. And time
and again, we’ve learned that these decisions go all the way to
the top.</p>

<p>The best leaders can change their minds in response to new
information. The best leaders can <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2022/05/04/tony-fadell-talks-about-steve-jobs-controversial-decisions-on-ipod-and-iphone-development/">be persuaded</a>. But we’ve had
decades of strife, lawsuits, and regulations, and Apple has
stubbornly dug in its heels even further at every turn. It seems
clear that there’s only one way to get a different result.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Covers a lot in a relatively short essay. I do not agree with Siracusa on his conclusion, but I’ve sat on linking to it, because — along with a few other recents posts and goings-on — it’s given me much to think about, and has helped me clarify my own thoughts, which I need to put in a piece of their own. But if you haven’t read Siracusa’s yet, you should.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘John Siracusa: ‘Apple Turnover’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/19/siracusa-apple-turnover">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Chad the Bird on ‘Star Wars’ Typography</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.instagram.com/reel/DJZ7uYbvN_O/?igsh=aWZhaGZham1zNWlp" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wc0" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/19/chad-the-bird-on-star-wars-typography" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41904</id>
	<published>2025-05-19T23:01:14Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-19T23:01:15Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The reader who sent me this video said, “I’ve never seen a more Star Wars + Gruber combo on Instagram” and — right down to the profanity — I have to agree.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Chad the Bird on ‘Star Wars’ Typography’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/19/chad-the-bird-on-star-wars-typography">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>WSJ: ‘Apple Considers Raising iPhone Prices, Without Blaming Tariffs’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/apple-iphone-price-increase-2eaebb14?st=P6hk65&amp;reflink=desktopwebshare_permalink" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wbz" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/19/wsj-apple-iphone-pricing-tariffs" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41903</id>
	<published>2025-05-19T20:38:34Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-19T20:40:22Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Rolfe Winkler and Yang Jie, reporting last week for The Wall Street Journal (main link is a gift link, but also <a href="https://apple.news/AbU9x9Q0fRl-Y0cJR3QGmmg">here’s a News+ link</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple is weighing price increases for its fall iPhone lineup, a
step it is seeking to couple with new features and design changes,
according to people familiar with the matter. The company is
determined to avoid any scenario in which it appears to attribute
price increases to U.S. tariffs on goods from China, where most
Apple devices are assembled, the people said.</p>

<p>The U.S. and China <a href="https://www.wsj.com/livecoverage/stock-market-today-tariffs-trade-war-05-12-2025">agreed Monday</a> to suspend most of the tariffs
they had imposed on each other in a tit-for-tat trade war. But a
20% tariff that President Trump imposed early in his second term
on Chinese goods, citing what he said was Beijing’s role in the
fentanyl trade, remains in place and covers smartphones. [...]</p>

<p>For Apple’s most profitable, high-end phones, such as the Pro and
Pro Max models, Chinese factories will continue to handle the bulk
of production, people familiar with Apple’s supply chain said.
While Indian factories are capable of producing Pro models,
India’s infrastructure and technical capabilities aren’t yet
sufficient to support mass production at the scale China can
currently deliver, they said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Even if Trump <em>weren’t</em> a vindictive thin-skinned angry kook, I’m sure that if this year’s iPhones have higher prices because of Trump’s tariffs, Apple would not attribute the price increases to the tariffs. At least publicly. But Trump <em>is</em> a vindictive thin-skinned angry kook, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/15/trump-cook-apple-india">irritated even that Apple is shifting some iPhone production to India</a> (which <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/04/how_many_iphones_can_fit_on_a_freight_plane">does assemble iPhones already</a>, and has the capability of producing more) instead of the United States (which only has the capability of assembling iPhones, at <em>any</em> sort of scale, in the fever dreams of Trump’s addled mind). So of course no one at Apple is going to blame any price increases — if they do indeed go up — on the tariffs.</p>

<p>But come on. If iPhone prices go up in September, everyone who isn’t drunk on MAGA juice is going to blame it on the tariffs. Like, even if Apple had been planning for years to raise prices for the iPhone 17 lineup — if price increases were already baked-in for this year’s models since before Trump was re-elected — now that the tariffs are here, everyone would attribute the price hikes to the tariffs. Especially after the summer of tariff-driven inflation I expect we’re about to go through.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘WSJ: ‘Apple Considers Raising iPhone Prices, Without Blaming Tariffs’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/19/wsj-apple-iphone-pricing-tariffs">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Trump Tells Walmart to ‘Eat the Tariffs’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/114523638623110397" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wby" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/19/trump-walmart-tariffs" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41902</id>
	<published>2025-05-19T20:17:29Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-19T20:47:36Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The president of the United States, on his blog:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Walmart should STOP trying to blame Tariffs as the reason for
raising prices throughout the chain. Walmart made BILLIONS OF
DOLLARS last year, far more than expected. Between Walmart and
China they should, as is said, “EAT THE TARIFFS,” and not charge
valued customers ANYTHING. I’ll be watching, and so will your
customers!!!</p>
</blockquote>

<p>F. Scott Fitzgerald wrote “The test of a first-rate intelligence is the ability to hold two opposed ideas in the mind at the same time, and still retain the ability to function.” So I guess I’m wrong that Trump is a know-nothing ding-dong slipping rapidly into dementia, and in fact possesses a first-rate intelligence. Because it’s Trump — soon to win a Nobel Prize in economics for this keen insight — who has been braying to the world, non-stop, for years, <a href="https://youtu.be/WhR3i2UAGSQ?t=33">that tariffs are “a tax on a foreign country”</a>. </p>

<p>So given that China pays for any tariffs the US imposes on Chinese-made goods, I, for one, don’t have the intellect to understand how there are any tariffs for Walmart to 
eat. I’m sure Trump is right and Walmart — a company whose “always low prices” brand results in <a href="https://www.macrotrends.net/stocks/charts/WMT/walmart/net-profit-margin">net profit margins between 2–3%</a> — will somehow “eat the tariffs” without losing money. I don’t know why the WSJ Editorial Board <a href="https://www.wsj.com/opinion/donald-trumps-everyday-high-prices-kamala-walmart-price-hike-tariff-439cb183">is so upset about this</a> — the Republican Party has always been in favor of government price controls.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Trump Tells Walmart to ‘Eat the Tariffs’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/19/trump-walmart-tariffs">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/05/more_insight_and_not-negativity" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wbx" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41901</id>
	<published>2025-05-19T19:14:41Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-19T19:51:19Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">I never linked to the viral blog post where Jobs was quoted recommending my article, I never mentioned it in a post, but I *did* acknowledge it, in what is clearly the most Daring-Fireball-ish way possible: I made it the slogan under the logo banner.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Some “<em>thank god some of you remembered because I thought I was going nuts</em>” follow-up regarding my remembrance the other day, “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/05/15_years_later_very_insightful_and_not_negative">15 Years Later: ‘Very Insightful and Not Negative’</a>”. I wrote:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>So, what would <em>you</em> do if Steve Jobs was quoted in a viral blog
post saying, “We think «<em>Your Name Here</em>»’s post is very
insightful and not negative”? I decided to just sit there with a
smug look on my face for a few days (which, arguably, isn’t all
that different from what I do most days) and pretend that it was
no big deal. I didn’t link to it or mention it on Daring Fireball,
and as far as I can tell, <a href="https://x.com/search?q=%22not%20negative%22%20(from%3Agruber)&amp;src=typed_query">I didn’t even tweet it</a>. As best I
can recall, I thought I should just play it cool. I mean of course
my article about why Apple changed Section 3.3.1 was right. Why
brag? Given that Steve Jobs was reading Daring Fireball, I didn’t
want him to read a post from me acting like it was a big deal that
he’d recommended a piece I wrote and agreed with it.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>About a dozen long-time readers recalled that I <em>did</em>, in fact, acknowledge it on Daring Fireball — and <a href="https://mastodon.social/@gruber/114523770015232774">as soon as I saw</a> the first message, it all came back to me. I never linked to the viral blog post where Jobs was quoted recommending my article. I never mentioned it in a post. But I <em>did</em> acknowledge it, in what is clearly the most Daring-Fireball-ish way possible: I made it the slogan under the logo banner. That it was only ever a slogan in a PNG logo graphic explains why I couldn’t find it by searching. And I still have that version of the logo (because I keep everything):</p>

<div style="text-align: center">
  <img
    src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/05/df_logo_insightful_not_negative_2010.png"
    alt = "The 2010 DF logo with the slogan “Insightful and Not Negative” underneath in small type."
    style = "background-color: #4a525a; margin-bottom: 1em;"
  />
</div>

<p>I can’t remember if I omitted the <em>very</em> before <em>insightful</em> for aesthetic length, humility, or because I somehow thought it was punchier. But my 2025 self thinks it was a mistake to omit it. It surely looks blurry on your screen today, because it’s a 1× graphic scaled to the correct size. In April 2010, 2× retina resolution wasn’t yet a thing — remember, that was the very month that Gizmodo <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fkK7_QEIJrg" title="Jon Prosser’s documentary: “The Biggest Apple Leak in History”">published details regarding a stolen iPhone 4 prototype</a>, which was the device that <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Hq8j5vsqCCo" title="Steve Jobs introducing and defining the retina display at WWDC 2010.">introduced “retina resolution” to the world</a>. At 50 percent, you can see it pixel-perfect (the slogan is rendered in <a href="https://kare.com/fonts/">Susan Kare’s exquisite Kare Five Dots</a> pixel font), but small:</p>

<div style="text-align: center">
  <img
    srcset = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/05/df_logo_insightful_not_negative_2010.png 2x"
    alt = "The 2010 DF logo with the slogan “Insightful and Not Negative” underneath in small type. Rendered at half-size to remain pixel-perfect on modern 2× retina resolution displays."
    style = "background-color: #4a525a; margin-bottom: 1em;"
  />
</div>

<p>In the very early days, there was always a slogan under the DF logo. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/design/1/">Originally</a>: “Mac Punditry and Curmudgeonry”. Then, for several years, I’d mix it up, with descriptive slogans like “Mac + Web Nerdery, Etc.”, but also with ones that were just there for fun: “Now With Retsyn”, “Simple Tricks and Nonsense”, and, during the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yBWg93q9qBA">2008 World Series</a>, “Phillies Fever”. But for the last decade or so, I’ve left the logo banner slogan-less most weeks of the year.</p>

<p>Feels like the right time to bring back a little whimsy, so I’ve put “Very Insightful and Not Negative” back as the slogan for now, and I’m thinking I should keep occasionally having some fun up there.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ More Insight and Not-Negativity</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Bolt</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://srv.buysellads.com/ads/long/x/THREKCSVTTTTTTTZHWQNETTTTTTDCFVJ2TTTTTTTADZJNBTTTTTTTRIV22DW47II2RZULYSCKY7FTBDDQ7QCCYPBG6BT" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wbw" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/18/bolt" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41900</id>
	<published>2025-05-19T00:53:21Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-19T00:53:40Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to Bolt for sponsoring last week at DF. You can prompt, run, edit, and deploy full-stack web and mobile apps with Bolt, the AI-powered web development agent that brings coding to your browser.</p>

<p>Bolt lets you build, edit, and test web applications in real time with simple, chat-based prompts. No experience needed.</p>

<p>Super-simple, super-fun. <a href="https://srv.buysellads.com/ads/long/x/THREKCSVTTTTTTTZHWQNETTTTTTDCFVJ2TTTTTTTADZJNBTTTTTTTRIV22DW47II2RZULYSCKY7FTBDDQ7QCCYPBG6BT">Try it yourself at Bolt.new</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Bolt’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/18/bolt">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Slate Truck: A $20–30K American-Made Electric Small Pickup With No Paint, No Stereo, No Touchscreen</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/electric-cars/655527/slate-electric-truck-price-paint-radio-bezos" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wbv" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/18/slate-truck" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41899</id>
	<published>2025-05-18T21:14:34Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-19T00:03:23Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Month-old news but I’m cleaning up tabs today. I love everything about this pickup except the fact that it doesn’t have a speaker system built-in. No one wants to put a Bluetooth boombox in their cabin and, worse, isn’t that sort of an obvious safety hazard? You get in a crash and now there’s a boombox flying around inside. Just put a simple bluetooth speaker system in.</p>

<p>But the aesthetics of this are chef’s-kiss good. It’s a beautiful little truck. It gets everything right that the Cybertruck gets wrong.</p>

<p>However, I have some questions about how real this is. You pay $50 now to get in the queue for pre-orders, but pre-orders haven’t even started. Deliveries are supposed to start in “late 2026” but Car and Driver is <a href="https://www.caranddriver.com/news/a64564869/2027-slate-truck-revealed/">cautiously describing it as a “2027 truck EV”</a>. I’m rooting for them but at this point it’s a promise not a truck.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Slate Truck: A $20–30K American-Made Electric Small Pickup With No Paint, No Stereo, No Touchscreen’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/18/slate-truck">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Joe Biden Has an Aggressive Form of Prostate Cancer</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/05/18/us/politics/biden-prostate-cancer.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wbu" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/18/biden-cancer" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41898</id>
	<published>2025-05-18T21:09:23Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-19T14:33:48Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Tyler Pager, The New York Times:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Former President Joseph R. Biden Jr. was diagnosed Friday with an
aggressive form of prostate cancer that has spread to his bones,
his office said in a statement on Sunday.</p>

<p>The diagnosis came after Mr. Biden reported urinary symptoms,
which led doctors to <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/05/12/us/politics/biden-prostate.html">find a “small nodule”</a> on his
prostate. Mr. Biden’s cancer is “characterized by a Gleason
score of 9 (Grade Group 5) with metastasis to the bone,” the
statement said.</p>

<p>“While this represents a more aggressive form of the disease, the
cancer appears to be hormone-sensitive which allows for effective
management,” according to the statement from Mr. Biden’s office,
which was unsigned. “The president and his family are reviewing
treatment options with his physicians.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Terrible news about a good man. But, man, does it feel like forever ago that he was president. It was only 118 days ago.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Joe Biden Has an Aggressive Form of Prostate Cancer’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/18/biden-cancer">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Jack Rix at Top Gear Reviews CarPlay Ultra in the Aston Martin DBX</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EQlLjVraA9g" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wbt" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/18/top-gear-carplay-ultra-aston-martin" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41897</id>
	<published>2025-05-18T17:01:47Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-19T16:15:28Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>There’s <a href="https://www.topgear.com/car-news/tech/new-apple-carplay-ultra-tested-hands-every-new-feature">an accompanying blog post</a> too, but the video (around 18 minutes) is (unsurprisingly, from Top Gear) better. It’s just a great tour of everything from how you set it up to what it offers, and what the various “themes” look like — and how you switch between them.</p>

<p>The DBX doesn’t have a ton of screen space, so we’re still left to wonder what the experience will be like in a car that has door-to-door screens spanning the dashboard, but Rix does a great job showing the driver’s perspective of the main instrument cluster. One thing Aston did right is that they still have a lot of physical controls — clicking buttons and twisting dials — for the most essential features like climate control. As you’d hope, the CarPlay Ultra interface updates live as you manipulate those physical controls in the car.</p>

<p>I don’t know if CarPlay Ultra came out of Apple’s abandoned “Titan” project to build its own line of vehicles, but it sure feels like for the first time in its modern era (see link below), Apple is licensing an OS to third-party hardware makers. A straightforward “<em>you do the hardware, we’ll do the software, and we’ll work together to make sure the result looks like a partnership between our brands</em>” sort of deal. That never made sense for Apple with other device classes, like PCs (where, in the mid-’90s, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2006/04/asinine_and_or_risky_ideas#:~:text=for%20Other%20PCs-,or%20License%20the%20Mac,-to%20Other%20PC">they briefly tried and it proved nearly ruinous</a> for the company), phones, or watches, but I think it might make a lot more sense for cars than if Apple had forged ahead with Titan.</p>

<p>They might really have something here, and brands — like Mercedes, which supports regular CarPlay but whose CEO <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/4/29/24144356/mercedes-benz-ceo-apple-carplay-next-gen-decoder">is opposed to CarPlay Ultra taking over all its screens</a>, or, more famously, the electric startups like Tesla and Rivian that are holding out against any CarPlay support at all — that don’t support CarPlay Ultra might see a <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/102579-how-did-you-go-bankrupt-two-ways-gradually-then-suddenly">Hemingway-style</a> slowly-then-quickly decline in customer demand that is more notable than the <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/02/gm-carplay-evs">remarkably high demand</a> for regular CarPlay.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Jack Rix at Top Gear Reviews CarPlay Ultra in the Aston Martin DBX’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/18/top-gear-carplay-ultra-aston-martin">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Puzzmo Is Getting a Native iOS App Monday</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/games/668478/puzzmo-is-finally-getting-an-app" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wbs" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/16/puzzmo-native-app" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41896</id>
	<published>2025-05-17T00:12:46Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-17T21:06:28Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Scheduled to drop Monday, but you can click-through to <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/puzzmo-solve-smile-share/id6714482734">pre-download it now</a>. If you’re not familiar, Puzzmo is sort of a collection of “<a href="https://www.theverge.com/23929222/puzzmo-newspaper-games-crossword-zach-gage">newspaper puzzle games for the online age</a>”. (Which is also a good description for <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/30/lex-games">recent DF sponsor</a> <a href="https://lex.games/df">Lex.Games</a>.) One of Puzzmo’s cofounders is <a href="http://stfj.net/">Zach Gage</a>, whose hits include <a href="http://www.reallybadchess.com/">Really Bad Chess</a> and <a href="https://playknotwords.com/">Knotwords</a>, and who was <a href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2022/05/09/ep-346">my guest on The Talk Show back in 2022</a>.</p>

<p>Anyway, if casual puzzle games are your jam, you should check out Puzzmo. My suggestion is check them out now, see how you like it as a web app on your iPhone, and then compare when the app hits the App Store on Monday. Puzzmo is a really good web app. I bet, though, the app is better.</p>

<p><strong>See also:</strong> <a href="https://blog.puzzmo.com/posts/2025/02/06/digging-into-perf/">This blog post from Puzzmo developer Orta Therox</a> from February, discussing some of the engineering changes they made while developing the app. </p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Puzzmo Is Getting a Native iOS App Monday’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/16/puzzmo-native-app">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple Is Not Reinstating Fortnite to the App Store, and Because of the Stunt-Like Way That Epic Submitted the Latest Build, Fortnite Is Currently No Longer Available on iOS Anywhere in the World</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://x.com/markgurman/status/1923404412090782109" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wbr" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/16/fortnite-still-banned" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41895</id>
	<published>2025-05-16T17:24:35Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-16T21:05:29Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>There’s an old adage in poker: If you look around the table and you can’t tell who <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glossary_of_poker_terms">the fish</a> is, that means you’re the fish.</p>

<p>If you’re surprised at how <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/01/apple-lost-but-did-epic-win">this publicity stunt</a> from Epic has turned out, especially if you’re a reporter and <a href="https://www.techmeme.com/250430/p57#a250430p57">ran a piece</a> accepting Tim Sweeney’s word that Fortnite was — not <em>might be</em>, but was — coming back to the US App Store as a fact, then you are Tim Sweeney’s fish. </p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Is Not Reinstating Fortnite to the App Store, and Because of the Stunt-Like Way That Epic Submitted the Latest Build, Fortnite Is Currently No Longer Available on iOS Anywhere in the World’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/16/fortnite-still-banned">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/05/15_years_later_very_insightful_and_not_negative" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wbq" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41894</id>
	<published>2025-05-16T00:26:20Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-16T03:30:58Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">So, what would *you* do if Steve Jobs was quoted in a viral blog post saying, “We think «*Your Name Here*»’s post is very insightful and not negative”? I decided to just sit there with a smug look on my face for a few days.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Earlier this week Nilay Patel was working on the show notes for <a href="https://www.theverge.com/decoder-podcast-with-nilay-patel/664802/apple-app-store-iphone-ios-fortnite-epic-games-lawsuit">the episode of Decoder I guested on</a>, and he texted me to ask if I could recall the time Steve Jobs sent some random developer a link to an article I wrote about the App Store. He wanted to cite it as an example of Daring Fireball being read, at high levels inside Apple, for a long time. I recalled the whole thing vaguely, as a “holy shit” moment, but not specifically. I hadn’t thought about it in years. But I was sure I could find it in the DF archives.</p>

<p>Turns out, I couldn’t find it, because, it turns out, in a fit of inexplicable modesty and humility, <em>I never linked to it</em>. (From <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2010/04/12/gruber-apple-was-right-adobe-get-over-it-video/">a TechCrunch interview I did at the time</a>, after the saga went somewhat viral: “When asked for his response to Steve’s shout-out, Gruber meekly grinned and said, ‘I just smiled.’”)</p>

<p>Here’s the rough timeline of events. On Thursday 8 April 2010, Apple updated the App Store guidelines to ban the use of Adobe’s then-new Flash-to-iPhone compiler. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2010/04/iphone_agreement_bans_flash_compiler">From my post on the change</a> (which, to some degree, broke the news):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Prior to today’s release of the iPhone OS 4 SDK, section 3.3.1 of
the iPhone Developer Program License Agreement read, in its
entirety:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>3.3.1 — Applications may only use Documented APIs in the manner
    prescribed by Apple and must not use or call any private
    APIs.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In the new version of the iPhone Developer Program License
Agreement released by Apple today (and which developers must agree
to before downloading the 4.0 SDK beta), section 3.3.1 now reads:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>3.3.1 — Applications may only use Documented APIs in the manner
    prescribed by Apple and must not use or call any private
    APIs. Applications must be originally written in Objective-C,
    C, C++, or JavaScript as executed by the iPhone OS WebKit
    engine, and only code written in C, C++, and Objective-C may
    compile and directly link against the Documented APIs (e.g.,
    Applications that link to Documented APIs through an
    intermediary translation or compatibility layer or tool are
    prohibited).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>My reading of this new language is that cross-compilers, such as
the <a href="http://labs.adobe.com/technologies/flashcs5/appsfor_iphone/">Flash-to-iPhone compiler</a> in Adobe’s upcoming Flash
Professional CS5 release, are prohibited. This also bans apps
compiled using <a href="http://monotouch.net/">MonoTouch</a> — a tool that compiles C# and .NET
apps to the iPhone.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This was <em>enormously</em> controversial at the time, but I also thought largely misunderstood by developers. Later that same day, I published another piece articulating my take on Apple’s reasoning for the change, “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2010/04/why_apple_changed_section_331">Why Apple Changed Section 3.3.1</a>”. From that article:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We’re still in the early days of the transition from the PC era to
the mobile era. Right now, Apple is winning. There are other
winners right now too — RIM is still growing, and Android has
grown a ton in the past year.</p>

<p>The App Store platform could turn into a long-term de facto
standard platform. That’s how Microsoft became Microsoft. At a
certain point developers wrote apps for Windows because so many
users were on Windows and users bought Windows PCs because all the
software was being written for Windows. That’s the sort of
situation that creates a license to print money.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That seems prescient. (The “license to print money” part — not the “RIM is still growing” part.)</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>So what Apple does not want is for some other company to establish
a de facto standard software platform <em>on top</em> of Cocoa Touch. Not
Adobe’s Flash. Not .NET (through MonoTouch). If that were to
happen, there’s no lock-in advantage. If, say, a mobile Flash
software platform — which encompassed multiple lower-level
platforms, running on iPhone, Android, Windows Phone 7, and
BlackBerry — were established, that app market would not give
people a reason to prefer the iPhone.</p>

<p>And, obviously, such a meta-platform would be out of Apple’s
control. Consider a world where some other company’s
cross-platform toolkit proved wildly popular. Then Apple releases
major new features to iPhone OS, and that other company’s toolkit
is slow to adopt them. At that point, it’s the <em>other</em> company
that controls when third-party apps can make use of these
features.</p>

<p>So from Apple’s perspective, changing the iPhone Developer Program
License Agreement to prohibit the use of things like Flash CS5 and
MonoTouch to create iPhone apps makes complete sense. I’m not
saying you have to like this. I’m not arguing that it’s anything
other than ruthless competitiveness. I’m not arguing (up to this
point) that it benefits anyone other than Apple itself. I’m just
arguing that it makes sense from Apple’s perspective — and it was
Apple’s decision to make.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Two days later, on 10 April 2010, developer Greg Slepak emailed Steve Jobs to complain about the decision, citing negative sentiment on Hacker News (much has changed since 2010, but some things have not), writing:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Hi Steve,</p>

<p>Lots of people are pissed off at Apple’s mandate that applications
be “originally written” in C/C++/Objective-C. If you go, for
example, to the Hacker News homepage right now:</p>

<p><a href="http://news.ycombinator.com/">http://news.ycombinator.com/</a></p>

<p>You’ll see that most of the front page stories about this new
restriction, with #1 being: “<a href="http://whydoeseverythingsuck.com/2010/04/steve-jobs-has-just-gone-mad.html">Steve Jobs Has Just Gone Mad</a>” with
(currently) 243 upvotes. The top 5 stories are all negative
reactions to the TOS, and there are several others below them as
well. Not a single positive reaction, even from John Gruber, your
biggest fan.</p>

<p>I love your product, but your SDK TOS are growing on it like an
invisible cancer.</p>

<p>Sincerely, <br />
Greg</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Jobs wrote back to Slepak (starting a brief exchange of emails):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We think John Gruber’s post is very insightful and not negative:</p>

<p><a href="http://daringfireball.net/2010/04/why_apple_changed_section_331">http://daringfireball.net/2010/04/why_apple_changed_section_331</a></p>

<p>Steve</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.taoeffect.com/blog/2010/04/steve-jobs-response-on-section-3-3-1/">Slepak posted the exchange to his blog</a>, Tao Effect, and, well, as Jobs himself might have said, “Boom.” (This was <a href="https://www.macstories.net/news/steve-jobs-what-have-you-done-thats-so-great/">a not infrequent thing</a> at the time, where random users or developers would email Jobs, he’d write back with something pithy, and they’d post the exchange. It was kind of crazy — the most famous CEO in the world, just doing customer service email — and his emails were always sharp.)</p>

<p>So, what would <em>you</em> do if Steve Jobs was quoted in a viral blog post saying, “We think «<em>Your Name Here</em>»’s post is very insightful and not negative”? I decided to just sit there with a smug look on my face for a few days (which, arguably, isn’t all that different from what I do most days) and pretend that it was no big deal. I didn’t link to it or mention it on Daring Fireball, and as far as I can tell, <a href="https://x.com/search?q=%22not%20negative%22%20(from%3Agruber)&amp;src=typed_query">I didn’t even tweet it</a>. As best I can recall, I thought I should just play it cool. I mean of course my article about why Apple changed Section 3.3.1 was right. Why brag? Given that Steve Jobs was reading Daring Fireball, I didn’t want him to read a post from me acting like it was a big deal that he’d recommended a piece I wrote and agreed with it.</p>

<p>That was pretty stupid on my part. Or at least silly. My older perspective, today, is not to overthink such things. If something cool happens, I link to it. It seems ridiculous in hindsight that I didn’t link to Slepak’s post. And, I was thinking this week, if <em>I</em> couldn’t find a link to the overall story because <em>I</em> wrongly presumed I must have linked to it at the time, I wondered how many other readers, over the years, have gone hunting for that “very insightful and not negative” story and couldn’t find it because it was never mentioned or linked to on Daring Fireball.</p>

<p>So, today, I wrote the post I should have written back then, and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2010/04/11/very-insightful-and-not-negative">backdated it to 11 April 2010</a>.</p>

<p>To complete the timeline, April 2010 was a busy month. That same month saw <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2010/04/28/hp-palm-deal-webos/">HP buy Palm</a> (in a last-ditch effort to remain relevant as the industry rapidly shifted from being PC-centric to mobile-centric), <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2010/04/28/siri">Apple acquire a company called “Siri”</a>, and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2010/04/28/slate-iphone">Gizmodo publish details on the iPhone 4 prototype</a> some poor Apple engineer accidentally left in a bar. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2010/04/the_ipad">The original iPad</a> had <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20100404043324/http://www.time.com/time/business/article/0,8599,1976935,00.html">just shipped</a>. And at the end of the month, Jobs published “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2010/04/29/jobs-thoughts-on-flash">Thoughts on Flash</a>” on the Apple.com homepage. It’s kind of wild that was all in one month — scrolling down <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2010/04/">the monthly archive page for April 2010</a> is just <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2010/04/30/cabin-fever">one gem</a> after <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2010/04/30/thoughts-on-horses">another</a>.</p>

<p>Re-reading “<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20100722001052/http://www.apple.com/hotnews/thoughts-on-flash/">Thoughts on Flash</a>” again now, for the umpteenth time, I’ll say this: I think Steve Jobs’s post was very insightful and not negative.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ 15 Years Later: ‘Very Insightful and Not Negative’</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Yours Truly With Nilay Patel on ‘Decoder’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/decoder-podcast-with-nilay-patel/664802/apple-app-store-iphone-ios-fortnite-epic-games-lawsuit" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wbo" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/15/yours-truly-with-nilay-patel-on-decoder" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41892</id>
	<published>2025-05-15T21:45:27Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-15T21:59:23Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Nilay Patel:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>There’s a lot of tactical stuff you might talk about in the
aftermath of this ruling — about what Apple might do next, how it
might impact revenue, and how developers might respond. But I
really wanted Gruber to talk about Apple’s big picture and how a
company that so often prides itself on doing the right thing ended
up so fully on the wrong side of the courts.</p>

<p>One theme you’ll hear throughout this conversation is that Apple
often presents itself as small, but the company is actually huge
in every way — Apple now sells nearly as many phones in a single
quarter as it did in the entire first three years of the iPhone’s
existence combined. It now operates in a geopolitical context that
binds the United States, China, and Taiwan in ways you would have
never imagined 15 years ago. And perhaps most importantly, Apple
has control over applications on the iPhone, which means it has
control over what kinds of businesses can and cannot exist on its
mobile phones.</p>

<p>That’s the context for the other major theme here that you’ll pick
up on in this conversation: Apple’s major shift toward digital
services and whether that’s fundamentally changed the company’s
culture. You see, as Apple kept selling newer and better iPhones,
it simply ran out of people to sell them to. So, in order to keep
growing revenue and keep Wall Street happy, it started squeezing
more money from its existing customer base, including the very
developers that put apps on the App Store.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Good episode, if I do say so myself.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Yours Truly With Nilay Patel on ‘Decoder’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/15/yours-truly-with-nilay-patel-on-decoder">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>RevenueCat Report Suggests In-App Purchases Perform Noticeably Better Than Link-Outs to the Web</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.revenuecat.com/blog/growth/iap-vs-web-purchases-conversion-test/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wbn" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/15/revenuecat-external-purchase-report" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41891</id>
	<published>2025-05-15T21:40:33Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-15T21:41:26Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/05/that_eu_app_store_warning_about_external_purchases_is_not_new">Speaking of</a> Jacob Eiting, his company RevenueCat today posted some interesting findings from a test comparing conversions rates for IAP vs. web checkout for the same app:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Two weeks ago, there was a court order in the Apple vs Epic case
that forced Apple to allow developers to circumvent in-app
purchases (IAP). As of April 30th 2025, developers were finally
allowed to send customers in the United States to an external
website to complete the purchases, and thus avoid the 30% fee that
App Store takes. We quickly released <a href="https://www.revenuecat.com/blog/growth/introducing-web-paywall-buttons/">Web Purchase Buttons</a>
that, combined with our <a href="https://www.revenuecat.com/billing/">Web Billing</a> product, create a
seamless way for developers to drive purchasers out of their app
to the web for check out.</p>

<p>IAP in the US is a $52B market, representing about half of all App
Store revenue, and this is the first time that Apple has opened up
such a major market to web purchasing. Previously, similar court
orders have been limited to much smaller markets. It has been much
debated over the years how much, or even if, this new-found
freedom would help developers make more money. The only real way
to know is to run a test, so we took this opportunity to run the
biggest open test of web purchases in history.</p>

<p>Last week, we deployed an experiment on Dipsea (the app we
acquired last year as a testing-ground) and we’re excited to share
initial results.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The initial conversion rate for IAP was around 28%; the conversion rate for the link-out web flow was just 18%. That’s a notable drop-off.</p>

<p>I don’t find it surprising at all though. IAP really is more convenient. Apple’s built a great system, and they don’t need exclusivity to keep users preferring it, and thus keep developers using it.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘RevenueCat Report Suggests In-App Purchases Perform Noticeably Better Than Link-Outs to the Web’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/15/revenuecat-external-purchase-report">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Andy Allen on the App Store’s Feature Stagnation</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.threads.com/@asallen/post/DJPLWZ-NwPZ" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wbm" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/15/andy-allen-app-store-feature-stagnation" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41890</id>
	<published>2025-05-15T21:24:27Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-15T21:24:28Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Andy Allen, of <a href="https://notbor.ing/">Not Boring Software</a>, last week on Threads:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>While the focus on the App Store injunction has been mostly on the
commission rate, what’s been overlooked is just how far the tools
of the App Store have fallen behind.</p>

<p>There’s a long and growing list of features common on most payment
and subscription service providers that still aren’t possible on
the App Store today. Price testing, refunds, managing
subscriptions, plan migrations, gifting, discount codes,
subscription bundles — to name just a few. Entire businesses have
spawned just to fill these critical gaps. [...]</p>

<p>Apple has always been one to embrace competition. It’s a
battlefield where they’ve historically done very well. They’ve
never been afraid to step into a crowded market with their intense
focus on design and user experience to show us how insanely great
something can be when you truly care.</p>

<p>More than anything, I hope this moment reignites that
competitive spirit.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s kind of bananas that it’s 2025 and the App Store still doesn’t allow developers to issue refunds. I’ve had this discussion with numerous developers. They’ll be doing customer support, and <em>want</em> to issue a refund, but explain that they can’t — and users find that so hard to believe they suspect the developer is bullshitting them. But you really do have to <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/118223">request a refund from Apple</a>, not from the developer directly, and step 2 of the process is “Wait 24 to 48 hours for an update on your request”.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Andy Allen on the App Store’s Feature Stagnation’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/15/andy-allen-app-store-feature-stagnation">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/05/that_eu_app_store_warning_about_external_purchases_is_not_new" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wbl" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41889</id>
	<published>2025-05-15T21:09:49Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-19T22:45:00Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Apple proposed a much less objectionable “external payments” disclosure in August, but claims that the EC told them not to implement it.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Some interesting follow-up on <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/14/app-store-eu-payment-warning">that piece yesterday</a> about the warning — with a prominent red “!” icon — in App Store listings for apps in the EU that use their own payment processing. Apple told me that exact same warning has been in place since the very beginning of their DMA compliance, in March 2024.</p>

<p>Jacob Eiting, CEO of RevenueCat, <a href="https://x.com/jeiting/status/1922010640539123921">tweeted on X</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I think this is EU only and might have been around for a while, I
just assumed nobody bothered with the DMA implementation for
external purchases since they were pointless.</p>

<p>Fewer than 100 developers have availed themselves of this option
for obvious reasons.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I think this blew up a bit yesterday because, despite the fact that it had been around since March 2024, few of us had ever seen it before because so few apps in the App Store use it. Eiting includes a link to <a href="https://developer.apple.com/support/alternative-payment-options-on-the-app-store-in-the-eu/#user-disclosures">Apple’s own developer documentation for its DMA compliance features</a>, which makes this clear:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>To help users understand whether an app contains an alternative
payment option, the App Store will display an informational banner
on the app’s product page to identify the developer’s enablement
of this entitlement. When downloading an app, users are also
informed if an app uses PSPs or links out on the purchase
confirmation sheet. Apps that contain an alternative payment
option are required to present users with a disclosure prior to
each transaction or link out to purchase to help them understand
that the purchase isn’t backed by Apple.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I actually think that’s very useful information that <em>should</em> be on an app’s App Store listing. Users should know what to expect, and iPhone users’ expectations are that digital goods transactions go through Apple’s IAP. The problem with this disclosure, as it stands, is the way it looks: like a big scary warning. It should be something more akin to the privacy “nutrition label” information.</p>

<p>And, it turns out, <a href="https://developer.apple.com/support/alternative-payment-options-on-the-app-store-in-the-eu/#user-disclosures">Apple itself publicly proposed exactly such a change back in August</a>. Apple’s proposed updated disclosure uses a small gray <em>i</em>-in-circle “info” icon (replacing the bigger red !-in-triangle “warning” icon), and the following text (<a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/05/user-disclosures-eu-transactions.png">screenshot</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Transactions in this app are supported
by the developer and not Apple.<br>
<a href="https://apps.apple.com/hu/story/id1726640865">Learn More</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>I would quibble with the fact that Apple’s proposal places that disclosure at the very top of the listing page in the App Store, above even the app’s name and icon, but visually and verbally it’s good. Clear, informative, and non-judgmental. </p>

<p>Per what I’ve been told by Apple, they were (and still are) prepared to implement these changes, including the new disclosure screen. The EC raised no objection to the new disclosure proposal, but insisted that Apple <em>not</em> implement the changes at the time. Then, according to Apple, the EC never provided further guidance, until last month when they fined Apple €500M for noncompliance. (And the EC <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/23/ec-clear-as-mud">still hasn’t told Apple</a> what it wants the company to do.)</p>

<p>This seems to be the exact dynamic <a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/apple-to-appeal-e500m-digital-fine-over-eus-silence-in-compliance-talks/">Politico reported on last week</a> (and that <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/15/apple-ec-proposals-feedback">I just linked to earlier today</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>According to correspondence seen by Politico, Apple offered last
summer <a href="https://developer.apple.com/news/?id=szrqxadx">to drop its rules</a> on how app developers can
communicate with users, but was told by the Commission to hold
off, pending feedback from developers.</p>

<p>By late September and following a round of consultations with
Apple critics like Spotify, Match Group and Epic Games, executives
at the U.S.-based firm began worrying that a lack of feedback from
the Commission meant it was teeing up a potential fine and
noncompliance decision.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Heads, Apple was going to get fined by the EC. Tails, Apple was going to get fined by the EC.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ That EU App Store Warning About External Purchases Is Not New, and Apple Proposed Improving It Nine Months Ago</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Apple, Appealing €500M DMA Fine, Contends It Made a Series of Proposals to the European Commission Throughout 2024 but Did Not Receive Feedback</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.politico.eu/article/apple-to-appeal-e500m-digital-fine-over-eus-silence-in-compliance-talks/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wbk" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/15/apple-ec-proposals-feedback" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41888</id>
	<published>2025-05-15T20:23:42Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-15T20:23:43Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jacob Parry, reporting last week for Politico:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“We have spent hundreds of thousands of engineering hours and made
dozens of changes to comply with this law, none of which our users
have asked for,” said Apple spokesperson Emma Wilson. “Despite
countless meetings, the Commission continues to move the goal
posts every step of the way.”</p>

<p>These public comments echo concerns the company raised directly
with the Commission.</p>

<p>According to correspondence seen by Politico, Apple offered last
summer <a href="https://developer.apple.com/news/?id=szrqxadx">to drop its rules</a> on how app developers can
communicate with users, but was told by the Commission to hold
off, pending feedback from developers.</p>

<p>By late September and following a round of consultations with
Apple critics like Spotify, Match Group and Epic Games, executives
at the U.S.-based firm began worrying that a lack of feedback from
the Commission meant it was teeing up a potential fine and
noncompliance decision.</p>

<p>In an October 2024 letter sent to senior officials in DG Connect
and DG Competition, and seen by Politico, an Apple executive
complained that the Commission’s case teams had “made clear” that
then-Commissioner Margrethe Vestager intended to issue a decision
with a “potentially significant fine.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Basically, it sounds like the European Commission worked backwards to fining Apple last year in a similar way to how Apple <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/04/gonzales_rogers_apple_app_store_ruling">worked backwards to arrive at a 27 percent</a> commission on web transactions initiated in apps from the App Store.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple, Appealing €500M DMA Fine, Contends It Made a Series of Proposals to the European Commission Throughout 2024 but Did Not Receive Feedback’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/15/apple-ec-proposals-feedback">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>More Old Mac Font Memories</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://leancrew.com/all-this/2025/05/font-memories-of-old-macs/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wbj" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/15/more-old-mac-font-memories" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41887</id>
	<published>2025-05-15T20:10:09Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-15T20:13:17Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Dr. Drang, writing at And Now It’s All This:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Back before the LaserWriter and PostScript (it’s an all InterCaps
day here at ANIAT) made resolution independence commonplace, most
printers were of the dot-matrix variety, usually at a fairly low
resolution. The original ImageWriter had a higher resolution than
most: 144 dpi. And this led to the interesting feature.</p>

<p>You may have noticed that the 144 dpi resolution of the
ImageWriter is exactly twice that of the Mac’s 72 dpi screen. The
ImageWriter printer driver on the Mac took advantage of that. If
you were writing a document using a 12-point font, and your Mac
had a 24-point version of that font, the Mac would send the
24-point font’s bitmaps (all Mac fonts were bitmapped in those
days) to the printer so it could render smoother text.</p>

<p>The upshot of this was a very slight breaking of the WYSIWYG
principle. On the screen, your Geneva 12 document would appear
with curly <em>y</em>s, but when you printed it out, it would have
straight <em>y</em>s. A fun idiosyncrasy that disappeared when PS fonts
and Adobe Type Manager took over.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I used ImageWriters a lot when I was using Apple II’s, but almost never from the Mac. When I got my first Mac in 1991 it came with a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/StyleWriter">StyleWriter</a>, a rather dreadful inkjet printer. (At the very least it was dreadfully slow.) But I do remember this curiosity with the different style <em>y</em> glyphs when printing text set in Geneva to an ImageWriter. The 144/72 DPI thing was perhaps Apple’s first @2× “double resolution” trick.</p>

<p>Here’s a copy of Apple’s 227-page (!) <a href="https://mirrors.apple2.org.za/ftp.apple.asimov.net/documentation/hardware/printers/Apple%20ImageWriter%20II%20Technical%20Reference%20Manual.pdf">user manual for the ImageWriter II from 1985</a>, which includes copious examples of source code in both Applesoft BASIC and Macintosh Pascal. It even contains instructions for designing your own custom bitmapped character glyphs.</p>

<p>Bonus points to Drang for including a screenshot illustrating that you chose font sizes from the Style menu (in a separate section underneath the actual, you know, styles) in early versions of MacWrite.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘More Old Mac Font Memories’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/15/more-old-mac-font-memories">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Trump Says He Has ‘A Little Problem With Tim Cook’ Regarding Apple’s Plans to Increase iPhone Production in India</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2025/may/15/trump-little-problem-tim-cook-apple-india-production-iphones" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wbi" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/15/trump-cook-apple-india" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41886</id>
	<published>2025-05-15T18:55:43Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-15T19:07:32Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Arjun Kharpal, reporting for CNBC:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“I had a little problem with Tim Cook yesterday,” Trump said. “I
said to him, ‘my friend, I treated you very good. You’re coming
here with $500 billion, but now I hear you’re building all over
India.’ I don’t want you building in India.”</p>

<p>Trump was referencing Apple’s commitment of a <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/02/24/apple-to-open-texas-ai-server-factory-in-500-billion-us-expansion.html">$500 billion
investment</a> in the U.S. which was announced in February.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And which would have <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/02/24/apple-500-billion-american-manufacturing-plan">almost certainly been the same thing they would have announced</a> if Kamala Harris had won the election. They announced <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2021/04/apple-commits-430-billion-in-us-investments-over-five-years/">a $430 billion US investment in 2021</a>, in the first year of the Biden administration.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple has been ramping up production in India with the aim of
making around 25% of global iPhones in the country in the next few
years, as it looks to reduce reliance on China, where around 90%
of its flagship smartphone is currently assembled.</p>

<p>“I said to Tim, I said, ‘Tim look, we treated you really good, we
put up with all the plants that you build in China for years, now
you got build us [<em>sic</em>]. We’re not interested in you building in India,
India can take care of themselves ... we want you to build here,’”
Trump said.</p>

<p>The U.S. president added that Apple is going to be “upping” its
production in the United States, without disclosing further
details.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>If Apple were to assemble a single iPhone in the United States, that would be upping its US iPhone production, which, since the original iPhone in 2007, is at zero. It’s not a matter of willpower or spending — <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/09/trump-think-us-has-resources-to-make-iphones">it just isn’t possible</a> at anything even vaguely approaching the iPhone’s scale.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Trump Says He Has ‘A Little Problem With Tim Cook’ Regarding Apple’s Plans to Increase iPhone Production in India’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/15/trump-cook-apple-india">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>CarPlay Ultra, the Next Generation of CarPlay, Is Now Available in New Aston Martins</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2025/05/carplay-ultra-the-next-generation-of-carplay-begins-rolling-out-today/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wbh" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/15/carplay-ultra-aston-martin" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41885</id>
	<published>2025-05-15T15:44:59Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-15T20:10:35Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Apple Newsroom:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Starting today, CarPlay Ultra, the next generation of CarPlay, is
available with new <a href="https://media.astonmartin.com/aston-martin-debuts-apple-carplay-ultra-for-iphone-users">Aston Martin</a> vehicle orders in the U.S.
and Canada, and will be available for existing models that feature
the brand’s next-generation infotainment system through a software
update in the coming weeks. CarPlay Ultra builds on the
capabilities of CarPlay and provides the ultimate in-car
experience by deeply integrating with the vehicle to deliver the
best of iPhone and the best of the car. It provides information
for all of the driver’s screens, including real-time content and
gauges in the instrument cluster, while reflecting the automaker’s
look and feel and offering drivers a customizable experience. Many
other automakers around the world are working to bring CarPlay
Ultra to drivers, including newly committed brands Hyundai, Kia,
and Genesis.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.theverge.com/2022/6/6/23156741/ios-16-carplay-apple-wwdc-hvac-deeper-integration">First announced at WWDC 2022</a>, simply as “the next generation of CarPlay”, it was originally set to ship “<a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2024/12/29/next-generation-carplay-still-yet-to-launch/">before the end of 2024</a>”. So it’s a little late, but by the standards of the auto industry, not <em>too</em> late. It looks really good — Apple’s Newsroom article is replete with photos and videos showing it in action. It feels true to both Apple’s and Aston Martin’s brand identities — but I’d say more Apple-y than Aston Martin-y, simply because the typography is all San Francisco.</p>

<p>Apple successfully kept the name “CarPlay Ultra” secret until today. (Would have been funny, given <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/14/hbo-max-again">other news this week</a>, if they’d called it “CarPlay Max”.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘CarPlay Ultra, the Next Generation of CarPlay, Is Now Available in New Aston Martins’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/15/carplay-ultra-aston-martin">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Max’, the Dumbest Name Ever, Changes Back to ‘HBO Max’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://variety.com/2025/tv/news/max-changes-name-hbo-max-1236397399/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wbg" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/14/hbo-max-again" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41884</id>
	<published>2025-05-14T23:28:38Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-17T21:07:00Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Variety:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The surprise announcement, made less than two months after <a href="https://variety.com/2025/digital/news/max-changes-logo-black-and-white-hbo-1236352161/">Max
tweaked its logo</a> to look more like the classic black-and-white HBO
color scheme, was revealed at Warner Bros. Discovery’s upfront
presentation to ad execs in New York on Wednesday.</p>

<p>In a press release, WBD said “returning the HBO brand into HBO Max
will further drive the service forward and amplify the uniqueness
that subscribers can expect from the offering. It is also a
testament to WBD’s willingness to keep boldly iterating its
strategy and approach — leaning heavily on consumer data and
insights — to best position itself for success.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Everyone should be clear on what to make fun of here. We should <em>not</em> be making fun of the fact that they’re changing the name back to HBO Max. No one likes to admit to mistakes. It’s intensely uncomfortable. And people who are good at politics and PR are good at spinning mistakes as not-mistakes. We should, in fact, congratulate them for admitting to this dumb fucking mistake and <a href="https://www.techmeme.com/250514/p27#a250514p27">re-embracing the “HBO” name</a>.</p>

<p>What we should be making fun of is <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2023/04/warner_max">the original decision</a> to name the platform “Max”, which was obviously stupid at the time, and has been obviously stupid every single day since. “Max” is one of those trendy words like “Plus” and “Pro” that companies append to their brand names when naming premium tiers. You can’t just name a service “Max” or “Plus” or “Pro” without any other words. It’s stupid. And to make it worse, Warner Bros. Discovery (itself an incredibly awkward and dumb-sounding name — just call the company “Warner Brothers” or “Warner” — no one gives a shit about Discovery) already owned the brand name that stands for “prestige TV”: HBO. They already owned it. People loved it. And now they’re like, “<em>Oh, geez, I guess we should use that?</em>”</p>

<p>I wrote two years ago <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/03/13/zaslav-hbo-max">that David Zaslav might be stupid</a>. That it took him two entire years to reverse this name change proves that there’s no maybe about it — he <em>is</em> stupid. If you were interviewing candidates to be the CEO of Warner Bros. Discovery (a dumb name that a good candidate for the job should suggest changing), and one of them told you that they’d like to name the company’s streaming service “Max” — just “Max” — you should end the interview right there. If I were interviewing someone for the job and they insisted that they were serious about removing “HBO” from the name of the service I’d start wondering if I smelled alcohol on them. If you had Dr. Evil-style ejector chairs you’d dump them into the shark tank or whatever. But instead, they hired the guy who thought “Max” was a great name. It’s absolutely unreal how much brand equity Zaslav has squandered.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Max’, the Dumbest Name Ever, Changes Back to ‘HBO Max’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/14/hbo-max-again">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The App Store Shows a Warning for EU Apps That Use External Purchases</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mjtsai.com/blog/2025/05/14/critical-warning-for-external-purchases-in-app-store/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wbf" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/14/app-store-eu-payment-warning" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41883</id>
	<published>2025-05-14T23:10:07Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-15T21:28:30Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The app in question, Instacar, is not available in the US App Store, but multiple people in the EU have confirmed this warning on its App Store page is real:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This app does not support the App Store’s private and secure
payment system. It uses external purchases.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The warning is decorated with a big red “!” icon. <strong>Update:</strong> You can see the warning, minus the red warning icon, <a href="https://apps.apple.com/hu/app/instacar/id6443874337">on the web version of the Hungarian App Store</a>.</p>

<p>The uncompetitive nature of the App Store — I’m using <em>un</em>competitive rather than <em>anti</em>competitive just to give Apple the benefit of the doubt here — has left at least some top Apple executives hopelessly naive about the state of online payments. It’s like when they still blather on about software being sold on discs inside boxes in physical retail stores. That <em>was</em> true. It <em>was</em> once relevant. It no longer is and hasn’t been for over a decade.</p>

<p>Same with payments. Online payments through, say, Stripe — which zillions of companies use — are completely private and secure today. Amazon payments are completely private and secure. I’m sure there remain sketchy corners of the Internet, but for the most part, all mainstream online payments today are private and secure. Apple’s IAP system has numerous advantages and user-centric features. (If Apple were actively competing, it would have many more.) But the fact that it’s “private and secure” is no longer distinguishing at all.</p>

<p><strong>Update, 15 May:</strong> Interesting follow-up: “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/05/that_eu_app_store_warning_about_external_purchases_is_not_new">That EU App Store Warning About External Purchases Is Not New, and Apple Proposed Improving It Nine Months Ago</a>”.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The App Store Shows a Warning for EU Apps That Use External Purchases’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/14/app-store-eu-payment-warning">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/05/single_story_a_classic_mac_system_1" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wbe" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41882</id>
	<published>2025-05-14T16:21:59Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-14T17:04:06Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">A single-story “a” in Chicago feels more blasphemous than that AI image Trump tweeted of himself as the new pope.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Following up on <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/12/that-stupid-apple-notes-a">my gripe regarding the alternative <em>a</em> glyph</a> used in Apple Notes, here’s <a href="https://www.threads.com/@kfury/post/DJlFkNfR5ik">Kevin Fox, tweeting on Threads</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>While we’re waxing nostalgic on the Original Mac, a Daring
Fireball post today (below) reminded me of another piece of Mac
128k trivia.</p>

<p>Until shortly before the official release, the ‘a’ in Geneva was a
single story ‘a’ like you see currently (and to some,
infuriatingly) in the Notes app.</p>

<p>The screenshots in the original Mac 128k user manual show the OS
using the pre-release single-story ‘a’ before it was changed.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I double-checked using the (amazing) <a href="https://infinitemac.org/">classic Mac emulators at Infinite Mac</a>, and it turns out, Apple actually shipped System 1.0 with a version of Geneva with a single-story <em>a</em> glyph — but only in the 9-point version of Geneva. At 12 points (and larger), Geneva’s <em>a</em> was double-story. Here are screenshots of the Finder showing Geneva 9 in System 1.0 (with single-story <em>a</em>):</p>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/05/system-1.0-geneva-a.png" class="noborder">
  <img
    src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/05/system-1.0-geneva-a.png"
    alt = "Screenshot of the Finder in Macintosh System 1.0, showing a version of the Geneva 9 font with a single-story “a” glyph."
    width = 512
  /></a></p>

<p>And System 2.0 (with double-story <em>a</em>):</p>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/05/system-2.0-geneva-a.png" class="noborder">
  <img
    src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/05/system-2.0-geneva-a.png"
    alt = "Screenshot of the Finder in Macintosh System 2.0, showing a version of the Geneva 9 font with a double-story “a” glyph."
    width = 512
  /></a></p>

<p>And a screenshot of MacWrite running on System 1.0 showing Geneva 9 and 12:</p>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/05/system-1.0-geneva-a-macwrite.png" class="noborder">
  <img
    src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/05/system-1.0-geneva-a-macwrite.png"
    alt = "Screenshot of MacWrite in System 1.0, showing the differences between Geneva 9 and 12."
    width = 512
  /></a></p>

<p>Geneva 9 — the eventual version, with a double-story <em>a</em> — is so intimately familiar to me that looking at those screenshots from System 1.0 makes me feel weird. It’s so clearly wrong. (What it feels like, to me, <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/retrobattlestations/comments/1e5k4xb/a_few_years_ago_i_bought_a_beautiful_transparent/">is the original Palm OS</a>, from the one-bit Palm Pilot / Handspring Visor days. Palm’s small sans serif font was very Geneva-9-ish, but their single-story <em>a</em> was distinctive.)</p>

<p>Fox also posted a link to <a href="https://vintageapple.org/macmanuals/pdf/Macintosh_1984.pdf">Vintage Apple’s high-res scan of the amazing original Mac user manual</a>, which, because it had to go to press before the 1.0 software was finished, contains screenshots of a few icons <a href="https://www.threads.com/@johncsiracusa/post/DJniWZ3NCCR">that changed by the time the original Mac was in customers’ hands</a>. What a remarkably good user manual this is — everything from the typography, to the clarity and tone of its writing, to its comprehensiveness is exemplary.</p>

<p>Here’s where it really gets nutty though. Marcin Wichary — <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/02/16/the-hardest-working-font-in-manhattan">whom you may recall</a> from his recent remarkable deep dive on the Gorton typeface (“<a href="https://aresluna.org/the-hardest-working-font-in-manhattan/">The Hardest Working Font in Manhattan</a>”), or from <em><a href="https://shifthappens.site/">Shift Happens</a></em>, his encyclopedic book on the history of keyboards — <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/aresluna.org/post/3lozitikp5k2d">chimed in on Bluesky</a> after observing that a few of the screenshots in that System 1.0 user manual show an early version of Chicago 12 with a single-story <em>a</em>. Seeing a single-story <em>a</em> in Chicago feels more blasphemous than that AI-generated image Trump tweeted of himself <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2025/05/04/world/trump-ai-image-pope-intl-hnk">as the new pope</a>.</p>

<p>One last note: I of course am not opposed to single-story <em>a</em>’s. Futura’s <em>a</em> is single-story, and <a href="http://neverusefutura.com/">Futura</a>, depending on my mood, might be my answer if asked to name my favorite typeface of all time. I just don’t particularly care for the alternate single-story <em>a</em> in San Francisco (Apple’s <a href="https://developer.apple.com/fonts/">modern San Francisco</a>, not <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/05/system-1.0-san-francisco.png">the one from 1984</a>), and to me it just gives an ever-so-slightly wrong — a little silly or unserious — vibe in the Notes app.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Single-Story a’s in Very Early Versions of Macintosh System 1</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Pete Rose and ‘Shoeless’ Joe Jackson Among Players Reinstated by MLB in Historic Decision</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.cnn.com/2025/05/13/sport/pete-rose-shoeless-joe-jackson-mlb-decision-spt" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wbd" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/14/pete-rose-reinstated" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41881</id>
	<published>2025-05-14T13:19:16Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-14T13:32:00Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Kyle Feldscher, CNN:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Major League Baseball on Tuesday removed Pete Rose and “Shoeless” Joe Jackson — two of the sport’s most famous players who were previously kicked out of baseball for gambling on the game — from the league’s permanently ineligible list.</p>

<p>The historic decision by MLB commissioner Rob Manfred allows Rose to be considered for induction into the Baseball Hall of Fame, an honor that had been ruled out as part of the settlement he reached with Major League Baseball. Rose died in September, and Manfred ruled that his lifetime ban ended with his death.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Like a stopped clock displaying the correct time twice a day, <a href="https://www.bleedcubbieblue.com/2025/4/22/24413338/placed-runner-extra-innings-rule-bad-bad-bad-rob-manfred">even</a> Rob Manfred occasionally makes a correct decision for baseball.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Pete Rose and ‘Shoeless’ Joe Jackson Among Players Reinstated by MLB in Historic Decision’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/14/pete-rose-reinstated">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://srv.buysellads.com/ads/long/x/THREKCSVTTTTTTTZHWQNETTTTTTDCFVJ2TTTTTTTADZJNBTTTTTTTRIV22DW47II2RZULYSCKY7FTBDDQ7QCCYPBG6BT" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wbc" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/05/bolt_what_do_you_want_to_build" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.41880</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-05-12T23:07:20Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-12T23:07:20Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Prompt, run, edit, and deploy full-stack web and mobile apps with Bolt, the AI-powered web development agent that brings coding to your browser.</p>

<p>Bolt lets you build, edit, and test web applications in real time with simple, chat-based prompts. No experience needed.</p>

<p>👉 <a href="https://srv.buysellads.com/ads/long/x/THREKCSVTTTTTTTZHWQNETTTTTTDCFVJ2TTTTTTTADZJNBTTTTTTTRIV22DW47II2RZULYSCKY7FTBDDQ7QCCYPBG6BT">Try it now at bolt.new</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Bolt: What Do You Want to Build?’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/05/bolt_what_do_you_want_to_build">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] Bolt: What Do You Want to Build?</title></entry><entry>
	<title>That Stupid Apple Notes ‘a’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.engadget.com/apps/the-only-thing-i-want-from-apples-big-2025-redesign-is-a-120023531.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wba" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/12/that-stupid-apple-notes-a" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41878</id>
	<published>2025-05-12T17:14:25Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-13T15:13:31Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Nathan Ingraham, writing for Engadget:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>There are <a href="https://www.engadget.com/mobile/apple-is-reportedly-planning-a-major-redesign-for-ios-19-and-macos-16-202804091.html">a lot of rumors</a> flying around about a big iOS and macOS redesign coming this year, perhaps as a distraction to the continued <a href="https://www.engadget.com/ai/apple-should-focus-on-fixing-siri-not-redesigning-ios-again-164446205.html">issues around Apple Intelligence</a>. And while I’m game for a fresh coat of paint across the software I use every single day, I have one plea while Apple’s at it: Please, for the love of god, make the Notes app render the letter “a” properly.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’ve been meaning to rant about this ever since <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2016/08/vesper_adieu">Vesper went under</a> and I switched to Apple Notes. I absolutely <em>despise</em> the alternate single-story <em>a</em> glyph that Apple Notes uses. I use Notes every single day and this <em>a</em> bothers me every single day. It hurts me. It’s a childish silly look, but Notes, for me, is one of the most serious, most important apps I use. And yet it renders the third-most common letter in English (after <em>e</em> and <em>t</em>) like you’re reading a first-grade primer.</p>

<p>To me, the core problem isn’t Apple’s decision to use the single-story alternate <em>a</em> glyph in Notes by default. It’s modern Apple’s aversion to preferences. (Or, as they call them now, settings.) If you want to make an unusual opinionated design decision, fine, but unusual opinionated design decisions should be preferences. Let us turn off this silly <em>a</em>, please.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘That Stupid Apple Notes ‘a’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/12/that-stupid-apple-notes-a">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>WorkOS: Scalable, Secure Authentication</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://workos.com/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wbb" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/12/workos" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41879</id>
	<published>2025-05-12T17:00:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-12T23:01:22Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to WorkOS for sponsoring last week at DF. Modern authentication should be seamless and secure. WorkOS makes it easy to integrate features like MFA, SSO, and RBAC. Whether you’re replacing passwords, stopping fraud, or adding enterprise auth, WorkOS can help you build frictionless auth that scales.</p>

<p>New features they launched just last month include:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://workos.com/blog/workos-connect?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025">WorkOS Connect</a> — “Sign in with [Your App]”</li>
<li><a href="https://workos.com/blog/vault?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025">WorkOS Vault</a> — Encryption Key Management (EKM) and Bring-Your-Own-Key (BYOK)</li>
<li><a href="https://workos.com/blog/custom-objects?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025">AuthKit Integrations</a> — Native support for several new identity providers including LinkedIn, Slack, GitLab, BitBucket, Intuit, and more.</li>
</ul>

<p>Future-proof your authentication stack with the identity layer trusted by OpenAI, Cursor, Perplexity, and Vercel.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘WorkOS: Scalable, Secure Authentication’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/12/workos">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Developers as Suppliers</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.threads.com/@benedictevans/post/DJVCqaZuN63" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wb9" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/10/benedict-evans-apple-developers-as-suppliers" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41877</id>
	<published>2025-05-10T16:30:26Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-10T20:26:37Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Benedict Evans, tweeting on Threads this week:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple thinks an awful lot about customer delight and customer satisfaction…</p>

<p>And separately, a whole other part of Apple treats its suppliers with quiet ruthlessness, squeezing them for every penny of margin.</p>

<p>And at some point Apple forgot that its developers are both customers and suppliers, and treated them like suppliers alone.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I think this is also why Phil Schiller has a different perspective on the App Store than Tim Cook or Luca Maestri. Schiller has been involved with developer relations at Apple for decades, since long before the iPhone even existed. In the mid-1990s, Schiller left Apple for a few years and was a senior executive at Macromedia, maker of then-essential design tools for the Mac. He knows that developers <em>need</em> to be treated as partners by Apple, that that’s the only way a platform can thrive. Games are different, but for all other apps, Apple should view developers as a precious resource to be cultivated, encouraged, and protected — not as a profit center to be squeezed. The only benefit from developers to Apple that Apple should be concerned with are the first-class apps those developers are creating to enrich and broaden Apple’s platforms. Especially apps that are exclusive to Apple’s platforms. (Why doesn’t Apple offer a lower App Store commission for platform-exclusive apps? What if the split were 70/30 for cross-platform apps but 90/10 for iOS/Mac-exclusive apps?)</p>

<p>I’m quite certain that everyone at Apple, right up to Tim Cook, would swear up and down that Apple <em>does</em> value third-party developers and does <em>not</em> treat them like they do suppliers.</p>

<p>But ask iOS and Mac developers, small or large, whether they agree with Evans’s succinct summary above. I don’t know any who wouldn’t agree that Evans’s pithy take is largely, if not entirely, true. You’ll have to ask them in private, though, because, like Apple’s suppliers, they’re afraid to speak in public about the App Store.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Developers as Suppliers’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/10/benedict-evans-apple-developers-as-suppliers">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Trump Administration ‘Actively Looking’ at Suspending Habeas Corpus</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/stephen-miller-says-trump-administration-actively-looking-at-suspending-habeas-corpus-to-deport-migrants/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wb8" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/09/trump-habeas-corpus" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41876</id>
	<published>2025-05-10T00:36:40Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-10T00:44:05Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>CBS News:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The Trump administration is “actively looking at” the possibility
of suspending the writ of habeas corpus to handle people the
administration says aren’t in the country legally, White House
deputy chief of staff Stephen Miller said Friday.</p>

<p>A writ of habeas corpus requires authorities to produce in court
an individual they are holding and justify their confinement.
Article I of the Constitution says the “privilege of the writ of
habeas corpus shall not be suspended, unless when in cases of
rebellion or invasion the public safety may require it.”</p>

<p>Miller made the comments to reporters at the White House Friday
when a journalist asked if President Trump is weighing the
possibility of suspending habeas corpus to handle illegal
immigration.</p>

<p>“Well, the Constitution is clear — and that, of course, is the
supreme law of the land — that the privilege of the writ of
habeas corpus can be suspended in a time of invasion,” Miller
said. “So it’s an option we’re actively looking at. Look, a lot of
it depends on whether the courts do the right thing or not.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There clearly is no “invasion”. An invasion hasn’t happened here since the War of 1812, when the British got us good and burned down the White House and set fire to the Capitol.</p>

<p>You can say, <em>Hey man, look, I’m with you Grubes, but I don’t go to Daring Fireball to read Trump stuff</em>. I swear I’m trying — I’ve been <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/01/meta_zuck_content_moderation_zig_zag">trying since before he took office again</a> — to pay attention only to what Trump and his lickspittle loathsome hateful idiot minions <em>do</em>, not just what they <em>say</em>. But when they even <em>say</em> they’re “actively looking at” suspending habeas corpus, justified by an “invasion” that obviously doesn’t exist, I think it’s on everyone to just stand up and say “Fuck that. This is America.”</p>

<p>I can’t wait to see Stephen Miller in prison.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Trump Administration ‘Actively Looking’ at Suspending Habeas Corpus’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/09/trump-habeas-corpus">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Epic Submits Fortnite to App Store Through Swedish Subsidiary</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/05/09/fortnite-apple-app-store-epic-games.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wb7" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/09/epic-submits-fortnite" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41875</id>
	<published>2025-05-10T00:02:07Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-10T02:15:15Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Kif Leswing, reporting for CNBC:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Epic Games said on Friday that it submitted Fortnite to Apple’s App Store, the month after a judge <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/04/30/court-finds-apple-executive-lied-under-oath.html">ruled in favor of the game maker</a> in a contempt ruling.</p>

<p>Fortnite was <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2020/08/14/apple-removes-fortnite-from-app-store.html#:~:text=On%20Thursday%2C%20Fortnite%20maker%20Epic,a%20prepared%20lawsuit%20shortly%20after.">booted</a> from iPhones and Apple’s App Store in 2020, after Epic Games updated its software to link out to the company’s website and avoid Apple’s commissions. The move drew Apple’s anger, and kicked off a legal battle that has lasted for years.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It was more than “drawing anger”. It was a blatant and purposeful stunt that violated rules for which the penalties were clear. This is like saying that someone doing time in prison for being convicted of stealing a car “drew the court’s anger”.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Last month’s ruling, a victory for Epic Games, said Apple was not
allowed to charge a commission on link-outs or dictate if the
links look like buttons, paving the way for Fortnite’s return.</p>

<p>Apple could still reject Fortnite’s submission. An Apple
representative did not respond to CNBC’s request for comment.
Apple is appealing last month’s contempt ruling.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I too asked Apple for comment on this earlier in the week, and they had nothing to state. Maybe Apple will just allow this. I don’t know. But if I were a betting man, I’d wager that Apple does not allow Fortnite back. That last week’s injunction was a big loss for Apple <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/01/apple-lost-but-did-epic-win">doesn’t make it a win for Epic</a>. If all were forgiven or forgotten, Epic wouldn’t need to submit this through their Swedish subsidiary, which has an Apple developer account only because the EU forced Apple to grant them one. There’s nothing in any US legal ruling that requires Apple to have even granted Epic Games a new developer account (or restore their old rescinded one), let alone require Apple to accept a submission for a justifiably banned developer through an EU loophole. If they’re not trying to make this happen through a loophole, why not just get Apple to reinstate Epic’s original Apple developer account? (Worth noting: Fortnite isn’t available in the App Store in the EU either — their Swedish developer account is only there to run the Epic Games Store.)</p>

<p>If someone blatantly violated the rules they’d agreed to, and is unapologetic for having done so, why would you trust them again? It’s the <em>Fool me once, shame on you; fool me twice, shame on me</em> axiom. What would stop Epic from re-enabling in-app purchases in Fortnite again?</p>

<p>Here’s <a href="https://x.com/Fortnite/status/1920878504284975585">the tweet from Epic Games</a> earlier today:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We’ve submitted Fortnite to Apple for review so we can launch on
the App Store in the U.S.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That sure lacks the certainty Sweeney was tweeting with a week ago, when he was, <a href="https://x.com/TimSweeneyEpic/status/1917716512347152499">ridiculously</a>, dictating terms to Apple. Tim Sweeney is a proven liar and one of the most unreliable narrators in the industry. I can’t believe how many publications <a href="https://www.techmeme.com/250509/p10#a250509p10">continue to take him and Epic at their word</a> that Fortnite is, for sure, coming back. Again, maybe it is! But that’s Apple’s choice, and if it happens, has zero to do with last week’s injunction against Apple other than the publicity and perception. I for one would find it somewhat surprising for Apple executives to allow Tim Sweeney to push them around and mock them.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Epic Submits Fortnite to App Store Through Swedish Subsidiary’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/09/epic-submits-fortnite">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>How Many Apps Used the Link-Out Policy That Apple Claims Complied With Judge Gonzales Rogers’s Original Anti-Steering Injunction?</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://appleinsider.com/articles/25/05/01/epic-vs-apple-what-apple-is-being-forced-to-do-to-the-app-store" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wb6" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/09/how-many-apps-used-the-app-store-link-out-policy" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41874</id>
	<published>2025-05-09T17:16:15Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-09T17:23:01Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>William Gallagher, writing last week for AppleInsider:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Judge Rogers maintains that Apple had successfully made as few
developers as possible benefit from the court’s original
anti-steering ruling. “As of the May 2024 hearing,” she wrote,
“only 34 developers out of the approximately 136,000 total
developers on the App Store applied for the program, and
seventeen of those developers had not offered in-app purchases in
the first place.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So 34 was the number in May <em>last year</em>. But did the number go up in any significant way since then? I was thinking about it this week, and I’ve not only never seen an app that used these link-outs, I’d never even heard about one that did. And I try more apps than most people, and I hear about a lot more apps than most people. If you’re aware of any apps that used this (or even better, if you’re a developer who did use it), <a href="https://daringfireball.net/contact/">let me know</a>.</p>

<p>It seems like no exaggeration to say that, effectively, no developers used this. Which does seem to have been Apple’s intention in setting the terms (27 percent commission, invasive rules for tracking users for a week after following a link from the app to the web, and odious requirements to allow Apple to view the developers’ internal accounting figures to make sure they weren’t cheating Apple out of commissions). But it really makes you wonder how anyone at Apple thought the court would see this plan as compliant.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘How Many Apps Used the Link-Out Policy That Apple Claims Complied With Judge Gonzales Rogers’s Original Anti-Steering Injunction?’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/09/how-many-apps-used-the-app-store-link-out-policy">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple Files Emergency Motion to Pause ‘Extraordinary’ App Store Ruling on Anti-Steering Injunction</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/05/08/apple-appeals-app-store-ruling-epic-games/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wb5" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/09/apple-antisteering-emergency-motion" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41873</id>
	<published>2025-05-09T17:01:42Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-09T17:16:35Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Tim Hardwick, reporting for MacRumors:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple has filed an emergency motion asking the Ninth Circuit Court
of Appeals to pause key parts of a recent ruling that dramatically
changes how the App Store operates, following a contempt finding
in its long-running legal battle with Fortnite maker Epic Games.</p>

<p><a href="https://fingfx.thomsonreuters.com/gfx/legaldocs/zgvojeggwpd/Apple%20motion%20Epic%20Games%20-%2020250507.pdf">In court documents filed Wednesday</a>, Apple called the district
court’s order “extraordinary” and argued it unlawfully forces the
company to permanently give up control over “core aspects of its
business operations.”</p>

<p>“A federal court cannot force Apple to permanently give away free
access to its products and services, including intellectual
property,” Apple’s lawyers wrote in the motion.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Apple’s argument here might go along the lines of Ben Thompson’s theory (<a href="https://stratechery.com/2025/apple-held-in-contempt-the-crux-of-the-case-the-takings-clause/">in a subscriber-only post last Friday</a>) on <a href="https://constitutioncenter.org/the-constitution/amendments/amendment-v/clauses/634">the “Takings Clause” of the 5th Amendment</a>. Thompson wrote:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>My use of the word “took” is deliberate, because I am referring to
the Takings Clause of the 5th Amendment (the clause is
emphasized):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>No person shall be held to answer for a capital, or otherwise
infamous crime, unless on a presentment or indictment of a Grand
Jury, except in cases arising in the land or naval forces, or in
the Militia, when in actual service in time of War or public
danger; nor shall any person be subject for the same offence to
be twice put in jeopardy of life or limb; nor shall be compelled
in any criminal case to be a witness against himself, nor be
deprived of life, liberty, or property, without due process of
law; <em>nor shall private property be taken for public use, without
just compensation</em>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It seems to me that Judge Gonzales Rogers just did exactly that:
her latest ruling basically says that companies like Spotify are
entitled to iOS APIs and App Store distribution without having to
pay Apple anything.</p>

<p>If this sounds like a new addition to the case, it is! The Takings
Clause has not come up in any previous litigation precisely
because Judge Gonzales Rogers’ original opinion acknowledged that
Apple had the right to charge a commission; the issue under the
California Unfair Competition Law was that Apple’s commission was
much higher than was justified precisely because Apple foreclosed
competition. To that end, what would have made much more sense
would have been if Judge Gonzales Rogers lowered Apple’s proposed
27% commission to something significantly lower; to simply wipe it
out completely is what prompts this discussion.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Files Emergency Motion to Pause ‘Extraordinary’ App Store Ruling on Anti-Steering Injunction’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/09/apple-antisteering-emergency-motion">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Yours Truly on ‘Primary Technology’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://primarytech.fm/74" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wb4" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/08/yours-truly-on-primary-technology" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41872</id>
	<published>2025-05-09T00:00:47Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-09T00:00:48Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Co-hosts Stephen Robles and Jason Aten were kind enough to have me on their podcast earlier today, and the show’s already up:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Special guest John Gruber joins us to break down Eddy Cue’s statements on AI replacing the iPhone in 10 years, using AI search in Safari, Apple’s continued fight for App Store control, and what we’ll hear about Siri and Apple Intelligence at WWDC 2025.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Available <a href="https://overcast.fm/itunes1723943281">in Overcast</a>, <a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/primary-technology/id1723943281">Apple Podcasts</a>, or wherever else you get your podcasts. Or <a href="https://youtu.be/WKqSvsiIftc">watch on YouTube</a>. Fun show.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Yours Truly on ‘Primary Technology’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/08/yours-truly-on-primary-technology">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Patrick Collison Interviews Former Apple Designer Jony Ive at Stripe Sessions</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://youtu.be/wLb9g_8r-mE" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wb3" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/08/collison-ive-interview" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41871</id>
	<published>2025-05-08T23:51:21Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-12T23:20:40Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>I’m about halfway through and already feel the need to link to this. Good questions and thoughtful answers. Just delightful.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Patrick Collison Interviews Former Apple Designer Jony Ive at Stripe Sessions’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/08/collison-ive-interview">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>How to Catch a North Korean Fake Worker</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/04/29/north_korea_worker_interview_questions/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wb2" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/08/north-korean-fake-workers" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41870</id>
	<published>2025-05-08T16:14:56Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-08T16:15:29Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Iain Thomson, for The Register:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>According to Adam Meyers, CrowdStrike’s senior veep in the counter
adversary division, North Korean infiltrators are bagging roles
worldwide throughout the year. Thousands are said to have
<a href="https://www.yahoo.com/news/thousands-north-korean-workers-infiltrated-110000417.html">infiltrated</a> the Fortune 500.</p>

<p>They’re masking IPs, exporting laptop farms to America so they can
connect into those machines and appear to be working from the USA,
and they are using AI — but there’s a question during job
interviews that never fails to catch them out and forces them to
drop out of the recruitment process.</p>

<p>“My favorite interview question, because we’ve interviewed quite
a few of these folks, is something to the effect of ‘How fat is
Kim Jong Un?’ They terminate the call instantly, because it’s
not worth it to say something negative about that,” he
<a href="https://path.rsaconference.com/flow/rsac/us25/FullAgenda/page/catalog/session/1728070288065001o6bO">told</a> a panel session at the <a href="https://www.theregister.com/special_features/spotlight_on_rsac/">RSA Conference</a> in
San Francisco Monday.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You could do the same thing with MAGA derps too. Just ask them how fat Trump is. (<a href="https://theoverspill.blog/2025/05/07/tulsi-gabbard-password-reuse-start-up-2432/#594cb0fdcaef316b95f55b34dd60373d">Via Charles Arthur</a>.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘How to Catch a North Korean Fake Worker’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/08/north-korean-fake-workers">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Trump Administration Signal Scandal, Somehow, Gets Worse</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://micahflee.com/despite-misleading-marketing-israeli-company-telemessage-used-by-trump-officials-can-access-plaintext-chat-logs/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wb1" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/08/trump-admin-tm-sgnl" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41869</id>
	<published>2025-05-08T16:06:13Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-08T18:56:58Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Micah Lee, in a spectacularly detailed post:</p>

<blockquote>
  <ul>
<li><p>On Thursday, 404 Media <a href="https://www.404media.co/mike-waltz-accidentally-reveals-obscure-app-the-government-is-using-to-archive-signal-messages/">reported</a> that in the Reuters
<a href="https://www.reutersconnect.com/item/us-national-security-advisor-mike-waltz-attends-a-cabinet-meeting-held-by-president-trump-at-the-white-house-in-washington/dGFnOnJldXRlcnMuY29tLDIwMjU6bmV3c21sX1JDMkg4RUFEOEtGRw%3D%3D">photo</a> showing former National Security Advisor and <a href="https://zeteo.com/p/signal-chat-war-crimes-revealed-yemen-trump-admin">war
criminal</a> Mike Waltz checking his Signal messages under the
table, he was actually using an obscure modified Signal app
called TM SGNL, and not the real and actually secure Signal app.</p></li>
<li><p>On Friday, I wrote <a href="https://micahflee.com/tm-sgnl-the-obscure-unofficial-signal-app-mike-waltz-uses-to-text-with-trump-officials/">an analysis</a> of everything I could find
out about TM SGNL using OSINT, including the fact that it’s
nearly impossible to install without a device enrolled in an MDM
service that’s tied to an Apple Business Manager or a Google
Enterprise account.</p></li>
<li><p>On Saturday, after <a href="https://todon.eu/@ljrk/114444796069542288">discovering</a> that TeleMessage
<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20250503004419/https://www.telemessage.com/developer/api-libraries/">published</a> the source code for the TM SGNL apps for
Android and iPhone themselves, I <a href="https://micahflee.com/heres-the-source-code-for-the-unofficial-signal-app-used-by-trump-officials/">re-published them</a> on
GitHub with the goal of making them easier to research. (It
looks like the iOS source code is actually just unmodified
Signal, so maybe they actually only published their Android
code.)</p></li>
<li><p>On Saturday night, an anonymous source told me they hacked
TeleMessage.</p></li>
<li><p>On Sunday, I, along with Joseph Cox, <a href="https://www.404media.co/the-signal-clone-the-trump-admin-uses-was-hacked/">published an article</a>
about the hack to 404 Media (and to <a href="https://micahflee.com/the-signal-clone-the-trump-admin-uses-was-hacked/">my blog</a>).</p></li>
<li><p>On Monday, NBC News <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/tech/security/telemessage-suspends-services-hackers-say-breached-app-rcna204925">reported</a> that TeleMessage suspended
its service after a <em>second hacker</em> breached TeleMessage and
“downloaded a large cache of files.”</p></li>
<li><p>Today, Senator Ron Wyden <a href="https://www.wyden.senate.gov/imo/media/doc/doj_letter_telemessage.pdf">published</a> a letter, which cites
the 404 Media article and my analysis of TM SGNL, to Attorney
General Pam Bondi, requesting that the Justice Department
investigate the “serious threat to U.S. national security posed
by TeleMessage, a federal contractor that sold dangerously
insecure communications software to the White House and other
federal agencies.”</p></li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>National security leaders using this app — which effectively just <em>removes</em> all of Signal’s actual security features by backing up all messages as plain text — is so stupid it’s surprising, even from these idiots Trump has surrounded himself with. I mean think about how stupid it is that Mike Waltz was using this app while in front of press photographers at a Cabinet meeting.</p>

<p>Lee goes deep, including an analysis of TM SGNL’s open source Android source code, to show that it’s designed to transmit backups of messages in plain text to publicly-facing servers. And it turns out those servers had easily-hackable flaws.</p>

<p><strong>See also:</strong> Wired: “<a href="https://www.wired.com/story/tm-signal-telemessage-plaintext-message-archive/">The Company Behind the Signal Clone Mike Waltz Used Has Direct Access to User Chats</a>”.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Trump Administration Signal Scandal, Somehow, Gets Worse’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/08/trump-admin-tm-sgnl">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Eddy Cue, on the Stand in U.S. v. Google Trial, Says Apple Is Eying a Move to AI in Safari</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2025-05-07/apple-working-to-move-to-ai-search-in-browser-amid-google-fallout" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wb0" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/07/eddy-cue-safari-ai" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41868</id>
	<published>2025-05-08T00:57:53Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-08T16:10:09Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Bloomberg:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple Inc. is “actively looking at” revamping the Safari web
browser on its devices to focus on AI-powered search engines, a
seismic shift for the industry hastened by the potential end of a
longtime partnership with Google.</p>

<p>Eddy Cue, Apple’s senior vice president of services, made the
disclosure Wednesday during his testimony in the US Justice
Department’s lawsuit against Alphabet Inc. The heart of the
dispute is the two companies’ estimated $20 billion-a-year deal
that makes Google the default offering for queries in Apple’s
browser. The case could force the tech giants to unwind the
pact, upending how the iPhone and other devices have long
operated.</p>

<p>Beyond that upheaval, AI is already making gains with consumers.
Cue noted that searches on Safari dipped for the first time last
month, which he attributed to people using AI. Cue said he
believes that AI search providers, including OpenAI, Perplexity AI
Inc. and Anthropic PBC, will eventually replace standard search
engines like Alphabet’s Google. He said he believes Apple will
bring those options to Safari in the future.</p>

<p>“We will add them to the list — they probably won’t be the
default,” he said, indicating that they still need to improve. Cue
specifically said the company has had some discussions with
Perplexity. “Prior to AI, my feeling around this was, none of the
others were valid choices,” Cue said. “I think today there is much
greater potential because there are new entrants attacking the
problem in a different way.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>If they can pay, Apple will listen. And I don’t think it’s bullshit, at all, that traditional web search is actually going into decline now because of AI. Honestly at this point it would be weird if it weren’t.</p>

<p>But. Let’s say Apple would prefer for the current arrangement between Apple and Google to continue as is. But it’s under threat as a remedy in Google’s monopoly case. Is this not the perfect testimony? Traditional web search is in decline, usage-wise — and Apple is considering deals with multiple upstarts. I think it’s all true. But I also think it helps make the case that the current deal between Apple and Google should not be disallowed.</p>

<p>I don’t think there’s any bullshit here. I think we’re at a highly competitive moment between browsers and chatbots and between old-school search and new-school AI. And I think Eddy Cue is right in the middle of it.</p>

<p>Also, a really interesting nugget that, according to Cue, searches in Safari dropped last month for the first time ever.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Eddy Cue, on the Stand in U.S. v. Google Trial, Says Apple Is Eying a Move to AI in Safari’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/07/eddy-cue-safari-ai">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Aftermath</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://aftermath.site/about-us-contact-us-aftermath" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/waz" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/07/aftermath" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41867</id>
	<published>2025-05-07T17:20:23Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-07T17:22:54Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Aftermath:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Welcome to Aftermath, a worker-owned, reader-supported news site
covering video games, the internet, and the cultures that
surround them.</p>

<p>You might remember most of us from Kotaku, where we broke news,
covered events, and brought you hard-hitting investigations. You
might also have seen us at Motherboard by Vice, The Verge and The
Washington Post’s games vertical Launcher. We got back together to
start this site not just so we could all blog together again, but
to try something new for ourselves and for games journalism.</p>

<p>These days it’s tough for journalism, especially about games. The
past few years have seen mass layoffs and site closures, with
remaining writers being asked to do more and more with less and
less. The ad-supported model is crumbling, social media is a mess,
and the businessmen and private equity firms buying up news
outlets don’t care about workers, readers, and quality writing,
they only care about profits. The five of us saw our sites closed,
ourselves and our colleagues laid off, and our workplaces turned
hostile in management’s pursuit of growth at all costs. [...]</p>

<p>As workers and owners, we’re beholden to no one but ourselves, and
to you, our readers. When you <a href="https://aftermath.site/products">subscribe</a>, you’ll get access to
writing that pursues the truth and casts a critical eye on gaming
and the internet, that doesn’t need to placate capital or kowtow
to PR. You’ll be supporting the kind of journalism our past
experience has shown us you like best: honest and irreverent,
written for people rather than SEO. You’ll get a site that
prioritizes the reader experience, with no invasive popups or ads
that burn up your device.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>They’re a smart crew, so of course, they’re <em>not</em> launching this on Substack. (They’re using a platform called <a href="https://joinlede.com/">Lede</a>, upon which the excellent <a href="https://defector.com/">Defector</a> has built itself.) How can you not love a site with this ode to a classic bit of kit: “<a href="https://aftermath.site/bob-barker-mic-gameshow-sony-ecm-51-match-game">Bring Back Those Long-Ass Game Show Mics</a>”. An elegant weapon, from a more civilized age.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Aftermath’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/07/aftermath">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Polygon Gutted by Large-Scale Layoffs After Sale to Sweatshop Aggregator Valnet</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2025/05/gaming-news-site-polygon-gutted-by-massive-layoffs-amid-sale-to-valnet/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/way" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/07/polygon-sold-gutted-by-layoffs" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41866</id>
	<published>2025-05-07T16:38:03Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-07T16:38:04Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Kyle Orland, reporting for Ars Technica last week:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Vox Media has sold video game specialist website Polygon to
<a href="https://www.valnetinc.com/our-brands">Internet brand aggregator Valnet</a>, the publisher of
content-churning sites including Game Rant, OpenCritic, Android
Police, and Comic Book Resources. The move comes alongside
significant layoffs for veteran journalists at the 13-year-old
outlet, including <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/plante.bsky.social/post/3lo4mn4noqc26">co-founder and editor-in-chief Chris
Plante</a> and <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/mmcwhertor.bsky.social/post/3lo4lsc3pqk2c">Senior Writer Michael McWhertor</a>. [...]</p>

<p>Polygon was <a href="https://arstechnica.com/civis/threads/polygon-com-its-a-website.1185405/">founded in 2012</a> when Vox Media <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/briansolomon/2012/10/24/the-inside-story-of-polygon-the-verges-new-gaming-sister-site/">spent
significant money</a> to poach top journalists from popular
gaming blogs like Kotaku, Joystiq, and The Escapist. After
initially publishing as the Gaming section of Vox.com for a few
months, the Polygon domain <a href="https://www.polygon.com/2012/10/24/3547938/welcome-to-polygon">launched</a> alongside <a href="https://botherer.org/2012/08/23/polygon-and-the-documentary-that-cured-cancer/">a series
of flashy videos</a> hyping up the staff’s lofty goals for
video game journalism. In the years since, Polygon has become a
respected source for news and views on the gaming and
entertainment industries — one that Ars Technica has cited
frequently during my tenure as senior gaming editor. [...]</p>

<p>According to publications like <a href="https://www.thewrap.com/valnet-labor-lawsuit-hassan-youssef-digital-media-sweat-shop/">The Wrap</a> and
<a href="https://aftermath.site/freelance-video-game-journalism-rates">Aftermath</a>, numerous Valnet writers have claimed that they
receive low pay for long articles, but Valnet insists that working
conditions are good. It even sued The Wrap in federal court,
saying that Valnet “relies on its reputation as a supporter of
high-quality journalism and of talented writers and editors to
staff its ever-growing business and need for engaging and
well-written content.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Just brutal. I’m not huge into games, but Polygon has been one of my go-to sources for game-related news for years. If I wanted to catch up on something like, say, Nintendo’s Switch 2 announcements, I knew I could go to Polygon and they’d have the coverage nailed. Polygon was everything you could want: good writing, good design, no hype, trustworthy coverage and analysis.</p>

<p>There’s very little good news in media these days. The only talented people I see launching new things are doing it on Substack, and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2024/11/regarding_and_well_against_substack">I think that’s going to end poorly</a> for all of them.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Polygon Gutted by Large-Scale Layoffs After Sale to Sweatshop Aggregator Valnet’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/07/polygon-sold-gutted-by-layoffs">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Amazon, Finally, Now Has a ‘Get Book’ Button in Its iOS Kindle App</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/news/661719/amazon-app-ios-apple-iphone-ipad-kindle-buy-books" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wax" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/06/amazon-kindle-get-book" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41865</id>
	<published>2025-05-07T01:23:56Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-08T23:34:58Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Andrew Liszewski, The Verge:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Contrary to prior limitations, there is now a prominent orange
“Get book” button on Kindle app’s book listings. [...]</p>

<p>Before today’s updates, buying books wasn’t a feature you’d find
in the Kindle mobile app following app store rule changes Apple
implemented in 2011 that required developers to remove links or
buttons leading to alternate ways to make purchases. You could
search for books that offered samples for download, add them to a
shopping list, and read titles you already own, but you couldn’t
actually buy titles through the Kindle or Amazon app, or even see
their prices.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’d love to just crack a joke here about Amazon, maybe, possibly, finally getting a chance to gain a bit of market share in the e-book market. I’d love to just crack that joke and move on.</p>

<p>But really, this whole situation with e-books has been <em>the</em> best argument against Apple’s App Store policies for at least the last 15 years. Physical printed books are typically sold under a wholesale model. The publishers sells the book to a bookseller for a wholesale price (say, perhaps, half the suggested retail price) and the bookseller is then free to charge whatever actual retail price they want to customers. But e-books are sold under <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2012/mar/12/amazon-ebooks-business-model">the agency model</a>: the <em>publisher</em> sets the retail price, and the bookseller keeps 30 percent. But Apple’s App Store policies therefore make it impossible for a third-party bookseller to sell e-books and make even a penny of profit. Let’s say there’s an e-book that the publisher decides will sell to customers for $10. When Amazon sells the Kindle edition of that book, the publisher gets $7, and Amazon keeps $3. But if the Kindle iOS app allowed purchases of books through IAP, Apple would take its 30 percent first. Apple would get $3, Amazon would still owe the publisher $7, and there’d be nothing left over — not a cent — for Amazon itself. Effectively they’d lose a bit of money on each sale, and it would be impossible to make even a penny of profit.</p>

<p>You can’t even fix this by raising prices. Double the retail price to $20 and then Apple would take $6, and the publisher would be owed $14. Still not a cent left for Amazon. The App Store model is just fundamentally incompatible with the agency model.</p>

<p>What Apple should have done, 15 years ago, is look at this situation and decide “Well, we have to allow something else. Kindle users should be able to buy books on iOS devices from the Kindle app.” And the solution is incredibly obvious: <em>let apps send users out of the app to the web to make purchases, without Apple taking a cent</em>. That’s what’s happening now, because of Judge Yvonne Gonzales Rogers’s injunction, but it should have been something Apple permitted 15 years ago because it’s so obviously fair and just. I’ve argued consistently that it’s fine for Apple to insist that in-app purchases for digital content must use Apple’s payment system. But I’ve also argued consistently that Apple should allow <em>from-app</em> purchases to freely go to the web. Tap a button or link, leave the app and go to the web, and make the purchases there. Then go back to the app and the app can sync up what you just purchased. Done. Simple.</p>

<p>Apple’s obstinance on this has created nothing but friction, confusion, and hassle for users for 15 years. It makes no sense for anyone. Until last week, not only were third-party apps forbidden from including buttons/links to send users to the web to buy books, they were forbidden from even informing users that they needed to go to the web to buy books. Apple’s rules included a rule that <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2020/07/parsing_cooks_opening_statement">forbade apps from explaining the rules to the users</a>.</p>

<p>I can see, at some level, where executives at Apple are like, “<em>Fuck Amazon. There’s no way for us to even make an Apple Books app for Kindles, let alone sell our own e-books on their devices, so they can go fuck themselves. Why should we let them sell e-books on our devices?</em>” That’s all true. There are no third-party apps on Kindles. There <em>are</em> third-party apps on iPhones and iPads. But at some point Apple should have just considered their own users. If their users are using the Kindle app looking to buy Kindle e-books on iOS devices, Apple should have just let it happen on the web — and used that as motivation to make Apple Books better so that maybe more users would prefer it to the Kindle ecosystem. What’s the word? Oh yeah ... <em>competed</em>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Amazon, Finally, Now Has a ‘Get Book’ Button in Its iOS Kindle App’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/06/amazon-kindle-get-book">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Florida Republican Congresswoman Kat Cammack Introduces ‘App Store Freedom Act’ to Mandate Third-Party App Stores on iOS and Android</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/news/662180/app-store-freedom-act-apple-third-party-app-stores" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/waw" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/06/cammack-app-store-freedom-act" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41864</id>
	<published>2025-05-06T23:58:42Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-06T23:59:33Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Emma Roth, reporting for The Verge:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Representative Kat Cammack (R-FL) introduced a bill Tuesday that
would require “large app store operators” like Apple to let users
install third-party app stores and set them as their default. The
bill, called <a href="https://cammack.house.gov/sites/evo-subsites/cammack.house.gov/files/evo-media-document/app-store-freedom-119.pdf">the App Store Freedom Act</a>, aims to “promote
competition and protect consumers and developers in the mobile
app marketplace,” according to a <a href="https://cammack.house.gov/media/press-releases/rep-cammack-introduces-app-store-freedom-act-promote-competition-protect">press release on
Tuesday</a>. [...]</p>

<p>It would also require Apple and Google to offer developers “equal
access to interfaces, features, and development tools without cost
or discrimination,” as well as allow users to remove or hide
pre-installed apps. Violations of the bill would result in
penalties from the Federal Trade Commission, along with an
additional civil penalty of up to $1 million for each violation.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is a stunt from the Epic/Spotify-backed <a href="https://appfairness.org/">Coalition for App Fairness</a> that we’ll probably never hear about again.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Florida Republican Congresswoman Kat Cammack Introduces ‘App Store Freedom Act’ to Mandate Third-Party App Stores on iOS and Android’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/06/cammack-app-store-freedom-act">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Tim Sweeney Talks to Peter Kafka, Still Thinks Fortnite Is Coming Back to iOS This Week</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.businessinsider.com/tim-sweeeney-epic-games-apple-app-store-interview-peter-kafka-2025-05" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wav" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/06/sweeney-kafka-fortnite" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41863</id>
	<published>2025-05-06T17:10:14Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-09T23:33:30Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>About 16 minutes <a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/channels-with-peter-kafka/id1080467174">into the podcast</a> (the whole thing is a great succinct interview):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Kafka:</strong> You said Fortnite is going to come back to iOS. You
guys were kicked off the platform in 2020 for violating Apple’s
rules. There’s nothing in the judge’s ruling that says Apple has
to reinstate Fortnite on iOS. Have you talked to Apple? How do you
imagine Fortnite will come back to iOS?</p>

<p><strong>Sweeney:</strong> Epic has a valid [Apple] developer account in good
standing. Our subsidiary Epic Games Sweden opened up an account in
order to distribute Fortnite in the European Union. Our dealings
with Apple on that account have been managed by their developer
relations team, who have been cordial.</p>

<p><strong>Kafka:</strong> Do you feel confident that I will be able to play
Fortnite on my iPhone later this week?</p>

<p><strong>Sweeney:</strong> I believe so. I would be very surprised — well, I
wouldn’t be terribly surprised if we had a bug that took a day or
two more to fix — but I would be very surprised if Apple decided
to brave the geopolitical storm of blocking a major app from iOS.</p>

<p>We’ve told Apple what we’re doing.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>But Apple has, for the last five years, already blocked a major game — Fortnite — from iOS. If Apple were going to allow Fortnite back into the App Store they could have done so at any point in the last four years. And there’s nothing, not a word, in Judge Yvonne Gonzalez Rogers’s decision last week that says Apple needs to reinstate Epic Games. I think Apple just stays the course and Fortnite remains <em>persona non grata</em> as far as the App Store is concerned.</p>

<p>But I could be wrong. <a href="https://x.com/TimSweeneyEpic/status/1919111157249458650">Sweeney tweeted over the weekend</a> “Not Monday or Tuesday. Beyond that, we’re working as hard as possible and aren’t certain what day it will be ready.”</p>

<p>Me, I’m not holding my breath.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Tim Sweeney Talks to Peter Kafka, Still Thinks Fortnite Is Coming Back to iOS This Week’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/06/sweeney-kafka-fortnite">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Listen Later</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.listenlater.net/?referrer=df" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wat" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/05/listen-later" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41861</id>
	<published>2025-05-05T13:05:38Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-05T13:05:38Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to Listen Later for sponsoring last week at DF. Listen Later is a super simple, super useful service that turns articles into podcast episodes. When you sign up, you get a custom email address to send articles to; every article you forward to your Listen Later address is transformed into <em>very</em> human-like narration, and gets delivered to your private podcast feed. You can subscribe to your private Listen Later podcast feed in any podcast app.</p>

<p>In addition to the email gateway, <a href="https://www.listenlater.net/tips">there’s a Shortcut</a> for sending articles from Safari (on Mac or iOS), a web extension for Chrome, and a simple web interface for submitting new articles. It’s very simple and the narrated versions sound great.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.listenlater.net/?referrer=df">Sign up for free and start listening today</a>. New users get $2 in credits to try it out — no commitment. And if you like it, you simply prepay for credits as you go. There’s no subscription — you simply pay for what you use. I wish more services had a pay-as-you-go model like Listen Later’s.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Listen Later’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/05/listen-later">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/04/gonzales_rogers_apple_app_store_ruling" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wam" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41854</id>
	<published>2025-05-01T02:46:59Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-02T04:22:38Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Are the results of this disastrous for Apple’s App Store business? I don’t think so at all. Gonzales Rogers is demanding that Apple ... do what Phil Schiller recommended they do all along. But are the results of this disastrous for Apple’s reputation and credibility? It sure seems like it.
</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>I’m linking <a href="https://www.techmeme.com/250430/p55#a250430p55">here to Techmeme’s roundup of news coverage and commentary</a>, but I highly recommend you start by reading <a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.cand.364265/gov.uscourts.cand.364265.1508.0_2.pdf">Gonzalez Rogers’s 80-page decision</a>. It is excoriating. I’ve read few legal decisions quite like it. But it’s also incredibly cogent and plainly written.</p>

<p>From the start:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>To summarize: <em>One</em>, after trial, the Court found that Apple’s 30
percent commission “allowed it to reap supracompetitive operating
margins” and was not tied to the value of its intellectual
property, and thus, was anticompetitive. Apple’s response: charge
a <em>27 percent commission</em> (again tied to nothing) on off-app
purchases, where it had previously charged nothing, and extend the
commission for a period of seven days after the consumer
linked-out of the app. Apple’s goal: maintain its anticompetitive
revenue stream. <em>Two</em>, the Court had prohibited Apple from denying
developers the ability to communicate with, and direct consumers
to, other purchasing mechanisms. Apple’s response: impose <em>new</em>
barriers and <em>new</em> requirements to increase friction and increase
breakage rates with full page “scare” screens, static URLs, and
generic statements. Apple’s goal: to dissuade customer usage of
alternative purchase opportunities and maintain its
anticompetitive revenue stream. In the end, Apple sought to
maintain a revenue stream worth billions in direct defiance of
this Court’s Injunction.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There’s quite a bit of fury in those italics. Rule one when you’re in court, any court, is “Don’t piss off the judge.” Apple has absolutely infuriated Gonzales Rogers through actions that all of us saw as outrageous.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In stark contrast to Apple’s initial in-court testimony,
contemporaneous business documents reveal that Apple knew exactly
what it was doing and at every turn chose the most
<em>anti</em>competitive option. To hide the truth, Vice-President of
Finance, Alex Roman, outright lied under oath. Internally, Phillip
Schiller had advocated that Apple comply with the Injunction, but
Tim Cook ignored Schiller and instead allowed Chief Financial
Officer Luca Maestri and his finance team to convince him
otherwise. Cook chose poorly. The real evidence, detailed herein,
more than meets the clear and convincing standard to find a
violation. The Court refers the matter to the United States
Attorney for the Northern District of California to investigate
whether criminal contempt proceedings are appropriate.</p>

<p>This is an injunction, not a negotiation. There are no do-overs
once a party willfully disregards a court order. Time is of the
essence. The Court will not tolerate further delays. As previously
ordered, Apple will not impede competition. The Court enjoins
Apple from implementing its new anticompetitive acts to avoid
compliance with the Injunction. <b><i>Effective immediately</i></b>
Apple will no longer impede developers’ ability to communicate with
users nor will they levy or impose a new commission on off-app purchases.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You know a judge is pissed when she busts out the bold italics. Later, on (page 21, citations omitted for readability):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Prior to the June 20 meeting, there were individuals within Apple
who were advocating for a commission, and others advocating for no
commission. Those advocating for a commission included Mr. Maestri
and Mr. Roman. Mr. Schiller disagreed. In an email, Mr. Schiller
relayed that, with respect to the proposal for “a 27% commission
for 24 hours,” “I have already explained my many issues with the
commission concept,” and that “clearly I am not on team
commission/fee.” Mr. Schiller testified that, at the time, he “had
a question of whether we would be able to charge a commission”
under the Injunction, a concern which he communicated.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Schiller comes across as Apple’s sole voice of reason, fairness, and dare I say honesty in this entire ruling. The only people in the world who seemed to think Apple could or should comply with the 2021 injunction (that apps be permitted to steer users to the web to make purchases) by charging a commission — any commission, let alone a 27 percent commission — on those web transactions were Apple’s finance team members, led by Luca Maestri and Alex Roman, and Tim Cook.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Unlike Mr. Maestri and Mr. Roman, Mr. Schiller sat through the
entire underlying trial and actually read the entire 180-page
decision. That Messrs. Maestri and Roman did neither, does not
shield Apple of its knowledge (actual and constructive) of the
Court’s findings.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I mean Jesus H. Christ, that’s scathing. </p>

<p>It’s worth pointing out that Luca Maestri is no longer Apple’s CFO. (<a href="https://www.apple.com/leadership/kevan-parekh/">Kevan Parekh is</a>.) Back in August, <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2024/08/apple-announces-chief-financial-officer-transition/">Apple announced</a> that Maestri was, effectively, retiring as CFO “as part of a planned succession”. Apple’s statement didn’t use the word <em>retiring</em>, but rather the word <em>transitioning</em>. With this ruling and Maestri’s central role in Apple’s decision to forge ahead with a compliance plan where they “allowed” steering to the web by charging the same effective commissions on web transactions as they do for in-app transactions, I now have to wonder whether Maestri retired or “retired”. “Cook chose poorly” (by following Maestri’s recommendation) is not the sort of sentence from a judge that keeps CFOs in their jobs.</p>

<p>As for Alex Roman, I think he’s in some serious trouble. Like doing-time-in-the-clink trouble:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Despite its own considerable evaluation, during the first May 2024
hearing, Apple employees attempted to mislead the Court by
testifying that the decision to impose a commission was grounded
in AG’s report. The testimony of Mr. Roman, Vice President of
Finance, was replete with misdirection and outright lies. He even
went so far as to testify that Apple did not look at comparables
to estimate the costs of alternative payment solutions that
developers would need to procure to facilitate linked-out
purchases.</p>

<p>The Court finds that Apple <em>did</em> consider the external
costs developers faced when utilizing alternative payment
solutions for linked out transactions, which conveniently exceeded
the 3% discount Apple ultimately decided to provide by a safe
margin. Apple <em>did not</em> rely on a substantiated bottoms-up analysis
during its months-long assessment of whether to impose a
commission, seemingly justifying its decision after the fact with
the AG’s report.</p>

<p>Mr. Roman did not stop there, however. He also testified that up
until January 16, 2024, Apple had no idea what fee it would impose
on linked-out purchases:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Q. And I take it that Apple decided to impose a 27 percent fee
 on linked purchases prior to January 16, 2024, correct?</p>

<p>A. The decision was made that day.</p>

<p>Q. It’s your testimony that up until January 16, 2024, Apple had
no idea what — what fee it’s going to impose on linked purchases?</p>

<p>A. That is correct.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Another lie under oath: contemporaneous business documents reveal
that on the contrary, the main components of Apple’s plan,
including the 27% commission, were determined in July 2023.</p>

<p>Neither Apple, nor its counsel, corrected the, now obvious, lies.
They did not seek to withdraw the testimony or to have it stricken
(although Apple did request that the Court strike <em>other</em>
testimony). Thus, Apple will be held to have adopted the lies and
misrepresentations to this Court.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There’s so much more. <a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.cand.364265/gov.uscourts.cand.364265.1508.0_2.pdf">The whole ruling</a> is compelling — and damning — reading.</p>

<p>Keep in mind this whole thing stems from an injunction from a lawsuit filed by Epic Games <em>that Apple largely won</em>. The result of that lawsuit was basically, “<em>OK, Apple wins, Epic loses, but this whole thing where apps in the App Store aren’t allowed to inform users of offers available outside the App Store, or send them to such offers on the web (outside the app) via easily tappable links, is bullshit and needs to stop. If the App Store is not anticompetitive it should be able to compete with links to the web and offers from outside the App Store.</em>”</p>

<p>Are the results of this disastrous for Apple’s App Store business? I don’t think so at all. Gonzales Rogers is demanding that Apple ... do what Phil Schiller recommended they do all along, which is to compete fair and square with purchases available on the web. She’s not demanding they do what, say, Tim Sweeney wanted them to do. She’s basically saying Phil Schiller was right. Read her entire ruling and it’s hard to imagine anyone disagreeing with that.</p>

<p>But are the results of this disastrous for Apple’s reputation and credibility? It sure seems like it. But it would be worse — much worse — for Apple’s reputation if Phil Schiller weren’t still there. Without him, this ruling makes it sound like they’d be lost, both ethically and legally.</p>

<p>I’ll give the final words to Gonzales Rogers’s own closing:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple <em>willfully</em> chose not to comply with this Court’s
Injunction. It did so with the express intent to create <em>new</em>
anticompetitive barriers which would, by design and in effect,
maintain a valued revenue stream; a revenue stream previously
found to be anticompetitive. That it thought this Court would
tolerate such insubordination was a gross miscalculation. As
always, the cover-up made it worse. For this Court, there is no
second bite at the apple.</p>

<p>It Is So Ordered.</p>
</blockquote>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Judge Yvonne Gonzalez Rogers Rules, in Excoriating Decision, That Apple Violated Her 2021 Court Order Regarding App Store Anti-Steering Provisions</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/04/is_chrome_even_a_sellable_asset" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wah" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41849</id>
	<published>2025-04-28T23:28:30Z</published>
	<updated>2025-05-06T23:39:27Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">It’s hard to come up with a buyer who could afford to pay a high price for Chrome and who would pass regulatory muster as its new owner. And if Chrome is not worth a high price, or simply isn’t sellable at one, then why is the DOJ trying to force Google to sell it? They might as well try to force Google to sell the two o’s from its name.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>There are two ways to consider a forced divestiture of Chrome by Google, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/11/20/technology/google-search-chrome-doj.html">as the U.S. Department of Justice has, for months now, been requesting</a> after Judge Amit P. Mehta ruled that Google has illegally maintained its monopoly in web search. One is from a business perspective (which I believe is the only perspective considered by the DOJ). The other is from a technical perspective. I don’t think either makes any sense. I’m not talking about whether it’s fair or just that Google be forced to sell Chrome. I’m talking about whether it’s even possible in any practical sense.</p>

<h2>The Business Perspective</h2>

<p>The whole premise that forcing Google to sell Chrome would be an appropriate remedy for their illegal monopolizing is predicated on the notion that Chrome, in and of itself, is a valuable asset. Here’s an article from Bloomberg reporters Leah Nylen and Josh Sisco that asserts in its headline “<a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2024-11-18/doj-will-push-google-to-sell-off-chrome-to-break-search-monopoly">Google’s Chrome Worth Up to $20 Billion If Judge Orders Sale</a>”. Their source for this valuation, which, again, they simply state as fact in their own headline, is a “Bloomberg Intelligence analyst”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Should a sale proceed, Chrome would be worth “at least $15-$20
billion, given it has over 3 billion monthly active users,” said
Bloomberg Intelligence analyst Mandeep Singh.</p>

<p>The price prospective buyers are willing to pay may depend on
their ability to link Chrome to other services, said Bob O’Donnell
of TECHnalysis Research. “It’s not directly monetizable,” he said.
“It serves as a gateway to other things. It’s not clear how you
measure that from a pure revenue-generating perspective.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>3 billion users = $15–$20 billion is not real math. It’s just bullshit. The users are only valuable right now because they perform a lot of Google web searches within Chrome. Chrome users also make money for Google by using other Google properties that show ads, like Maps and Gmail. And Chrome encourages users, in general, to use Google properties and services like Docs. If you try to work out how valuable Chrome is to Google, it’s seemingly worth a veritable fortune. But that doesn’t mean Chrome holds any value of its own, on its own.<sup id="fnr1-2025-04-28"><a href="#fn1-2025-04-28">1</a></sup></p>

<p>Google also makes money from showing search ads to users of other browsers, like Safari and Firefox, but with those browsers Google pays traffic acquisition fees to Apple and Mozilla (respectively). In 2021 those fees amounted to over $26 billion, almost $20 billion of which went to Apple alone. <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/10/27/23934961/google-antitrust-trial-defaults-search-deal-26-3-billion">David Pierce, writing for The Verge in 2021</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Just to put that $26.3 billion in context: Alphabet, Google’s
parent company, announced in <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/10/24/23929496/google-alphabet-q3-2023-earnings-ads-ai-sge">its recent earnings report</a>
that Google Search ad business brought in about $44 billion over
the last three months and about $165 billion in the last year. Its
entire ad business — which also includes YouTube ads — made a
bit under $90 billion in profit. This is all back-of-the-napkin
math, but essentially, Google is giving up about 16 percent of its
search revenue and about 29 percent of its profit to those
distribution deals.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A key point to remember is that Google doesn’t pay Apple or Mozilla to make Google the default search engine in Safari and Firefox. They pay Apple and Mozilla <em>per search that goes to Google</em> from those browsers. It may or may not be in their contracts that Apple and Mozilla <em>will</em> make Google the default search engine in their browsers, but even if it is, that’s not what Google is paying for. They pay per search. It seems widely understood that one of the remedies that will come out of the <em>U.S. v. Google</em> verdict is that Google will be banned from any agreements that make Google search the default in other browsers. But I think it’s pretty clear how that will play out.</p>

<p>Option (a) would be that Apple (and Mozilla, and Samsung, and the handful of other companies that make browsers with sizable market share who currently set Google search as the default<sup id="fnr2-2025-04-28"><a href="#fn2-2025-04-28">2</a></sup>) continue to make Google the default for search, even though it would no longer be a contractual demand in the Traffic Acquisition Cost (<a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/t/traffic-acquisition-cost-tac.asp">TAC</a>) agreement between Google and the browser maker. In other words, right now, I think the contract between Google and Apple for TAC is currently like this:</p>

<p><em>Google will pay Apple $X per web search that goes to Google from Safari, and Apple will make Google the default search in Safari.</em></p>

<p>After the dust settles on the DOJ case against Google, it might look like this:</p>

<p><em>Google will pay Apple $X per web search that goes to Google from Safari, but Apple is under no obligation to make Google the default search in Safari.</em></p>

<p>And then Apple will simply choose to keep Google as the default search in Safari, and the TAC payments will continue to flow unabated. Same for Mozilla and Samsung and any other browser with Google as the current default. The money is good, Google is still considered the best general purpose web search engine, and users expect those searches to go through Google.</p>

<p>Even if Google is somehow forbidden from accepting default search engine placement in other browsers, I don’t think it would change the TAC situation. But such a ruling would be weird, right? It’s Google that lost a major antitrust lawsuit and now faces a remedy reckoning, so it seems reasonable that Google might be forbidden from any contract that requires Google search to be the search default in another browser. Apple didn’t lose an antitrust case. (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_v._Apple_(2024)">Yet</a>?) Mozilla certainly didn’t. So how could Apple or Mozilla be forbidden from choosing, of their own volition, to keep Google as the default search engine in their browsers? But even if they were, they wouldn’t switch the default search in Safari and Mozilla to Bing or DuckDuckGo or whatever. They’d have no default search at all, and instead present a choice screen to new users, with Google as one of the handful of options, and the overwhelming number of users would pick Google, and very little would change. The DMA requires these choice screens in the EU and Google search <a href="https://gs.statcounter.com/search-engine-market-share/all/europe">still has over 90 percent share there</a>. It’s hard to fathom a US court ruling that browser makers aren’t allowed even to offer Google search as an option for built-in search. (Even the EU didn’t do that.)</p>

<p>It would seem even more punishing to Apple and Mozilla and Samsung <em>et al.</em> if the DOJ attempted to prevent Google from making TAC payments to browser makers, period. In that scenario Google would just get to keep all the money they’re currently paying to those companies for the traffic — it would be a reward to Google and a punishment to Apple. (And possibly a death sentence for Mozilla.)</p>

<p>With Chrome, Google gets to show users ads without paying any sort of traffic acquisition fee to the browser maker, because they’re the browser maker. Chrome is extremely profitable for Google not because it makes any money on its own, but because every Google search that starts in Chrome is a search Google doesn’t have to pay a TAC fee for.</p>

<p>If Google were forced to sell Chrome, and found a buyer, presumably the entire appeal to the buyer would be that they’d start collecting those TAC fees from Google, just like Apple does with Safari.</p>

<p>Here’s MG Siegler, <a href="https://spyglass.org/google-chrome-spin-out/">spitballing last year on who might possibly buy Chrome</a>, if the U.S. Department of Justice is successful in its attempt to force Google to divest it:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It’s not clear who could pay what for Chrome. Bloomberg throws out
the notion of OpenAI being one potential home, but would the
government really want that? That would risk anointing — well,
really entrenching — a king in a new field. OpenAI’s main
benefactor, Microsoft, could acquire it, especially now that their
own Edge browser is all-in on Chromium. But they would probably
just use it to bolster not just Bing but also their own AI
products and services. And that would be <a href="https://spyglass.org/google-disrupted-microsoft/">extremely awkward for
the government</a> as well.</p>

<p>Apple wouldn’t want Chrome and shouldn’t be allowed to buy it for
obvious reasons. Mozilla has built Firefox on completely different
technologies, but with that company in some amount of peril,
perhaps it would be worth the “hail mary” — but could they
possibly afford it? And honestly, what would they really do with
it? They famously don’t have their own search engine. And their AI
work is nascent at best. So they buy Chrome and strike a deal with
Bing or DuckDuckGo? Does anyone want such a Frankenstein product?
Same story with Opera, etc.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s hard to come up with a buyer who could afford to pay a high price for Chrome and who would pass regulatory muster as its new owner. And if Chrome is not worth a high price, or simply isn’t sellable at one because there’s no plausible buyer, then why is the DOJ trying to force Google to sell it? They might as well try to force Google to sell the two o’s from its name.</p>

<h2>The Technical Perspective</h2>

<p>Ryan Whitwam, writing for Ars Technica just last week, “<a href="https://arstechnica.com/ai/2025/04/chatgpt-head-tells-court-openai-is-interested-in-buying-chrome/">OpenAI Wants to Buy Chrome and Make It an ‘AI-First’” Experience</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The remedy phase of Google’s antitrust trial is underway, with the
government angling to realign Google’s business after the company
was <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2024/08/google-loses-dojs-big-monopoly-trial-over-search-business/">ruled a search monopolist</a>. The Department of Justice
is seeking a plethora of penalties, but perhaps none as severe as
<a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2025/04/chrome-on-the-chopping-block-as-googles-search-antitrust-trial-moves-forward/">forcing Google to sell Chrome</a>. But who would buy it? An
OpenAI executive says his employer would be interested. Among the
DOJ’s witnesses on the second day of the trial was Nick Turley,
head of product for ChatGPT at OpenAI.</p>

<p>While Judge Amit Mehta has expressed some skepticism about the
DOJ’s proposal to divest Chrome, the government claims the browser
is core to Google’s anticompetitive conduct. Further, the DOJ team
believes that selling Chrome would level the online playing field,
but it has not been clear who would buy the browser.</p>

<p>According to Turley, OpenAI would throw its proverbial hat in the
ring if Google had to sell. When asked if OpenAI would want
Chrome, he was unequivocal. “Yes, we would, as would many other
parties,” <a href="https://www.theinformation.com/articles/openai-buy-chrome-executive-testifies">Turley said</a>.</p>

<p>OpenAI has reportedly considered building its own Chromium-based
browser to compete with Chrome. Several months ago, the company
hired former Google developers Ben Goodger and Darin Fisher, both
of whom worked to bring Chrome to market.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is the aspect of the US case against Google that most shows the DOJ has little real idea how anything actually works in tech. The non-Google aspects of Chrome are completely open source. No need for dick quotes around the “open” there. Just <a href="https://www.chromium.org/Home/">go to the Chromium project</a> and download the code, which includes all of Blink, Chromium’s web engine that <a href="https://blog.chromium.org/2013/04/blink-rendering-engine-for-chromium.html">Google forked from WebKit in 2013</a>. There’s even an open source project called <a href="https://github.com/ungoogled-software/ungoogled-chromium">Ungoogled Chromium</a> that delivers a completely Google-free Chromium experience. Everything about Chromium, the browser app, looks and feels like Chrome. Except it doesn’t have any of the integration with Google’s web services and your Google account(s).</p>

<p>There are dozens of for-profit browsers built from the Chromium code base. Microsoft’s <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/edge">Edge</a>. <a href="https://brave.com/">Brave</a>. <a href="https://vivaldi.com/">Vivaldi</a>. Even the venerable <a href="https://www.opera.com/">Opera</a> — a browser that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_the_Opera_web_browser">first debuted in 1994</a>! — <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20130214043259/http://my.opera.com/ODIN/blog/300-million-users-and-move-to-webkit">became a forked version of Chromium</a> a decade ago.</p>

<p>We know the value of a Google-free version of Chrome. Nothing. Zero. You can install and use that browser today, or even modify and compile its source code, free of charge. And if a commercial entity wants to take that base and build its own proprietary layer on top of that, they can do it. Microsoft and Brave and the others already have. And we know how popular those browsers are — which is not very popular at all.</p>

<p>If, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_v._Microsoft_Corp.">back in the late 1990s</a>, Microsoft had been forced to sell off its Office suite of apps, or split into two separate companies, a Windows/OS company and an Office/apps company, you can see how there would have been value in both entities. Windows generated (and still generates) a lot of revenue on its own. Office generated (and still generates) a lot of revenue on its own. There was also tremendous technical value in the closed source code to both “divisions”. There’s no value like that at all with Chrome, independent of Google as a whole.</p>

<p>What has value are the billions of users using the actual Chrome from Google. All of those users could be using Edge or Brave or Vivaldi — or just plain Chromium — instead. They’d be getting the exact same rendering engine and the exact same basic browser user interface. But they’re not. They’re using Chrome. For chrissake Microsoft still owns and controls Windows and has made Edge — which I repeat is just a fork of Chromium — Windows’s default browser and <a href="https://gs.statcounter.com/browser-market-share/desktop/worldwide">Edge has just 14% desktop market share and Chrome has 66%</a>.</p>

<p>The DOJ can’t force Google to sell Chrome’s user base because they’re not Chrome users, per se, they’re Google users. In practical terms what the DOJ is asking is for Google to be forced to shut Chrome down, and then I guess sell off the husk of its remains. Chrome does hold incredible value, but that value is inherent to Google and to Google/Chrome’s users. It’s not a standalone product with any commercial value whatsoever. It’s just a software layer between Google and its users.</p>

<p>The more I think about it, the more it looks to me like a complete fantasy that Google even <em>could</em> sell Chrome. It would be at least a somewhat different situation if Chrome were mostly closed source. But it’s not. In fact, it’s the opposite — it’s almost entirely open source. So what even is there to buy?</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>

<li id="fn1-2025-04-28">
<p>Given that Safari generates over $20 billion in revenue for Apple annually, almost all of it in TAC fees from Google, and that surely almost all of that revenue is profit, and that Chrome has more than 3× Safari’s global web browser market share (across all devices, desktop and mobile), surely Chrome saves Google at least, say, $20-30 billion in TAC fees that Google would be paying to another company if some other company owned Chrome. If Apple generates $20 billion in profit from TAC fees for Safari, surely Chrome would generate at least as much, if not more, for a hypothetical buyer of Chrome who somehow managed to keep Chrome, under its ownership, as popular as Chrome is under Google’s. But so that would mean Chrome, as a purchasable asset, would surely be worth far, far more than $20 billion. If you valued Chrome at 10× revenue, that would mean it’s worth like $200-300 billion. But of course it’s not worth that much as a standalone entity, because it would never work out that a new owner could keep Chrome as popular as it is today, as an integrated Google product.</p>

<p>As a spitball thought exercise, consider what Safari is worth, if Apple were forced to sell it. We know Safari generates $20 billion per year. But Safari doesn’t generate that money because Safari is Safari. It generates that money because Safari is the integrated default browser on iPhones, iPads, and Macs. Safari is extremely valuable to Apple as an integrated part of Apple’s platforms, but it would hold relatively no value at all as an independent standalone web browser. It’s like trying to ask what the Apple logo is worth, on its own.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-04-28"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
</li>


<li id="fn2-2025-04-28">
<p>The only popular browser that ships with something other than Google as the built-in default for web search is Microsoft Edge, which, of course, defaults to Bing. <a href="https://gs.statcounter.com/browser-market-share">Statcounter pegs Edge’s global market share</a> at 5 percent overall, and 14 percent on desktop. That’s a minority share, to be sure, but it’s something. <a href="https://gs.statcounter.com/os-market-share/desktop/worldwide">Statcounter puts MacOS’s share of the desktop market</a> at 15 percent. So about the same percentage of desktop users are using Edge as their web