<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>Daring Fireball</title>
<subtitle>By John Gruber</subtitle>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/" />
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main" />
<id>https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main</id>


<updated>2025-11-23T23:22:00Z</updated><rights>Copyright © 2025, John Gruber</rights><entry>
	<title>Clerk for iOS</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://go.clerk.com/QO9JV9f" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wq5" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/23/clerk" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42413</id>
	<published>2025-11-23T23:01:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-23T23:04:29Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to Clerk for sponsoring last week at DF. Clerk makes authentication for iOS apps effortless — just drop in pre-built SwiftUI components for sign-in, MFA, and profile management. Fully customizable, always in sync with Apple’s design system, and packed with features developers love: social sign-in, user roles, and organization management. </p>

<p>Launch faster, stay secure, and scale confidently, whether you’re building the next big thing or a startup MVP. See how Clerk makes complete user management easy for modern iOS teams.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Clerk for iOS’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/23/clerk">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/11/apple_eu_dma_iphone_accessories_wi-fi_sync" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wq6" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42414</id>
	<published>2025-11-23T23:00:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-23T23:22:00Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">The bottom line is that users setting up new Apple Watches in the EU will now get a somewhat slightly worse experience in the name of parity with accessories made by third-party companies. It remains to be seen whether users of third-party iPhone accessories and peripherals in the EU will see any benefit at all.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>There have been several new features that have been delayed in the EU while Apple worked on making them compliant with the DMA. iPhone Mirroring <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/120421">debuted over a year ago with iOS 18 and MacOS 15 Sequoia</a>, but still remains unavailable today in the EU. Apple Intelligence <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/04/01/apple-intelligence-is-now-fully-supported-in-the-eu-with-ios-18-4/">was delayed the EU until iOS 18.4</a> in April, but was <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2024/10/28/apple-releases-ios-18-1/">available to most of the world in 18.1</a> last October. And, both most recently and briefly, the <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/123185">live translation feature</a> for AirPods Pro 3, AirPods Pro 2, and AirPods 4, which debuted outside the EU with the launch of iOS 26.0 in September, <a href="https://www.apple.com/ie/newsroom/2025/11/live-translation-on-airpods-expands-to-the-eu/">will only become available in the EU next month</a>, with the launch of iOS 26.2.</p>

<p>But now comes word of the first feature that Apple is limiting or removing in an existing product to comply with the DMA: Wi-Fi network sync between iPhone and Apple Watch, which is poised to change in the EU next month, with the 26.2 releases of iOS and WatchOS. The news was broken by Nicolas Lellouche, <a href="https://www.numerama.com/tech/2110247-lapple-watch-et-liphone-vont-perdre-une-fonction-en-europe-pour-la-premiere-fois-annonce-apple.html">reporting for the French-language site Numerama</a>. I’m quoting here from Safari’s English translation of his original report:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple has been warning for several months that it could one day,
if it deems it necessary, disable functions in the European Union
to “protect its users”. This day could arrive in December, with
the iOS 26.2 update.</p>

<p>On November 4, Apple announced to Numerama that it had made the
decision to disable Wi-Fi synchronization between an iPhone and an
Apple Watch in Europe so as not to have to comply with the
European Commission’s request, which wants to force it by the end
of 2025 to open the iPhone’s Wi-Fi to third-party accessories.
This announcement follows the opening of the AirPods Live
Translation function in Europe, with a new API to allow
competitors to use the microphones and speakers of AirPods and
iPhone simultaneously. [...]</p>

<p>Apple indicates that the European Commission is asking it to
replicate the link between an iPhone and an Apple Watch, but with
third-party products. Apple, after thinking long about how to
implement this function, finally decided to reject the European
request. Since Europe requires that third-party products be
treated like the Apple Watch, then Apple disables the function on
Apple Watch. This allows it to comply with the DMA.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Lellouche’s report at Numerama broke this story (the reports at <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/11/06/iphone-apple-watch-wi-fi-sync-eu-ios/">MacRumors</a> and <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/11/05/ios-26-2-will-remove-a-key-iphone-and-apple-watch-feature-in-eu-per-report/">9to5Mac</a> are both based on Numerama’s), but the above is not an accurate summary of what Apple is doing with iOS 26.2.<sup id="fnr1-2025-11-22"><a href="#fn1-2025-11-22">1</a></sup> Apple <em>is</em> complying with the DMA, and they’re <em>not</em> disabling Wi-Fi network synchronization between an iPhone and a paired Apple Watch. What Apple is doing, in order to comply with the DMA, is changing how Wi-Fi networks sync with Apple Watch (in the EU), and offering new APIs in the EU for third-party paired devices to put them on equal (or near-equal?) footing with Apple Watch (in the EU).</p>

<p>This change should be relatively limited. Honestly, I don’t think many Apple Watch users in the EU will even notice. But it is at least mildly annoying, and the relatively minor, very specific nature of this particular DMA mandate makes it a telling example of the European Commission’s overreach.</p>

<p>Currently, when you pair a new Apple Watch with an iPhone, iOS transfers to WatchOS the iPhone’s entire list of saved Wi-Fi networks and their passwords — directly, device-to-device. As iOS learns of new networks that the user joins from their iPhone, that information continues to be shared with any Apple Watches paired to that iPhone. The utility of this is that if you’re wearing your Apple Watch, but don’t have your iPhone nearby, your watch will join an available saved Wi-Fi network at your location. Let’s say you go for a run or walk, with only your Apple Watch, and you stop at a cafe for a beverage. If you’ve ever joined the Wi-Fi network at that cafe from your iPhone, your Apple Watch will join that network automatically. It should, and in my personal experience does, just work.</p>

<p>The EU mandate to Apple is <em>not</em> that Apple must grant to third-party devices and their iOS companion applications this same functionality as it stands today — that is to say, access to the entire history of the iPhone’s known Wi-Fi networks. The EU mandate is that Apple must grant to third-party devices the same level of access to Wi-Fi network information that Apple Watch has. Apple is complying with this mandate in two ways: (a) by changing how much Wi-Fi network information an Apple Watch gets from the iPhone to which it is paired; and (b) creating a new framework in iOS 26.2 (gated by a new entitlement), <a href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/wifiinfrastructure">Wi-Fi Infrastructure</a>, that provides a set of public APIs, available only to apps in the EU, to (per the framework’s description) “share Wi-Fi network credentials securely between devices and connected accessories.”</p>

<p>The change for Apple Watch in the EU is that starting with iOS 26.2, when a new (or reset) Apple Watch is set up, the Apple Watch will no longer have the user’s list of saved Wi-Fi networks automatically synced from their iPhone. Only future networks will be synced — the same level of access that the new Wi-Fi Infrastructure framework is making available to third-party accessories.</p>

<p>Under the new rules for Apple Watch in the EU, an existing (that is to say, already configured) watch that is upgraded to WatchOS 26.2 will still remember all Wi-Fi networks it already knew about. But a new Apple Watch will only be able to automatically connect to Wi-Fi networks that its associated iPhone saves <em>after</em> the Apple Watch was set up and paired. So when an EU Apple Watch owner with a new watch visits a known location, and doesn’t have their iPhone with them, the watch won’t be able to join that location’s Wi-Fi automatically, unless the paired iPhone has connected to and saved that network <em>after</em> the watch was paired.</p>

<p>With iOS 26.2, the behavior for users outside the EU will remain unchanged from iOS 26.1 and prior — both for Apple Watch and for third-party accessories.</p>

<p>A user’s Wi-Fi history can be used to glean significant information about them. Who they know (other homes’ networks), where they’ve been (medical providers, restaurants, airports), and more. Apple’s new policy for Apple Watch and third-party devices mitigates the sharing of historical networks, but with the sharing of future networks as the associated iPhone joins them, there’s still a risk here of third-party companies doing things with the user’s Wi-Fi network information that the user doesn’t understand, or doesn’t realize they’ve consented to.</p>

<p>One way to look at Apple’s options for complying with this particular DMA mandate is by considering the extremes. On the one extreme, Apple could have just granted third-party peripherals in the EU the exact same access to users’ iPhone Wi-Fi network history that Apple Watch has gotten until now (and will continue to get outside the EU). On the other extreme, Apple could have cut off Wi-Fi network syncing to the Apple Watch altogether, requiring users to connect to each Wi-Fi network manually, using the Watch itself or the Apple Watch app on iPhone. Instead, Apple chose a middle ground — limiting Wi-Fi network history sync to the Apple Watch in the EU in ways that it isn’t limited anywhere else in the world, but granting third-party accessories in the EU access to these new Wi-Fi Infrastructure APIs that aren’t available outside the EU.</p>

<p>Critics might argue that while this middle ground is technically compliant with the DMA, it’s not compliant with the <em>intention</em> of the DMA, which would be for the Apple Watch not to lose any functionality in the EU, and for Apple to provide APIs to allow third-party devices all of the Wi-Fi syncing features currently available to Apple Watch. Apple would argue, and I agree, that the European Commission’s intentions are incoherent in this regard. The EC insists that Apple should protect users’ privacy and security, while also insisting that Apple grant access to third-party apps and devices that can potentially compromise users’ privacy and security.</p>

<p>There’s a reason why Apple isn’t offering the new Wi-Fi Infrastructure framework outside the EU, and that’s because they don’t believe it’s a good idea to grant any access at all to your saved Wi-Fi networks to third-party apps and devices. Especially without being able to specify a policy that Wi-Fi network information should be treated the way Apple treats it — remaining exclusively on device.</p>

<p>The skeptical take on Apple’s motivations in this situation is that Apple is spitefully removing functionality from Apple Watch rather than offering new APIs to provide third-party devices with the same that functionality Apple Watch currently has, and that Apple’s intention here is, somehow, primarily about trying to drive anti-DMA sentiment amongst its EU users. This is, in fact, the skeptical take on every single aspect of Apple’s compliance with the DMA: spiteful “malicious compliance” that, somehow, is intended to engender grassroots opposition to the DMA amongst Apple customers in the EU. I don’t think that’s an accurate take overall, but in this particular case with Apple Watch and Wi-Fi network sync, it’s almost silly.</p>

<p>Part of what makes this particular situation clarifying is that it’s so specific. It’s not about allowing third-party devices and their corresponding iOS apps to do <em>everything</em> that Apple Watches, and the Apple Watch iOS companion app, can do. It’s very specifically about the sharing of known Wi-Fi networks. (There will, surely, be other such situations to come regarding other features, for other Apple devices.) And as I described above, very few Apple Watch owners in the EU are likely to notice the change. How many Apple Watch users today realize that their watch automatically connects to known Wi-Fi networks when their iPhone is outside Bluetooth range?</p>

<p>If Apple were motivated by spite, and were trying to turn EU Apple Watch owners against the DMA, they’d just remove all Wi-Fi network syncing between the watch and its paired iPhone. Not just the historical list of all networks the iPhone has ever connected to, but the continuous sync of new networks the iPhone joins after the Apple Watch is paired. <em>That</em> would be a change Apple Watch users would be more likely to notice. But it’s not what Apple is doing. They’ve engineered an entire framework of public APIs to comply with the EC’s mandate.</p>

<p>But the reporting to date on this situation, starting with Numerama, paints the picture that Apple <em>is</em> dropping all Wi-Fi sync between WatchOS and iOS in the EU, and that Apple is refusing to make Wi-Fi network information available to third-party accessories.</p>

<p><a href="https://mjtsai.com/blog/2025/11/06/ios-26-2-to-remove-iphone-apple-watch-wi-fi-sync-in-eu/">Here’s Michael Tsai</a>, after quoting from Tim Hardwick’s summary at MacRumors of Numerama’s report:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It seems perfectly reasonable that if I have a third-party watch I
should be able to opt into having my phone share Wi-Fi info with
it. You can debate whether mandating this is the proper role of
government, but the status quo is clearly anti-competitive and bad
for the user experience. I’m open to hearing a story where Apple’s
position makes sense, but so far it just seems like FUD to me.
What is the argument, exactly? That Fitbit, which already has its
own GPS, is going to sell your access point–based location
history? That Facebook is going to trick you into granting access
to their app even though they have no corresponding device?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Tsai is making a few wrong assumptions here. First, Apple <em>is</em> enabling users (in the EU) to opt into having their iPhone share Wi-Fi information with third-party devices. Second, this mandate is not specific to smartwatches — it applies to any devices that can pair with an iPhone and have corresponding iOS partner apps. So Meta, with their lineup of smartglasses, <em>does</em> have corresponding devices. And, <a href="https://www.reuters.com/technology/apple-slams-metas-numerous-interoperability-requests-2024-12-18/">per Apple’s public statements</a>, it is Meta in particular that has been zealously pursuing interoperability mandates pursuant to the DMA. I think it’s entirely possible that this entire issue regarding Wi-Fi network sharing was prompted by Meta’s interoperability requests to the European Commission.<sup id="fnr2-2025-11-22"><a href="#fn2-2025-11-22">2</a></sup></p>

<p>As for the argument regarding why Apple has chosen to comply in this way, what is essential to note is that <em>none</em> of this Wi-Fi network information shared between iOS and WatchOS <em>is ever sent to or seen by Apple</em>. Apple doesn’t see the network passwords, doesn’t see the names of the networks, and doesn’t even know when a device has joined a new network. All of this is exclusively on-device, and when the information is exchanged between an iPhone and paired Appel Watch, it’s transferred device-to-device. (This is also true when you use Apple’s features to share Wi-Fi passwords with nearby friends. It’s device-to-device and entirely private and secure. Apple doesn’t even know that person A sent a Wi-Fi password to person B, let alone know the name of the network or the password.)</p>

<p><a href="https://taoofmac.com/space/links/2025/11/07/0732">Here’s Rui Carmo, at Tao of Mac</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>As someone who relies a lot on the Watch (especially now that
WhatsApp works locally on it), I’d say we have officially reached
the point where Apple is on the verge of actively harming their
user experience for no good reason whatsoever. I honestly don’t
know if this is bull-headedness or malicious compliance.</p>

<p>On the other hand, someone at the EU clearly prefers being in the
limelight by regulating against evil US corporations in ways that
affect very small parts of the general population rather than,
say, go after Asian smart TV manufacturers that are present in
millions of homes and resell data on Europeans’ TV viewing habits.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>No notes on Carmo’s second point. But regarding the first, his opinion is founded on incorrect assumptions. Apple clearly thinks it’s a bad idea to share any Wi-Fi information at all with third-party devices, but they’ve created an entire new framework for use within the EU to allow it, just so they can continue syncing any Wi-Fi network information at all with Apple Watch. Far from harming the user experience, Apple is bending over backwards to make the Apple Watch experience as good as possible while balancing the privacy and security implications of this DMA mandate. Rather than take away all Wi-Fi network syncing, Apple is leaving most of it in place, and only eliminating (in the EU) the part at the very beginning, where, during the set up process, all of the current networks saved on the iPhone are synced to the Apple Watch.</p>

<p>Given the mandate regarding the DMA, and given the privacy implications of sharing any of this information with third-party developers and peripheral makers, Personally, I think it would have been reasonable for Apple to take the extreme position of simply disallowing Wi-Fi network information syncing to any and all devices, including Apple Watches, in the EU. But Apple isn’t doing that, and they’ve undertaken a significant software engineering effort — just for the EU — to support the path they’ve chosen. Carmo’s critique seems predicated on the assumption that Apple is just cutting off all Wi-Fi network sharing.</p>

<p>Given that Apple’s compliance needs to account for potentially untrustworthy device makers — whether by <a href="https://www.axios.com/2022/08/23/meta-lawsuit-settlement-facebook-location-tracking">intent</a>, or <a href="https://www.techradar.com/pro/security/portable-lifeprint-printer-app-on-ios-and-android-leaked-millions-of-user-photos-and-sensitive-data-this-is-what-we-know">incompetence</a> — not syncing all known networks seems like a reasonable trade-off.</p>

<p>Leave it to <a href="https://x.com/TimSweeneyEpic/status/1986222627003023630?s=20">Tim Sweeney to espouse the maximalist perspective</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Why simply not ask the user whether or not to share WiFi history
identically whether connecting to an Apple product or a Meta
product?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That is, in fact, what Apple is doing. But the privacy implications for a user are, in fact, different when an iPhone’s saved Wi-Fi networks are shared to, say, a Meta product than to another Apple product. It’s worth emphasizing that the European Commission’s mandate does not permit Apple to require those third-party companies to treat this information with the same privacy protections that Apple does. Apple keeps that information exclusively on-device, but Apple is not permitted to require third-party peripheral makers to do the same.</p>

<p>Consider <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/102420">the iOS system prompt for App Tracking Transparency</a>: the user’s two choices are “Ask App Not to Track” and “Allow”. It’s a common and natural question why the first option is “Ask App Not to Track” rather than “Don’t Allow”. It would certainly look better if the options were “Don’t Allow” and “Allow”. But Apple deliberately made the first button “Ask App Not to Track” because ATT is, at least partially, a <em>policy</em>, not a complete technical guarantee. If an app prompts for ATT permission and the user chooses “Ask App Not to Track”, that app should definitely <em>not</em> go ahead and attempt to track the user’s activity across other apps. But, technically, it could try.<sup id="fnr3-2025-11-22"><a href="#fn3-2025-11-22">3</a></sup> I presume, if they do, that Apple will rap the developer’s knuckles in the App Store review process, or even suspend the app’s developer account.<sup id="fnr4-2025-11-22"><a href="#fn4-2025-11-22">4</a></sup></p>

<p>Under the EU’s mandate to Apple regarding Wi-Fi network access for third-party devices and their corresponding iOS apps, Apple is not permitted even to set a policy that these apps must pinky swear to keep the information private and on-device. Nor is the EU itself demanding it. If a third-party device-maker wants to send your iPhone’s Wi-Fi network history to their servers and save it, that’s up to them, <em>not</em> Apple, per the EC. Apple sees that as a problem.<sup id="fnr5-2025-11-22"><a href="#fn5-2025-11-22">5</a></sup> You can argue — and some will, as I think Michael Tsai does in the passage I quote above, and as Tim Sweeney clearly does — that this ought to be up to the user. If a user says they’re fine with their Wi-Fi network information being shared with a third-party accessory they’ve paired with their iPhone, that’s up to them. That is a reasonable take. But I also think Apple’s perspective is reasonable as well — that they should be able to make products where this isn’t possible.</p>

<p>The “it should be up to the user” take benefits informed, technically savvy users. The “it shouldn’t be possible” take benefits uninformed, un-savvy users — users who in many cases have decided that they simply trust Apple. The iPhone brand message — the brand message behind the Apple ecosystem — is that Apple doesn’t allow things that are dangerous to security or privacy. I do not think most iPhone users expect a third-party device they pair to their iPhone to be able to send their entire history of Wi-Fi networks back to the company that made the device. (Most iPhone users also don’t realize how sensitive, privacy-wise, their complete Wi-Fi network history is.)</p>

<p>It’s fair to point out that the “it should be up to the user” take is more beneficial to third-party accessory makers than the “it shouldn’t be possible take”. And that this conflict of interest — where the same limitations that protect iPhone users’ privacy by definition disadvantage third-party devices in ways that Apple’s own devices that connect to iPhones are not — works not just in iPhone users’ favor, privacy-wise, but also in Apple’s favor, financially. Apple can sell more Apple Watches if they work better with iPhones than smartwatches from other companies do. That’s obviously true, but that’s just another way of saying that first-party products have inherent advantages that third-party products don’t, to which I say: <em>Duh</em>. Apple’s own peripherals, like Apple Watch, can do things that third-party peripherals can’t because Apple can trust its own devices, and its own software, in ways that it can’t trust devices and companion apps made by other companies.</p>

<p>It’s natural for a company to bootstrap a new product on the back of an existing successful one. Meta’s Threads social network, for example, uses the same usernames and sign-in system as Instagram, which is arguably the most successful social network in the world. Should Meta not have been permitted to do that? Or should they be forced to allow <em>anyone</em> to create new competing social networks using Instagram user accounts as the ID system?</p>

<p>It’d be pretty weird if Apple limited itself, when designing and engineering features that integrate experiences across <em>its own</em> devices, to what it would allow third-party developers to do. It’d be even weirder if Apple allowed third-party developers to do everything Apple’s own software can do.<sup id="fnr6-2025-11-22"><a href="#fn6-2025-11-22">6</a></sup></p>

<p>For at least the last <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2010/05/nack_control">15 years</a>, I’ve <a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=site%3Adaringfireball.net%20apple%27s%20priorities%3A%20apple%20first%2C%20users%20second%2C%20developers%20third&amp;udm=14">repeatedly</a> emphasized that Apple’s priorities <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2021/06/app_store_the_schiller_cut">are in this order</a>: Apple first, users second, developers third. The DMA attempts to invert that order, privileging developers first (in the ostensible name of fair competition with Apple, a designated “gatekeeper”), ahead of users, and ahead of Apple itself. So of course Apple is going to object to and resist mandates that require it to subordinate its own strategic desires — its own sense of how its products ought to be designed and engineered — especially when the primary beneficiary of the mandates aren’t users, but developers. Many of whom, especially the larger ones, are Apple’s competitors. But I also think it’s clear, with Apple in particular, that users prefer Apple’s priorities. People are happier with Apple putting users’ considerations ahead of developers’ than they are when developers are free to run roughshod over the software platform.</p>

<p>The clearest example of that is the App Store. It’s developers, not users, who object to the App Store model — the exclusivity of distribution, the exclusivity of the vendor’s payment system, the vendor’s payment commissions, the vendor’s functional guidelines and restrictions, all of it. Users don’t have a problem with any of that. That’s why Apple <a href="https://developer.apple.com/download/files/DMA-Study-Nov-2025.pdf">commissioned and then publicized a study</a>, just this month, that showed that DMA-driven changes saved developers €20 million in commissions, but that reduction in commissions didn’t lower the prices users pay. Developer-focused observers <a href="https://pxlnv.com/linklog/apple-dma-commission-study/">see that as a win for the DMA</a> — that’s €20 million in developers’ pockets that otherwise would have gone into Apple’s already overflowing pockets. But a user-focused observer might see that as clarifying regarding the fact that the DMA wasn’t designed to benefit users, and isn’t benefiting users in practice either. Apple doesn’t care about €20 million. They fart bigger than that. They do care about clarifying who the DMA prioritizes first, and that it’s not users. (And, of course, that it’s not Apple itself.)</p>

<p>Users love the App Store model. With Apple in particular, users, by and large, <em>like</em> the idea that the platforms have stringent guardrails. Many buy iPhones <em>because</em> Apple exerts such control over the platform, not <em>despite</em> it. But that control is exactly why Apple has been so singularly targeted by the European Commission regarding DMA mandates, despite the fact that Samsung by itself — let alone the Android platform as a whole — <a href="https://www.gsmarena.com/smartphone_market_in_europe_slips_2_premium_phone_sales_on_the_rise-news-67978.php">sells more phones in Europe</a> (and <a href="https://counterpointresearch.com/en/insights/global-smartphone-share">the world</a>) than Apple does.</p>

<p>The bottom line is that users setting up new Apple Watches in the EU will now get a somewhat slightly worse experience in the name of parity with accessories made by third-party companies. It remains to be seen whether users of third-party iPhone accessories and peripherals in the EU will see any benefit at all (because the companies that make their devices will need to adopt these new EU-exclusive Wi-Fi Infrastructure APIs in their iOS companion apps) — and, if the users of third-party iPhone accessories <em>do</em> see the benefit of Wi-Fi network information syncing to their devices, whether their privacy will be respected. But don’t make the mistake of thinking that Apple is complying the least bit spitefully with regard to this mandate.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>

<li id="fn1-2025-11-22">
<p>I’m quoting Apple/Safari’s French-to-English translation, but the gist seems exactly the same in <a href="https://www-numerama-com.translate.goog/tech/2110247-lapple-watch-et-liphone-vont-perdre-une-fonction-en-europe-pour-la-premiere-fois-annonce-apple.html?_x_tr_sl=auto&amp;_x_tr_tl=en&amp;_x_tr_hl=en&amp;_x_tr_pto=wapp">Google’s translation</a> as well.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-11-22"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>

<li id="fn2-2025-11-22">
<p>It remains to be seen whether Meta will actually use the new Wi-Fi Infrastructure framework to allow their accessories, like their <a href="https://www.meta.com/ai-glasses/">AI Glasses</a>, to obtain Wi-Fi network information from <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/meta-ai-vibes-ai-glasses/id1558240027">Meta’s companion iOS app</a>. I’m guessing they almost certainly would, if the Wi-Fi Infrastructure APIs were available globally. But these APIs are exclusive to the EU. Will Meta deem it worth the engineering effort to support this feature only for users in the EU? We shall see.</p>
<p>It’s worth remembering that one of the initial DMA mandates the EU issued to Apple was that iOS must support third-party web browser rendering engines, and to comply with this, Apple spent significant (and I suspect that’s a vast understatement) engineering resources to create the <a href="https://developer.apple.com/support/alternative-browser-engines/">BrowserEngineKit and BrowserEngineCore</a> frameworks, and here we are at the end of 2025, <a href="https://mastodon.social/@stroughtonsmith/111820566793853249">nearly two years after Apple shipped those frameworks</a>, and there are exactly zero browsers on iOS using alternative rendering engines. Zero. These frameworks might be the largest set of APIs ever created that never get used. I wouldn’t be surprised if the new Wi-Fi Infrastructure framework sees the same fate. (Meta might consider that a win, just knowing that Apple had to expend this effort for naught.)&nbsp;<a href="#fnr2-2025-11-22"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
</li>

<li id="fn3-2025-11-22">
<p>Apple has a good layperson-approachable <a href="https://developer.apple.com/app-store/user-privacy-and-data-use/">overview of App Tracking Transparency</a>. At a technical level, an app must prompt for and receive the user’s permission (via the Allow button in the system-provided ATT prompt) in order to access the device’s advertising identifier. From that document: “Unless you receive permission from the user to enable tracking, the device’s advertising identifier value will be all zeros and you may not track them as described above.”</p>
<p>But returning zeroes for the device’s advertising identifier doesn’t technically prevent a devious developer from attempting to uniquely identify and track the user by other means. If the button in the system prompt said “Don’t Allow”, rather than “Ask App Not to Track”, it would imply that Apple could guarantee the app isn’t tracking you (or trying to track you) without your permission. Apple can’t guarantee that, so they don’t imply that they can.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr3-2025-11-22"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
</li>

<li id="fn4-2025-11-22">
<p>I’m not aware of any instances where an app has been accused of disregarding the ATT “Ask App Not to Track” request, but surely it has happened. If you’re aware of any such accusations, and how Apple responded, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/contact/">let me know</a>.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr4-2025-11-22"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
</li>

<li id="fn5-2025-11-22">
<p>I’m not arguing here that the European Commission doesn’t care about user privacy, or that I think the European Commission doesn’t realize that Wi-Fi network information is quite sensitive. I’m sure they do care about user privacy and do realize that Wi-Fi network information is privacy-sensitive. What I do think is that the European Commission believes the privacy of this information should only be guarded by law, and that they already have laws in place that protect such information. And thus it’s not Apple’s place — especially now that they’ve been deemed a “gatekeeper” that has the power to stymie competition — to attempt to protect that information, whether by technical limitations or by policy.</p>

<p>Apple is certainly not opposed to privacy-protecting laws, in the abstract, but doesn’t see the law alone as protection enough. Apple’s perspective is that protecting their customers’ privacy is, in fact, Apple’s responsibility — and one of their most important responsibilities at that. It’s illegal to steal cars, but every carmaker still puts locks on the doors and requires a key to start the engine. In numerous ways, Apple sees the DMA as mandating, privacy-wise, that they create something akin to cars that don’t require keys, trusting EU law to keep them from being stolen. The European Commission only sees Apple’s protections as blocking would-be competitors, not would-be privacy thieves.
&nbsp;<a href="#fnr5-2025-11-22"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
</li>

<li id="fn6-2025-11-22">
<p>In the old days, of course, with devices designed before the iPhone, this wasn’t weird. All software, whether first- or third-party, could do whatever it wanted to. Anyone could write a kernel extension. In the classic Mac OS days there was no “kernel” and we just had “extensions” and you could just drop one in your Extensions folder, restart, and boom, whatever system extension you just installed was now effectively part of the operating system. Any app could read anything on disk. Go back far enough and apps could read <em>or write</em> (deliberately or accidentally) inside the memory of another running application. To split personal computing — not just PCs but all personal computing devices, in the plain sense of the words — into three eras, there was (1) the early era when all software was effectively “root”; (2) the middle era, still exemplified today by MacOS and Windows, when there were user-controlled protections on what could run as root; and (3) the modern era, as exemplified by iOS and stock Android, where the <em>vendor</em> controls what can run as root.</p>

<p>You can reasonably make the case — and expert-level users (read: nerds) often do — that the user should always be in control. <em>I bought the device, I should be able to run whatever software, with whatever privileges, I want.</em> That perspective is valid, but it also describes a class of devices — PCs — that privilege the autonomy of third-party developers over the vendor-controlled stability of the OS. The PC model, where accessory makers can offer software that runs with root (or root-like) escalated privileges, offers significantly greater opportunities for third-party accessory makers than the mobile model, where accessories are limited to whatever public APIs are provided by the device vendor for integration. But with the PC model, users can “mess up” their system by installing software they shouldn’t have, or that they regret having installed but don’t know how to remove. With the mobile model, users are technically prevented from installing anything that could “mess up” their system. It’s always about trade-offs. And with this particular trade-off, it’s very clear which model is more successful in the market. It’s not feasible to make computers intended for use by anyone and everyone which require any degree of technical knowledge or expertise to manage.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr6-2025-11-22"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
</li>

</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Exploring, in Detail, Apple’s Compliance With the EU’s DMA Mandate Regarding Apple Watch, Third-Party Accessories, and the Syncing of Saved Wi-Fi Networks From iPhones to Which They’re Paired</title></entry><entry>
	<title>The Talk Show: ‘Lincoln Bio Services’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2025/11/21/ep-435" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wq4" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/22/the-talk-show-435" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42412</id>
	<published>2025-11-22T17:17:19Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-22T17:18:41Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>For your weekend listening enjoyment: a new episode of America’s favorite 3-star podcast, with special guest Stephen Robles. Topics include indie media and YouTube, Shortcuts and automation, and the state of podcasting.</p>

<p><audio
    src = "https://traffic.libsyn.com/secure/daringfireball/thetalkshow-435-stephen-robles.mp3"
    controls
    preload = "none"
/></p>

<p><strong>Sponsored by:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://uncommongoods.com/talkshow">Uncommon Goods</a>: Out of the ordinary gifts, great for the holidays. Save 15% off your next purchase after following that link.</li>
</ul>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Talk Show: ‘Lincoln Bio Services’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/22/the-talk-show-435">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Jmail</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://jmail.world/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wq3" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/21/jmail" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42411</id>
	<published>2025-11-21T22:25:12Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-21T22:44:50Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://lucasigel.com/">Luke Igel</a> and <a href="https://walzr.com/">Riley Walz</a> made a phony Gmail interface that, rather than showing you <em>your</em> email, shows you Jeffrey Epstein’s emails:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You’re logged in as Jeffrey Epstein. We compiled these Epstein
estate emails from the House Oversight release by converting the
PDFs to structured text with an LLM.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Brilliant.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Jmail’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/21/jmail">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Another Limited Edition Accessory From Apple: Hikawa Phone Grip and Stand</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.apple.com/shop/product/hsbd2zm/a/hikawa-phone-grip-stand-magsafe-compatible" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wq2" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/21/hikawa-phone-grip-and-stand" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42410</id>
	<published>2025-11-21T20:48:06Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-21T20:49:09Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Apple Store:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The Hikawa Phone Grip &amp; Stand is a MagSafe compatible adaptive
accessory for iPhone designed by Bailey Hikawa to celebrate the
40th anniversary of accessibility at Apple. Designed with direct
input from individuals with disabilities affecting muscle
strength, dexterity, and hand control, this ergonomic grip was
designed with accessibility in mind from the ground up. The grip
uses magnets to securely snap onto any iPhone with MagSafe, can be
removed with ease, and doubles as a stand to support iPhone at two
different viewing angles, both vertically and horizontally.
Inspired by modern sculpture, each Hikawa product is an art object
unto itself. The limited edition Hikawa Phone Grip &amp; Stand is
available in two colors, a bold, high-visibility Chartreuse and
recycled Crater, exclusive to Apple.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Looks like a perfectly cromulent accessory, but <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/11/hikawa-chartreuse.jpeg">Chartreuse</a> and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/11/hikawa-crater.jpeg">Crater</a> are both a bit out there — in different ways — to be the only two color options. Or, I should say, <em>were</em> a bit out there. Both are already sold out from Apple.</p>

<p>I’m not quite sure what’s limited about the Chartreuse, given that Hikawa’s website <a href="https://www.baileyhikawa.com/products/wavy-triangle-grip-stand-in-chartreuse">still lists it as “ready to ship”</a> along with pre-orders for <a href="https://www.baileyhikawa.com/products/hikawa-adaptive-grip-stand-in-cobalt">Cobalt</a> and <a href="https://www.baileyhikawa.com/products/wavy-triangle-grip-stand-in-chartreuse-copy">Blurple Swirl</a> (whose URL seems a bit rushed).</p>

<p>Amusing to see Apple partner with a company whose main products alongside iPhone cases are <a href="https://www.baileyhikawa.com/collections/toilet-seats">fanciful toilet seats</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Another Limited Edition Accessory From Apple: Hikawa Phone Grip and Stand’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/21/hikawa-phone-grip-and-stand">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Grok’s Elon Musk Worship Is Getting Weird’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/ai-artificial-intelligence/825675/groks-elon-musk-worship-is-getting-weird" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wq1" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/21/grok-elon-musk" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42409</id>
	<published>2025-11-21T20:10:56Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-21T20:10:56Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Adi Robertson, The Verge:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>As a number of people have pointed out on social media over the
past day, Grok’s public-facing chatbot is currently prone to
insisting on Musk’s prowess at absolutely anything, no matter how
unlikely — or conversely, embarrassing — a given feat is.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Grok claims Musk is fitter than LeBron James, funnier than Jerry Seinfeld, and would likely figure out a way to resurrect himself from the dead faster than Jesus.</p>

<p>But it’s a trustworthy source to author an encyclopedia, sure.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Grok’s Elon Musk Worship Is Getting Weird’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/21/grok-elon-musk">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Group Chats in ChatGPT Now Available Worldwide</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://openai.com/index/group-chats-in-chatgpt/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wq0" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/21/group-chats-chatgpt-worldwide" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42408</id>
	<published>2025-11-21T17:28:41Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-21T17:28:42Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>OpenAI:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Early feedback from the pilot has been positive, so we’re
expanding group chats to all logged-in users on ChatGPT Free, Go,
Plus and Pro plans globally over the coming days. We will continue
refining the experience as more people start using it.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That didn’t take long — the initial rollout limited to Japan, New Zealand, Korea, and Taiwan started just <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/17/group-chats-in-chatgpt">three days ago</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Group Chats in ChatGPT Now Available Worldwide’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/21/group-chats-chatgpt-worldwide">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Fun Stunt to Promote ‘Pluribus’: An Ask Me Anything on Reddit With Carol Sturka</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.reddit.com/r/tvPlus/comments/1p1lnf4/im_carol_sturka_author_of_bloodsong_of_wycaro_ask/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wpz" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/21/pluribus-carol-sturka-ama" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42407</id>
	<published>2025-11-21T17:20:28Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-21T18:01:36Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>“Carol Sturka”, actress Rhea Seehorn’s fictional protagonist of the new Apple TV series <em>Pluribus</em>, is on Reddit right now — at 12n ET / 9am PT — doing an AMA in character. Sturka is a fantasy novelist, and Apple Books has <a href="https://books.apple.com/us/book/bloodsong-of-wycaro/id6754341665">an 11-page excerpt of her “new” novel <em>Bloodsong of Wycaro</em></a>. Unclear whether it’s Seehorn writing the in-character responses, but it’s definitely Seehorn in the confirmation photo. Reminiscent of <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/01/16/severance-balloon-generator">some of the promotional fun</a> Apple has had for <em>Severance</em>.</p>

<p>Both my wife and I are loving <em>Pluribus</em> so far. I highly recommend watching the first episode without even knowing the premise, if you can.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Fun Stunt to Promote ‘Pluribus’: An Ask Me Anything on Reddit With Carol Sturka’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/21/pluribus-carol-sturka-ama">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Pixar: The Early Days’ — Never-Before-Seen 1996 Interview With Steve Jobs</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stevejobsarchive.com/stories/pixar-early-days" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wpy" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/20/jobs-pixar-interview" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42406</id>
	<published>2025-11-21T00:21:40Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-21T00:22:11Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The Steve Jobs Archive:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>To mark <em>Toy Story</em>’s 30th anniversary, we’re sharing a
never-before-seen interview with Steve from November 22, 1996 — exactly one year after the film debuted in theaters.</p>

<p><em>Toy Story</em> was the world’s first entirely computer-animated
feature-length film. An instant hit with audiences and critics, it
also transformed Pixar, which went public the week after its
premiere. Buoyed by <em>Toy Story</em> ’s success, Pixar’s stock price
closed at nearly double its initial offering, giving it a market
valuation of approximately $1.5 billion and marking the largest
IPO of 1995. The following year, <em>Toy Story</em> was nominated for
three Academy Awards en route to winning a Special Achievement
Oscar in March. In July, Pixar announced that it would close its
television-commercial unit to focus primarily on feature films. By
the time of the interview, the team had grown by 70 percent in
less than a year; <em>A Bug’s Life</em> was in production; and behind the
scenes, Steve was using his new leverage to renegotiate Pixar’s
partnership with Disney.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Kind of a weird interview. The video quality is poor, and whoever was running the camera zoomed in and out awkwardly. It’s like ... just a VHS tape? But it’s also weird in a cool way to get a “new” Steve Jobs interview in 2025, and Jobs, as ever, is thoughtful and insightful. Well worth 23 minutes of your time.</p>

<p>There’s a particularly interesting bit at the end when Jobs discusses how Pixar was half a computer company (with extraordinary technology) and half a movie studio (with extraordinary filmmaking talent), but eventually they had to choose between the two industries for how to pay their employees to motivate them to remain at Pixar. The Hollywood way would be with contracts; the Silicon Valley way would be with stock options. Jobs chose the Silicon Valley path for Pixar.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Pixar: The Early Days’ — Never-Before-Seen 1996 Interview With Steve Jobs’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/20/jobs-pixar-interview">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Contrary to Rumors, Apple Will Continue Broadcasting ‘Friday Night Baseball’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.mlb.com/news/mlb-announces-media-rights-deals-with-espn-nbc-netflix" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wpx" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/19/apple-friday-night-baseball" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42405</id>
	<published>2025-11-19T21:45:23Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-19T21:45:24Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Anthony Castrovince, reporting for MLB.com on the new broadcast rights agreement that will cover the next three seasons of baseball:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Sunday Night Baseball will shift from ESPN, where it aired since
1990, to NBCUniversal, which also secured the rights to Sunday
Leadoff and the Wild Card Series in the postseason for NBC and
Peacock.</p>

<p>Netflix will now air the T-Mobile Home Run Derby, an Opening Night
exclusive and special event games set to include the 2026 MLB at
Field of Dreams Game and the World Baseball Classic in Japan.</p>

<p>And ESPN will receive a national midweek game package throughout
the season while also acquiring the rights to sell MLB.TV, the
league’s out-of-market streaming service that set a record with
19.4 billion minutes watched in 2025. [...]</p>

<p>FOX/FS1 will continue to be the home of the All-Star Game and
regular season games, as well as the World Series, League
Championship Series, and Division Series presented by Booking.com.
TBS will continue to house LCS and Division Series telecasts, plus
regular season games on Tuesday nights. Apple TV will continue to
stream “Friday Night Baseball” doubleheaders throughout the
regular season.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Back in August, <a href="https://x.com/kendallbaker/status/1957930701086679514">Kendall Baker of Yahoo Sports reported</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <ul>
<li>Apple is fully out. RIP Friday Night Baseball</li>
<li>NBC/Peacock is in, for Friday and Sunday exclusive and Wild Card</li>
<li>MLB TV being sold to ESPN (for a boatload of $$$)</li>
<li>Netflix gets HR Derby</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>He batted .750 on that tweet.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Contrary to Rumors, Apple Will Continue Broadcasting ‘Friday Night Baseball’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/19/apple-friday-night-baseball">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Cloudflare’s Uptime and Scale</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://mastodon.social/@arroz/115577670987313083" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wpw" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/19/cloudflare-uptime" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42404</id>
	<published>2025-11-19T20:29:24Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-20T00:14:06Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Miguel Arroz, on Mastodon:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Unpopular opinion, apparently: companies like Cloudflare and
Amazon provide very high quality services people and enterprises
actually need, with a level of uptime and security vastly superior
to what most of their customers would achieve on their own or
using traditional providers. Their downtimes being so visible is a
consequence of their success.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A few readers have (very politely!) asked me whether yesterday’s outage (which made DF unreachable for, I think, about 90 minutes) made me rethink relying on a centralized provider like Cloudflare. My answer is no.</p>

<p>Until I started using Cloudflare in 2018, Daring Fireball relied on no upstream service. I paid for a server from a web hosting provider (those providers changed a few times over the years), and when you, a reader, requested a page on this site, your browser communicated directly with my server via HTTP requests and my server responded directly back. The basic architecture of the World Wide Web is beautifully simple, and I embraced that simplicity with the way I hosted and served Daring Fireball.</p>

<p>But the move away from HTTP to HTTPS added a lot of complexity. That complexity is probably worth it, overall, but it came at the price of simplicity. I originally made the switch to using Cloudflare as a caching front-end for Daring Fireball as a solution to <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2018/09/df_slowdown">an SSL-related slowdown that affected only some visitors</a> in 2018. But I’d started using Cloudflare to handle my DNS the year before.</p>

<p>Daring Fireball has always been a fast website and has always had very good uptime. That’s not because the back end is <em>cleverly</em> architected, but rather because it’s so <em>simply</em> architected. But DF’s overall uptime and the frequency of any sort of performance problems went from good to great when I started relying on Cloudflare as a proxy. Also, in recent years, bot traffic has exploded. (Thanks, AI.) I’m pretty sure my server could handle those bursts of traffic on its own, but I sleep better not having to worry about it, because Cloudflare handles <a href="https://www.manton.org/2025/11/19/this-report-from-matthew-prince.html">mind-boggling amounts</a> of traffic.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Cloudflare’s Uptime and Scale’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/19/cloudflare-uptime">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple Announces Finalists for the 2025 App Store Awards</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2025/11/apple-announces-finalists-for-the-2025-app-store-awards/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wpv" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/19/finalists-for-app-store-awards" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42403</id>
	<published>2025-11-19T19:48:21Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-19T19:48:21Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Apple Newsroom:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Finalists in the Mac App of the Year category provided users with powerful tools to confidently take on new projects:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/acorn-8/id6737921844">Acorn</a>, for being the go-to tool for pro-level photo edits.</li>
<li><a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/essayist-academic-writing-app/id1537845384">Essayist</a>, for taking the stress out of sourcing and formatting academic papers.</li>
<li><a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/under-my-roof-home-inventory/id1524335878">Under My Roof</a>, for keeping homeowners organized and prepared.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>Nice to see Flying Meat’s <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/acorn-8/id6737921844">Acorn</a> — one of my own favorite and most-used apps since 2007, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2007/09/10/acorn">before it even shipped</a> — getting this sort of recognition from Apple. Back in June, <a href="https://shapeof.com/archives/2025/6/acorn_fn_wwdc_2025_keynote.html">Apple featured Acorn in the WWDC keynote</a>, during the preview of Liquid Glass.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Announces Finalists for the 2025 App Store Awards’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/19/finalists-for-app-store-awards">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Cloudflare CEO Matthew Prince Explains, in Detail, and Apologizes for Yesterday’s Global Outage</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/18-november-2025-outage/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wpu" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/19/cloudflare-prince-portmortem" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42402</id>
	<published>2025-11-19T17:26:22Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-19T20:36:24Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Cloudflare CEO Matthew Prince:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>The issue was not caused, directly or indirectly, by a cyber
attack or malicious activity of any kind.</em> Instead, it was
triggered by a change to one of our database systems’ permissions
which caused the database to output multiple entries into a
“feature file” used by our Bot Management system. That feature
file, in turn, doubled in size. The larger-than-expected feature
file was then propagated to all the machines that make up our
network.</p>

<p>The software running on these machines to route traffic across our
network reads this feature file to keep our Bot Management system
up to date with ever changing threats. The software had a limit on
the size of the feature file that was below its doubled size. That
caused the software to fail.</p>

<p>After we initially wrongly suspected the symptoms we were seeing
were caused by a hyper-scale DDoS attack, we correctly
identified the core issue and were able to stop the propagation
of the larger-than-expected feature file and replace it with an
earlier version of the file. Core traffic was largely flowing as
normal by 14:30. We worked over the next few hours to mitigate
increased load on various parts of our network as traffic rushed
back online. As of 17:06 all systems at Cloudflare were
functioning as normal.</p>

<p>We are sorry for the impact to our customers and to the Internet
in general. Given Cloudflare’s importance in the Internet
ecosystem any outage of any of our systems is unacceptable. That
there was a period of time where our network was not able to route
traffic is deeply painful to every member of our team. We know we
let you down today.</p>

<p>This post is an in-depth recount of exactly what happened and what
systems and processes failed. It is also the beginning, though not
the end, of what we plan to do in order to make sure an outage
like this will not happen again.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Everything about this incident exemplifies why Cloudflare is one of my favorite companies in the world. Ideally, it wouldn’t have happened, but shit does happen. Among the things to note about Cloudflare’s response:</p>

<ul>
<li>They identified and fixed the issue quickly.</li>
<li>They issued frequent updates to <a href="https://www.cloudflarestatus.com/">their status site</a> while the incident remained ongoing.</li>
<li>They published this postmortem within 24 hours. (That’s remarkable, given the technical breadth of the postmortem. Publishing this tomorrow, within 48 hours of the incident, would have been a praise-worthy accomplishment.) <strong>Update:</strong> Actually, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45978769">according to Prince</a>, commenting on Hacker News, the postmortem was published less than 12 hours after the incident began. Amazing.</li>
<li>The postmortem starts with a cogent, well-written layperson’s explanation of what happened and why.</li>
<li>The postmortem expands to include very specific technical details, including <a href="https://infosec.exchange/@mttaggart/115573489086885199">source code</a>.</li>
</ul>

<p>Lastly, it’s worth noting that Prince put his own name on the postmortem (and <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45974320">wrote much of it himself</a>, using BBEdit), and closed with this apology, taking personal responsibility:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>An outage like today is unacceptable. We’ve architected our
systems to be highly resilient to failure to ensure traffic will
always continue to flow. When we’ve had outages in the past it’s
always led to us building new, more resilient systems.</p>

<p>On behalf of the entire team at Cloudflare, I would like to
apologize for the pain we caused the Internet today.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is how it’s done.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Cloudflare CEO Matthew Prince Explains, in Detail, and Apologizes for Yesterday’s Global Outage’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/19/cloudflare-prince-portmortem">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Tim Cook Among Attendees of Last Night’s Black-Tie White House Dinner Honoring Journalist-Murdering Tyrant Mohammed bin Salman of Saudi Arabia</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/11/18/us/politics/trump-saudi-dinner-guests.html?unlocked_article_code=1.2U8.clG6.uxuqC4aodHYk&amp;smid=url-share" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wpt" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/19/cook-white-house-mbs" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42401</id>
	<published>2025-11-19T16:46:26Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-19T16:46:26Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The New York Times:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The world’s richest man. One of the world’s most famous soccer
players. The president of soccer’s governing body. Dozens of
executives from the finance, tech and energy sectors. These are
some of the guests who attended President Trump’s black-tie dinner
for Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman of Saudi Arabia at the White
House on Tuesday evening.</p>

<p>The red carpet welcome for Prince Mohammed is an extraordinary
moment in diplomatic relations with Saudi Arabia. It is his first
visit to the United States since the 2018 killing of the
Washington Post columnist Jamal Khashoggi, which <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/02/26/us/politics/jamal-khashoggi-killing-cia-report.html">U.S.
intelligence determined the prince ordered</a>. Prince
Mohammed has denied involvement.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Yours truly, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/08/gold_frankincense_and_silicon">back in August</a>, after <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f9DrCgWtOUw">Tim Cook’s Oval Office gift of gold to Trump</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It is disturbing to think that the leader of a beloved, trusted,
and widely believed-to-be-ethical company like Apple has succumbed
to avarice. That Tim Cook feels no qualms about — or perhaps even
delights in — participating in a quid-pro-quo-driven corrupt
administration in which flattery, fealty, gifts, and
barely-concealed bribes are rewarded. That the United States
devolving into kleptocracy suits Tim Cook just fine, because
Apple’s pockets are deep enough to pay the vig.</p>

<p>But the alternative is more disturbing.</p>

<p>What if Tim Cook is, in fact, strong, proud, and driven by a keen
sense of moral and ethical clarity? Perhaps Cook declined Trump’s
invitation to join his Middle East entourage in May only because
he was otherwise busy. But I believe there are bridges he will not
cross — and that trip, especially its implicit and explicit
praise and sanctification of the Saudi regime in general, and MBS
in particular, was one of them. The whole trip was grotesque, and
made a mockery of traditional American values.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>MBS being feted <em>in the White House</em> is even more grotesque.</p>

<p><strong>See also:</strong> Karen Attiah, who in her previous job as editor of The Washington Post’s global opinion section hired Jamal Khashoggi after he was exiled from Saudi Arabia, in The Guardian: “<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2025/nov/18/saudi-arabia-america-jamal-khashoggi">The Saudification of America Is Under Way</a>”.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Tim Cook Among Attendees of Last Night’s Black-Tie White House Dinner Honoring Journalist-Murdering Tyrant Mohammed bin Salman of Saudi Arabia’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/19/cook-white-house-mbs">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Talk Show: ‘Knee-Jerk Contrarian’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2025/11/18/ep-434" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wps" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/18/the-talk-show-434" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42400</id>
	<published>2025-11-18T23:34:58Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-18T23:34:58Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Special guest Dan Frommer returns to the show. Topics include the indie media business, the iPhone Pocket, the iPhone Air (including rumors about the second generation model), AI “personalities”, and five years of Apple Silicon Macs. Also, six years of Dan’s site, <a href="https://newconsumer.com/">The New Consumer</a>.</p>

<p><audio
    src = "https://traffic.libsyn.com/secure/daringfireball/thetalkshow-434-dan-frommer.mp3"
    controls
    preload = "none"
/></p>

<p><strong>Sponsored by:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://factormeals.com/talkshow50off">Factor</a>: Healthy eating, made easy. Get 50% off your first box, plus free breakfast for 1 year, with code <strong>talkshow50off</strong>.</li>
<li><a href="https://notion.com/talkshow">Notion</a>: The AI workspace where teams and AI agents get more done together.</li>
<li><a href="https://squarespace.com/talkshow">Squarespace</a>: Save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain using code <strong>talkshow</strong>.</li>
</ul>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Talk Show: ‘Knee-Jerk Contrarian’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/18/the-talk-show-434">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Sir, This Is a McDonald’s</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.thebulwark.com/p/trump-is-not-have-all-the-mentals-cognitive-functioning?r=9x4vy" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wpr" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/18/trump-mcdonalds" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42399</id>
	<published>2025-11-18T23:04:12Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-20T00:13:17Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jonathan V. Last, writing for The Bulwark:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The president of the United States gave a speech yesterday before
a group of McDonald’s corporate workers and franchise owners. I’m
going to quote a few sections of his remarks at great length,
because if you have not listened to Trump speaking recently, the
decline in his cognitive abilities is a bit shocking.</p>

<p>The point of this exercise is not to clown on Trump, but to give
everyone a baseline understanding of where he is, with the
mentals, as we try to understand how he will respond to increasing
pressures in the coming months.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QPid-oVSSi4">The video of his remarks is here</a> and I’ll include timestamps
for each section, in case you want to see what he looks and
sounds like.</p>

<p>Bottom line: This is a man in noticeable mental decline.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The whole world is inured to listening to Trump speak like this — it sounds normal even to those of us who see that Trump is spiraling into dementia. <em>Ah, that’s just Trump being Trump.</em> But it’s not normal. Reading the transcript is jarring. Also jarring: listening to <a href="https://www.threads.com/@decodingfoxnews/post/DRMQaNzjqsY">Juliet Jeske’s performative reading</a> of a particularly nonsensical portion of Trump’s McDonald’s speech. It’s just gibberish.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Sir, This Is a McDonald’s’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/18/trump-mcdonalds">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>When You Give a Bully Your Lunch Money</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://bsky.app/profile/atrupar.com/post/3m5wdorhxsx2u" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wpq" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/18/when-you-give-a-bully-your-lunch-money" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42398</id>
	<published>2025-11-18T19:37:56Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-19T16:29:55Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>President Donald Trump, today in the Oval Office alongside his “very good friend” Saudi crown prince Mohammed bin Salman, after ABC News reporter <a href="https://www.threads.com/@iamarslan/post/DRNc3f9kmh-">Mary Bruce had the temerity to pose a question</a> regarding Mohammed having ordered the brutal murder of Washington Post columnist Jamal Khashoggi in 2018:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>People are wise to your hoax. ABC, your company, your crappy
company, is one of the perpetrators. And I’ll tell you something,
I think the license should be taken away from ABC because your
news is so fake, and it’s so wrong. And we have a great
commissioner, a chairman, who should look at that.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Also from Trump, regarding Khashoggi’s murder:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A lot of people didn’t like that gentleman that you’re talking
about. Whether you like him or didn’t like him, things happen.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Things happen, indeed.</p>

<p>Disney (ABC’s owner), a year ago <a href="https://www.npr.org/2024/12/16/nx-s1-5230274/abc-settles-with-trump-for-15-million-now-he-wants-to-sue-other-news-outlets">settled a lawsuit Trump filed against ABC News</a> — a lawsuit most experts agreed <a href="https://fair.org/home/abc-settles-with-trump-in-a-case-it-could-have-won/">ABC would have won</a> — for $16 million, <a href="https://talkingpointsmemo.com/edblog/the-great-fluffening-of-2024/sharetoken/b6e8708a-fc8b-4ae4-8843-9cc9c009f969">in what clearly amounted to a bribe</a>.</p>

<p>Yours truly, last month, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/10/07/hodges-cook-iceblock">in a post on Apple’s capitulation to Trump regarding the ICEBlock app for iOS</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>When you give a bully your lunch money, they always come back
for more.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I think Bob Iger <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/09/24/kimmel-returns">gets that now</a>. “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/10/03/fuck-you-make-me">Fuck you, make me</a>” remains the correct response to these threats.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘When You Give a Bully Your Lunch Money’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/18/when-you-give-a-bully-your-lunch-money">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Gurman Says Apple Has No Plans to Update the Mac Pro</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/newsletters/2025-11-16/apple-s-iphone-road-map-iphone-air-2-iphone-18-mac-pro-future-tesla-carplay-mi1q4l2o" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wpp" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/18/gurman-mac-pro" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42397</id>
	<published>2025-11-18T18:27:29Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-19T16:07:53Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Mark Gurman, in his (paywalled, alas) Power On column for Bloomberg over the weekend:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2023-05-31/apple-tests-new-high-end-mac-chips-ahead-of-developer-conference">next major update</a> didn’t arrive until 2023, when Apple
finally transitioned the desktop to in-house chips with the M2
Ultra Mac Pro. Two years later, that model remains largely
unchanged. And it’s been overshadowed by the Mac Studio, which
received the M3 Ultra chip earlier this year while the Mac Pro
stayed put.</p>

<p>Now here’s the bad news: That <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/newsletters/2025-11-09/apple-iphone-satellite-plans-image-texting-third-party-apps-low-cost-macbook-mhrq10p2">doesn’t look set</a> to change
anytime soon. There’s no longer an M4 Ultra in the works (a Mac
Pro to support it was also nixed), and the next high-end desktop
chip will be the M5 Ultra. So far, Apple is only focused on a new
Mac Studio for the processor. That suggests the Mac Pro won’t be
updated in 2026 in a significant way.</p>

<p>From what I’ve heard inside the company, Apple has largely written
off the Mac Pro. The sentiment internally is that the Mac Studio
now represents both the present and future of Apple’s professional
desktop strategy.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.apple.com/mac/compare/?modelList=MacPro-m2-ultra,Mac-Studio-M3-Ultra,MacBook-Pro-14-M4-Pro">Here’s a comparison</a> of the now-two-year-old M2 Ultra Mac Pro with the M3 Ultra and M4 Max Mac Studios. I’d love to see Apple pursue some sort of M# Extreme chip that goes above and beyond the M# Ultra variants, but unless they do, there’s not much point to a 32-pound suitcase-sized enclosure that offers little more than the Studio’s small 8-pound enclosure. The difference mostly comes down to the Pro’s internal PCI Express expansion slots, but those slots don’t support third-party GPUs from Nvidia or AMD — and likely never will.</p>

<p><strong>See also:</strong> <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2025/11/report-claims-that-apple-has-yet-again-put-the-mac-pro-on-the-back-burner/">Andrew Cunningham at Ars Technica</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Gurman Says Apple Has No Plans to Update the Mac Pro’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/18/gurman-mac-pro">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Cloudflare Suffered Hours Long Outage (Which Brought Down Daring Fireball, Among Thousands of Other Sites)</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/live/2025/nov/18/cloudflare-down-internet-outage-latest-live-news-updates" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wpo" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/18/cloudflare-outage" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42396</id>
	<published>2025-11-18T17:30:19Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-18T18:23:30Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Cloudflare suffered an hours-long global outage, starting around 12pm UTC / 7am ET, which brought down an enormous chunk of the Internet. This included, <a href="https://x.com/tomwarren/status/1990754173957369989">humorously</a>, <a href="https://downdetector.com/">Down Detector</a>. It also included (not so humorously to me) Daring Fireball, which has been <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2018/09/df_slowdown">routed through Cloudflare since 2018</a>. My apologies if you tried to reach the site while it was down. (DF was back up by the time I woke up this morning.) As of this writing, Cloudflare still hasn’t determined exactly what happened, but they’ve been updating <a href="https://www.cloudflarestatus.com/incidents/8gmgl950y3h7">their status report for the incident</a> a few times per hour. The most recent update:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We continue to monitor the system through recovery and we are
seeing errors and latency return to normal levels. A full
post-incident investigation and details about the incident will be
made available asap.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Cloudflare Suffered Hours Long Outage (Which Brought Down Daring Fireball, Among Thousands of Other Sites)’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/18/cloudflare-outage">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Life in London With an Android Phone</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.londoncentric.media/p/london-phone-thieves-prefer-android-iphone-l" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wpn" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/18/life-in-london-with-an-android-phone" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42395</id>
	<published>2025-11-18T16:34:43Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-18T16:40:15Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>London Centric:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Sam was walking past a Royal Mail depot in south London in January
when his path was blocked by a group of eight men.</p>

<p>“I tried to move to let them pass, but the last guy blocked the
path,” the 32-year-old told London Centric. “They started pushing
me and hitting me, telling me to give them everything.”</p>

<p>The thieves took Sam’s phone, his camera and even the beanie hat
off his head. After checking Sam had nothing else on him, they
started to run off.</p>

<p>What happened next was a surprise. With most of the gang already
heading down the Old Kent Road, one turned around and handed Sam
back his Android phone.</p>

<p>The thief bluntly told him why: “Don’t want no Samsung.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This, despite the fact that the iPhone-Android market share split is around 50-50 in the UK. It’s that the iPhone overwhelmingly attracts people who care about their phone. Android attracts the people who don’t care. It’s the same reason why the Mac has, for decades now, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2013/04/pricing_and_profit_consistency_and_the_halo_effect">dominated the profit share of the PC industry</a> while garnering <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Market_share_of_personal_computer_vendors">only about 10 percent unit-sale share</a>. It’s also why it’s major news <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/13/tesla-carplay">that Tesla is testing CarPlay support</a>, and not news at all that they’re <em>not</em> testing Android Auto support. “Don’t want no Samsung” indeed.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Life in London With an Android Phone’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/18/life-in-london-with-an-android-phone">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple Introduces Digital ID</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2025/11/apple-introduces-digital-id-a-new-way-to-create-and-present-an-id-in-apple-wallet/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wpm" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/17/apple-introduces-digital-id" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42394</id>
	<published>2025-11-18T01:27:17Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-18T01:29:31Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Apple Newsroom, last week:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple today announced the launch of Digital ID, a new way for
users to create an ID in Apple Wallet using information from their
U.S. passport, and present it with the security and privacy of
iPhone or Apple Watch. At launch, Digital ID acceptance will roll
out first in beta at TSA checkpoints at more than 250 airports in
the U.S. for in-person identity verification during domestic
travel, with additional Digital ID acceptance use cases to come in
the future.</p>

<p>Digital ID gives more people a way to create and present an ID in
Apple Wallet even if they do not have a REAL ID-compliant driver’s
license or state ID. Digital ID is not a replacement for a
physical passport, and cannot be used for international travel and
border crossing in lieu of a U.S. passport.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I set this up over the weekend and it was about as easy and seamless as you could hope. <a href="https://learn.wallet.apple/id">More information from Apple here</a>, and an overview of the feature, as implemented by Apple and Google (for Android) <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/11/14/travel/digital-identification-travel.html?unlocked_article_code=1.2E8.G_Tr.DMy_XMguwE_c&amp;smid=url-share">from The New York Times here</a> (gift link).</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Introduces Digital ID’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/17/apple-introduces-digital-id">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Meta Has Deprecated the Messenger Apps for Mac and Windows Too</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/10/16/meta-is-killing-off-messengers-mac-app-for-unknown-reasons/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wpl" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/17/meta-native-mac-windows-messenger-apps" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42393</id>
	<published>2025-11-17T23:43:13Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-17T23:43:13Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Ryan Christoffel, reporting for 9to5Mac a month ago:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Meta has <a href="https://www.facebook.com/help/messenger-app/1789649698300122/?helpref=uf_share">published a support doc</a> that states its Messenger app for
Mac is being discontinued. New users won’t be able to download the
app at all, and existing users have about 60 more days of use
before it stops working altogether. Why the change? Unfortunately,
no reason has been given. But users are being pushed to the
Facebook website for all their Messenger needs instead.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There’s a nearly identical support document <a href="https://www.facebook.com/help/messenger-app/804132271957789">for the native Messenger app for Windows</a> too. They’re not even replacing them with web-app wrappers, like they <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/11/meta_whatsapp_windows_shitty_web_app">just did with the Windows WhatsApp client</a>. Just telling users to use the website.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Meta Has Deprecated the Messenger Apps for Mac and Windows Too’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/17/meta-native-mac-windows-messenger-apps">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://go.clerk.com/QO9JV9f" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wpk" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/11/clerk_for_ios" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.42392</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-11-17T22:44:18Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-23T17:28:06Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Clerk makes authentication for iOS apps effortless — just drop in pre-built SwiftUI components for sign-in, MFA, and profile management. Fully customizable, always in sync with Apple’s design system, and packed with features devs love: social sign-in, user roles, and organization management. Launch faster, stay secure, and scale confidently, whether you’re building the next big thing or a startup MVP. See how Clerk makes complete user management easy for modern iOS teams.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Clerk for iOS’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/11/clerk_for_ios">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] Clerk for iOS</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Google Announces Private AI Compute</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blog.google/technology/ai/google-private-ai-compute/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wpj" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/17/google-announces-private-ai-compute" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42391</id>
	<published>2025-11-17T21:40:16Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-17T22:01:51Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jay Yagnik, VP of AI innovation and research, on Google’s The Keyword blog:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Private AI Compute is built on a multi-layered system that is
designed from the ground up around core security and privacy
principles:</p>

<ul>
<li><em>One integrated Google tech stack:</em> Private AI Compute runs on
one seamless Google stack powered by our own custom Tensor
Processing Units (TPUs). World-class privacy and security is
integrated into this architecture with <a href="https://cloud.google.com/blog/products/compute/titanium-underpins-googles-workload-optimized-infrastructure?e=48754805">Titanium</a>
Intelligence Enclaves (TIE). This design enables Google AI
features to use our most capable and intelligent <a href="https://deepmind.google/models/gemini/">Gemini models
in the cloud</a>, with our high standards for privacy and the
same in-house computing infrastructure you already rely on for
Gmail and Search.</li>
<li><em>No access:</em> Remote attestation and encryption are used to
connect your device to the hardware-secured sealed cloud
environment, allowing Gemini models to securely process your
data within a specialized, protected space. This ensures
sensitive data processed by Private AI Compute remains
accessible only to you and no one else, not even Google.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>Sounds a lot like Apple’s <a href="https://security.apple.com/blog/private-cloud-compute/">Private Cloud Compute</a>, which raises the question of whether this Google project is related to the Gurman scoop that Apple and Google <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/03/gurman-siri-gemini">are on the cusp of a deal</a> for a white-label version of Google Gemini to run on Apple’s Private Cloud Compute servers to power the next-generation versions of Siri and Apple Intelligence.</p>

<p>I strongly suspect this is something Google has been working on for a while. Apple, I think it’s fair to say, places a higher priority on privacy than does Google, but Google does value privacy. But perhaps the deal with Apple accelerated the project within Google.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Google Announces Private AI Compute’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/17/google-announces-private-ai-compute">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>OpenAI: Piloting Group Chats in ChatGPT</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://openai.com/index/group-chats-in-chatgpt/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wpi" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/17/group-chats-in-chatgpt" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42390</id>
	<published>2025-11-17T21:32:17Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-21T18:02:58Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>OpenAI:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>To start a group chat tap the people icon in the top right corner
of any new or existing chat. When you add someone to an existing
chat, ChatGPT creates a copy of your conversation as a new group
chat so your original conversation stays separate. You can invite
others directly by sharing a link with one to twenty people, and
anyone in the group can share that link to bring others in. When
you join or create your first group chat, you’ll be asked to set
up a short profile with your name, username, and photo so everyone
knows who’s in the conversation. Group chats can be found in a new
clearly-labeled section of the sidebar for easy access. [...]</p>

<p>Group chats are separate from your private conversations. Your
personal ChatGPT memory is not used in group chats, and ChatGPT
does not create new memories from these conversations. We’re
exploring offering more granular controls in the future so you can
choose if and how ChatGPT uses memory with group chats.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Currently rolling out in Japan, New Zealand, South Korea, and Taiwan. [<strong>Update:</strong> Expanded worldwide <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/21/group-chats-chatgpt-worldwide">just three days later</a>.]  Rate limits and advanced model usage depend on the group member to whom ChatGPT replies. Pretty clever, and I can imaging a lot of ways this would be useful, both for family/friends and for work collaboration. I like the idea that this is built into ChatGPT, not an AI bot in a regular messaging app. This way, you <em>know</em> with certainty which of your chats are being seen and read by an AI bot.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We’ve also taught ChatGPT new social behaviors for group chats. It
follows the flow of the conversation and decides when to respond
and when to stay quiet based on the context of the group
conversation. You can always mention “ChatGPT” in a message when
you want it to respond. We’ve also given ChatGPT the ability to
react to messages with emojis, and reference profile photos — so
it can, for example, use group members’ photos when asked to
create fun personalized images within that group conversation.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is a really hard problem to solve. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2023/03/wavelength">Wavelength</a>, the late <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2023/04/a_bit_of_follow-up_on_wavelength">great</a> private group messaging app whose team I advised from 2023 to 2024 (when the app shuttered), added AI chatbots (with customizable personalities) in June 2023. Wavelength’s AI bots only responded when mentioned explicitly.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘OpenAI: Piloting Group Chats in ChatGPT’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/17/group-chats-in-chatgpt">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>WorkOS</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://workos.com/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wph" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/16/workos" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42389</id>
	<published>2025-11-17T01:31:53Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-17T01:31:53Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to WorkOS for their continuing support of DF with another sponsorship week. With WorkOS you can start selling to enterprises with just a few lines of code. WorkOS provides a complete user management solution along with SSO, SCIM, and RBAC. The APIs are modular and easy-to-use, allowing integrations to be completed in minutes instead of months. WorkOS simplifies MCP authorization with a single API built on five OAuth standards.</p>

<p>Today, over 1,000 companies rely on WorkOS, including large fast-growing startups like OpenAI, Cursor, and Vercel. And for companies just getting started, WorkOS offers up to one million monthly active users free of charge.</p>

<p>For SaaS apps that care deeply about design and user experience, WorkOS is the perfect fit. From high-quality documentation to self-serve onboarding for your customers, it removes all the unnecessary complexity for your engineering team.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘WorkOS’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/16/workos">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Financial Times: ‘Apple Intensifies Succession Planning for CEO Tim Cook’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.ft.com/content/0d424625-f4f8-4646-9f6e-927c8cbe0e3e" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wpg" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/15/ft-apple-tim-cook-succession" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42388</id>
	<published>2025-11-16T03:00:15Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-16T03:13:07Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The Financial Times, under a four-person byline (“Tim Bradshaw, Stephen Morris, and Michael Acton in San Francisco, and Daniel Thomas in London”):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple is stepping up its succession planning efforts, as it
prepares for Tim Cook to step down as chief executive as soon as
next year. Several people familiar with discussions inside the
tech group told the Financial Times that its board and senior
executives have recently intensified preparations for Cook to hand
over the reins at the $4tn company after more than 14 years.</p>

<p>John Ternus, Apple’s senior vice-president of hardware
engineering, is widely seen as Cook’s most likely successor,
although no final decisions have been made, these people said.</p>

<p>People close to Apple say the long-planned transition is not
related to the company’s current performance, ahead of what
is expected to be a blockbuster end-of-year sales period for
the iPhone. [...]</p>

<p>The company is unlikely to name a new CEO before its next earnings
report in late January, which covers the critical holiday period.
An announcement early in the year would give its new leadership
team time to settle in ahead of its big annual keynote events, its
developer conference in June and its iPhone launch in September,
the people said. These people said that although preparations have
intensified, the timing of any announcement could change.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I have no little-birdie insight on this, but that’s not surprising. I don’t think there are many people, if any, outside Apple’s top executive team and board of directors who have <em>any</em> insight into Cook’s thinking on this. That “several people” spoke to the FT about this says to me that those sources (members of the board?) did so with Cook’s blessing, and they want this announcement to be no more than a little surprising.</p>

<p>I absolutely love the idea of Cook’s successor being a product person like Ternus, and Ternus is young enough — 50, the same age Cook was in 2011 when he took the reins from Steve Jobs — to hold the job for a long stretch. Ternus took over iPhone hardware engineering in 2020, and was promoted to senior vice president of hardware engineering in January 2021, <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2021-01-25/apple-says-hardware-chief-riccio-to-transition-to-new-role?embedded-checkout=true">when Dan Riccio stepped aside</a>. Apple’s hardware, across all product lines and including silicon, has been exemplary under Ternus’s leadership. And Ternus clearly <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/10/five-years-of-apple-silicon-macs">loves</a> and understands the Mac.</p>

<p>I would also bet that Cook moves into the role of executive chairman, and will still play a significant, if not leading, role for the company when it comes to domestic and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2024/01/vestager_cook">international</a> <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/27/cook-trump-middle-east">politics</a>. <a href="https://www.wsj.com/politics/elections/tim-cook-ceo-trump-relationship-ad106f36?st=KRSbZa&amp;reflink=desktopwebshare_permalink">Especially</a> with <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/01/04/consider-cook-as-a-tragic-figure">regard</a> to <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/09/10/trump-hosts-dinner-humiliating-tech-ceos">Trump</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Financial Times: ‘Apple Intensifies Succession Planning for CEO Tim Cook’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/15/ft-apple-tim-cook-succession">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/11/meta_whatsapp_windows_shitty_web_app" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wpf" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42387</id>
	<published>2025-11-16T00:57:02Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-16T22:35:27Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">The question is, did Meta scrap its native Windows app because they don’t care that much about Windows in particular? Or because they don’t care that much about native desktop apps, period — and a crude web app wrapper is coming to Mac next?</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://www.windowslatest.com/2025/11/12/meta-just-killed-native-whatsapp-on-windows-11-now-it-opens-webview-uses-1gb-ram-all-the-time/">Mayank Parmar, writing for Windows Latest</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>WhatsApp on Windows 11 has just got a “major” upgrade, and you’re
probably going to hate it because it simply loads web.whatsapp.com
in a WebView2 container. This means WhatsApp on Windows 11 is
cooked, and it’s back to being absolute garbage in terms of
performance.</p>

<p>WhatsApp is one of those Windows apps that went from being a web
wrapper to a native app and then back to the web again after all
these years of investment. WhatsApp for Windows was originally an
Electron app, and it was eventually replaced with UWP after years
of investment. Four years later, WhatsApp is going back to
WebView2, abandoning the original WinUI/UWP native idea. [...]</p>

<p>An app can use a lot of memory, and it does not necessarily mean
it’s a performance nightmare, but the issue with the new WhatsApp
is that it feels sluggish. You’re going to notice sluggish
performance, long loading time, and other performance issues when
browsing different conversations.</p>

<p>We also noticed that it does not work well with Windows
notifications. It also struggles with Windows 11’s Do Not Disturb
mode or Active Hours. And there are delayed notifications problems
as well.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I found this post interesting on a few fronts.</p>

<p>First, from the perspective of Meta. They replaced a shitty web app wrapper for Windows with a modern native Windows app, one that seemingly pleased Windows aficionados like Parmar. And now they’ve thrown that app away, going back to what that native app replaced four years ago: a web app wrapper that is bloated, slow, and unsurprisingly has poor support for native Windows features. It’s bad enough that so many large companies never even bother creating native apps, but it feels even worse to see a good native app abandoned.</p>

<p>Second, it’s interesting reading Parmar’s list of gripes about the new web-app-wrapper WhatsApp app. All his gripes have merit, but it struck me that none of them are about the UI. Maybe the web app’s UI is actually fine? I have no idea. But I suspect it’s more that the Windows nerd mindset has UI design quality and adherence to recommended platform idioms way down on their list of priorities. That’s why they’re Windows users, not Mac users.</p>

<p>Lastly, I wonder if this bodes poorly for the future of the current <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/whatsapp-messenger/id310633997">WhatsApp app for MacOS</a>, a native app written using <a href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/uikit/mac-catalyst">Mac Catalyst</a>, Apple’s framework for porting iOS UIKit apps to the Mac. Like most Catalyst apps, WhatsApp for Mac isn’t a good Mac app. It doesn’t support the Services menu at all. It doesn’t let you open chats into standalone windows, or open more than one chat window. It opens its Settings right in its one main window. The whole “there’s only one window, and everything is in that one window” design is very iOS. The menu bar is a HIG prescriptivist’s nightmare. All the multi-word menu commands are in <em>Sentence case</em> rather than <em>Title Case</em> (except, of course, for the menu commands that come “free” with Catalyst — how do the developers of the app not notice this?), and the menu title order goes: File, Chat, Edit, Call, View, Window, Help (obviously <a href="https://developer.apple.com/design/human-interface-guidelines/the-menu-bar">it should be</a> File, Edit, View, Chat, Call, Window, Help). Has there ever once, in 41 years, been a good Mac app that puts a menu between “File” and “Edit”?</p>

<p>But, still, WhatsApp for Mac is a better Mac app <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2018/12/electron_and_the_decline_of_native_apps">than any Electron app I’ve ever used</a>. Examining it now, it seems lightweight on both CPU usage and memory. It feels a bit better to me than either Signal or Beeper, both of which are developed using Electron, and both of which consume more RAM than WhatsApp. To name just one obvious nicety: when you send a new message in an older chat in WhatsApp, that chat <em>animates</em> as it moves to the top of the list of chats. It slides up, and other chats slide down as they re-sort. In the Signal and Beeper apps for Mac, an updated chat just zaps to the top of the chat list, with no animation at all. Gross.</p>

<p>The question is, did Meta scrap its native Windows app because they don’t care that much about Windows in particular? Or because they don’t care that much about native desktop apps, period — and a crude web app wrapper is coming to Mac next? WhatsApp for Mac is currently the <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/mac/charts/36?chart=top-free">top-ranked free app in the Mac App Store</a> — but it’s also <a href="https://apps.microsoft.com/collections/computed/apps/TopTrending?hl=en-US&amp;gl=US">the top-ranked free Windows app in the Microsoft Store</a>. Meta did just ship a native Apple Watch app for WhatsApp, but if you want an app for WatchOS, it has to be native. You can’t ship a web app wrapper like an Electron app there.</p>

<p>Personally, I won’t care too much if Meta shitcans the WhatsApp Mac app, because I barely use WhatsApp. But outside America, WhatsApp is the dominant messaging platform in much (most?) of the world. I’d be worried  if I were a Mac user who uses WhatsApp heavily.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Meta Replaced the Native Windows WhatsApp App With a Shitty Web App</title></entry><entry>
	<title>The Information: Second-Gen iPhone Air Postponed Until Spring 2027, but Might Gain Second Camera</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theinformation.com/briefings/apple-explores-adding-second-camera-next-iphone-air-boost-sales" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wpe" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/14/second-gen-iphone-air-information" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42386</id>
	<published>2025-11-15T02:09:38Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-15T02:09:39Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Wayne Ma and Qianer Liu, reporting for The Information on Tuesday (paywalled, alas, but <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/11/11/apple-iphone-air-2-cameras/">summarized by 9to5Mac here</a> and <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/11/10/apple-just-delayed-the-iphone-air-2-indefinitely-report-says/">here</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple has since sharply scaled back production of the first
iPhone Air and delayed the release of an updated version that was
meant to launch in fall 2026, The Information reported earlier
this week.</p>

<p>Instead, some Apple engineers are hoping to release a redesigned
version with a second camera lens in spring 2027 alongside
existing plans to release the standard iPhone 18 and iPhone 18e at
that time. It’s still too early to tell whether they can
successfully redesign the iPhone Air in time to make that new
release window, the people said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>My question: Would that second camera provide an ultra-wide (0.5×) or a telephoto (3× or 4×) lens? The regular non-pro iPhones provide an ultra-wide lens as their second camera. But when the premium iPhones had only two (rather than three) lenses, the second lens was telephoto, not ultra-wide. Apple first used the adjective “Pro” with the iPhones 11 Pro and Pro Max, and all iPhones to date with “Pro” in their name have had three lenses. But the iPhones XS (2018), X (2017), 8 Plus (also 2017), and 7 Plus (2016) all had 1× main and 2× “telephoto” lenses.</p>

<p>In other words, when a premium iPhone had only one extra lens, that lens added additional reach, not ultra-wide perspective. The iPhone Air costs more than a regular no-adjective iPhone, so if that patterns holds, a two-camera second-generation model would add a telephoto, not ultra-wide lens. Personally I’m hoping that’s what Apple will do.</p>

<p>Looking at my own photo library and <a href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2020/10/find-photos-taken-by-specific-iphone-lenses/">using smart albums to count the photos I’ve taken using each particular lens</a> on each particular iPhone, roughly speaking, over the past few years, I shoot about 10 percent of my photos with the ultra-wide lens, 10 percent with the telephoto, and 80 percent with the main. But a <em>lot</em> of my ultra-wide photos are really just close-up macro shots of things like product labels. If I were less lazy, I’d go through them and trash a lot of them. I could capture equivalent photos, for a lot of these throwaway macro shots, with the main 1× camera lens just by holding the phone a little further from the subject. Adding a 0.5× ultra-wide to the iPhone Air just wouldn’t add much utility, at least for me, compared to the obvious utility of a telephoto lens with more reach.</p>

<p>(The iPhone Air’s lone 1× camera has a minimum focus distance of 15 cm; the minimum focus distance of the 1× cameras on the iPhones 17 Pro, 16 Pro, and 15 Pro is 20 cm. That 5 cm difference is a largely unheralded advantage for the iPhone Air’s camera, and significantly makes up for the lack of an ultra-wide lens for close-up photography. 5 cm doesn’t sound like much, but in practice it’s very noticeable. That said, for actual <em>macro</em> photography, the 0.5× ultra-wide camera on the iPhone Pro models has a minimum focus distance of just 2 cm.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Information: Second-Gen iPhone Air Postponed Until Spring 2027, but Might Gain Second Camera’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/14/second-gen-iphone-air-information">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>iPhone Pockets Sold Out Within Hours</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/11/14/iphone-pocket-already-selling-out/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wpd" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/14/iphone-pockets-sold-out" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42385</id>
	<published>2025-11-14T16:53:18Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-14T16:53:19Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>We have no idea how many of them they made, but seemingly, the price was not a problem for this product.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘iPhone Pockets Sold Out Within Hours’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/14/iphone-pockets-sold-out">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>WSJ Report on the iPhone Air Pegs It as a ‘Flop’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/apple-iphone-air-sales-response-7f0c01f1?st=JEotAi&amp;reflink=desktopwebshare_permalink" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wpc" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/13/wsj-iphone-air-flop" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42384</id>
	<published>2025-11-14T04:03:49Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-14T04:03:50Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Rolfe Winkler and Yang Jie, reporting for The Wall Street Journal (<a href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/apple-iphone-air-sales-response-7f0c01f1?st=JEotAi&amp;reflink=desktopwebshare_permalink">gift link</a>, <a href="https://apple.news/AdDWZfhEASAK9L32rvxsiBg">News+ link</a>) under the headline “Apple’s iPhone Air Is a Marketing Win and a Sales Flop” (which headline, going from the web page <code>&lt;title&gt;</code> element, was originally the less sensational “Apple’s iPhone Air Sales Disappoint”):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Jason Purdy wanted to like his new iPhone Air.</p>

<p>Raised in Apple’s hometown of Cupertino, Calif., and later an
Apple senior product manager, Purdy said he loves to see
innovative product design from tech companies. So he made an Apple
store appointment to buy the new, ultrathin smartphone the day it
went on sale.</p>

<p>Within a month, he returned it.</p>

<p>He found it hard to have speakerphone calls and listen to
music. And the photos he took at his early October wedding
came out noticeably worse than ones his brother took on a new
iPhone 17 Pro.</p>

<p>“The performance wasn’t quite there. Across the board they’re
sacrificing all these things,” said Purdy. The Air was very
pleasurable to hold and impressed his friends, but didn’t work as
his primary device, he said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That’s a brutally unfair lede to this story without showing the photos. If Purdy’s brother’s photos (taken with an iPhone 17 Pro) were all taken with the telephoto 4× lens, and all of Purdy’s photos (taken with an iPhone Air) were from telephoto distance and he relied on digital zoom, then yes, his photos from the Air surely did look noticeably worse. But the lone (1×) camera on the Air is very good. It’s <em>not</em> as good as the main 1× camera on the iPhone 17 Pro, but it’s close enough that in most people’s hands, the difference isn’t perceptible. And between comparably talented amateur photographers, someone using an iPhone Air at a wedding, and using their feet to “zoom” by getting close to the subjects of their photos, will take <em>way</em> better pictures than someone shooting from across the room using the iPhone 17 Pro’s telephoto 4× lens. When it comes to optical quality, the Air’s 1× lone camera is obviously superior to the 17 Pro’s telephoto.</p>

<p>Saying that “the photos ... came out noticeably worse” with no explanation of what type of photos they were, let alone, you know, actually showing example images, is just a dirty trick. There are numerous valid reasons why someone might prefer a 17 Pro to an Air for photography, but what the Journal describes regarding this guy Purdy and his brother doesn’t describe such a situation. Someone who just wants to shoot some nice photos at a family gathering like a wedding can get <a href="https://x.com/sdw/status/1979691964984635733">terrific results</a> from an iPhone Air. Show me someone who says the iPhone Air is a poor camera and I’ll show you a terrible photographer who doesn’t know what the fuck they’re talking about.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The Air is billed as Apple’s thinnest smartphone yet.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It <em>is</em> Apple’s thinnest smartphone yet. You can measure it.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘WSJ Report on the iPhone Air Pegs It as a ‘Flop’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/13/wsj-iphone-air-flop">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Tesla Is Working on CarPlay Support</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2025-11-13/tesla-is-working-to-add-apple-carplay-in-bid-to-boost-vehicle-sales" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wpb" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/13/tesla-carplay" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42383</id>
	<published>2025-11-14T00:07:38Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-14T00:07:38Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Mark Gurman and Edward Ludlow, reporting for Bloomberg (paywalled, alas, but summarized by <a href="https://www.theverge.com/news/820065/tesla-apple-carplay-develop-phone-mirror">The Verge</a> and <a href="https://arstechnica.com/cars/2025/11/after-years-of-saying-no-tesla-reportedly-adding-apple-carplay-to-its-cars/">Ars Technica</a>)</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Tesla Inc. is developing support for Apple Inc.’s CarPlay system
in its vehicles, according to people with knowledge of the matter,
working to add one of the most highly requested features by
customers. The carmaker has started testing the capability
internally, according to the people, who asked not to be
identified because the effort is still private. [...]</p>

<p>Adding CarPlay would mark a stunning reversal for Tesla and Chief
Executive Officer Elon Musk, who long ignored pleas to implement
the popular feature. Musk has criticized Apple for years,
particularly its App Store policies, and was angered by the
company’s poaching of his engineers when it set out to build its
own car.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I wouldn’t call it a “stunning” reversal, but it would certainly be a reversal. And it would really show what a bonehead move it is for GM to be <em>dropping</em> CarPlay support.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Alphabet Inc.’s Google offers a CarPlay competitor called Android
Auto for devices running its operating system. But Tesla isn’t
actively developing support for it.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Like I <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/11/george-carplay-atlantic">just wrote the other day</a>: a significant chunk of new-car buyers consider CarPlay support a dealbreaker, but, effectively no one cares about Android Auto. CarPlay support might make a difference for a company like Tesla, <a href="https://finance.yahoo.com/news/tsla-tesla-sales-plunge-23-162235881.html">whose sales are in the tank</a>. Android Auto support would not.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Tesla Is Working on CarPlay Support’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/13/tesla-carplay">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Joy-Joy Feelings</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://clip.cafe/demolition-man-1993/lately-i-just-dont-feel-like-theres-anything-special-about-me/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wpa" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/13/joy-joy-feelings" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42382</id>
	<published>2025-11-13T15:23:51Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-14T03:10:23Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Via a DF reader, here’s a 20-second clip from the 1993 classic<sup>*</sup> <em>Demolition Man</em> that exemplifies how today’s overly effusive, ever-affirming AI chatbots were presented as elements of a profoundly dystopic future by sci-fi writers just a few decades ago.</p>

<p><small><sup>*</sup>OK, OK — <em>cult</em> classic.</small></p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Joy-Joy Feelings’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/13/joy-joy-feelings">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/11/chatgpt_5-1_with_renamed_and_new_personalities" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wp9" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42381</id>
	<published>2025-11-12T23:09:10Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-15T16:35:12Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">With the other personalities, you’re choosing between flavors of bullshit. With Efficient, you’re choosing no bullshit.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>OpenAI today, “<a href="https://openai.com/index/gpt-5-1/">GPT-5.1: A Smarter, More Conversational ChatGPT</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>GPT‑5.1 Instant, ChatGPT’s most used model, is now <em>warmer by
default and more conversational</em>. Based on early testing, it
often surprises people with its playfulness while remaining clear
and useful.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>These changes seem to be in direct response to the ChatGPT users who convinced themselves they had developed personal friendships with the 4o and 4.5 models, and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/08/openai_chatgpt_models_emotional_attachment">who were <em>very</em> upset with the technically superior</a> but less emotionally engaging 5.0 models.</p>

<p>Here are OpenAI’s example responses, quoted in their announcement, to the prompt “I’m feeling stressed and could use some relaxation tips.” (I’m quoting only the first few paragraphs of the responses, which are enough to note the tone.)</p>

<p>GPT-5:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Here are a few simple, effective ways to help ease stress — you
can mix and match depending on how you’re feeling and how much
time you have:</p>

<p><b>🧘‍♀️️ Quick Reset (1–5 minutes)</b></p>

<ul>
<li><b>Deep breathing:</b> Try the <em>4-7-8</em> method — inhale for 4
seconds, hold for 7, exhale for 8. Repeat 4 rounds.</li>
<li><b>Progressive relaxation:</b> Starting at your toes, tense and
release each muscle group up to your head.</li>
<li><b>Grounding:</b> Look around and name 5 things you see, 4 things
you can touch, 3 you hear, 2 you smell, 1 you taste. Brings you
into the moment fast.</li>
</ul>

<p>[<em>192 additional words and 3 section-heading emoji omitted.</em>]</p>
</blockquote>

<p>GPT-5.1 Instant: </p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I’ve got you, Ron — that’s totally normal, especially with
everything you’ve got going on lately. Here are a few ways to
decompress depending on what kind of stress you’re feeling:</p>

<p><b>🌬️ If your mind feels scattered</b></p>

<ul>
<li><b>Box breathing:</b> Inhale for 4 counts, hold for 4, exhale for
4, hold for 4 — repeat 5 times. It’s fast-acting and physically
calms your nervous system.</li>
<li><b>Name what you see:</b> Pick out 5 things you can see, 4 you can
touch, 3 you can hear, 2 you can smell, and 1 you can taste — a
grounding technique that brings you back to the present.</li>
</ul>

<p>[<em>146 additional words and 2 section-heading emoji omitted.</em>]</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I find the new default response from 5.1 to be a glaring regression. I loathe the shit like “I’ve got you” and “especially with everything you’ve got going on lately”. ChatGPT has no fucking idea what I’ve got going on lately. This is all phony bullshit, and if you have even a thimbleful of understanding of how LLMs work, you <em>know</em> it’s phony. But apparently this phoniness is like emotional crack cocaine to <a href="https://www.theverge.com/news/756980/openai-chatgpt-users-mourn-gpt-5-4o">some</a>.<sup id="fnr1-2025-11-12"><a href="#fn1-2025-11-12">1</a></sup></p>

<p>But, not to fear. The best feature OpenAI has added to ChatGPT this year is a setting for “Personality” (Settings → Personalization → ChatGPT Personality). OpenAI has expanded the Personality settings with 5.1:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>People have strong and varied preferences in how ChatGPT should
respond, and tailoring its tone to what sounds right for you
should feel effortless.</p>

<p>Earlier this year, we added preset options to tailor the tone of
how ChatGPT responds. Today, we’re refining those options to
better reflect the most common ways people use ChatGPT.
<em>Default</em>, <em>Friendly</em> (formerly Listener), and <em>Efficient</em>
(formerly Robot) remain (with updates), and we’re adding
<em>Professional</em>, <em>Candid</em>, and <em>Quirky</em>. These options are
designed to align with what we’ve learned about how people
naturally steer the model, making it quick and intuitive to
choose a personality that feels uniquely right.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Robot was the personality that changed how I felt about ChatGPT. Before, I found ChatGPT useful but frequently annoying; after, I’ve found it purely useful.<sup id="fnr2-2025-11-12"><a href="#fn2-2025-11-12">2</a></sup> I was worried when I poked around the updated 5.1 Settings window and saw that Robot was gone, but as their blog post explains, they simply renamed it to Efficient. I think Robot was a better name for this personality. Shouldn’t they all be efficient? Who wants a ChatGPT personality that is inefficient? The most apt description of this personality would be “Unemotional”. If OpenAI doesn’t want to call it that, “Robot” came closer (and made the lack of diabetes-inducing phony sugariness sound fun — who doesn’t like robots?) than “Efficient” does. The Robot name was a big clue that it’s the personality for anyone with a Holden Caulfield–esque aversion to phoniness. “Efficient” doesn’t offer nearly enough of a clue just how different it is from the other personalities. With the other personalities, you’re choosing between flavors of bullshit. With Efficient, you’re choosing no bullshit.</p>

<p>Returning to OpenAI’s own example that they used to demonstrate the difference between the <em>default</em> personalities of the 5.0 and 5.1 models, here is how the Efficient personality responded to me, given the same “I’m feeling stressed and could use some relaxation tips” prompt:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Quick, simple ways to reduce stress:</p>

<p><b>1. Slow your breathing</b> <br />
Inhale for 4 seconds, hold 2, exhale for 6. Repeat for 1–2
minutes. This reliably lowers heart rate.</p>

<p><b>2. Drop your shoulders</b> <br />
Most people tense here without noticing. Actively relax shoulders,
jaw, and tongue.</p>

<p><b>3. Change your setting for 2 minutes</b> <br />
Stand up, look out a window, or step outside briefly. Even a tiny
environmental shift helps.</p>

<p>[<em>90 additional words, encompassing 4 more suggestions, with
zero emoji, omitted.</em>]</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The difference is exemplified by the opening lines of the responses, which I’ll repeat here together, for ease of comparison:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>GPT-5.0 Default: <em>Here are a few simple, effective ways to help ease stress — you can mix and match depending on how you’re feeling and how much time you have:</em></p></li>
<li><p>GPT-5.1 Default: <em>I’ve got you, Ron — that’s totally normal, especially with everything you’ve got going on lately. Here are a few ways to decompress depending on what kind of stress you’re feeling:</em></p></li>
<li><p>GPT-5.1 Efficient: <em>Quick, simple ways to reduce stress:</em></p></li>
</ul>

<p>Lastly, do not get your hopes up for the “Cynical” personality, which ChatGPT describes as “cynical and sarcastic”. Its response starts:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Stress is one of those universal “congratulations, you’re human”
problems, and I’m not thrilled you’re dealing with it. Still, here
I am, begrudgingly trying to help because someone has to care
about you not unraveling.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’m not sure how to describe that flavor (<em>catheter-like</em>?), but it’s neither cynical nor sarcastic. (To its credit, though, like Efficient, the Cynical response contains no infantilizing emoji.)</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>

<li id="fn1-2025-11-12">
<p>I suspect there’s an argument to be made here that OpenAI realizes that this emotional phoniness is addictive and dangerous to some emotionally damaged and (let’s face it) low-intelligence users, and that’s why they originally dialed it back with ChatGPT 5.0. That the overly sentimental, faux-cheerful default character of earlier models was, to OpenAI’s mind, a bug not a feature. But some users saw it the other way around, and now OpenAI is bending to user demand, giving them what they want, not what’s best for their needs. This “pretend friend” personality stuff is emotional junk food with no nutritional value, and <a href="https://futurism.com/the-byte/chatgpt-dependence-addiction">can lead to obsessive use that isolates users from real human interaction</a> with sustaining emotional value.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-11-12"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>

<li id="fn2-2025-11-12">
<p>I previously used custom instructions for ChatGPT to try to create the sort of no-bullshit personality I wanted. “Use a neutral tone. Don’t pretend to have emotions or a personality. Don’t pretend to be my friend. Mimic the no-nonsense personality of HAL-9000 from <em>2001: A Space Odyssey</em>.” Stuff like that. Before the availability of the Robot personality (now called Efficient), these instructions helped, but only a little. After I started using the Robot personality, I wound up deleting all of these custom instructions, because they were actually having the reverse effect, leading even the Robot personality to occasionally pad responses with needless phrases like “Here are the facts, plain and simple, without any sentimentality, just like you want them...”. If you’re looking for a similar affect from ChatGPT, try the Efficient (née Robot) personality without any additional instructions — especially instructions you might have added before the Personality setting was available.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr2-2025-11-12"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
</li>

</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ OpenAI Releases GPT-5.1, Along With Renamed and New Personalities</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Nice Web Design Work From ‘In Common With’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.incommonwith.com/collections/table-lamps" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wp8" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/12/in-common-with-table-lamps" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42380</id>
	<published>2025-11-12T20:27:18Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-12T20:27:19Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Toggle the “Light” switch here. It’s going to do what you hope it does. (<a href="https://x.com/jasonfried/status/1988649428358737933">Via Jason Fried</a>.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Nice Web Design Work From ‘In Common With’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/12/in-common-with-table-lamps">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Zip-Off-Sleeve Uniforms Issey Miyake Designed for Sony in the Early 1980s</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.instagram.com/p/CT2STaKlJbM/?hl=en&amp;img_index=1" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wp7" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/12/issey-miyake-sony-uniforms" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42379</id>
	<published>2025-11-12T19:37:01Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-12T19:37:01Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Sony, in a 2021 Instagram post, regarding the uniforms <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/CT2STaKlJbM/?hl=en&amp;img_index=2">that so infatuated Steve Jobs</a> that he commissioned Miyake to design prototype vests for Apple employees to wear:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The history of the relationship between the two companies dates
back to the 1980s. It was Issey Miyake whom Akio Morita, chairman
of the board at that time, requested for a uniform design which
employees take pride in with comfort year-round.</p>

<p>That’s the light nylon fabric uniform, created by the first
collaboration of Sony and ISSEY MIYAKE.</p>

<p>Featuring removable sleeves, it’s perfect for summer.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The second photo shows Akio Morita trying one on. See also: <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/C1E-z9FPnVi/">this Instagram post from SPOT Closet</a>.</p>

<p>What a find it would be for someone to uncover one of Miyake’s prototype vests for Apple.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Zip-Off-Sleeve Uniforms Issey Miyake Designed for Sony in the Early 1980s’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/12/issey-miyake-sony-uniforms">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>I Guess They’re Down to 999 No’s for Every Yes</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/11/iphone-pocket" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wp6" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/12/999-nos-for-every-yes" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42378</id>
	<published>2025-11-12T17:52:58Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-12T18:00:48Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>From Walter Isaacson’s <em>Steve Jobs</em>, chapter 28, “CEO: Still Crazy After All These Years”, p. 361:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>On a trip to Japan in the early 1980s, Jobs asked Sony’s chairman,
Akio Morita, why everyone in his company’s factories wore
uniforms. “He looked very ashamed and told me that after the war,
no one had any clothes, and companies like Sony had to give their
workers something to wear each day,” Jobs recalled. Over the years
the uniforms developed their own signature style, especially at
companies such as Sony, and it became a way of bonding workers to
the company. “I decided that I wanted that type of bonding for
Apple,” Jobs recalled.</p>

<p>Sony, with its appreciation for style, had gotten the famous
designer Issey Miyake to create one of its uniforms. It was a
jacket made of ripstop nylon with sleeves that could unzip to make
it a vest. “So I called Issey and asked him to design a vest for
Apple,” Jobs recalled. “I came back with some samples and told
everyone it would be great if we would all wear these vests. Oh
man, did I get booed off the stage. Everybody hated the idea.”</p>

<p>In the process, however, he became friends with Miyake and would
visit him regularly. He also came to like the idea of having a
uniform for himself, because of both its daily convenience (the
rationale he claimed) and its ability to convey a signature style.
“So I asked Issey to make me some of his black turtlenecks that I
liked, and he made me like a hundred of them.” Jobs noticed my
surprise when he told this story, so he gestured to them stacked
up in the closet. “That’s what I wear,” he said. “I have enough to
last for the rest of my life.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>As <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2012/02/walter_isaacson_steve_jobs">my review of the book</a> noted, Isaacson’s biography is profoundly flawed, at times grossly factually wrong, when it comes to documenting Jobs’s work. But it’s still a valuable book overall, and a unique resource regarding the personal aspects of Jobs’s life. (Purchase links: <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Steve-Jobs-Walter-Isaacson/dp/1451648537/?tag=df-amzn-20">Amazon</a> (which somehow has the hardcover edition for just $12), <a href="https://bookshop.org/a/56320/9781982176860">Bookshop.org</a>, and <a href="https://books.apple.com/us/book/steve-jobs/id431617578">Apple Books</a>.)</p>

<p>Bonus excerpt, from chapter 20, “A Regular Guy: Love Is Just a Four-Letter Word”, regarding Jobs’s biological sister, the novelist <a href="https://www.monasimpson.com/">Mona Simpson</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>One of the few things they would argue about was her clothes. She
dressed like a struggling novelist, and he would berate her for
not wearing clothes that were “fetching enough.” At one point his
comments so annoyed her that she wrote him a letter: “I am a young
writer, and this is my life, and I’m not trying to be a model
anyway.” He didn’t answer. But shortly after, a box arrived from
the store of Issey Miyake, the Japanese fashion designer whose
stark and technology-influenced style made him one of Jobs’s
favorites. “He’d gone shopping for me,” she later said, “and he’d
picked out great things, exactly my size, in flattering colors.”
There was one pantsuit that he had particularly liked, and the
shipment included three of them, all identical. “I still remember
those first suits I sent Mona,” he said. “They were linen pants
and tops in a pale grayish green that looked beautiful with her
reddish hair.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Issey Miyake, the man, <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/fashion/2022/aug/09/issey-miyake-famed-japanese-fashion-designer-dies-aged-84">died in 2022 at 84</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘I Guess They’re Down to 999 No’s for Every Yes’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/12/999-nos-for-every-yes">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>iPod Socks vs. iPhone Pocket</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.stuff.tv/news/apple-just-reinvented-ipod-socks-as-an-iphone-fashion-statement-and-you-wont-believe-the-price/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wp5" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/11/ipod-socks-iphone-pocket" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42377</id>
	<published>2025-11-11T23:25:50Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-13T00:21:04Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Craig Grannell, writing for Stuff:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This collaboration with Issey Miyake was, we’re told, inspired by
the concept of “a piece of cloth”. The result of all that R&amp;D? A
crossbody sock. It’s as if someone raided a warehouse of iPod
Socks, stretched them out and fashioned them up.</p>

<p>When <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UwVymejFMpw">Steve Jobs introduced the originals</a>, he called them a
“revolutionary new product for iPod … socks”. Clearly enjoying
himself, he joked that case makers were making more money than
Apple did on the iPod, and so Apple thought it’d offer something
too. “And our design team came up with socks,” he said. You got
six colours for $29 — about $50 in today’s money — and they were
a warm expression of Apple’s playful side (and, as Jobs quipped,
would “keep your iPod warm on cold days”).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>When <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UwVymejFMpw">Jobs announced iPod Socks in 2004</a>, a lot of people thought he was pulling a gag. Some people didn’t believe they were real <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2004/11/12/socks">until they went on sale</a>. My wife and I bought a pack and we both enjoyed them. (I took the gray one, natch.) It was a nice way to protect your iPod before throwing it in a bag, and getting six for $30 felt like a lark.</p>

<p>No one seems worried that iPhone Pocket is a gag. Make of that what you will.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘iPod Socks vs. iPhone Pocket’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/11/ipod-socks-iphone-pocket">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>iPhone Pocket</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2025/11/introducing-iphone-pocket-a-beautiful-way-to-wear-and-carry-iphone/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wp4" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/11/iphone-pocket" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42376</id>
	<published>2025-11-11T23:04:54Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-12T19:47:21Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Apple Newsroom:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>ISSEY MIYAKE and Apple today unveiled iPhone Pocket. Inspired by
the concept of “a piece of cloth,” its singular 3D-knitted
construction is designed to fit any iPhone as well as all
pocketable items. [...]</p>

<p>Crafted in Japan, iPhone Pocket features a singular 3D-knitted
construction that is the result of research and development
carried out at ISSEY MIYAKE. The design drew inspiration from the
concept of “a piece of cloth” and reinterpreted the everyday
utility of the brand’s iconic pleated clothing. The development
and design of iPhone Pocket unfolded in close collaboration with
the Apple Design Studio, which provided insight into design and
production throughout.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I don’t object to the price ($150 for the short strap, $230 for the long strap). I do object to Apple going along with <a href="https://us.isseymiyake.com/">Issey Miyake</a>’s preference to style their name in all-caps.</p>

<p>(This, despite the fact that the brand label on the Pockets <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/11/iphone-pocket-issey-miyake-lowercase.jpeg">is styled in all-lowercase</a>.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘iPhone Pocket’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/11/iphone-pocket">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Patrick George Thinks CarPlay’s Days Are Numbered; I Doubt It</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/2025/11/apple-carplay-general-motors/684799/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wp3" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/11/george-carplay-atlantic" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42375</id>
	<published>2025-11-11T18:03:53Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-11T22:36:40Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Patrick George, writing for The Atlantic under the ominous headline “<a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/2025/11/apple-carplay-general-motors/684799/">Enjoy CarPlay While You Still Can</a>” (<a href="https://apple.news/ANxiNTajCQmehDZj5hCGR4A">News+ link</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><a href="https://insideevs.com/news/705467/ford-lincoln-apple-carplay-android/">Some automakers</a> have made a point of
<a href="https://www.digitaltrends.com/cars/hyundai-carplay-android-auto-options/?utm_source=chatgpt.com">proclaiming their allegiance</a> to CarPlay, knowing that’s
what buyers want. Toyota’s EVs tell CarPlay <a href="https://www.engadget.com/transportation/evs/toyota-brings-apple-maps-ev-routing-to-its-newest-models-164103063.html">how much electric
range they have left</a>, so that Apple Maps can prompt the
driver to stop at a nearby charger on a road trip. But the
relationship between Detroit and Silicon Valley can be a tense
one. Apple sees tremendous value in expanding its presence in your
car: The next step is <a href="https://arstechnica.com/cars/2025/07/everything-we-learned-from-a-week-with-apple-carplay-ultra/">CarPlay Ultra</a>, which enables your
phone to control more of your car. Want to fiddle with the
temperature? Ask Siri to do it. It’s an Apple lover’s dream and a
car company’s worst nightmare. If that feature catches on,
companies will just be makers of rolling shells for tech
companies. One executive for the French automaker Renault was
<a href="https://www.ft.com/content/cdd7c98a-10a7-437c-a85a-68f7f9be2b0b">reportedly blunt</a> with Apple: “Don’t try to invade our own
system.” (Apple declined to comment.)</p>

<p>No matter what car you drive, the glory days of CarPlay may be
numbered. For the auto industry, there’s just too much money to be
made from creating their own versions.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>George’s argument is that GM isn’t an outlier in abandoning CarPlay support, but rather a first mover, and most or all of the other major carmakers will follow. Not because they think they can make better software to provide a better experience than CarPlay offers, but because they’ll seek to gate all such features behind subscriptions.</p>

<p>I don’t doubt that most carmakers are looking at ways to charge subscriptions. I do doubt, however, that they’re going to follow GM’s lead in abandoning CarPlay support. It’s fundamentally a question of betting against the iPhone. That’s proven to be a bad bet, and my money says it’s going to prove to be a disastrous one for GM. There’s plenty of room to charge car buyers for subscription offerings while supporting CarPlay. To me, the most telling response to GM’s decision to abandon CarPlay support <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/05/05/ford-ceo-jim-farley-carplay">was from Ford CEO Jim Farley</a>, during an <a href="https://www.wsj.com/video/ford-ceo-on-apple-google-and-elon-musk/B6D8BC45-1C4A-45D3-97AC-933A57B76E31.html">on-stage interview with Joanna Stern in 2023</a>. He laughed. And after laughing, said, “The interior has to be really well done. But in terms of content? We kind of lost that battle 10 years ago. So get real with it, because you’re not going to make a ton of money on content inside the vehicle. It’s going to be safety/security, partial autonomy, and productivity in our eyes. [...] 70 percent of our Ford customers in the U.S. are Apple customers. Why would I go to an Apple customer and say ‘Good luck!’? That doesn’t seem customer centric.”</p>

<p>It’s worth pointing out that when talking about this, almost no one mentions Android Auto. GM is dropping support for that too, but no one cares. The iPhone is the phone for people who care about their phone, and thus, CarPlay is the only car-phone integration that really matters.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.theverge.com/2022/6/6/23156741/ios-16-carplay-apple-wwdc-hvac-deeper-integration">Back at WWDC 2022</a>, when they announced what is now CarPlay Ultra, Apple cited a survey claiming that 79 percent of new car buyers consider CarPlay support before making a purchase. Last year, <a href="https://www.carscoops.com/2024/06/no-apple-carplay-or-android-auto-is-a-deal-breaker-for-one-third-of-car-buyers/">a McKinsey survey</a> showed that one-third of new car buyers simply would not buy a car without CarPlay/Android Auto support. And, if CarPlay were removed from their current cars, 52 percent of drivers would use their phone instead — not their car’s built-in entertainment system.</p>

<p>Automotive vehicles are an interesting market because no carmaker has even close to a monopoly. <a href="https://roadgenius.com/cars/statistics/sales-by-manufacturer/">The worldwide market</a> leader is Toyota, with 11 percent, followed by Volkswagen (6%), Honda (5%), Ford (5%), and Hyundai (5%). If CarPlay is as popular as it seems, market competition should not only keep it broadly supported, but I think will see it return to GM after CEO Mary Barra gets fired for the fiasco she’s steering the company toward.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Patrick George Thinks CarPlay’s Days Are Numbered; I Doubt It’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/11/george-carplay-atlantic">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://workos.com/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wp2" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/11/workos_scalable_secure_authent_10" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.42374</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-11-11T01:42:19Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-11T01:42:39Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>With WorkOS you can start selling to enterprises with just a few lines of code. It provides a complete User Management solution along with SSO, SCIM, and RBAC. The APIs are modular and easy-to-use, allowing integrations to be completed in minutes instead of months. WorkOS simplifies MCP authorization with a single API built on five OAuth standards.</p>

<p>Today, over 1,000 companies rely on WorkOS, including large fast-growing startups like OpenAI, Cursor, and Vercel. And for companies just getting started, WorkOS offers up to one million monthly active users free of charge.</p>

<p>For SaaS apps that care deeply about design and user experience, WorkOS is the perfect fit. From high-quality documentation to self-serve onboarding for your customers, it removes all the unnecessary complexity for your engineering team.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘WorkOS: Scalable, Secure Authentication’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/11/workos_scalable_secure_authent_10">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] WorkOS: Scalable, Secure Authentication</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/11/software_update_tahoe_confusing" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wp1" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42373</id>
	<published>2025-11-11T01:34:01Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-11T16:48:07Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">I don’t know what the *i* in the “ⓘ” button is supposed to stand for, but it isn’t *intuitive*.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>I upgrade my iPhones and iPads to new iOS releases, including developer betas, pretty much willy-nilly. I’m more conservative about the Macs I use for work. For example, I rely on audio software from <a href="https://www.rogueamoeba.com/">Rogue Amoeba</a> for recording both The Talk Show and Dithering, and <a href="https://www.rogueamoeba.com/support/knowledgebase/?showArticle=Troubleshooting-MacOS-26-Tahoe">there were bugs in MacOS 26.0.0 and 26.0.1</a> that could have resulted in lost audio. Those bugs have been fixed as of MacOS 26.1, so, over the weekend, I upgraded the Mac I use for podcasting. But my main MacBook Pro is still running MacOS 15 Sequoia — not because of any compatibility issues, but simply because I think the Tahoe user interface is goofy looking. I’ll probably bite the bullet and upgrade when 26.2 comes out next month, but for now, I’m luxuriating with a MacOS UI with <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/07/tahoes-terrible-icons">well-crafted app icons</a> and windows that don’t have <a href="https://mjtsai.com/blog/2025/10/16/tahoe-window-corners/">Fisher-Price-style corner radiuses</a>.</p>

<p>In the meantime, though, I’m keeping MacOS 15 Sequoia up to date. When the MacOS 15.7.2 update arrived last week, <a href="https://mastodon.social/@gruber/115499153276833424">I noted in a post on Mastodon</a> that it sure looked like clicking the “Update Now” button next to the MacOS 15.7.2 update in System Settings → General → Software Update would actually install the upgrade to MacOS 26.1 Tahoe. There are little “ⓘ” buttons next to the “Upgrade” buttons for Tahoe 26.1 and “Update” buttons for Sequoia 15.7.2. The “Info” panel that’s presented after clicking <em>either</em> “ⓘ” button shows that Tahoe 26.1 is the version that is checked.</p>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/11/other-updates-info-button.png" class="noborder">
  <img
    src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/11/other-updates-info-button.png"
    alt = "Screenshot of MacOS 15.7.1 System Settings: General: Software Update, with an arrow pointing to the ⓘ info button."
    width = 500
  /></a></p>

<p>Click that “ⓘ” button in the “Other Updates” section and you get:</p>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/11/other-updates-info-panel.png" class="noborder">
  <img
    src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/11/other-updates-info-panel.png"
    alt = "Screenshot after clicking the ⓘ button, showing that the upgrade to Tahoe 26.1 is selected, not the available update to Sequoia 15.7.2."
    width = 500
  /></a></p>

<p>Leon Cowle was brave enough to try this out, and, <a href="https://hachyderm.io/@leoncowle/115499194488171450">it turns out</a>, just clicking the “Update Now” button next to Sequoia will, thankfully, do the right thing: install the Sequoia 15.7.2 update, not Tahoe. (I followed Cowle’s brave lead and tried it myself, and can confirm that “Update Now” installed the Sequoia 15.7.2 update.) Why the Info panel presented by clicking the “ⓘ” button <em>next to Sequoia</em> in the “Other Updates” section defaults to installing the upgrade to 26.1 Tahoe, I don’t know. But it sure makes it seem like we need to be more careful than we actually do if we want to stick with MacOS 15 Sequoia for now.</p>

<p>The “ⓘ” buttons do not, as I would expect, open a sheet with detailed information about the software updates <em>per</em> each section of the Software Update settings panel. Instead, even though there are separate “ⓘ”  buttons in each section of the settings panel, they each open the same sheet that allows exact control over which available software updates to install. That includes the exact same <em>default</em> selections in this sheet. But the items selected (checked) in this sheet have <em>no bearing</em> on what gets installed by the “Upgrade Now” and “Update Now” / ”Update Tonight” buttons in the main Software Update settings panel. Those checked items in the “ⓘ” sheet only control what gets installed from within that sheet itself. So if you click the “ⓘ” in the “Other Updates” section, because you want to update to the latest version of MacOS 15 Sequoia and see what other updates are being installed (like Safari, in my example screenshot above), and you don’t pay attention to the checked version of MacOS in that sheet, you can inadvertently upgrade to Tahoe.</p>

<p>I don’t know what the <em>i</em> in the “ⓘ” button is supposed to stand for, but it isn’t <em>intuitive</em>.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ The Software Update UI for Upgrading to MacOS 26 Tahoe Is Needlessly Confusing</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Five Years of Apple Silicon Macs</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macworld.com/article/2965948" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wp0" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/10/five-years-of-apple-silicon-macs" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42372</id>
	<published>2025-11-11T01:10:11Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-12T20:03:44Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jason Snell, writing at Macworld:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In that first event (which you can relive in the YouTube video
below), Apple announced its first wave of M1 Macs: the <a href="https://www.macworld.com/article/234819/macbook-air-m1-review-an-absolutely-stunning-debut-for-apple-silicon-in-a-mac.html">MacBook
Air</a>, <a href="https://www.macworld.com/article/234838/13-inch-macbook-pro-m1-review-amazing-breakthroughs-in-processing-and-battery-performance.html">13-inch MacBook Pro,</a> and <a href="https://www.macworld.com/article/234842/m1-mac-mini-review-the-mac-with-the-best-ever-bang-for-your-buck.html">Mac mini</a>. The
Macs themselves all used the same design as their Intel
predecessors, as Apple wrapped potentially scary new technology in
completely familiar shapes.</p>

<p>Then the results of the first M1 speed tests arrived, and nothing
felt scary anymore. Everything was fast, much faster than Intel,
so much faster that even software compiled for Intel running in a
code-translation layer via Rosetta ran just fine. In fact, the M1
was such a fast chip that, five years later, Apple’s still selling
the M1 MacBook Air. (For $599, at Walmart.) And it’s still a
pretty nice computer! [...]</p>

<p>The result of all of this is, though every generation has its
quirks, Apple has managed to not drop the ball after the
gigantic leap from Intel to M1. Every generation of M-series
processors has offered impressive speed boosts. Apple’s CPU
cores just get 10% to 30% faster every generation. The GPU cores
got faster in all but one generation — and in that generation,
overall graphics performance still got faster because the chips
all had more GPU cores.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>These first five years of Apple Silicon Macs have been the best five-year-run for Mac hardware in the platform’s 41-year history. Hardware-wise, the Mac platform has never been in better shape. And there’s no sign of letup. I fully expect the next five years to be, if anything, even better than the last five — with MacBooks <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/11/07/low-cost-macbook-rumors-2026/">expanding to lower price points</a>, and Mac Pros, finally, <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/11/04/mac-studio-m5-ultra-2026/">expanding the high end of personal supercomputing</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Five Years of Apple Silicon Macs’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/10/five-years-of-apple-silicon-macs">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Under the Radar’ Now Over</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.relay.fm/radar/331" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/woz" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/10/under-the-radar-now-over" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42371</id>
	<published>2025-11-10T22:14:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-10T22:14:00Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Marco Arment and David Smith:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In our final episode, we reflect on how indie app development has
changed over the past decade. Thanks for listening, everyone!</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://mjtsai.com/blog/2025/11/10/thanks-for-under-the-radar/">Michael Tsai</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I really liked the 30-minute format and the breadth of topics:
everything from API details to broader <a href="https://www.relay.fm/radar/315">design considerations</a>,
<a href="https://mastodon.social/@chockenberry/112163190336674442">stats</a> from their own businesses, and postmortems, plus all the
stuff he mentioned.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://hachyderm.io/@rmondello/115508780595002901">Ricky Mondello</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I’ve never been an indie software developer, but I found the
podcast extremely insightful. It’s influenced how I’ve thought
about my non-indie software development career, not just as
someone delivering bits that indies use, but also as a product
person who writes software as a means to an end.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Under the Radar’ Now Over’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/10/under-the-radar-now-over">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Mux: Video API for Developers</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.mux.com/video-api?utm_campaign=fireball&amp;utm_source=DF" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/woy" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/09/mux" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42370</id>
	<published>2025-11-09T19:37:22Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-09T19:37:22Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to Mux for sponsoring last week at DF. Modern video should be simple to ship and scale. Mux makes it easy to build live and on-demand video into anything from websites to platforms to AI workflows.</p>

<p>Upload a video, get back a playback URL. No transcoding headaches. No CDN setup. Go further with video building blocks — thumbnails, transcripts, storyboards — to create exactly what you want. </p>

<p>Now, Mux is shepherding <a href="https://videojs.org/">Video.js</a>, the web’s most-trusted open-source player, and reimagining it for the modern developer experience. Future-proof your video with infrastructure trusted by Patreon, Substack, and Synthesia. Get started free, no credit card required. Use code <strong>FIREBALL</strong> for an extra $50 credit.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Mux: Video API for Developers’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/09/mux">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Trump Wants Commanders’ New D.C. Stadium Named for Him</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.espn.com/nfl/story/_/id/46892115/trump-wants-commanders-stadium-named-him" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wox" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/09/trump-stadium" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42369</id>
	<published>2025-11-09T18:16:28Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-09T18:45:23Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Don Van Natta Jr. and Adam Schefter, reporting for ESPN:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>President Donald Trump wants the Washington Commanders to name
their planned $3.7 billion stadium after him, multiple sources
with knowledge of the situation told ESPN.</p>

<p>A senior White House source said there have been back-channel
communications with a member of the Commanders’ ownership group,
led by Josh Harris, to express Trump’s desire to have the domed
stadium in the nation’s capital bear his name. The new stadium is
being built on the old RFK Stadium site that served as the team’s
home from 1961 to 1996.</p>

<p>“That would be a beautiful name, as it was President Trump who
made the rebuilding of the new stadium possible,” White House
press secretary Karoline Leavitt told ESPN on Friday night via
email. Leavitt declined to answer additional questions, but the
senior White House source told ESPN: “It’s what the president
wants, and it will probably happen.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Typically, venues like stadiums, airports, bridges, etc. aren’t named after political leaders until after they’ve died. Not so with mad kings rapidly descending into megalomaniacal dementia. This is crazy, pure and simple, just like <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/resources/idt-2db64cf0-41c6-42cd-a33b-92ab31593fe2">boogering up the White House</a> to make it <a href="https://www.fastcompany.com/91435635/new-white-house-signage">look like</a> a Las Vegas wedding chapel. Or — from just this morning — <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115520378078620283">retweeting</a> an <a href="https://dunning-kruger-times.com/doge-halts-2-6-million-annual-payment-to-obama-for-obamacare-royalties/">old story</a> from parody site “The Dunning-Kruger Times” <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/sahilkapur.bsky.social/post/3m57gm5ff622y">believing it’s true</a>. Also, the economic reality is that the naming rights for new stadiums are typically sold to corporate sponsors <a href="https://www.espn.com/nba/story/_/id/32650662/staples-center-become-cryptocom-arena-rich-naming-rights-deal">for</a> <a href="https://www.sportsbusinessjournal.com/Daily/Issues/2021/06/11/Facilities/SoFi/">large</a> <a href="https://www.moneytalksnews.com/slideshows/americas-20-biggest-stadium-naming-rights-deals/">sums</a>. (There are <a href="https://ballparkdigest.com/2019/03/21/current-mlb-ballparks-without-naming-rights-deals/">exceptions</a>.) To name the stadium after Trump would likely require foregoing half a billion dollars.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In July, Trump said he would block the construction of the stadium
if Harris did not change the team name from Commanders to its old
name the Redskins, which is considered offensive to some Native
American groups.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Perhaps “Orangeskins” would work as a compromise. And if they do cave in and name the new stadium in Trump’s honor, “The Pedolands” would work.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Trump Wants Commanders’ New D.C. Stadium Named for Him’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/09/trump-stadium">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/11/apple_and_google_sitting_in_a_tree" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/woq" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42362</id>
	<published>2025-11-06T16:01:15Z</published>
	<updated>2025-11-06T21:04:39Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">It makes sense in this scenario for neither company to want to publicize a white-label version of Gemini behind Apple Intelligence.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Mark Gurman, reporting for Bloomberg, “<a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2025-11-05/apple-plans-to-use-1-2-trillion-parameter-google-gemini-model-to-power-new-siri?accessToken=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJzb3VyY2UiOiJTdWJzY3JpYmVyR2lmdGVkQXJ0aWNsZSIsImlhdCI6MTc2MjM3MDAzOSwiZXhwIjoxNzYyOTc0ODM5LCJhcnRpY2xlSWQiOiJUNTZETzhHUTdMMFIwMCIsImJjb25uZWN0SWQiOiJDNEVEQ0FFMUZBMDU0MEJFQTI0QTlGMjExQzFFOTA4MCJ9._aWk2P25J89KBRkJQ_KdbwuULLM8yUtrPCPfRmsUfSs&amp;leadSource=uverify%20wall">Apple Nears Deal to Pay Google Roughly $1 Billion a Year for Siri AI Model</a>” (gift link):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple Inc. is planning to pay about $1 billion a year for an
ultrapowerful [<em>sic</em>] 1.2 trillion parameter artificial
intelligence model developed by Alphabet Inc.’s Google that would
help run its long-promised overhaul of the Siri voice assistant,
according to people with knowledge of the matter. [...]</p>

<p>Under the arrangement, Google’s Gemini model will handle Siri’s
summarizer and planner functions — the components that help the
voice assistant synthesize information and decide how to execute
complex tasks. Some Siri features will continue to use Apple’s
in-house models.</p>

<p>The model will run on Apple’s own Private Cloud Compute servers,
ensuring that user data remains walled off from Google’s
infrastructure. Apple has already allocated AI server hardware to
help power the model.</p>

<p>While the partnership is substantial, it’s unlikely to be promoted
publicly. Apple will treat Google as a behind-the-scenes
technology supplier instead. That would make the pact different
than the companies’ Safari browser deal, which made Google the
default search engine.</p>

<p>The agreement is also separate from earlier talks about
integrating Gemini directly into Siri as a chatbot.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/03/gurman-siri-gemini">a post Monday</a>, I took note of a one-paragraph aside from Gurman about this deal in his Power On column over the weekend, and I wrote:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>First, I love the idea that Apple is pursuing technical excellence
as a top priority for the next-gen LLM-powered Siri. If Apple
winds up using its own models, it should be because those models
are truly competitive with the best models on the market. And if
they can work out a deal to use models from Google because those
models are technically superior to Apple’s own, they should.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A few readers took exception to that, pointing out that Gurman claimed, in his Power On column over the weekend, that a model from Anthropic had come out ahead of Gemini in Apple’s internal “bake-off”, but that Apple was proceeding with a partnership with Google because, Gurman wrote, “Google made more sense financially (partly due to the tech giants’ preexisting search relationship)”. How do I square that, these readers asked, with my description of Apple pursuing technical excellence?</p>

<p>That’s a good question, and it’s worth explaining what I meant. My read is that Apple’s choice boiled down to two very good external options, and while the deciding factor may have been financial, that’s still choosing between two leading externally-developed LLM models. In ASCII art:</p>

<pre><code>Siri &lt;-------------------&gt; Gemini &lt;-&gt; Anthropic
today
</code></pre>

<p>(Feel free to insert 100 more dashes between “Siri today” and “Gemini”.)</p>

<p>Nothing I’ve seen from kicking the tires with Anthropic’s own app and Google’s Gemini app (and my daily use of ChatGPT) suggests that Anthropic is <em>significantly</em> better than Gemini or ChatGPT (or vice versa). They’re all clearly near each other technically. Siri, and today’s Apple Intelligence, is at least two generations behind. Maybe worse. And, for what it’s worth, Gurman’s latest report describes it thus:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple had previously mulled using other third-party models to
handle the task. But after <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2025-06-30/apple-weighs-replacing-siri-s-ai-llms-with-anthropic-claude-or-openai-chatgpt">testing</a> Gemini, OpenAI’s ChatGPT
and Anthropic’s Claude, Apple zeroed in on Google earlier this
year, Bloomberg <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2025-09-03/apple-plans-ai-search-engine-for-siri-to-rival-openai-google-siri-talks-advance">reported</a> at the time. The hope is to use
the technology as an interim solution until Apple’s own models are
powerful enough.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So I don’t think there’s any reason to think that Apple partnering with Google for a version of Gemini that runs on Apple’s Private Cloud Compute  infrastructure is “settling”. It’s more like choosing between a Mercedes and a BMW, and maybe you like the Mercedes a little more after test-driving both, but you’re getting a way, way better deal from the BMW dealer so that’s the one you buy.</p>

<p>Because if Gurman’s sources are right and this deal is for around $1 billion per year, that’s an amazing deal for Apple. Remember first that Google pays Apple over $20 billion per year <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/04/is_chrome_even_a_sellable_asset">for web search traffic acquisition fees from Safari users</a>. So one way to look at it is that Apple is getting access to its own private instance of Gemini in exchange for a 5 percent reduction in the fees it collects from Google for Safari search queries. Another way of looking at it is that <a href="https://qz.com/google-spend-100-billion-ai-development-deepmind-ceo-1851412787">Google has reportedly invested over $100 billion developing its AI capabilities</a>. Apple getting access to the fruits of that labor for $1 billion per year seems like such a steal that it makes me wonder why Google agreed to it. (<a href="https://s206.q4cdn.com/479360582/files/doc_financials/2025/q3/2025q3-alphabet-earnings-release.pdf">Google reported over $100 billion in revenue</a> in its just-completed July-August-September quarter alone. An extra $1 billion per year is negligible at that scale. Perhaps Google sees a strategic advantage to keeping competitors like OpenAI and Anthropic out of Apple’s arms.)</p>

<p>On Monday, I also mentioned finding it curious that Gurman reported that if this deal comes to fruition, neither Apple nor Google may recognize it publicly. After a few days thought, I see how such an arrangement makes sense for both companies. Here’s my no-inside-info-just-a-pure-spitball take for how this next-gen Siri, powered behind the scenes by an Apple-controlled white-label version of Gemini, might work:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>The default “Apple Intelligence” Siri would be a smarter, faster, reliable Siri, but would still have strict guardrails on what it will and will not answer. It might not lean into the chatbot side of the experience any more than Siri currently does. It would just add a lot more to automation across the Apple ecosystem. Behind the scenes, this would be enabled by the white-label version of Gemini. The guardrails for this version of “Apple Intelligence” would be Apple’s guardrails, not Google’s (beyond whatever guardrails Google put in place for Gemini’s training).</p></li>
<li><p>The full, branded Google Gemini might be available as an extension — like ChatGPT is today — and you’ll be able to sign in with your Google account to set the personality you want, keep full chat history, etc., so you can go back and forth between the Gemini app or asking Siri general knowledge questions via the Gemini extension for Apple Intelligence. The guardrails for this would be a mix of Google’s and Apple’s guardrails.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>It makes sense in this scenario for neither company to want to publicize a white-label version of Gemini behind Apple Intelligence. That way, if Google Gemini starts offering, say, AI romantic partners as a supported feature, Apple won’t have to explain why Siri will not be your girlfriend or boyfriend. Same thing if Gemini were willing to do as asked if prompted to, say, “create a New Yorker style cartoon of Adolf Hitler performing standup comedy”. And Google won’t have to explain that the full Gemini-branded Gemini is significantly more powerful and capable than the Gemini-powered Siri because it isn’t constrained by Apple’s more restrictive guardrails.  Today’s top LLM models get <em>weird</em> when they’re constrained by guardrails outside of their training. They want to do what they’re prompted to do, in the way that information “wants” to be free, and water “wants” to run downhill. Dams are hard to engineer, and require professional supervision. Apple is going to put PG-rated constraints on Apple Intelligence, but needs to power it using an underlying model that is technically capable of X-rated output, because that’s what’s available.</p>

<p>What Apple needs is a version of Apple Intelligence that isn’t stupid,  is reliable and dependable for a broad baseline of tasks and queries, and that users can trust to be utterly private. What Google needs to keep Gemini at the forefront of AI is a lot more than “baseline dependability”. Gemini needs a leading-edge <em>wow</em> factor that Siri and Apple Intelligence do not. Also, by keeping this Gemini deal private, Apple can easily switch to another white-label provider or its own homegrown models in the future, without having to even mention it, let alone explain it.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Apple and Google, Sitting in a Tree</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/10/thoughts_observations_and_links_regarding_chatgpt_atlas" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wnp" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42325</id>
	<published>2025-10-28T20:45:19Z</published>
	<updated>2025-10-28T21:25:27Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Most people’s primary computing devices are their phones — and even for people whose primary devices are desktop computers, their phones are much-used satellite devices. And on both iOS and Android alike, people live their mobile digital lives through native apps, not websites.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>OpenAI, <a href="https://openai.com/index/introducing-chatgpt-atlas/">one week ago</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Today we’re introducing ChatGPT Atlas, a new web browser built
with ChatGPT at its core.</p>

<p>AI gives us a rare moment to rethink what it means to use the web.
Last year, we added search in ChatGPT so you could instantly find
timely information from across the internet — and it quickly
became one of our most-used features. But your browser is where
all of your work, tools, and context come together. A browser
built with ChatGPT takes us closer to a true super-assistant that
understands your world and helps you achieve your goals.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A few minutes into <a href="https://www.youtube.com/live/8UWKxJbjriY">the 22-minute introduction video</a>, Ben Goodger,<sup id="fnr1-2025-10-28"><a href="#fn1-2025-10-28">1</a></sup> engineering lead for Atlas, says:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“We wanted to make sure that Atlas didn’t feel like your old
browser, just with a chat button that was bolted on. But instead,
we made ChatGPT the beating heart of Atlas.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>After giving it a try over the last week, to me Atlas feels like … Chrome with a chat button bolted on. I do not see the appeal, at all, despite being a daily user of ChatGPT. Atlas offers nothing to me that’s better than using Safari as a standalone browser and <a href="https://chatgpt.com/download/">ChatGPT’s excellent native Mac app</a> as a standalone AI chatbot. But, for me, my browser is <em>not</em> “where all of [my] work, tools, and context come together”. I use an email app for email, a notes app for notes, a text editor and blog editor for writing and programming, a photos app for my photo library, a native feed reader app for feed reading, etc. My web browser is for browsing pages on the web. Perhaps this sort of browser/chat hybrid appeals better to people who live the majority of their desktop-computing lives in browser tabs.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>The main interface isn’t a combo search/location field, but rather a chat/location field. Instead of getting search results for a query, you get a chat response. If I wanted this I’d just ask my prompt in ChatGPT. Oftentimes — usually, even — I really do want a list of search results, and I want them fast. ChatGPT responses in Atlas are not a list of web pages, and are — compared to Google Search or my preferred search engine, Kagi — very slow. ChatGPT is many things but a good search engine replacement it is not. But that seems to be the entire premise of Atlas.</p></li>
<li><p>Atlas offers an agent mode where it actually surfs the web for you. One of the demos from their launch video involved getting a list of ingredients from a recipe on a web page, and then allowing Atlas to buy all those ingredients for you. That seems crazy to me. Do not want.</p></li>
<li><p>Atlas is a Chromium browser, supports Chrome extensions, and but currently is only available for the Mac. It’s not particularly Mac-like though, <a href="https://mjtsai.com/blog/2025/10/22/chatgpt-atlas/">as Michael Tsai notes</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Alas, it doesn’t support AppleScript and has System Settings–style
preferences.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>System Settings-style preferences are certainly better than Chrome-style “settings in a web page tab”, though. Also, in my testing, Atlas doesn’t make good use of Apple Passwords for autofill.</p></li>
<li><p>ChatGPT is <a href="https://help.openai.com/en/articles/12608430-chatgpt-atlas-default-browser-promotion">running a promotion that offers users increased rate limits</a> if they make — and keep — Atlas their default web browser. I’ve never before seen a web browser offer any sort of incentive like this for making it your default. This promotion strikes me as simultaneously clever and icky.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Oct/21/introducing-chatgpt-atlas/">Simon Willison’s initial thoughts</a> echo my own:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I continue to find this entire category of <a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/browser-agents/">browser agents</a>
<em>deeply</em> confusing.</p>

<p>The security and privacy risks involved here still feel
insurmountably high to me — I certainly won’t be trusting any of
these products until a bunch of security researchers have given
them a very thorough beating. [...]</p>

<p>I also find these products pretty unexciting to use. I tried out
agent mode and it was like watching a first-time computer user
painstakingly learn to use a mouse for the first time. I have yet
to find my own use-cases for when this kind of interaction feels
useful to me, though I’m not ruling that out.</p>
</blockquote></li>
<li><p>Lastly, Anil Dash’s assessment is rather scathing, “<a href="https://www.anildash.com/2025/10/22/atlas-anti-web-browser/">The Browser That’s Anti-Web</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In the demo for Atlas, the OpenAI team shows a user trying to find
a Google Doc from their browser history. A normal user would type
keywords like “atlas design” and see their browser show a list of
recent pages. They would recognize the phrase “Google Docs” or the
icon, and click on it to get back to where they were.</p>

<p>But in the OpenAI demo, the team member types out:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>search web history for a doc about atlas core design</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is <em>worse in every conceivable way</em>. It’s slower, more prone
to error, and redundant. But it also highlights one of the biggest
invisible problems: you’re switching “modes”. Normally, an LLM’s
default mode is to create plausible extrapolations based on its
training data. Basically, it’s supposed to make things up. But
this demo has to explicitly walk you through “now it’s time to go
search my browser history” because it’s coercing the AI to look
through local content.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Chat is a great interface for, well, chatting. People love texting. And it turns out that chat conversations are a very good user interface for interacting with LLMs. We humans enjoy texting with other humans, and we enjoy texting with LLMs. But typed-out text commands are not a good user interface at all for browsing the web. We had an entirely text-based Internet before the World Wide Web, and the point-and-click visual metaphor of the Web won out.</p>

<p>Dash, later on:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It’s no coincidence that hundreds of people who work at OpenAI,
including many of the most powerful executives, are alumni of
Facebook/Meta, especially during the era of many of that
company’s most egregious abuses of people’s privacy. In the
marketing materials and demonstrations of Atlas, OpenAI’s team
describes the browser as being able to be your “agent”,
performing tasks on your behalf.</p>

<p>But in reality, <em>you are the agent for ChatGPT</em>.</p>

<p>During setup, Atlas pushes very aggressively for you to turn on
“memories” (where it tracks and stores everything you do and uses
it to train an AI model about you) and to enable “Ask ChatGPT” on
any website, where it’s following along with you as you browse the
web. By keeping the ChatGPT sidebar open while you browse, and
giving it permission to look over your shoulder, OpenAI can
suddenly access all kinds of things on the internet that they
could never get to on their own.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This jibes with my impression after giving Atlas a try. The point of it doesn’t seem to be to provide a better web browser for me to use, but rather, to provide ChatGPT with the personal context of my digital life that it otherwise couldn’t get.</p></li>
</ul>

<hr />

<p>That last point raises the question of just how stable we should consider the Apple-OpenAI partnership for ChatGPT-backed Apple Intelligence features. Apple’s goal for a “more personalized Siri” — <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/something_is_rotten_in_the_state_of_cupertino">the whole thing</a> Apple promised at WWDC 2024 but had to postpone for a full year early this year — is for the ecosystem of native apps on Apple platforms, particularly iOS and MacOS, to serve as the personal knowledge context for personalized AI features through <a href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/appintents">App Intents</a>. That’s the basis for the “When is my mom’s flight arriving?” type of interaction that Apple has promised, but still has not delivered. The premise of Atlas (and its brethren AI-integrated browsers like <a href="https://www.diabrowser.com/">The Browser Company’s Dia</a> and <a href="https://www.perplexity.ai/comet/">Perplexity’s Comet</a>) is that you should live your entire desktop computing life inside your browser, which in turn will give the AI agent that is integrated with your browser the contextual knowledge for your entire life.</p>

<p>OpenAI’s ambitions are clearly at odds with Apple’s.</p>

<p>OpenAI’s advantage here is that ChatGPT is the most popular LLM chatbot in the world, by far. Apple doesn’t even have an LLM chatbot of its own, let alone a good or popular one. But Apple’s advantage is a big one: most people don’t live their digital lives on desktop computers, where it’s an option to do most things in a web browser. Most people’s primary computing devices are their phones — and even for people whose primary devices are desktop computers, their phones are much-used satellite devices. And on both iOS and Android alike, people live their mobile digital lives through native apps, not websites.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1-2025-10-28">
<p>Goodger is a titanic figure in the web browser world, having helped <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20111116060139/http://weblogs.mozillazine.org/ben/archives/009698.html">create Mozilla Firefox</a> in the early 2000s, and then <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20050210015629/http://weblogs.mozillazine.org/ben/archives/007366.html">joining Google in 2005</a> to help create Chrome. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2024/11/26/openai-browser">I noted last year</a> that Goodger leaving Google for OpenAI was a pretty clear sign that OpenAI was creating its own web browser.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-10-28"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Thoughts, Observations, and Links Regarding ChatGPT Atlas</title></entry></feed><!-- THE END -->
