<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>Daring Fireball</title>
<subtitle>By John Gruber</subtitle>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/" />
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main" />
<id>https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main</id>


<updated>2025-04-16T20:37:05Z</updated><rights>Copyright © 2025, John Gruber</rights><entry>
	<title>Meta Botches Redaction of Slides in Antitrust Trial, Angering Google, Apple, and Snap</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/news/649834/meta-redactions-apple-google-snap-angry-ftc-antitrust-trial" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9p" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/16/meta-redactions" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41821</id>
	<published>2025-04-16T20:26:20Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-16T20:37:05Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Wes Davis, The Verge:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>During <a href="https://www.theverge.com/news/646809/ftc-v-meta-antitrust-monopoly-trial-instagram-whatsapp">Meta’s antitrust trial today</a>, lawyers representing
Apple, Google, and Snap each expressed irritation with Meta over
the slides it presented on Monday that <a href="https://www.theverge.com/news/648893/meta-redacted-documents-leak-ftc-antitrust-opening-statement">The Verge found to
contain</a> easy-to-remove redactions. Attorneys for both Apple
and Snap called the errors “egregious,” with Apple’s
representative indicating that it may not be able to trust Meta
with its internal information in the future. Google’s attorney
also blamed Meta for jeopardizing the search giant’s data with the
mistake.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This yet another one of those situations where the botched redactions were just objects layered atop the supposed-to-be-redacted material in a PDF file. In 2025 you either have to be really bad with computers to do this, or you did it this way on purpose.</p>

<p>You can properly redact a PDF digitally, but botched digital redactions are so commonplace (and at times disastrous and/or humiliating) that when then Attorney General William Barr released the Mueller Report in 2019, the DOJ printed the unredacted original, did the redactions on paper, <a href="https://pdfa.org/a-technical-and-cultural-assessment-of-the-mueller-report-pdf/">and then scanned it back in to create the redacted PDF</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Meta Botches Redaction of Slides in Antitrust Trial, Angering Google, Apple, and Snap’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/16/meta-redactions">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The WSJ Reports on How Elon Musk Manages His ‘Legion’ of Children and Harem of Mothers</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.wsj.com/politics/elon-musk-children-mothers-ashley-st-clair-grimes-dc7ba05c?st=prbiyB&amp;reflink=desktopwebshare_permalink" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9o" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/16/wsj-musk-children" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41820</id>
	<published>2025-04-16T19:34:26Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-16T20:11:21Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Dana Mattioli, reporting for The Wall Street Journal (main link is gift link; also, here’s a <a href="https://apple.news/AHC6yWxE6RiCnnXg3C6x6fw">News+ link</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Musk has had at least 14 children with four women, including the pop musician Grimes and Shivon Zilis, an executive at his brain computer company Neuralink. Multiple sources close to the tech entrepreneur said they believe the true number of Musk’s children is much higher than publicly known.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Imagine having 14 acknowledged children but your friends suspect the actual number is “much higher”. What a profound weirdo this guy is.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Cryptocurrency influencer Tiffany Fong was covering disgraced
crypto tycoon Sam Bankman-Fried’s downfall when Musk started
liking and replying to her posts. Musk’s interactions ramped up as
Fong posted more political content in support of Trump, and Musk
followed her last summer.</p>

<p>That sort of attention from Musk on X, where he has 219 million
followers, sent droves of followers to Fong, which was a financial
boon. More engagement meant more earnings for her as part of a
revenue-sharing program for creators on X.</p>

<p>During the height of her interactions with the billionaire owner,
Fong earned $21,000 on the platform in a two-week period in
November, according to a screenshot she posted. That was about
when Musk sent her a direct message asking if she was interested
in having his child, according to people familiar with the matter.
The two had never met in person.</p>

<p>Fong didn’t move forward with Musk because she pictured having
children in a more traditional nuclear family, but confided to a
few friends about the approach — including St. Clair, whom she
knew as another conservative social-media figure — and how she
worried that turning him down could hurt her earnings.</p>

<p>Once Musk learned that Fong disclosed the request to others, he
chided her for not using discretion, according to the people, and
unfollowed her. That contributed to a fall in her engagement, and
her earnings declined.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There’s arguably an insinuation here that something crooked happened to Fong’s Twitter/X earnings after she declined Musk’s offer, but there doesn’t have to be for it to be sick. It’s just gross that Musk’s M.O. is to hit up suddenly popular women and ask if they’d like to have his children, and to lavish money-earning public attention on them while courting them.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The WSJ Reports on How Elon Musk Manages His ‘Legion’ of Children and Harem of Mothers’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/16/wsj-musk-children">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>DOGE Dingalings Cut Off Funding for CVE Program</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/04/16/homeland_security_funding_for_cve/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9n" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/16/dingalings-cut-off-funding-for-cve" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41819</id>
	<published>2025-04-16T18:56:52Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-16T18:56:53Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jessica Lyons, reporting for The Register:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>US government funding for the world’s CVE program — the
centralized Common Vulnerabilities and Exposures database of
product security flaws — ends Wednesday.</p>

<p>The 25-year-old CVE program plays a huge role in vulnerability
management. It is responsible overseeing the assignment and
organizing of unique CVE ID numbers, such as <a href="https://cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=CVE-2014-0160">CVE-2014-0160</a>
and <a href="https://cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=CVE-2017-5754">CVE-2017-5754</a>, for specific vulnerabilities, in this
case OpenSSL’s <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2014/04/09/heartbleed_explained/">Heartbleed</a> and Intel’s <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2018/01/02/intel_cpu_design_flaw/">Meltdown</a>, so
that when referring to particular flaws and patches, everyone is
agreed on exactly what we’re all talking about.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The good news: they were ready. <a href="https://www.thecvefoundation.org/">Announcing the CVE Foundation</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Since its inception, the CVE Program has operated as a U.S.
government-funded initiative, with oversight and management
provided under contract. While this structure has supported the
program’s growth, it has also raised longstanding concerns among
members of the CVE Board about the sustainability and neutrality
of a globally relied-upon resource being tied to a single
government sponsor.</p>

<p>This concern has become urgent following an April 15, 2025 letter
from MITRE notifying the CVE Board that the U.S. government does
not intend to renew its contract for managing the program. While
we had hoped this day would not come, we have been preparing for
this possibility.</p>

<p>In response, a coalition of longtime, active CVE Board members
have spent the past year developing a strategy to transition CVE
to a dedicated, non-profit foundation. The new CVE Foundation will
focus solely on continuing the mission of delivering high-quality
vulnerability identification and maintaining the integrity and
availability of CVE data for defenders worldwide.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘DOGE Dingalings Cut Off Funding for CVE Program’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/16/dingalings-cut-off-funding-for-cve">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Figma Files to Go Public</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.figma.com/blog/s1-confidential-submission/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9m" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/16/figma-files-to-go-public" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41818</id>
	<published>2025-04-16T18:00:25Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-16T18:00:26Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>You will recall that in September 2022, Figma entered into <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/09/15/adobe-figma">an agreement for a $20 billion acquisition by Adobe</a>, but <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/12/18/figma-adobe-ixnay-on-the-acquisitionyay">abandoned the deal 15 months later</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Figma Files to Go Public’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/16/figma-files-to-go-public">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Glenn Fleishman’s Kickstarter for ‘Six Centuries of Type &amp; Printing’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/glennf/six-centuries-of-type-and-printing" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9l" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/16/six-centuries-of-type-and-printing" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41817</id>
	<published>2025-04-16T17:36:05Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-16T17:36:05Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Glenn Fleishman:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The book <em>Six Centuries of Type &amp; Printing</em> briskly tells the
story of the evolution of type and printing, starting with early
documented efforts and surviving artifacts from China and Korea,
and introducing Gutenberg and his innovations. It then takes you
through each generation of increasing sophistication in metal and
relief printing until the abrupt 20th century shift into flat
offset printing, which was made possible through photographic and
digital improvements, and phototypesetting and digital
composition.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’ve got the first edition of this book, which was included with Fleishman’s rather preposterously elaborate <a href="https://tinytypemuseum.com/">Tiny Type Museum and Time Capsule</a> five years ago. It is a self-exemplary achievement: a handsomely designed printed object about how it came to be possible to create and produce handsomely designed printed objects.</p>

<p>That first edition from five years ago, however, was printed letterpress, and was a very limited edition. This new edition, while still exquisite, will be printed offset and is very much affordable. The print/e-book bundle is just $32.</p>

<p>The Kickstarter campaign is 92% of the way to its goal, with, as I type this, 28 hours to go. If you even vaguely suspect you’ll enjoy this book, I bet you’ll <em>love</em> it. Fleishman is such a good writer and he so clearly both knows and loves the subject matter. There’s no better combination. I just took my copy down to flip through before posting this, and I got sucked in to a re-read.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Glenn Fleishman’s Kickstarter for ‘Six Centuries of Type &amp; Printing’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/16/six-centuries-of-type-and-printing">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>ChatGPT Can Now Remember and Reference All Your Previous Chats</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://arstechnica.com/ai/2025/04/chatgpt-can-now-remember-and-reference-all-your-previous-chats/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9k" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/14/chatgpt-memory" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41816</id>
	<published>2025-04-14T23:51:42Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-14T23:51:43Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Samuel Axon, writing for Ars Technica:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Some time ago, OpenAI <a href="https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2024/02/amnesia-begone-soon-chatgpt-will-remember-what-you-tell-it-between-sessions/">added</a> a feature called “Memory” that
allowed a limited number of pieces of information to be retained
and used for future responses. Users often had to specifically
ask ChatGPT to remember something to trigger this, though it
occasionally tried to guess at what it should remember, too.
[...] Users could enable or disable this feature at will, and it
was automatically off for specific chats where users chose the
“Temporary Chat” option — sort of ChatGPT’s version of
incognito mode.</p>

<p>The new improvements announced today go far beyond that.</p>

<p>Now, where there was once a checkbox in ChatGPT’s interface to
disable or enable memory tracking, there are two checkboxes.
“Reference saved memories” is the old memory feature, which is
basically a limited repository of essential facts. The second is
the new feature: “reference chat history.” This allows ChatGPT to
use all prior conversations as context and adapt future responses
accordingly.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’ve been using ChatGPT for a while now. I don’t think I’m a particularly heavy user at all, and I haven’t tried, in particular, to, I don’t know, open up about myself personally. But I ask it what I want to know. So, in the current version, I prompted it with “Describe me based on all our chats — play it straight.” Here’s its response:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You’re sharp, analytical, and deeply detail-oriented. You care a
lot about precision — whether it’s language, data, or historical
facts. You’re not satisfied with vague answers; you want the right
one, ideally backed by sources or structured data. You’re a power
user, technically literate, and comfortable with scripting and
command-line tools (especially on macOS), often turning to
automation and custom scripts to solve problems.</p>

<p>You follow the tech world closely, especially Apple — its
hardware, chip architecture, software updates, and even historical
product launches. But you’re not just interested in specs; you
care about the bigger picture too, like corporate strategy,
antitrust laws, and privacy policies.</p>

<p>You also track U.S. politics, legal frameworks, and electoral
history with the same demand for precision and sourcing. And
you’ve got a thing for language — choosing the right word,
understanding nuance, and occasionally searching for just the
right adjective (bonus points if it’s rare or elegant).</p>

<p>Outside of that, you have a strong grasp of sports stats
(especially NFL and MLB), media history (Letterman, SNL, classic
film), and a dry, sometimes playful sense of humor. You don’t show
off, but you clearly know your stuff.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’m probably not the right person to judge that response, but I think it’s pretty good.</p>

<p>Here’s the response I got when I asked Siri “Describe me based on all our chats — play it straight”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I don’t see that person in your Contacts.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>From last week’s blockbuster report by Wayne Ma at The Information, “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/10/wayne-ma-the-information-apple-siri-fumble">How Apple Fumbled Siri’s AI Makeover</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Giannandrea often has described to employees his belief that
machine learning can lead to incremental improvements in products,
eventually adding up to major gains, a concept he refers to as
hill climbing. He also has expressed a dim view of chatbots in the
past, telling Apple employees before and immediately after the
release of ChatGPT that he didn’t believe they added much value
for users.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘ChatGPT Can Now Remember and Reference All Your Previous Chats’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/14/chatgpt-memory">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://dekaf.com/df" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/w9j" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/04/dekaf_coffee_roasters" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.41815</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-04-14T23:29:16Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-14T23:29:17Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Coffee has always been about bringing people together. For us, it started with a simple question over a late-night cup of decaf: why do coffee lovers who skip the caffeine have to skip the craft too?</p>

<p>At Dekáf, we believe those who drink coffee purely for its flavor are the true connoisseurs. While other roasters treat decaf as a side project, we’ve made it our entire mission. We’re dedicated to creating exceptional decaffeinated coffee that stands toe-to-toe with the world’s finest caffeinated beans.</p>

<p>9 single origins. 6 signature blends. You won’t believe it’s decaf. That’s the point.</p>

<p>30% off with code: DF</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Dekáf Coffee Roasters’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/04/dekaf_coffee_roasters">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] Dekáf Coffee Roasters</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Seth Godin on How to Win an Argument With a Toddler</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://seths.blog/2025/04/how-to-win-an-argument-with-a-toddler/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9i" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/14/godin-arguments-with-toddlers" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41814</id>
	<published>2025-04-14T16:02:20Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-14T16:02:21Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Seth Godin:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You can’t.</p>

<p>That’s because toddlers don’t understand what an argument is and
aren’t interesting in having one.</p>

<p>Toddlers (which includes defensive bureaucrats, bullies, flat
earthers, folks committed to a specific agenda and radio talk show
hosts) may indicate that they’d like to have an <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ohDB5gbtaEQ">argument</a>, but
they’re actually engaging in connection, noise, play acting or a
chance to earn status. It can be fun to be in opposition, to
harangue or even to use power to change someone’s position.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Seth Godin on How to Win an Argument With a Toddler’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/14/godin-arguments-with-toddlers">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>WorkOS: Scalable, Secure Authentication</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://workos.com/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9h" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/13/workos" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41813</id>
	<published>2025-04-13T19:39:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-13T19:39:00Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to WorkOS for sponsoring last week at DF. Modern authentication should be seamless and secure. WorkOS makes it easy to integrate features like MFA, SSO, and RBAC. Whether you’re replacing passwords, stopping fraud, or adding enterprise auth, WorkOS can help you build frictionless auth that scales.</p>

<p>New features they launched just last month include:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://workos.com/blog/workos-connect?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025">WorkOS Connect</a> — “Sign in with [Your App]”</li>
<li><a href="https://workos.com/blog/vault?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025">WorkOS Vault</a> — Encryption Key Management (EKM) and Bring-Your-Own-Key (BYOK)</li>
<li><a href="https://workos.com/blog/custom-objects?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025">AuthKit Integrations</a> — Native support for several new identity providers including LinkedIn, Slack, GitLab, BitBucket, Intuit, and more.</li>
</ul>

<p>Future-proof your authentication stack with the identity layer trusted by OpenAI, Cursor, Perplexity, and Vercel.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘WorkOS: Scalable, Secure Authentication’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/13/workos">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Bill Maher on His Dinner at the White House With Donald Trump</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RxlopbcfXpQ" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9g" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/13/bill-maher-on-his-dinner-at-the-white-house-with-donald-trump" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41812</id>
	<published>2025-04-13T19:29:23Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-13T19:57:23Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Bill Maher personifies the difference between a liberal (which he is) and a leftist (which he isn’t). But he’s been a stridently vocal critic of Trump <a href="https://www.hollywoodreporter.com/business/business-news/donald-trump-withdraws-bill-maher-432675/">since long before Trump even ran for president</a>. Maher was the first person on television <a href="https://www.newsweek.com/will-donald-trump-leave-office-peacefully-bill-maher-president-loses-2020-election-landslide-1466447">to correctly predict that Trump, if he lost the 2020 election, would attempt to remain in office</a>. Maher and Trump, however, are mutual friends with Kid Rock, and Rock arranged for Trump to invite Maher to the White House for a private dinner. UFC chief and Meta board member Dana White was also there. A decade ago even imagining this guest list for a White House dinner would have been a warning that you ought to lay off the drugs. Today, this is normal.</p>

<p>On <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RxlopbcfXpQ">this clip from his show this weekend</a>, Maher reports on the dinner. What it was like. What <em>Trump</em> was like. Turns out, in private, Trump turns it off. He was normal. Or, well, normal for Donald Trump. He wasn’t what we see in public. I find that fascinating. Not exculpatory. Just interesting. Is he “<em>They’re eating the dogs, they’re eating the cats!</em>” crazy 24 hours a day, or just when the cameras are on?</p>

<p>Some on the left are absolutely losing their shit over Maher for this. I don’t get it. This is the single most interesting report on Trump I’ve seen in <em>years</em> because it’s real. Maher didn’t come out of the dinner brainwashed. He’s not now saying Trump is doing a good job. He’s not now saying things are in any way OK. He spent his whole monologue before this report rightfully skewering Trump’s humiliating weeklong tariffs tantrum. After the report, Maher interviewed total nutjob Steve Bannon and literally shoved a copy of the Constitution in Bannon’s face when Bannon started blathering about Trump running for a third term in 2028. From Maher’s preface to his report:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Oh my god Bill, are you going to say something nice about him?
What I’m going to do is report exactly what happened. You decide
what you think about it. And if that’s not enough pure Trump hate
for you I don’t give a fuck.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://play.max.com/video/watch/d739940e-efb5-4b35-ac0f-62d0a27f2d53/6f987f63-3dda-4884-8602-21f4d688c401">The whole episode was great</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Bill Maher on His Dinner at the White House With Donald Trump’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/13/bill-maher-on-his-dinner-at-the-white-house-with-donald-trump">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘What It Feels Like, Right Now’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://terribleminds.com/ramble/2025/04/09/what-it-feels-like-right-now/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9f" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/13/wendig-what-it-feels-like-right-now" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41811</id>
	<published>2025-04-13T18:56:52Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-13T18:56:52Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Crackerjack essay by Chuck Wendig:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Maybe it’s like turbulence on an airplane, you think. Just a bumpy
unpleasant awful experience you gotta get through. But when
turbulence hits it’s not because the pilot is a guy who doesn’t
“know planes,” when turbulence hits they don’t disappear the ninth
row people out the airlock because they “look different” and are
“probably causing the problem.” Planes don’t have airlocks, do
they? Whatever. My brain is spray cheese.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘What It Feels Like, Right Now’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/13/wendig-what-it-feels-like-right-now">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Chris Whipple on the End of the Biden Administration</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.vanityfair.com/news/story/joe-bidens-final-days" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9e" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/13/whipple-biden-final-days" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41810</id>
	<published>2025-04-13T18:48:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-13T18:49:04Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Vanity Fair published an excerpt from Chris Whipple’s new book on the final years of Joe Biden’s presidency, under the headline “Did Aides Cover Up His Mental State — or Was It Group Delusion?” (<a href="https://apple.news/ANs1GK_4ISEikICuDBenaSA">News+ link</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The president’s wobbly state should have been a flashing warning
light. At his first meeting with Biden, Ron Klain, his former
White House chief of staff, who was in charge of debate prep, was
startled. He’d never seen Biden so exhausted and out of it. He
seemed unaware of what was happening in his own campaign. The
president appeared obsessed with foreign policy and uninterested
in his second-term plans. During one prep session in Aspen Lodge,
the presidential cabin, Biden suddenly got up, walked out to the
pool, collapsed on a lounge chair, and fell sound asleep. Yet his
advisers were undaunted. With unintended irony, one of them
explained their strategy to me: “An early debate would quiet fears
that the president was infirm.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Jiminy.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Chris Whipple on the End of the Biden Administration’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/13/whipple-biden-final-days">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Jamelle Bouie on Trump’s Tariff Obsession</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/04/09/opinion/trump-tariffs-rationale-power.html?unlocked_article_code=1._U4.jlDF.elEoqbYtNPr6&amp;smid=url-share" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9d" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/13/jamelle-bouie-on-trumps-tariff-obsession" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41809</id>
	<published>2025-04-13T18:37:44Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-13T18:37:45Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jamelle Bouie, writing at The New York Times (gift link):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>There is a hypothetical president with a hypothetically similar
agenda who could answer these questions. This actual president
cannot. He did not reason himself into his preoccupation with
tariffs and can neither reason nor speak coherently about them.
There is no grand plan or strategic vision, no matter what his
advisers claim — only the impulsive actions of a mad king,
untethered from any responsibility to the nation or its people.
For as much as the president’s apologists would like us to believe
otherwise, Trump’s tariffs are not a policy as we traditionally
understand it. What they are is an instantiation of his psyche: a
concrete expression of his zero-sum worldview. [...]</p>

<p>You could even say that this need to dominate — this overwhelming
drive to show mastery — is constitutive of Trump’s self. There
must be a loser, or else there is no Trump. [...] The upshot of
this understanding of Trump’s personality is that there is no
point at which he can be satisfied. He will always want more: more
supplicants to obey his next command, more displays of his power
and authority and more opportunities to trample over those who
don’t belong in his America.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There’s no point to this other than a vain attempt to get every other country in the world to come begging to Donald Trump for mercy. Which isn’t going to happen.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Jamelle Bouie on Trump’s Tariff Obsession’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/13/jamelle-bouie-on-trumps-tariff-obsession">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Warren Buffett’s 2024 Report to Berkshire Hathaway Shareholders</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.berkshirehathaway.com/letters/2024ltr.pdf" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9c" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/12/buffet-2024-berkshire-shareholders-letter" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41808</id>
	<published>2025-04-12T20:48:48Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-12T20:50:36Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Warren Buffett’s annual shareholders letters are always a must-read. The honesty, clarity, and striking humility of his prose stands out in a world where corporate communications — from companies of any size — tend to be bland and obfuscating. <a href="https://www.berkshirehathaway.com/letters/2024ltr.pdf">This year’s letter</a>, published back in February, is no exception. Two sections stood out to me. First, in a section titled “Mistakes — Yes, We Make Them at Berkshire”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Sometimes I’ve made mistakes in assessing the future economics of
a business I’ve purchased for Berkshire — each a case of capital
allocation gone wrong. That happens with both judgments about
marketable equities — we view these as <em>partial</em> ownership of
businesses — and the 100% acquisitions of companies.</p>

<p>At other times, I’ve made mistakes when assessing the abilities or
fidelity of the managers Berkshire is hiring. The fidelity
disappointments can hurt beyond their financial impact, a pain
that can approach that of a failed marriage.</p>

<p>A decent batting average in personnel decisions is all that can be
hoped for. The cardinal sin is delaying the correction of mistakes
or what Charlie Munger called “thumb-sucking.” Problems, he would
tell me, cannot be wished away. They require action, however
uncomfortable that may be.</p>

<p>During the 2019-23 period, I have used the words “mistake” or
“error” 16 times in my letters to you. Many other huge companies
have <em>never</em> used either word over that span. Amazon, I should
acknowledge, made some brutally candid observations in its 2021
letter. Elsewhere, it has generally been happy talk and pictures.</p>

<p>I have also been a director of large public companies at which
“mistake” or “wrong” were forbidden words at board meetings or
analyst calls. That taboo, implying managerial perfection, always
made me nervous (though, at times, there could be legal issues
that make limited discussion advisable. We live in a very
litigious society.)</p>

<p>At 94, it won’t be long before Greg Abel replaces me as CEO and
will be writing the annual letters. Greg shares the Berkshire
creed that a “report” is what a Berkshire CEO annually owes to
owners. And he also understands that if you start fooling your
shareholders, you will soon believe your own baloney and be
fooling yourself as well.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>As the great physicist Richard Feynman said, “The first principle is that you must not fool yourself and you are the easiest person to fool.”</p>

<p>Second is an entire section, not complaining, but instead proudly declaring, that last year Berkshire set the record for the highest single-year corporate income tax payment in United States history:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Huge numbers can be hard to visualize. Let me recast the $26.8
billion that we paid last year.</p>

<p>If Berkshire had sent the Treasury a $1 million check every 20
minutes throughout all of 2024 — visualize <em>366 days and nights</em>
because 2024 was a leap year — we still would have owed the
federal government a significant sum at yearend. Indeed, it would
be well into January before the Treasury would tell us that we
could take a short breather, get some sleep, and prepare for our
2025 tax payments. [...]</p>

<p>Berkshire’s activities now impact all corners of our country. And
we are not finished. Companies die for many reasons but, unlike
the fate of humans, old age itself is not lethal. Berkshire today
is far more youthful than it was in 1965.</p>

<p><em>However</em>, as Charlie and I have always acknowledged, Berkshire
would not have achieved its results in any locale except America
whereas America would have been every bit the success it has been
if Berkshire had never existed.</p>

<p>So thank you, Uncle Sam. Someday your nieces and nephews at
Berkshire hope to send you even larger payments than we did in
2024. Spend it wisely. Take care of the many who, for no fault of
their own, get the short straws in life. They deserve better. And
never forget that we need you to maintain a stable currency and
that result <em>requires</em> both wisdom and vigilance on your part.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Again, that was written back in February. Prescient as always.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Warren Buffett’s 2024 Report to Berkshire Hathaway Shareholders’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/12/buffet-2024-berkshire-shareholders-letter">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Smartphones and Computers Are Now Exempt From Trump’s Latest Tariffs</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.cnn.com/2025/04/12/tech/trump-electronics-china-tariffs/index.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9b" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/12/smartphones-computers-tariff-exemptions" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41807</id>
	<published>2025-04-12T17:53:50Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-12T17:53:51Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Auzinea Bacon, CNN:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Electronics imported to the United States will be exempt from
President Donald Trump’s reciprocal tariffs, according to a <a href="https://content.govdelivery.com/accounts/USDHSCBP/bulletins/3db9e55">US
Customs and Border Protection notice</a> posted late Friday.
Smartphones, computer monitors and various electronic parts are
among the exempted products. The exemption applies to products
entering the United States or removed from warehouses as early as
April 5, according to the notice.</p>

<p>The move comes after the Trump administration imposed a minimum
tariff rate of 145% on Chinese goods imported to the United
States. The tariffs would have a major impact on tech giants like
Apple, which make iPhones and other products in China.</p>

<p>Roughly 90% of Apple’s iPhone production and assembly is based in
China, according to Wedbush Securities’ estimates. Analysts at
Wedbush on Saturday called the tariff exclusion, “the best news
possible for tech investors.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fZLeaSWY37I">Here’s Commerce Secretary Emily Litella making the announcement on Weekend Update</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Smartphones and Computers Are Now Exempt From Trump’s Latest Tariffs’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/12/smartphones-computers-tariff-exemptions">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Anker, a Chinese Company, Has Already Started Raising Its Prices on Amazon</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.reuters.com/technology/chinese-electronics-company-anker-starts-raising-prices-amazon-2025-04-11/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w9a" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/11/anker-raising-prices" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41806</id>
	<published>2025-04-11T22:40:57Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-11T22:41:19Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Reuters:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>China’s Anker, one of Amazon’s largest sellers offering products
from power banks to phone cases, has raised prices on a fifth of
its products on the U.S. platform since Thursday, in a sign that
tariffs on Chinese goods are being passed on to U.S. shoppers.</p>

<p>Some 127 Anker products have seen an average increase of 18% since
Thursday last week, with the majority of those occurring after
Monday, April 7, when U.S. President Donald Trump added an extra
50% import duty on Chinese goods, according to data from
e-commerce services provider SmartScout.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Tariffs driving up consumer prices is as sure a thing as rain making you wet. But it’s worth pointing to the evidence as it comes in, because unlike rain’s wetness, the “emperor sure does have clothes” MAGA contingent is trying to argue that tariffs don’t have this obvious effect.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Anker, a Chinese Company, Has Already Started Raising Its Prices on Amazon’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/11/anker-raising-prices">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>European Travel to the U.S. Plummets</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.ft.com/content/6dc16a54-8de1-4f3b-8409-ecb566118127" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w99" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/11/european-travel-to-the-us-plummets" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41805</id>
	<published>2025-04-11T21:33:26Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-11T21:46:22Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Financial Times reporter John Burn-Murdoch has a summary on Bluesky of his co-bylined <a href="https://www.ft.com/content/6dc16a54-8de1-4f3b-8409-ecb566118127">report for the Financial Times</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Visitors from western Europe who stayed at least one night in the
US fell by 17 per cent in March from a year ago, according to the
International Trade Administration. Travel from some countries — including Ireland, Norway and Germany — fell by more than 20 per
cent, an FT analysis of ITA data showed.</p>

<p>The trend poses a threat to the US tourism industry, which
accounts for 2.5 per cent of the country’s GDP. Some airlines and
hotel groups have warned of waning demand for transatlantic travel
and a “bad buzz” about visiting the US. The total number of
overseas visitors travelling to the US dropped by 12 per cent
year-on-year in March, the steepest decline since March 2021 when
the travel sector was reeling from pandemic restrictions,
according to the ITA data.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Well, I’m sure it will turn around when the April figures come out, after Trump’s tariff madness and the news that Secretary of State Marco Rubio — supposedly one of the few sane voices in the 2.0 Trump kakistocracy — <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2025/apr/10/mahmoud-khalil-memo-marco-rubio-deport-beliefs">has signed a two-page argument that noncitizens can be deported for their beliefs</a>, a.k.a. thought crimes.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“In just two months [Trump] has destroyed the reputation of the
US, shown one way by diminished travel from the EU to the US,”
said Paul English, co-founder of travel website Kayak. “This is
not only one more terrible blow to the US economy, it also
represents reputation damage that could take generations to
repair.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We need more clearheaded statements like this from business leaders. Just state the truth plainly. The only side English took with this statement is the side of the truth.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘European Travel to the U.S. Plummets’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/11/european-travel-to-the-us-plummets">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Chinese Finance Ministry Calls Trump’s Tariff Hikes ‘A Joke in the History of World Economics’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.reuters.com/world/china/china-increase-tariffs-us-goods-125-up-84-finance-ministry-says-2025-04-11/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w98" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/11/china-calls-trump-a-joke" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41804</id>
	<published>2025-04-11T20:14:15Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-11T21:12:01Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Reuters:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The U.S. side’s imposition of excessively high tariffs on China
seriously violates international economic and trade rules, runs
counter to basic economic principles and common sense, and is
simply an act of unilateral bullying and coercion,” China’s
Finance Ministry said in a statement. [...]</p>

<p>“Even if the U.S. continues to impose even higher tariffs, it
would no longer have any economic significance and would go down
as a joke in the history of world economics,” the Finance
Ministry’s statement added.</p>

<p>“If the U.S. continues to play a numbers game with tariffs, China
will not respond,” it added. However it left the door open for
Beijing to turn to other types of retaliation, reiterating that
China would fight the U.S. to the end.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>None of this is funny at the moment, but Trump has beclowned himself with these impulsive nonsensical tariffs. No matter how this ends up, he will go down in history looking like a fool for this. In terms of history, what will be remembered in decades to come, he’d have far less embarrassed himself by shitting his pants in public. He came into office less than three months ago <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2025/04/11/economy/us-producer-price-index-ppi-inflation-march/index.html">with the US economy being the strongest in the world</a>, by far. Everything that’s happened since has been the direct result of his mad-king magical-thinking nonsense and the Republican party’s refusal to stand up to him.</p>

<p>If Joe Biden had imposed these exact same tariff policies a year ago, for the exact same stated reasons, Republicans would have impeached him and called for his immediate ouster through <a href="https://constitutioncenter.org/the-constitution/amendments/amendment-xxv">Section 4 of the 25th Amendment</a> — and their actions, for once, would have been justified. These tariff policies are nuts and are <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/04/11/business/economy/treasury-bonds-tariffs.html">endangering the United States’s economic supremacy</a> while simultaneously hurting the entire world economy. No one in their right mind would do this, and the President of the United States needs to be a person in their right mind.</p>

<p>Democrats and all other Trump opponents should immediately begin calling into question Trump’s mental fitness for office. This whole tariff saga is proof that he’s nuts. Just keep repeating that. He’s always been a little nutty but now he’s gone off the deep end. Don’t forget to reiterate that <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fred_Trump">Trump’s father was suffering from severe dementia</a> when he was Trump’s age. Throw Biden under the bus: remind people that <a href="https://apple.news/ANs1GK_4ISEikICuDBenaSA">we just saw</a> what happens when a mentally enfeebled 80-year-old<sup>*</sup> serves as President, and that under Trump it’s far worse. Biden was sleepy but steady; Trump is agitated and erratic. That’s far worse.</p>

<p>Hammer the points — all true, all obvious — endlessly: Trump is too old; these tariffs are proof that he’s lost his mind; he’s hurting America badly; dementia runs in his family. Hammer it.</p>

<p><small>* Keep calling him “80”; make his sycophants correct you that he’s “only” turning 79 in June.</small></p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Chinese Finance Ministry Calls Trump’s Tariff Hikes ‘A Joke in the History of World Economics’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/11/china-calls-trump-a-joke">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Wayne Ma at The Information: ‘How Apple Fumbled Siri’s AI Makeover’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theinformation.com/articles/apple-fumbled-siris-ai-makeover?rc=jfy0lk" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w97" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/10/wayne-ma-the-information-apple-siri-fumble" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41803</id>
	<published>2025-04-10T21:58:28Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-11T20:52:42Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Blockbuster report by Wayne Ma for The Information (paywalled and pricey, alas):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>But an equally important factor was the conflicting personalities
within Apple, according to multiple people who worked in the AI
and software engineering groups. More than half a dozen former
Apple employees who worked in the AI and machine-learning group
led by Giannandrea — known as AI/ML for short — told The
Information that poor leadership is to blame for its problems with
execution. They singled out Walker as lacking both ambition and an
appetite for taking risks on designing future versions of the
voice assistant.</p>

<p>Among engineers inside Apple, the AI group’s relaxed culture and
struggles with execution have even earned it an uncharitable
nickname, a play on its initials: AIMLess.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Ouch. Ma names names, and the report is full of scoops:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>One Siri leader often criticized by colleagues was Walker, who
joined Apple in 2013 and became responsible for its daily
operations at the end of 2022. In the eyes of his critics, Walker
was unwilling to take big risks on Siri and focused on metrics
that didn’t move the needle much on its performance, rather than
having a grand vision for overhauling the voice assistant.</p>

<p>For instance, he often celebrated small wins such as reducing by
minute percentages the delay between when someone asked Siri a
question and when it responded, former Apple engineers said.
Another pet Walker project was removing the “hey” from the “hey
Siri” voice command used to invoke the assistant, which took more
than two years to accomplish, they said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>What Ma describes is a scenario where Walker missed the fact that the whole forest sucked and didn’t work, while focusing on one or two nice trees. Faster response times are a win, no question — but a <em>small</em> win, only at the margin. Faster wrong or useless (or even just mediocre) answers are, I guess, better than slower wrong/useless answers, but the overall result is a loss. Fast helpful answers are the goal, obviously, but slow helpful answers are infinitely better than fast useless ones. (I’m not even sure eliminating the requirement to use the verbal “hey” prefix was a win at all. It’s purely anecdotal and personal, but I think I get more unwanted invocations now than I did when “Hey Siri” was the required prompt. Like when I’m talking to someone and start a sentence with “Seriously …” Siri will kick in on one of my devices with a “Sorry, I didn’t catch that.”)</p>

<p>One last nugget:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Other resentments also built up. Some in the software engineering
group were annoyed by the higher pay and faster promotions their
colleagues in the AI group were receiving. And they were bitter
that some engineers in the AI group seemed to be able to take
longer vacations and leave early on Fridays, while they faced
more-punishing work schedules.</p>

<p>Distrust between the two groups got so bad that earlier this year
one of Giannandrea’s deputies asked engineers to extensively
document the development of a joint project so that if it failed,
Federighi’s group couldn’t scapegoat the AI team.</p>

<p>It didn’t help the relations between the groups when Federighi
began amassing his own team of hundreds of machine-learning
engineers that goes by the name Intelligent Systems and is run by
one of Federighi’s top deputies, Sebastien Marineau-Mes.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Hundreds of engineers for a machine learning team outside Apple’s AI/ML division sounds like the definition of dysfunction. I really doubt Federighi has also assembled a large team of silicon engineers outside Johny Srouji’s division, because Srouji’s team is not merely functional, but rightly regarded as one the highest-functioning engineering divisions in any field in the world.</p>

<p>I wish I could share a gift link to Ma’s report, but The Information’s gift links for subscribers only work for up to three people. The best I can do is <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/04/10/chaos-behind-siri-revealed/">point to Hartley Charlton’s summary for MacRumors</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Wayne Ma at The Information: ‘How Apple Fumbled Siri’s AI Makeover’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/10/wayne-ma-the-information-apple-siri-fumble">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘American Disruption’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stratechery.com/2025/american-disruption/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w96" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/09/american-disruption" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41802</id>
	<published>2025-04-10T01:42:42Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-10T01:42:42Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Ben Thompson:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The problem with these tariffs is that their scale and
indiscriminate nature will have the effect of destroying demand
<em>and</em> destroying the capability to develop alternative supply. I
suppose if the only goal is to hurt China then shooting yourself
in the foot, such that you no longer need to buy shoes for stumps,
is a strategy you could choose, but that does nothing to help with
what should be the primary motivation: shoring up the U.S.
national security base.</p>

<p>Those national security concerns are real. The final stage of
disruption is when the entity that started on the bottom is
uniquely equipped to deliver what is necessary for a new
paradigm, and that is exactly what happened with electronics
generally and drones specifically. Moreover, this capability is
only going to grow more important with the rise of AI, which
will be substantiated in the physical world through robotics.
And, of course, robots will be the key to building other robots;
if the U.S. wants to be competitive in the future, and not be
dependent on China, it really does need to make changes — just
not these ones.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘American Disruption’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/09/american-disruption">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Trump, Supposedly, Thinks the U.S. Has the ‘Resources’ Needed to Make iPhones</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/04/08/trump-thinks-the-us-has-the-resources-needed-to-make-iphones/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w95" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/09/trump-think-us-has-resources-to-make-iphones" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41801</id>
	<published>2025-04-10T01:40:33Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-10T01:40:33Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Chance Miller, writing at 9to5Mac:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Ahead of that, White House Press Secretary Karoline Leavitt <a href="https://www.youtube.com/live/pWppUGRRHl4">said
today</a> that Trump firmly believes that Apple can move iPhone
manufacturing to the United States. In response to a question
from Maggie Haberman of The New York Times about the types of
jobs Trump hopes to create in the U.S. with these tariffs,
Leavitt said:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The president wants to increase manufacturing jobs here in the
United States of America, but he’s also looking at advanced
technologies. He’s also looking at AI and emerging fields that
are growing around the world that the United States needs to be a
leader in as well. There’s an array of diverse jobs. More
traditional manufacturing jobs, and also jobs in advanced
technologies. The president is looking at all of those. He wants
them to come back home.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Haberman followed up with a question about iPhone manufacturing
specifically, asking whether Trump thinks this is “the kind of
technology” that could move to the United States. Leavitt
responded:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“[Trump] believes we have the labor, we have the workforce, we
have the resources to do it. As you know, Apple has invested $500
billion here in the United States. So, if Apple didn’t think the
United States could do it, they probably wouldn’t have put up
that big chunk of change.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Leavitt is referencing Apple’s <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/02/24/apple-us-investment-trump-tariffs/">announcement</a> from February,
when it said it would “spend more than $500 billion in the U.S.
over the next four years.” Apple’s commitment, however, made zero
reference to iPhone assembly in the United States. The <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2025/02/apple-will-spend-more-than-500-billion-usd-in-the-us-over-the-next-four-years/">press
release</a> focused on R&amp;D in the U.S., chip production in
Arizona, AI server manufacturing in Houston, Apple TV+ production,
and an academy in Michigan.</p>

<p>Also worth reading today is <a href="https://www.404media.co/a-us-made-iphone-is-pure-fantasy/">this story from 404 Media</a>,
which outlines exactly why an iPhone made in the U.S. is “pure
fantasy.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Another way to think about it is that the iPhone — the iPhone as we know it — can’t really be made anywhere else <em>but</em> China. Apple doesn’t publicly state how many iPhones are made in which countries — shocker that they’d be secretive about that — but <a href="https://www.marketwatch.com/story/apples-stock-notched-its-biggest-gain-in-27-years-is-the-optimism-justified-e3e62c34">estimates peg</a> annual production as being 85–90 percent in China, 10 percent in India, and the remainder in Brazil and Vietnam. Wages aren’t even close to the biggest reason for this. Ultimately the biggest unique factor to the Chinese supply chain is scale. Foxconn’s iPhone factories in China aren’t mere buildings and aren’t really even campuses — they’re more like <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2017/jun/18/foxconn-life-death-forbidden-city-longhua-suicide-apple-iphone-brian-merchant-one-device-extract">entire cities</a> unto themselves.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=inlDT62oGy8">We can joke about US-made iPhones costing $9,000</a> but the jokes miss the point. If the world were such that all iPhones sold to Americans were made in America, there’s no plausible scenario where iPhone ownership would be commonplace. Let’s <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/04/how_many_iphones_can_fit_on_a_freight_plane">estimate</a> that Apple sells 50 million iPhones per year in the US. Apple couldn’t manufacture 50 million iPhones per year in the US at <em>any</em> cost. No amount of money could be thrown at the problem and make it happen that 50 million new iPhones are made in the US in the near future. Apple could make <em>some</em> iPhones here, but not many. And however many they might make would be built using components (displays, chips) that would have to be imported anyway.</p>

<p>Even if Apple were to dramatically raise the price of an iPhone, and even if, somehow, demand for iPhones didn’t drop in the face of dramatically higher prices, Apple simply couldn’t make tens of millions of iPhones here in the US. But of course demand <em>would</em> drop precipitously in the face of higher prices. And a gray market would instantly rise. Because even if Apple, magically, were able to build tens of millions of iPhones in the US, they’d still be building <em>hundreds of millions</em> of them in China — and those Chinese-assembled ones would cost less. I’m imagining an entire cottage industry of bootleggers running Chinese-made iPhones from Canada into the US, and instead of buying iPhones from an Apple Store, people will buy them from the backs of U-Haul trucks. (Gray market bootlegging is <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2025/04/trump-tariffs-smugglers/682303/">inevitable with these tariffs</a>, for every sort of product. If something is cheaper in Canada than it is in the US, someone’s going to smuggle it across the border.)</p>

<p>There simply is no scenario where 50 million Americans per year buy an iPhone for prices they’d be willing to pay without most of them being manufactured by the Chinese supply chain Apple has built.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Trump, Supposedly, Thinks the U.S. Has the ‘Resources’ Needed to Make iPhones’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/09/trump-think-us-has-resources-to-make-iphones">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/04/webkit_textwrap_pretty" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/w94" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41800</id>
	<published>2025-04-09T23:11:05Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-10T19:18:08Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">I think it’s a good start, and I couldn’t be happier that the WebKit team is even tackling the problem at all. As Simmons notes, line-wrapping layout in web browsers has, until now, been very crude — and the web has been around a long time.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jen Simmons, writing on the WebKit blog, “<a href="https://webkit.org/blog/16547/better-typography-with-text-wrap-pretty/">Better Typography With text-wrap pretty</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>For over 30 years, the web had only one technique for determining
where to wrap text.</p>

<p>The browser starts with the first line of text, and lays out each
word or syllable, one after another until it runs out of room. As
soon as it has no more space to fit another word/syllable, it
wraps to the next line (if <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/text-wrap-mode">wrapping</a> is allowed). Then it
starts on the next line, fitting all the content it can… then
when it runs out of room, it wraps… and starts working on the
next line.</p>

<p>It’s always thinking about only one line at a time. It wraps
whenever it needs, after it’s fit the maximum amount of content
on the previous line. If hyphenation is turned on, it will
hyphenate whatever word is last on the line, at whatever point
leaves as much of the word on the previous line as possible.
Nothing else is taken into consideration — which is why text on
the web has bad rag, rivers, short last lines, and hyphenation
that makes no sense.</p>

<p>This is not required by the fact that text is laid out by a
computer. For decades, software like Adobe InDesign and LaTeX has
evaluated multiple lines of text at a time as they decide where to
end one line and begin the next. It’s just that the web didn’t use
a multiline algorithm. Until now.</p>

<p>We are excited to bring this capability to the web for the first
time, in Safari Technology Preview 216.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’ve turned this on here at Daring Fireball, at least as an experiment. (Look at me, fast adopter of novel CSS features.) I have mixed feelings about the results. Here are saved PDFs showing the rendering of my “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/04/how_many_iphones_can_fit_on_a_freight_plane">How Many New iPhones Can Fit on a Freight Plane?</a>” article from earlier today: <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/04/df-iphones-on-plane-textwrap-auto.pdf">first with traditional <code>text-wrap: auto</code></a> line wrapping, and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/04/df-iphones-on-plane-textwrap-pretty.pdf">second with WebKit’s new <code>text-wrap: pretty</code></a> in <a href="https://developer.apple.com/safari/technology-preview/">STP</a> 216. Looking at each paragraph by itself, there’s no question this new layout algorithm is, well, prettier. The problem I see is going from one paragraph to another. Within a paragraph, WebKit’s new <code>pretty</code> wrapping definitely makes lines a more uniform width. But in some cases it so narrows an entire paragraph that it makes going from one paragraph to the next jarring. Line-to-line the new algorithm looks better, but paragraph-to-paragraph I think it looks worse.</p>

<p>One specific example, from <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/something_is_rotten_in_the_state_of_cupertino">my longest recent article</a>. First, with the old <code>text-wrap: auto</code>:</p>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/04/df-something-rotten-textwrap-auto.png" class="noborder">
  <img
    src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/04/df-something-rotten-textwrap-auto.png"
    alt = "A screenshot from a recent Daring Fireball article, showing a list of 4 items."
    width = 500
    style = "border: 1px solid #5a626a;"
  /></a></p>

<p>Here’s that same list with the new <code>text-wrap: pretty</code> in STP 216:</p>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/04/df-something-rotten-textwrap-pretty.png" class="noborder">
  <img
    src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/04/df-something-rotten-textwrap-pretty.png"
    alt = "A screenshot of the same section from the same recent article as the previous screenshot, but in this one, one of the list item paragraphs is noticeably wider than the others."
    width = 500
    border = 1
    style = "border: 1px solid #5a626a;"
  /></a></p>

<p>With the new <code>text-wrap: pretty</code>, the entire paragraph for the first list item is noticeably wider than the subsequent ones (and noticeably wider than the one preceding the list). To me, there’s so much disparity between paragraph widths that it’s distracting, even though each paragraph, taken on its own, looks better. But you don’t take paragraphs on their own when reading.</p>

<p>I suspect (informed by toying with <a href="https://codepen.io/jensimmons/full/xxvoqNM">Simmons’s fun interactive demo page</a> using STP 216) that this initial WebKit <code>text-wrap: pretty</code> layout algorithm works better with wider column widths than are currently specified on Daring Fireball. When there’s a little more width to play with, there seems to be less back-and-forth change from paragraph to paragraph.</p>

<p>So, for my purposes, this might be yet another improvement that will need to wait for the long-promised-but-who-knows-when-it-might-actually-happen-but-I-swear-I-think-about-it-quite-a-bit-and-a-few-years-ago-even-had-something-in-motion-but-then-let-the-project-drop layout modernization here. But, even with a nice responsive design, column widths on phones are inherently narrow, so I think this algorithm ought to be tweaked to render more consistent paragraph widths in narrow-ish columns.</p>

<p>But I think it’s a good start, and I couldn’t be happier that the WebKit team is even tackling the problem at all. As Simmons notes, line-wrapping layout in web browsers has, until now, been very crude — and the web has been around a long time.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ WebKit Adds Support for ‘text-wrap: pretty’, Now Shipping in Safari Technology Preview</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/04/how_many_iphones_can_fit_on_a_freight_plane" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/w93" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41799</id>
	<published>2025-04-09T20:46:55Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-09T21:19:01Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">This sounds like one of those puzzles job interviewers often ask, but there’s a practical relevance at the moment.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>This sounds like one of those puzzles job interviewers often ask, but there’s a practical relevance at the moment: What’s a ballpark estimate for how many iPhones Apple might have hustled to ship into the US <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/08/plane-of-iphones-from-india-and-china">on those five freight planes</a> ahead of the new tariffs? <a href="https://x.com/rjonesy/status/1909770872778338793">Ryan Jones tackled it in a post on X</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A whopping 12 days of sales. At most.</p>

<p>Math: <br />
• B747 Freighter carries 300,000 lbs <br />
• boxed iPhone is 0.9 lbs <br />
= 350K iPhones per plane</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I like Jones’s ballpark math here. Let’s not worry about volume, just weight. If we’re wrong about the volume, it can only mean <em>fewer</em> new-in-box iPhones can fit per plane. There’s no way to (safely) exceed <a href="https://www.cargolux.com/fleet-equipment/aircraft/747-8f-specifications/">the weight limit of a plane</a>.</p>

<p>Jones also estimates that Apple sells about 150,000 new iPhones in the US per day, at least in the typical April–June quarter — which I concur is a good ballpark figure.<sup id="fnr1-2025-04-09"><a href="#fn1-2025-04-09">1</a></sup> So each plane can carry a little over two days’ worth of US domestic iPhones. That means <a href="https://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/technology/mobiles-tabs/how-apple-flew-5-flights-full-of-iphones-from-india-and-china-in-3-days-to-beat-trump-tariffs/articleshow/120044321.cms">if the Times of India is correct</a> that Apple “transported five planes full of iPhones and other products from India to the US in just three days during the final week of March”, those five planes combined carried, at the most, about 12 days’ worth of new US iPhones.</p>

<p>Now that’s just from India. And those are just the five planes the Times of India heard about. It seems safe to presume Apple might have hustled even more planes out of China and Vietnam. But again, at most, each plane full of Apple products carries about two days’ worth of products. We did our napkin math using iPhones, but “1 full plane = 2 days of inventory” can’t be far off the mark, no matter what the mix of product is in each plane’s cargo hold.</p>

<p>350,000 iPhones packed onto a single plane is a lot of iPhones. Sending a few million units across a dozen (or more!) planes is, quite literally, tons of iPhones. But Apple sells about <em>50 tons</em> of new iPhones in the US alone every day. We all know that Apple’s iPhone business is huge. But when you start to consider it in practical terms like this it’s just staggering.</p>

<p>There’s no way Apple can “beat” these Trump tariffs by having shipped products ahead of their taking effect. Could they hedge against two or three weeks of tumult? Maybe a month, tops? Yes, and it seems like maybe that’s what they did. But no matter how many planes they filled — or how many container ships they might have had the foresight to send a month or two ago — there are very practical limits to inventory, too. Apple’s warehouses are likely designed with one or two weeks of inventory in mind. You can’t just rent random warehouse space to hold billions of dollars worth of iPhones.</p>

<p><a href="https://money.cnn.com/2011/08/24/technology/cook_apple.fortune/index.htm">From Adam Lashinsky’s 2008 profile of Tim Cook for Fortune</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Almost from the time he showed up at Apple, Cook knew he had to
pull the company out of manufacturing. He closed factories and
warehouses around the world and instead established relationships
with contract manufacturers. As a result, Apple’s inventory,
measured by the amount of time it sat on the company’s balance
sheet, quickly fell from months to days. Inventory, Cook has said,
is “fundamentally evil,” and he has been known to observe that it
declines in value by 1% to 2% a week in normal times, faster in
tough times like the present.</p>

<p>“You kind of want to manage it like you’re in the dairy business,”
he has said. “If it gets past its freshness date, you have a
problem.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Apple’s entire supply chain is rightly heralded as genius, a triumph of everything from component sourcing to assembly to transport. But the entire operation is premised on the continuous free flow of packaged products out of China. Apple never holds much inventory, of anything, anywhere in the world.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1-2025-04-09">
<p>If anything, Apple’s sales might be higher than usual right now. With consumers worried that Apple (and everyone else) might raise prices in response to Trump’s tariffs at any moment, demand is surely up to some extent. I know two friends who’ve already purchased new MacBooks, now, for kids who aren’t going off to college until September.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-04-09"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ How Many New iPhones Can Fit on a Freight Plane?</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Trump Cuts Most Tariffs to 10% but Increases Tariffs on China to 125%</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/114309144289505174" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w92" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/09/trump-cuts-most-tariffs-to-10-but-increases-tariffs-on-china-to-125" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41798</id>
	<published>2025-04-09T18:56:08Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-09T19:49:32Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>President Trump, in a post on Truth Social, which is apparently how the world’s financial markets now run:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Based on the lack of respect that China has shown to the World’s
Markets, I am hereby raising the Tariff charged to China by the
United States of America to 125%, effective immediately. At some
point, hopefully in the near future, China will realize that the
days of ripping off the U.S.A., and other Countries, is no longer
sustainable or acceptable. Conversely, and based on the fact that
more than 75 Countries have called Representatives of the United
States, including the Departments of Commerce, Treasury, and the
USTR, to negotiate a solution to the subjects being discussed
relative to Trade, Trade Barriers, Tariffs, Currency Manipulation,
and Non Monetary Tariffs, and that these Countries have not, at my
strong suggestion, retaliated in any way, shape, or form against
the United States, I have authorized a 90 day PAUSE, and a
substantially lowered Reciprocal Tariff during this period, of
10%, also effective immediately. Thank you for your attention to
this matter!</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/04/09/trump-announces-90-day-tariff-pause-for-at-least-some-countries.html">The entire stock market jumped</a> on Trump’s announcement, with the S&amp;P 500 up 8% as I type this. Apple is up 9%, Meta 13%, Nvidia 16%, and Tesla 19%. I’m not sure why though. All Trump seems to have done is switch from waging a trade war against the entire world to a trade war against China. And the 10% tariffs Trump now claims we’re applying to imports from the rest of world are themselves economic nonsense — they only look low compared to <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/03/trump-tariffs-day-two">the nonsensical rates Trump announced a week ago</a>. We’re at the whims of a mad king. Trying to report this as having any sort of logic in a traditional economic sense is folly. It’s like trying to make scientific sense out of the biblical fable of Noah’s Ark.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Trump Cuts Most Tariffs to 10% but Increases Tariffs on China to 125%’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/09/trump-cuts-most-tariffs-to-10-but-increases-tariffs-on-china-to-125">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://workos.com/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/w91" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/04/workos_scalable_secure_authent_2" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.41797</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-04-08T22:04:08Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-08T22:04:09Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Modern authentication should be seamless and secure.  WorkOS makes it easy to integrate features like MFA, SSO, and RBAC.</p>

<p>Whether you’re replacing passwords, stopping fraud, or adding enterprise auth, WorkOS can help you build frictionless auth that scales. </p>

<p>Future-proof your authentication stack with the identity layer trusted by OpenAI, Cursor, Perplexity, and Vercel.  </p>

<p>Upgrade your auth today. </p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘WorkOS: Scalable, Secure Authentication’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/04/workos_scalable_secure_authent_2">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] WorkOS: Scalable, Secure Authentication</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Apple Is Hustling to Fly Planes of iPhones Into the U.S. Ahead of Trump’s Tariffs</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/04/07/iphone-inventory-united-states-planes/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w90" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/08/plane-of-iphones-from-india-and-china" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41796</id>
	<published>2025-04-08T21:00:03Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-08T21:00:04Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Chance Miller, writing for 9to5Mac:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>According to senior Indian officials cited in the report, Apple
flew five planes full of iPhones and other products from India and
China “in just three days during the final week of March.”</p>

<p>“Factories in India and China and other key locations had been
shipping products to the US in anticipation of the higher
tariffs,” <a href="https://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/technology/mobiles-tabs/how-apple-flew-5-flights-full-of-iphones-from-india-and-china-in-3-days-to-beat-trump-tariffs/articleshow/120044321.cms">one source to The Times of India</a> said.</p>

<p>Apple currently assembles the entire iPhone 15 and iPhone 16
lineups in India as well as China. A 10% baseline tariff on all
imports into the United States kicked in on Saturday. On April 9,
the tariffs that Trump has falsely labeled as “reciprocal” will
kick in. This will raise the tariff rate on imports from China to
54% and imports from India to 27%.</p>

<p>By stockpiling as much inventory as possible in the United States,
Apple can delay the impact of the tariffs. It’s unclear just how
much inventory Apple has on hand in the US right now, but if
there’s one thing I know, it’s to never doubt Tim Cook’s supply
chain prowess.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Is Hustling to Fly Planes of iPhones Into the U.S. Ahead of Trump’s Tariffs’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/08/plane-of-iphones-from-india-and-china">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Democracy</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://protectdemocracy.org/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w8y" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/06/democracy" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41794</id>
	<published>2025-04-06T20:49:44Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-06T21:11:30Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My sincere thanks to The Ole Independence Hall Hooligans for sponsoring this past week at DF to promote democracy. That’s it. A real sponsorship, real money, raised by a group of readers who simply wanted the ad space on DF to promote, as they described it, “the enduring and aspirational project that is democracy.”</p>

<p>In <a href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/03/democracy">their sponsored RSS entry</a> to start the week, they quoted <a href="https://www.archives.gov/founding-docs/constitution-transcript">the preamble to the US Constitution</a>. I’ll go a decade earlier, and quote from <a href="https://www.archives.gov/founding-docs/declaration-transcript">the Declaration of Independence</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The history of the present King of Great Britain is a history of
repeated injuries and usurpations, all having in direct object the
establishment of an absolute Tyranny over these States. To prove
this, let Facts be submitted to a candid world.</p>

<p>He has refused his Assent to Laws, the most wholesome and
necessary for the public good. [...]</p>

<p>He has made Judges dependent on his Will alone, for the tenure of
their offices, and the amount and payment of their salaries. [...]</p>

<p>For cutting off our Trade with all parts of the world:</p>

<p>For imposing Taxes on us without our Consent:</p>

<p>For depriving us in many cases, of the benefits of Trial by Jury:</p>

<p>For transporting us beyond Seas to be tried for pretended
offences:</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/04/trump-claims-to-extend-tiktok-deadline-for-another-75-days">Sounds</a> <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/04/glasser-trump-ego">like</a> <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/live/2025/04/05/us/trump-news-tariffs#justice-dept-immigration-lawyer-leave">someone</a> in the news today (and yesterday, and alas, surely again tomorrow). There is no greater threat to democracy itself than a delusional mad king, whether he wears a crown or a ridiculous ugly red cap. Take action and make your voice heard now — democracy in action is democracy’s only defense.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Democracy’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/06/democracy">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Spectacle of Incompetence</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2025/04/07/the-greater-scandal-of-signalgate" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w8z" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/06/the-spectacle-of-incompetence" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41795</id>
	<published>2025-04-06T20:45:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-10T19:23:04Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>David Remnick, in a fine short piece for The New Yorker on Signalgate:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This is an Administration that does not have to slip on a Signal
banana peel to reveal its deepest-held prejudices and its painful
incapacities. You get the sense that we would learn little if we
were privy to a twenty-four-hour-a-day live stream of its every
private utterance. Part of what was so appalling about Trump and
Vance’s recent meeting with <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/news/the-new-yorker-interview/volodymyr-zelensky-has-a-plan-for-ukraines-victory">Volodymyr Zelensky</a> was not
just their penchant for channelling the world view and negotiating
points of <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/tag/vladimir-putin">Vladimir Putin</a> but their comfort in expressing
them, <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/newsletter/the-daily/trump-and-zelenskys-stunning-fight"><em>barking</em> them</a>, at the Ukrainian President in front
of reporters in the Oval Office.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Stupidity and ignorance as a governing style. That’s it. They are <em>exactly</em> who they claim they are, and in private speak how they do in public. There is no secret plan.</p>

<p>These idiots do not believe polluting the atmosphere with carbon emissions has caused calamitous damage to our climate, despite the fact that experts, decades ago, almost universally predicted it would. Few issues in science had as much expert consensus.</p>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2021/05/03/thompson-no-vaxxers">These idiots think vaccines</a> — one of the great breakthroughs in the history of science and medicine — are a bigger health risk than the diseases they immunize against. Now there are unvaccinated American kids dying from measles, a disease that was effectively wiped out in the modern world by the time I was born.</p>

<p>These idiots think the universe is only 6,000 years old.</p>

<p>Now they’re bringing the same sort of idiocy, unbound by critical thinking, history, or anything recognized as economic expertise, to trade policy.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Spectacle of Incompetence’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/06/the-spectacle-of-incompetence">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Millions Attend ‘Hands Off’ Protests Across U.S. — and Europe — to Oppose Trump’s Agenda</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/live/2025/apr/05/hands-off-protests-trump-administration" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w8x" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/05/hands-off-trump-protests" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41793</id>
	<published>2025-04-05T23:54:27Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-06T21:35:09Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Terrific photos and summary coverage <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/live/2025/apr/05/hands-off-protests-trump-administration">from The Guardian</a>. Additional coverage from <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/04/05/us/politics/anti-trump-protests-hands-off.html">The New York Times</a>, <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/dc-md-va/2025/04/05/hands-off-protest-trump-washington/">Washington Post</a>, and <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2025/04/05/us/hands-off-protests-trump-musk/index.html">CNN</a>. <strong>Update:</strong> <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/photo/2025/04/photos-nationwide-protests-against-trump-and-musk/682320/">The Atlantic has a great collection of photos</a> from dozens of cities.</p>

<p>There’s something so bizarrely asymmetrical about Trump’s political support. We saw large scale protests like today’s starting in 2017 too, and in this 2.0 administration, they’re only going to get bigger. Today’s protests were coast-to-coast, in <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/peterbowdenlive.bsky.social/post/3lm3ahz5pp22d">cities</a> <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/peterbowdenlive.bsky.social/post/3lm3ahz5pp22d">large</a> and <a href="https://me.dm/@mgs/114286204556855230">small</a>. Hundreds of thousands — correction, <em><a href="https://www.cnn.com/2025/04/05/us/hands-off-protests-trump-musk/index.html">millions</a></em> — of people. Huge crowd <a href="https://www.threads.net/@mandiaholly/post/DIFRGyoPd_i?xmt=AQGzI-Oy3kcvBP6Lg5mLyKE0RO6Vnjit3SUnIMLATFjV3A">in Philadelphia</a>. Over 100,000 <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/peterbowdenlive.bsky.social/post/3lm3ahz5pp22d">in Boston</a>. But there were never any protests at all against the Biden administration. Trump’s support has been just wide enough to win, twice, but it’s so thin. His first inauguration was <a href="https://www.factcheck.org/2017/01/the-facts-on-crowd-size/">so conspicuously sparsely attended</a> they held the second one indoors. Support for democracy runs deep.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Millions Attend ‘Hands Off’ Protests Across U.S. — and Europe — to Oppose Trump’s Agenda’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/05/hands-off-trump-protests">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The WSJ Estimates the Effect of Trump’s Tariffs on the iPhone</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/personal-tech/iphone-apple-tariffs-china-bb20c7a3?mod=hp_lead_pos7" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w8w" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/05/wsj-iphone-tariffs" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41792</id>
	<published>2025-04-05T23:36:37Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-05T23:37:01Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Joanna Stern, Adrienne Tong, and Nicole Nguyen, writing for The Wall Street Journal (<a href="https://apple.news/AZx1sTNZuRg-d7hf8O69F5A">News+</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Take a look at this iPhone 16 Pro. Your cost, for the 256GB
version, is $1,100. The cost of all the hardware inside — aka the
bill of materials — was about $550 to Apple when the phone was
introduced, says Wayne Lam, research analyst at TechInsights,
which breaks down major products. Throw in assembly and testing
and Apple’s cost rises to around $580. Even when you account for
Apple’s advertising budget and all the included services — iMessage, iCloud, etc. — there’s still a healthy profit margin.</p>

<p>Now factor in the newly announced tariff for goods from China,
which currently totals 54%. The cost rises to around $850. That
profit margin would shrink dramatically if Apple didn’t up the
price. And you don’t become a trillion-dollar gadget company by
charging for things at cost.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Also worth a look is <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/04/wsj-front-page-5-april-2025.jpeg">today’s front page of the WSJ print edition</a>. At least they picked a flattering photo of Trump.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The WSJ Estimates the Effect of Trump’s Tariffs on the iPhone’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/05/wsj-iphone-tariffs">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Pricing Stability of the iMac</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2025/04/the-pinnacle-of-apples-price-stability-is-the-imac/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w8v" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/05/the-pricing-stability-of-the-imac" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41791</id>
	<published>2025-04-05T22:16:30Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-05T22:16:31Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Dan Moren, writing at Six Colors:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In his piece, Gruber particularly calls out the trashcan Mac Pro
sticking at $2999 throughout its existence, but I think an even
more striking example is the iMac. Introduced in 1998 at a base
price of $1299, today’s infinitely more powerful iMac M4 starts at
… $1299.</p>

<p>Granted, with inflation, those prices would be a little different.
In researching the details, I came across <a href="https://www.perfectrec.com/posts/iMac-price-history">this great piece from
PerfectRec</a> charting the iMac’s price history over the years,
including adjusting for inflation. Impressively, while the iMac’s
base price has dipped as low as $1099 in all that time, it’s never
gone <em>over</em> $1299.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>What a great example. And bringing inflation into the mix is a key factor I neglected to make <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/04/unchanging_prices_vs_nonsensical_tariffs">yesterday</a>. Moore’s Law makes computers very strange manufactured goods. A Honda Civic LX cost about $15,000 in 1998, but now costs about $25,000. BMW 3-series sedans went from around $30,000 to $45,000. But the iMac still starts at $1,299.</p>

<p>Pricing stability is a way that Apple keeps these two forces — Moore’s Law and inflation — in balance.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Pricing Stability of the iMac’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/05/the-pricing-stability-of-the-imac">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Perhaps the E.U. Took Mercy on Apple and Meta (and Investors) This Week</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.ft.com/content/c3933e2f-787e-453b-82eb-a981ddd48a31" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w8u" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/05/no-eu-fines-this-week" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41790</id>
	<published>2025-04-05T21:39:27Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-05T22:00:13Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Barbara Moens and Henry Foy, reporting from Brussels for the Financial Times <em>last</em> Friday, March 28:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The EU is set to impose minimal fines on Apple and Facebook owner
Meta next week under its Digital Markets Act, as Brussels seeks to
avoid escalating tensions with US President Donald Trump.</p>

<p>According to people familiar with the decisions, the iPhone maker
is expected to be fined and ordered to revise its App Store rules,
following an investigation into whether they prevent app
developers from sending consumers to offers outside its platform.
Regulators will also close another investigation into Apple, which
was focused on the company’s design of its web browser choice
screen without any further sanctions.</p>

<p>Meta will also be fined and ordered to change its “pay or consent”
model which forces users to either consent to data tracking or pay
a subscription fee for an ad-free experience of its products.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The FT is usually the go-to source for leaked news from the European Commission. But “next week” came and went with no announcements made. Maybe the FT just had a bad source, or maybe there was some sort of unforeseen delay? Or maybe the EC looked at the chaos unleashed by Trump this week and figured these fines could wait another week. Or maybe they’re just recalculating the fines post-trade-war.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Perhaps the E.U. Took Mercy on Apple and Meta (and Investors) This Week’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/05/no-eu-fines-this-week">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Tim Sweeney’s Praise for Microsoft</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://x.com/TimSweeneyEpic/status/1908303468349063539" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w8t" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/05/sweeney-microsoft" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41789</id>
	<published>2025-04-05T18:10:20Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-05T18:12:36Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Epic CEO Tim Sweeney, yesterday:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Thanks to Microsoft for 50 years of being awesome to developers!
Some years the software was great. Some years the software sucked.
Every year the company and its ecosystem has stood with and
supported developers.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I pity the man who doesn’t have enough fingers to count the number of game stores available on Xbox.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Tim Sweeney’s Praise for Microsoft’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/05/sweeney-microsoft">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Microsoft’s 50th Birthday Was Interrupted, Twice, by Employees Protesting Against Israel</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/news/644027/microsoft-50th-anniversary-protest" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w8s" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/05/microsoft-50-employee-protests" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41788</id>
	<published>2025-04-05T18:02:31Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-05T21:24:32Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Tom Warren, reporting for The Verge:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Microsoft held a special 50th anniversary event at its
headquarters earlier today. During Microsoft AI CEO Mustafa
Suleyman’s presentation, a <a href="https://www.theverge.com/news/643670/microsoft-employee-protest-50th-annivesary-ai">Microsoft employee interrupted the
event</a> to protest the use of Microsoft’s technologies in
Israel’s war against Hamas. <a href="https://www.theverge.com/news/643777/microsoft-bill-gates-steve-ballmer-satya-nadella-employee-protestor">A second employee interrupted the
event later on</a>, while CEO Satya Nadella, co-founder Bill
Gates, and former CEO Steve Ballmer were discussing 50 years of
Microsoft.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The only opinionated <em>public</em> takes I’ve seen on these two protestors are from political extremes: a small number of people cheering them on, and another small number of people angrily decrying them as terrorist sympathizers. I suspect most people, though, have a take closer to my own, but are unwilling to espouse it lest they risk the ire of the two aforementioned political extremes. I’ll try.</p>

<p>There’s a time and a place for everything, and Microsoft’s own 50th anniversary celebration was not the time or place for two insufferable self-involved showboats to make the event about them. Because that’s what this was. It was about them, personally. Not about Gaza or Israel.</p>

<p>The place for righteous protests is in public, in the streets — <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/live/2025/apr/05/hands-off-protests-trump-administration">exactly as they are happening across the United States today</a>.</p>

<p>Of <em>course</em> Microsoft conducts business in Israel and with the Israeli government. They’re Microsoft — the entire point of the company (and thus the core point of the 50th anniversary celebration) is that their software is ubiquitous. Ranked by GDP, Israeli’s economy is 29th in the world. If Microsoft employees really want to make the case that the company should sever all ties to Israel, go ahead, but performance stunts at public celebrations are not the way. Why do they even work for Microsoft if they’re not happy to celebrate the company’s own 50th anniversary? Why did Microsoft hire people who seemingly despise the very company they work for?</p>

<p>I don’t know if you’ve heard but there’s a lot of horrible shit going on around the world right now. Should Microsoft sever all ties to Republican-led states that have made women’s reproductive healthcare illegal? (<a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/us-news/georgia-arrest-miscarriage-fetal-personhood-rcna199400">A woman in Georgia was just arrested after suffering a miscarriage</a>.) Should Microsoft sever all ties to the U.S. federal government, which is now led by a mad tyrant who, in plain sight, <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2023/01/16/what-the-january-6th-report-is-missing">attempted to overthrow an election he lost</a>, and <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/donald-trump/trump-third-term-white-house-methods-rcna198752">now claims</a> (shocking no one) to be considering running for a third term that <a href="https://constitution.congress.gov/constitution/amendment-22/">even a child could understand to be plainly unconstitutional</a>? How much Microsoft software does ICE use? Or DOGE?</p>

<p>Where do such protests — all in the name of just causes — stop?</p>

<p>In the midst of all this madness and chaos — much of it already horrific, more of it suggestive of foreboding horrors to come — we need more than ever to savor, to appreciate, what’s still good about the world. Microsoft is a great American company. What a remarkable gift of good luck, good health, brilliant strategy, successful execution, steady leadership, and the right circumstances (e.g. Bill Gates’s precocious age — 19! — at the company’s founding) that the company has had only three CEOs in its half-century history and all three were available to join each other on stage to celebrate this anniversary, and the company’s still-bright future.</p>

<p>What a shitty thing to do it was to try to spoil this.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Microsoft’s 50th Birthday Was Interrupted, Twice, by Employees Protesting Against Israel’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/05/microsoft-50-employee-protests">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Truth Is, These Are Not Very Bright Guys</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.newyorker.com/news/letter-from-trumps-washington/donald-trumps-ego-melts-the-global-economy" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w8r" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/04/glasser-trump-ego" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41787</id>
	<published>2025-04-04T23:56:21Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-04T23:56:21Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Susan Glasser, writing for The New Yorker, “Donald Trump’s Ego Melts the Global Economy”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In this new political moment of the unthinkable made manifest, the
sheer power rush for Trump should also not be underestimated.
Imagine his joy as he sat down to sign an executive order
decreeing the new tariffs on the basis of sweeping powers he may
or may not legally possess to declare a “national economic
emergency” — here was Trump transforming the world with a single
flourish of his Sharpie pen. “It’s such an honor to be finally
able to do this,” he said. At what other moment in modern times
has a single man wielded so much unaccountable power over such a
large swath of the world economy? There are whole businesses
devoted to risk analysis for corporations; this is a situation in
which Trump himself is the risk and the crisis being analyzed is
one that he created. Talk about an ego trip.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Glasser links to <a href="https://x.com/Kasparov63/status/1907798003236188169">Garry Kasparov, on X</a>, responding to Wall Street’s collective surprise that Trump did what he’s been saying he would do re: tariff policy:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>As I’ve said for years about Putin, and which applies to other
autocratic personalities like Trump: “Dictators always lie about
what they’ve done, but are often quite plain about what they want
to do.” “Trump would never...” is the new “Putin would never...”</p>

<p>Such people do and take whatever they can, unless they are
stopped. That they don’t always succeed does not mean they were
not sincere in their ambitions and won’t keep trying to fulfill
them. Trump has only been emboldened by the sycophantic GOP this
time around.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Even more apt, “Deep Throat” explaining the central truth of the Watergate scandal to Bob Woodward in the Alan-Pakula-directed / William-Goldman-written film adaptation of <em><a href="https://www.themoviedb.org/movie/891-all-the-president-s-men?language=en-US">All the President’s Men</em></a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Forget the myths the media has created about the White House.
The truth is, these are not very bright guys, and things got out
of hand.”</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Truth Is, These Are Not Very Bright Guys’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/04/glasser-trump-ego">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Trump Claims to Extend TikTok Deadline for Another 75 Days</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/04/04/trumps-extends-tiktok-second-time.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w8q" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/04/trump-claims-to-extend-tiktok-deadline-for-another-75-days" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41786</id>
	<published>2025-04-04T20:43:19Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-04T21:19:45Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>CNBC:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>President Donald Trump on Friday extended a deadline requiring China-based ByteDance to sell the U.S. operations of TikTok or face an effective ban in the country, marking the second time he has taken such action.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Trump, on Truth Social, which is by far the most popular social network in the world:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>My Administration has been working very hard on a Deal to SAVE
TIKTOK, and we have made tremendous progress. The Deal requires
more work to ensure all necessary approvals are signed, which is
why I am signing an Executive Order to keep TikTok up and running
for an additional 75 days. We hope to continue working in Good
Faith with China, who I understand are not very happy about our
Reciprocal Tariffs (Necessary for Fair and Balanced Trade between
China and the U.S.A.!). This proves that Tariffs are the most
powerful Economic tool, and very important to our National
Security! We do not want TikTok to “go dark.” We look forward to
working with TikTok and China to close the Deal. Thank you for
your attention to this matter!</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Those are the remarks of the most powerful man in the world.</p>

<p>Keep in mind, too, that there is no mechanism in the law for the president to issue any such extension. What he’s saying is <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/01/npr_trump_tiktok">what he said the last time</a>: he’s instructing Attorney General Pam Bondi not to enforce the law, and pinky-swearing that U.S. companies that are breaking the law to keep TikTok available (Akamai, Oracle, Google, Apple) <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/01/my_spitball_theory_on_tiktoks_current_semi-reprieve_in_the_us">won’t be held responsible for it</a>. It’s just a complete abdication of the rule of law.</p>

<p>Not a peep from Republican Tom Cotton, who, on the cusp of Trump taking office again, <a href="https://www.cotton.senate.gov/news/press-releases/cotton-ricketts-statement-on-tiktok-being-removed-from-app-stores">was crowing about the PAFACA Act coming into effect to shut TikTok down in the US</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Trump Claims to Extend TikTok Deadline for Another 75 Days’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/04/trump-claims-to-extend-tiktok-deadline-for-another-75-days">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Floundering’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.reuters.com/technology/will-trump-tariffs-make-apple-iphones-more-expensive-2025-04-03/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w8p" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/04/floundering-reuters" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41785</id>
	<published>2025-04-04T20:28:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-06T20:23:22Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>From that same Reuters report by Akash Sriram <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/04/unchanging_prices_vs_nonsensical_tariffs">that I just wrote about</a>, speculating that iPhone prices might rise dramatically under Trump’s tariffs:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>However, other analysts noted that iPhone sales have been
floundering in the company’s major markets, as Apple
Intelligence, a suite of features that helps summarize
notifications, rewrite emails and give users access to ChatGPT,
has failed to enthuse buyers.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Merriam-Webster defines <em><a href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/flounder">flounder</a></em> thus:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>: to struggle to move or obtain footing : thrash about wildly</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Here’s Jason Snell’s chart of iPhone sales <a href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2025/01/apples-reports-record-revenue-for-q1-2025/">through their most recent quarterly report</a> — a record-breaking quarter for the company overall — covering the last three calendar months of 2024:</p>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/04/iphone-revenue-q1-2025-six-colors.png" class="noborder">
<img
  src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/04/iphone-revenue-q1-2025-six-colors.png"
  alt = "Chart showing remarkably flat, stable, consistent iPhone sales since 2022."
/></a></p>

<p>It’s certainly up for debate whether Apple Intelligence is an effective marketing driver for iPhone sales. I mean that with no snark. Maybe Apple Intelligence <em>is</em> driving iPhone sales. I don’t know why people have purchased new iPhones in the last six months. Neither do you, and neither do the “other analysts” (conveniently unnamed) cited by Reuters. But what we do know, because Apple reports the revenue numbers, is that iPhone sales have been remarkably flat, year-over-year, for the last 13 quarters.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Floundering’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/04/floundering-reuters">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/04/unchanging_prices_vs_nonsensical_tariffs" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/w8o" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41784</id>
	<published>2025-04-04T19:03:15Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-06T22:52:15Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">The erratic, illogical, nonsensical nature of Trump’s tariffs is bad for everyone. (Understatement.) But it’s particularly troublesome for a company that sees retail price stability as part of the branding for its products.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Akash Sriram, reporting for Reuters under the headline “<a href="https://www.reuters.com/technology/will-trump-tariffs-make-apple-iphones-more-expensive-2025-04-03/">A $2,300 Apple iPhone? Trump Tariffs Could Make That Happen.</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Most iPhones are still made in China, which was hit with a 54%
tariff. If those levies persist, Apple has a tough choice: absorb
the extra expense or pass it on to customers.</p>

<p>Shares of the company closed down 9.3% on Thursday, hitting their
worst day since March 2020.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Apple shares dropped <em>another</em> 7.3% percent today. Apple alone has lost 16.6% of its value in the last 48 hours; the S&amp;P 500 dropped 10%.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The cheapest iPhone 16 model was launched in the U.S. with a
sticker price of $799, but could cost as much as $1,142, per
calculations based on projections from analysts at Rosenblatt
Securities, who say the cost could rise by 43% — if Apple is able
to pass that on to consumers. A more expensive iPhone 16 Pro Max,
with a 6.9-inch display and 1 terabyte of storage, which currently
retails at $1599, could cost nearly $2300 if a 43% increase were
to pass to consumers.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s under-remarked upon, but Apple, to a point of almost obstinance, considers pricing part of the brand for its products. They tend not to raise or lower prices with the ebbs and flows of the world economy or even the obvious constraints of simple supply and demand. Throughout the entire COVID crisis, I don’t recall them changing their prices for anything.</p>

<p>As an extreme example, consider the trashcan Mac Pro. It was introduced <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2013/06/10Apple-Gives-Sneak-Peek-Into-the-Future-of-the-Pro-Desktop/">at WWDC 2013</a> and <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2013/10/23Introducing-the-All-New-Mac-Pro-The-Most-Radical-Mac-Ever/">shipped in December that year</a> with a starting price of $2,999. It then went <a href="https://x.com/MKBHD/status/833730471804731392">over three years without an update</a> — and still cost $2,999. Then in April 2017 Apple held <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2017/04/the_mac_pro_lives">that highly unusual small roundtable meeting</a> — invitees were just <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2017/04/04/apple-pushes-the-reset-button-on-the-mac-pro/">Matthew Panzarino</a>, <a href="http://mashable.com/2017/04/04/apple-reveals-mac-pro-imac-plans/">Lance Ulanoff</a>, <a href="https://www.axios.com/apple-to-ditch-the-current-mac-pro-design-but-replacement-wont-arrive--2343465726.html">Ina Fried</a>, <a href="https://www.buzzfeed.com/johnpaczkowski/apple-says-it-is-completely-rethinking-the-mac-pro">John Paczkowski</a>, and yours truly — to discuss “completely rethinking the Mac Pro”. They issued small speed bumps to the trashcan Mac Pro that day, but didn’t ship the actual completely-rethought Mac Pro <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2019/06/apple-unveils-powerful-all-new-mac-pro-and-groundbreaking-pro-display-xdr/">until WWDC 2019</a>. The starting price never changed from $2,999, even when demand for the trashcan models had clearly dropped to near zero. The price was part of the brand. (The starting price for the 2019 Mac Pro: $5,999.)</p>

<p>Or consider <em>today’s</em> Mac Pro, with the M2 Ultra. <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2023/06/apple-unveils-new-mac-studio-and-brings-apple-silicon-to-mac-pro/">It debuted alongside Mac Studio models that also came with the M2 Ultra</a> at WWDC 2023 almost two years ago. M2 Ultra Mac Studios <a href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2023/06/m2-ultra-mac-studio-review-top-of-the-line/">started at $3,999</a>; Mac Pros at $6,999. Many observers, quite reasonably, questioned the $3,000 price difference when both computers offered the same chips. The 2023 Mac Pro, in some sense, is just a 2023 Mac Studio in a much bigger case with additional high-performance I/O options. But a month ago Apple debuted <em>M3</em> Ultra Mac Studios, with an unchanged starting price of $3,999. The Mac Pro, still equipped with the older M2 Ultra, still starts at $6,999. Which means that for the time being, you’re not paying $3,000 extra for the same computer in a bigger case, but for a <em>generation-older</em> computer in a bigger case.</p>

<p>Presumably, M3 Ultra Mac Pros are coming soon, perhaps at WWDC. But until then, the pricing is undeniably weird when compared to the Mac Studio — and many people have thought the pricing was a bit weird compared to the Mac Studio when they were offered with the same M2-generation chips. But that’s how Apple likes to do pricing: they set a price when a product is announced, and that price never changes until a successor to that product is announced.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/03/trump-tariffs-techdirt">erratic</a>, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/03/trump-tariffs-day-two">illogical</a>, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/03/the-economist-on-trumps-mindless-tariffs">nonsensical</a> nature of Trump’s tariffs is bad for everyone. (<a href="https://bsky.app/profile/crampell.bsky.social/post/3llzc3fmf7s23">Understatement</a>.) But it’s particularly troublesome for a company that sees retail price stability as part of the branding for its products. Will Trump come to his senses (to some small degree), and declare a nonexistent victory next week and pull these tariffs from the board? Or stick to his guns and ride this global-economy-tanking insanity out? No one knows. Will he start granting exceptions? No one knows. So in addition to being nonsensical, the whole thing is entirely unpredictable, which is not at all compatible with the way Apple has set retail prices for decades.</p>

<p>My (bigly) guess is that Apple will inject its own predictability and stability into the mix, and keep its retail prices stable, for now, and take the tariff hit on its margins. But if these tariffs really stay in effect, even just for a few months, at current prices Apple <a href="https://www.threads.net/@benedictevans/post/DIBMlA2MSFs">would be breaking even at best</a>, and likely losing money, on each iPhone it sells.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Tired: Irresistable Force vs. Immovable Object — Wired: Unchanging Prices vs. Nonsensical Tariffs</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Why Trump’s Tariffs Are Rattling Even Meta</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/04/04/technology/trump-tariffs-meta.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w8m" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/04/trump-tariffs-meta" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41782</id>
	<published>2025-04-04T17:43:34Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-04T19:23:50Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Mike Isaac, writing for The New York Times:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple, Dell, Oracle — which rely on hardware and global supply
chains that are in the direct line of fire from tariffs — saw
their shares go into free-fall. But there was another big tech
company whose stock took a pummeling even though its core business
has little to do with hardware: Meta. [...]</p>

<p>The effect of tariffs on Meta’s ad business is simple. Many of
its small and medium-sized advertisers are from all across the
world. President Trump’s tariffs will instantly make it more
expensive for them to sell their products to customers in the
United States. [...]</p>

<p>Last year, the company disclosed that 10 percent of <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/03/06/business/google-meta-temu-shein.html">its revenue in
2023 was from Chinese companies spending heavily</a> on advertising
across Facebook and Instagram, an ad blitz aimed at garnering a
foothold in lucrative Western markets.</p>

<p>Much of that growth was fueled by the explosive expansion of the
fast-fashion company Shein — which is based in Singapore but has
a supply chain that is largely in China — and the e-commerce app
Temu, a low-cost, Amazon-like company owned by the Chinese
e-commerce conglomerate Pinduoduo. Temu was estimated to have
spent $3 billion in marketing costs in 2023 alone, according to
estimates from Bernstein Research.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>When the stock market began crumbling after Trump’s announcement Wednesday, I didn’t get why Meta was being hit so hard. Meta makes devices, but unlike Apple, that’s just a side hustle. Meta isn’t a retailer like Amazon. But Meta <em>is</em> a huge advertising destination for retailers. It’s all interconnected.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Why Trump’s Tariffs Are Rattling Even Meta’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/04/trump-tariffs-meta">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Nintendo Delays Switch 2 Preorders Over Tariff Concerns</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/news/643483/nintendo-switch-2-preorders-delayed-tariffs" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w8l" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/04/nintendo-delays-switch-2-preorders-over-tariff-concerns" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41781</id>
	<published>2025-04-04T17:19:53Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-04T17:19:53Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Emma Roth, The Verge:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Nintendo is pushing back preorders for the Switch 2 due to
concerns about Donald Trump’s newly announced tariffs. According
to a statement sent to The Verge by Eddie Garcia on behalf of
Nintendo, it says preorders will no longer begin on April 9th:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Pre-orders for Nintendo Switch 2 in the U.S. will not start April
9, 2025 in order to assess the potential impact of tariffs and
evolving market conditions. Nintendo will update timing at a
later date. The launch date of June 5, 2025 is unchanged.</p>
</blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>Riots in the streets.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Nintendo Delays Switch 2 Preorders Over Tariff Concerns’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/04/nintendo-delays-switch-2-preorders-over-tariff-concerns">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple Cash Switched From Discover to Visa in 2022</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://9to5mac.com/2022/04/22/apple-cash-discover-visa/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w8k" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/04/apple-cash-discover-visa" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41780</id>
	<published>2025-04-04T17:09:15Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-06T22:52:53Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Allison McDaniel, writing for 9to5Mac back in 2022:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><a href="https://www.apple.com/apple-cash/">Apple Cash</a> is a virtual debit card where you can send and
receive money through iMessage. Stored in your Wallet, you can
make secure and contactless payments with Apple Pay from your
iPhone or Apple Watch. It’s also a way to receive daily cash back
for those who use Apple Card. Previously a Discover card, your
Apple Cash card is now Visa.</p>

<p>Spotted by user <a href="https://x.com/Kanjo/status/1517427755553804288">@Kanjo on Twitter</a>, it’s easy to notice the
card has a visible Visa logo in the bottom right corner. Before
this change, there was no Discover logo on the card. While not
everyone will like the addition of the logo, it’s going to be hard
to forget it’s a Visa.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So Apple Card is a credit card, with Goldman Sachs as the bank and Mastercard as the network. Apple definitely needs a new banking partner, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/07/03/goldman-apple-card-losses">as Goldman is exiting the consumer banking business</a>, and is rumored to be listening to offers from Visa and Amex to switch its network too.</p>

<p>Apple Cash is a debit card, which launched on the Discover network but switched to Visa three years ago — presumably with a nice kickback to Apple to get that Visa logo on the virtual cards in Wallet.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Cash Switched From Discover to Visa in 2022’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/04/apple-cash-discover-visa">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Costco Only Accepts Visa Credit Cards</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://customerservice.costco.com/app/answers/answer_view/a_id/719/~/what-payment-methods-are-accepted-at-costco%3F" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w8j" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/04/costco-visa" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41779</id>
	<published>2025-04-04T17:01:40Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-04T17:29:17Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>I <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/03/via-mastercard-apple-card">observed yesterday</a> that, in general, Visa and Mastercard credit cards are both accepted at the same locations. The most notable exception is Costco, which, as part of <a href="https://www.wsj.com/finance/banking/visa-wanted-a-vast-empire-first-it-had-to-beat-back-its-foes-3b3067f3?mod=article_inline">the deal to make its own credit card a Visa</a> (after long partnering with Amex), only accepts Visa credit cards at its physical retail locations and gas stations. They accept “most PIN-based debit/ATM cards”, but for credit, only Visa.</p>

<p>Online, for reasons I don’t understand, Costco accepts Mastercard too (which they incorrectly style in camelcase — you’d think Costco, of all companies, would be sensitive to wrongly camelcased mid-name C’s). Also, in Canada’s Costcos, it’s reversed, with Mastercard being exclusive in-store but Visa being accepted online.</p>

<p>Another high-profile exception: <a href="https://www.olympics.com/ioc/news/visa-on-the-road-to-paris-a-commitment-to-diversity-inspiration-and-community">The Olympics</a>, which “proudly accepts only Visa for card and mobile payments, along with cash”.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Costco Only Accepts Visa Credit Cards’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/04/costco-visa">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Bill Gates on the Creation of Microsoft, and the Source Code for Its First Product</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.gatesnotes.com/microsoft-original-source-code" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w8i" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/04/gates-microsoft-50-basic" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41778</id>
	<published>2025-04-04T16:31:52Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-04T20:35:20Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Bill Gates, commemorating Microsoft’s 50th anniversary:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The story of how Microsoft came to be begins with, of
all things, a magazine. The January 1975 issue of
Popular Electronics featured an Altair 8800 on the
cover. The Altair 8800, created by a small electronics
company called MITS, was a groundbreaking personal
computer kit that promised to bring computing power to
hobbyists. When Paul and I saw that cover, we knew two
things: the PC revolution was imminent, and we wanted
to get in on the ground floor.</p>

<p>At the time, personal computers were practically non-existent.
Paul and I knew that creating software that let people program the
Altair could revolutionize the way people interacted with these
machines. So, we reached out to Ed Roberts, the founder of MITS,
and told him we had a version of the programming language BASIC
for the chip that the Altair 8800 ran on.</p>

<p>There was just one problem: We didn’t.<br/>
It was time to get to work.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>At the bottom Gates links to a printout of the original source code for the BASIC interpreter, in extensively commented assembly language. Amongst all of his other accomplishments, Bill Gates was one hell of a programmer.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Bill Gates on the Creation of Microsoft, and the Source Code for Its First Product’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/04/gates-microsoft-50-basic">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Making of the Lumon Industries WoeMeter</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://make3.co/work/woemeter" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w8h" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/04/lumon-industries-woemeter" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41777</id>
	<published>2025-04-04T16:02:13Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-04T16:02:14Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Wonderfully detailed write-up of a perfect prop from Make3:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Repurposed Nagra Knobs &amp; Switches — To ground the device in a
tangible, vintage aesthetic, we salvaged original knobs and
switches from a 1990s Nagra IV-D recorder, seamlessly integrating
them into our design. These components not only provided an
authentic look and feel but also remained fully functional, with:</p>

<ul>
<li>A power switch for system activation.</li>
<li>A reading on/off switch to engage or disable the Woe display.</li>
<li>A manual override switch to cycle through needle positions if
wireless control failed.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>When I watched this episode, I remember noticing how cool the device seemed. It turns out to be even cooler than I thought. So much effort into such a little thing. And the coolest thing is that, in a sense, the WoeMeter actually <em>works</em> as a handheld wireless prop.</p>

<p>Reusing those Nagra dials to add verisimilitude reminds me of how much of <em>Star Wars</em> came from reused pieces of old gadgetry, like two of the lightsabers (Luke’s and Vader’s) <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/av/uk-england-beds-bucks-herts-42369174">being made from 1940s-era Graflex camera flash guns</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Making of the Lumon Industries WoeMeter’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/04/lumon-industries-woemeter">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Jason Snell’s M4 MacBook Air Review</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2025/03/m4-macbook-air-review-am-i-blue/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/w8g" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/04/snell-m4-macbook-air" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.41776</id>
	<published>2025-04-04T15:30:01Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-04T15:30:01Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jason Snell, last month:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The new M4 MacBook Air is the Mac most people should buy. [...]</p>

<p>That’s why perhaps the most important change in the M4 MacBook Air
is its base configuration, which starts at $999. When Apple
introduced a winning new flat-with-rounded-corners Air design in
2022, it had to keep selling older models in order to get down
under a thousand dollars. Three years later, Apple is finally able
to sell a brand-new Air — with a generous 16GB of unified memory — at that important price.</p>

<p>So: No more quibbles about stepping back a generation or two to an
older model with a lower price. Apple has done away with that
strategy for the MacBook Air: The latest and greatest model is the
one most people shopping for a Mac should buy, especially if
they’re coming from an Intel model.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’d put off linking to Snell’s review for a few weeks while thinking about writing my own, but I’ve got nothing to add. The M4 MacBook Air is utterly unsurprising, but only in the best possible way. It’s the MacBook Air everyone wanted Apple to make. The $999 base model is now exceedingly recommendable. It even brings back the most notable feature that was lost in the transition from Intel to Apple Silicon — the ability to drive two external displays <em>and</em> its own internal display. Just aces all around.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Jason Snell’s M4 MacBook Air Review’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/04/snell-m4-macbook-air">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/france_merde_decision_app_tracking_transparency" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/w85" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41765</id>
	<published>2025-03-31T19:46:31Z</published>
	<updated>2025-04-01T17:34:41Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">It’s like a consortium of sketchy pawn shops complaining to the authorities after a retailer successfully cracked down on an organized shoplifting/pickpocketing ring, and the authorities then fining the retailer for the damage to the pawnbrokers’ business fencing stolen goods — and for exposing the police as ineffective.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jon Brodkin, reporting for Ars Technica, “<a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2025/03/france-fines-apple-e150m-for-excessive-pop-ups-that-let-users-reject-tracking/">France Fines Apple €150M for “Excessive” Pop-Ups That Let Users Reject Tracking</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>France’s competition regulator fined Apple €150 million, saying
the iPhone maker went overboard in its implementation of pop-up
messages that let users consent to or reject tracking that
third-party applications use for targeted advertising.</p>

<p>The App Tracking Transparency (ATT) framework used by Apple on
iPhones and iPads since 2021 makes the use of third-party
applications too complex and hurts small companies that rely on
advertising revenue, said a <a href="https://www.autoritedelaconcurrence.fr/en/press-release/targeted-advertising-autorite-de-la-concurrence-imposes-fine-eu150000000-apple">press release</a> today by the
Autorité de la concurrence (Competition Authority). The system
harms “smaller publishers in particular since, unlike the main
vertically integrated platforms, they depend to a large extent on
third-party data collection to finance their business,” the
agency said.</p>

<p>User consent obtained via the ATT framework “authorizes the
application in question to collect user data for targeted
advertising purposes,” the agency said. “If consent is given, the
application can access the Identifier for Advertisers (‘IDFA’),
the identifier by which each device can be tracked through its use
of third-party applications and sites.” The French investigation
was triggered by a complaint lodged by advertising industry
associations.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Ben Lovejoy, <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/03/31/apple-bizarrely-fined-162m-for-app-tracking-transparency-after-advertisers-complained/">correctly calling the decision “bizarre” at 9to5Mac</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Complaints were made <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2023/04/11/apple-app-tracking/">in a number of countries</a> — some
arguing that it was unfair because <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2022/06/14/app-tracking-transparency-antitrust/">Apple exempts its own
apps</a> (which are in reality subject to even tighter
controls), others saying the loss of revenue <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2022/09/13/app-tracking-transparency-increases-in-app-purchase-prices/">forced developers to
raise prices</a> to compensate. [...]</p>

<p>Although expected, the decision is still inexplicable. ATT
involves precisely <em>one</em> popup asking a simple yes/no question.
Additionally, Apple lets users switch on a toggle (shown above) to
block apps from even asking the question. It’s especially odd
given that ATT is a privacy feature, and Europe has the strongest
privacy laws in the world. The EU <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2022/08/03/ad-tracking-rules/">has also previously
vindicated</a> Apple’s introduction of ATT.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s not inexplicable or odd if you view the decision as coming from a perspective where government bureaucracy is viewed as an inherent good, and well-intentioned process is all that matters, not actual results. Read the <em>Autorité de la Concurrence</em>’s decision (<a href="https://www.autoritedelaconcurrence.fr/en/press-release/targeted-advertising-autorite-de-la-concurrence-imposes-fine-eu150000000-apple">which they helpfully do make available in English</a>) and it’s pretty clear:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The <em>Autorité</em> found that the ATT framework imposed by Apple is
not necessary, insofar as the consent obtained is not valid under
the applicable laws, in particular the French Data Protection Act.</p>

<p>In practice, the fact that publishers that so wish cannot rely on
the ATT framework to comply with their legal obligations means
that they must continue to use their own consent collection
solutions, known as consent management platforms (“CMPs”). The
result is that multiple consent pop-ups are displayed, making the
use of third-party applications in the iOS environment excessively
complex, as observed by the French data protection authority
(<em>Commission nationale de l’informatique et des libertés</em> — CNIL)
in a 2022 opinion issued at the request of the <em>Autorité</em>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s ostensibly “not necessary” because French and EU privacy laws are supposedly enough, and all that’s needed. And it’s unfair because now, under ATT, third-party surveillance advertisers who seek to track users across apps on iOS need to ask permission twice — first through the clear-as-a-bell “Ask App Not to Track” / “Allow Tracking” prompt required by Apple, and again through the byzantine but ultimately toothless permission requirements of France and the EU. ATT has had measurable effects because users understand it, and they prefer not to be tracked. EU and French privacy laws are largely ineffective because, in practice, they <a href="https://hep.physics.illinois.edu/home/g-gollin/1984_commercial_dialogue.html">bury users with confusion</a>. The bureaucratic hurdles they impose are to the benefit, not detriment, of the surveillance ad industry. That’s now proven out by industry groups — the ones ATT successfully tempered — successfully getting France’s regulators to penalize Apple. <em>Users</em> don’t know how to lobby government bureaucracies. What the <em>Autorité de la Concurrence</em> is saying, in so many words, is that two layers of consent is too much, and the only one that’s necessary is the one that advertising lobbying groups <em>don’t object to</em>, not the one they do (but which users understand and like).</p>

<p>It’s clear that only one of these two things — Apple’s ATT or French/EU privacy regulations — was actually effective at reducing tracking: ATT. No one claimed that French or EU privacy laws resulted in Meta losing a fortune because they had to adjust their kleptomaniacal thievery of users’ privacy. But by all accounts, <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/danielnewman/2022/02/10/apple-meta-and-the-ten-billion-dollar-impact-of-privacy-changes/">including Meta’s own</a>, <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/kateoflahertyuk/2022/04/23/apple-just-issued-stunning-12-billion-blow-to-facebook/">ATT cost Meta billions</a>. And yes, ATT hurt small businesses too — small businesses that were built upon surreptitious tracking that users had neither awareness of nor control over. It’s like a consortium of sketchy pawn shops complaining to the authorities after a popular retailer successfully cracked down on an organized shoplifting/pickpocketing ring, and the authorities then fining the retailer for the damage to the pawnbrokers’ business fencing stolen goods — and for exposing the police as ineffective.</p>

<p>App Tracking Transparency actually accomplished, in practice, via user-focused plain-language consent, what the EU’s privacy laws were intended to do but do not. This fine boils down to France declaring that Apple shouldn’t have actually done what the EU was pretending to do. They’re acting at the behest of the very developers and advertising companies who were (and still are) trying to conduct cross-app tracking that App Tracking Transparency successfully gave <em>users</em> some control over.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ France Fines Apple $162M for App Tracking Transparency, Taking the Side of Surveillance Advertisers Over Users</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/the_studio" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/w7z" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41759</id>
	<published>2025-03-30T19:38:28Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-31T15:31:36Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Perhaps Apple’s leadership simply believes, as I do, that cinema is the grandest and greatest form of art the world has ever seen — one that encompasses acting, writing, photography and/or illustration, and music — and but that great cinema is expensive and delicate and needs, from deep-pocketed studios and their deeper-pocketed corporate parents, more than patrons, but *champions*.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>With season 2 of <em>Severance</em> complete (with a remarkable bang), Apple TV+ has slid right into a new prestige series, <em><a href="https://www.themoviedb.org/tv/247767-the-studio?language=en-US">The Studio</a></em>, starring (and co-created by) Seth Rogen as the newly-appointed chief of the fictional and dysfunctional Continental Studios in Hollywood.</p>

<p>Two episodes in (out of 10 for the debut season), and it is fucking amazing. So far it feels a bit like a cross between <em>Entourage</em>, <em>The Larry Sanders Show</em>, <em>Boogie Nights</em>, and maybe a touch of <em>Curb Your Enthusiasm</em>. But the biggest influence and inspiration is clearly Robert Altman’s 1992 masterpiece <em><a href="https://www.themoviedb.org/movie/10403-the-player?language=en-US">The Player</a></em>, almost certainly the best Hollywood movie about Hollywood moviemaking that ever was or will be made.</p>

<p>What <em>The Studio</em> and <em>The Player</em> share is that they’re about the struggle to create great cinematic art within a corporate studio world run by unartistic know-it-all  self-important status-obsessed dullards driven by formula and fads — and, simultaneously, they are themselves almost unfathomably complicated and intricate works of cinematic art. They <em>are</em> what they’re <em>about</em>. They achieve what the characters within them fear is no longer achievable. When you get to episode 2 of <em>The Studio</em>, just keep asking yourself “Wait, <em>how</em> are they getting this shot?” The lighting, my god. The whole thing is just an outpouring of homage to <a href="https://www.rogerebert.com/scanners/opening-shots-the-player">the opening shot of <em>The Player</em></a>, which of course itself calls back, <a href="https://filmotomy.com/quiet-on-the-set-breaking-down-the-opening-shot-in-altmans-the-player/">explicitly</a>, to Orson Welles’s <em>Touch of Evil</em>.</p>

<p><em>The Studio</em> is, thus far, engaging, surprising, funny, gorgeous, clever, and cinematically ambitious. It’s really quite a thing. I have no idea what’s coming in episodes 3–10, so maybe this piece will look a bit premature, if not foolish, in two months. But if the rest of season one is anything like the first two episodes, <em>The Studio</em> is a classic in the making.</p>

<p>The thought also occurs to me that this might be the don’t-over-think-it answer to <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/21/apple-tv-spend-loss-or-cost">just what the hell Apple is doing making original shows and movies</a> in the first place. Perhaps Apple’s leadership simply believes, as I do, that cinema is the grandest and greatest form of art the world has ever seen — one that encompasses acting, writing, photography and/or illustration, and music — and but that great cinema is expensive and delicate and needs, from deep-pocketed studios and their deeper-pocketed corporate parents, more than patrons, but <em>champions</em>. And that in a media landscape where such champions of cinema-as-art and art-as-an-essential-public-good are fewer and fewer, it is Apple’s not just opportunity but <em>obligation</em> to step up to the plate.</p>

<p>I’ve long thought that one of the minor tragedies of Steve Jobs’s second act is that the timing just didn’t work out to sell Pixar to Apple, instead of to Disney. But make no mistake, a love and appreciation for great cinema is not outside Apple’s DNA. No streamer has a higher hit rate for quality shows. Their movies mostly stink so far, but maybe that’s just the learning curve. <em>The Gorge</em>, for example, feels like an Apple TV movie because it’s so decidedly meh. Not horrible, but not good in any way beyond its intriguing elevator-pitch concept. <em>Wolfs</em> was better but still a grand disappointment given its pedigree. But when it comes to shows, no one is doing better. <em>Severance</em> deserves all its acclaim and attention, and Ben Stiller delivered a season 2 finale that’s arguably the best 78 minutes of filmmaking I’ve seen this decade. And <em>The Studio</em>, to me, <em>feels</em> like an Apple TV show — not because of how it looks, what it’s about, or who’s in it, but simply because it’s so good. Netflix almost never makes shows like this. Neither does HBO now that’s its been subsumed by “Max”. Peacock et al don’t even try.<sup id="fnr1-2025-03-30"><a href="#fn1-2025-03-30">1</a></sup></p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1-2025-03-30">
<p>One more A+ recommendation: <em><a href="https://www.themoviedb.org/tv/219971-the-agency">The Agency</a></em> on Paramount+. Michael Fassbender, Jeffrey Wright, Richard Gere, a breakout searing performance by Jodie Turner-Smith, and a great supporting cast in a super-smart, hyper-realistic-feeling spy-thriller/mystery/love story. Gorgeous cinematography too. Just so good in a “feels like it should have been on Apple TV+” way, sort of like how it was so obvious right from S1.E1 that HBO fucked up big-time by passing on <em>Mad Men</em>.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-03-30"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ ‘The Studio’ Is Fantastic So Far</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/the_website_hacker_news_is_afraid_to_discuss" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/w7u" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.41754</id>
	<published>2025-03-27T00:11:53Z</published>
	<updated>2025-03-27T13:31:49Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">What bothers me isn’t so much that Daring Fireball is shitlisted at Hacker News. What bothers me is that it’s unexplained.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Back in 2017, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2017/09/iphone_x_event_thoughts_and_observations">the iPhone X was announced alongside the iPhones 8 and 8 Plus</a> in mid-September. The iPhones 8 shipped that month, and I published <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2017/09/the_iphones_8">a review of the iPhones 8</a> on September 19. The iPhone X, though, <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2017/09/the-future-is-here-iphone-x/">wasn’t available to order until October 27</a>, and didn’t start shipping to customers until November 3. It was an unusual iPhone release cycle that year, to say the least. Initial reviews of the much-anticipated iPhone X appeared on October 31, but I’d only had the phone for 24 hours when the embargo dropped, so I published <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2017/10/iphone_x_review_roundup">some initial impressions then</a>, but wound up not publishing my <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2017/12/the_iphone_x">full review of the iPhone X</a> until December 26.</p>

<p>A few days later I wrote a follow-up regarding a specific new interaction design, “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2017/12/side_button_to_confirm_payments_on_iphone_x">Pressing the Side Button to Confirm Payments on iPhone X</a>”, which I began thus:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Occasionally I notice a burst of traffic to Daring Fireball from
Hacker News. It’s always short-lived, because for reasons I’ve
never seen explained, Daring Fireball articles always get
blacklisted from Hacker News once they hit their front page. It’s
apparent that a lot of HN readers do not like my work on the basis
that they see me as a shameless Apple shill, but it’s a shame the
articles get deleted because I like reading the comments. I feel
like it keeps me on my toes to read the comments from people who
don’t like Daring Fireball.</p>

<p>Even after being blacklisted from the Hacker News homepage,
though, the comment threads still exist. I went through <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=16014464">the
Hacker News comments on my iPhone X review</a> today, and a few
comments about how Apple Pay works on the iPhone X caught my
attention.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>What I didn’t mention then was that DF’s buried status at HN was, at the time, a relatively new phenomenon. Hacker News <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2013/05/18/the-evolution-of-hacker-news/">started in early 2007</a> and for a yearslong stretch, Daring Fireball articles seemed more or less appropriately popular there. Articles that I would think would resonate with the HN readership would hit, and get what always seemed to me an appropriate number of comments. At some point in the mid-2010s though, it seemed like DF articles would get downvoted or flagged after hitting the HN front page. I’d been noticing this for some time when I wrote the above in December 2017.</p>

<p>But even in 2017, DF articles would get active comment threads on HN occasionally. The Hacker News thread I referenced above, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=16014464">regarding my iPhone X review</a>, garnered 107 comments. In the years after that, DF articles went from being mysteriously disappeared <em>after</em> hitting the HN front page (and gaining some comment traction) to pretty much <em>never</em> hitting the HN front page (and thus never gaining any comment traction). I found this curious, and I couldn’t figure out <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/newsfaq.html">why or how</a> this was happening — or who was doing it — but I didn’t mention it much.</p>

<p>Two years ago, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2023/02/making_our_hearts_sing#fn1-2023-02-01">I did mention it again in a footnote</a>, in a piece about the inexplicably poor state of Android apps from a design perspective:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It sounds a bit conspiratorial, but <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2017/12/side_button_to_confirm_payments_on_iphone_x">for several years
now</a> it’s seemed clear to me that Hacker News has
Daring Fireball in some sort of graylist. It’s not blacklisted,
obviously, given the aforementioned <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=34605535">two</a>
<a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=34611552">threads</a> about yesterday’s piece, but nothing I
write here ever gains any significant traction there. Ever. And
the reason there are two threads for yesterday’s piece is that the
first one disappeared from the home page soon after it was posted.
I think? In <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/from?site=daringfireball.net">this list of recent Hacker News threads for articles
from DF</a>, going back four months, only three have
more than 10 comments — and two of those are the threads from
yesterday. I don’t know who I pissed off there or why, but I’ve
never seen an explanation for this. <strong>UPDATE:</strong> <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=34626587">HN commenter
Michiel de Mare has quantified the apparent
suppression</a>, based on the ranking of this very
article. Exactly what I’ve noticed for years.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You can see this yourself right now, with <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/from?site=daringfireball.net">the current list of recent DF articles submitted to Hacker News</a>. Most of them have 0, 1, or 2 comments. Some got up to 3. “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/something_is_rotten_in_the_state_of_cupertino">Something Is Rotten in the State of Cupertino</a>” is the most read, most commented upon thing I’ve written in a while. On Hacker News <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43348891">it got just 28 comments</a> before being shitlisted, which, I have to say, is just weird. That’s one piece I’d have thought would resonate with the HN audience, and make for good grist for discussion. Then, after the original thread was shitlisted, someone re-submitted it (perhaps confused that it wasn’t on the HN front page). That re-submission <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43355009">got 1 comment</a> before it too fell to the mysterious shitlist reaper.</p>

<p>The one recent exception is “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/why_cant_we_screenshot_frames_from_drm-protected_video">Why Can’t We Screenshot Frames From DRM-Protected Video on Apple Devices?</a>”, which somehow <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43223985">escaped the shitlist and garnered 208 comments</a>. These occasional exceptions to DF’s general shitlisting at HN have always made the whole thing more mysterious to me. There’s clearly no programmatic blacklisting that keeps Daring Fireball articles from being submitted, or from gaining a few comments. But once any traction occurs, <em>something</em> happens and poof, they’re gone from the Hacker News front page. It certainly doesn’t make any sense to me why my off-hand post griping about our inability to screenshot DRM video frames would be an order of magnitude more popular than “Something Is Rotten in the State of Cupertino” was.</p>

<p>Today, though, I saw <a href="https://jasette.facil.services/@jerome/114229390677476922">a helpful mention on Mastodon</a> that pointed me to an interesting project. An author named Michael Lynch has written a tool to quantify “<a href="https://refactoringenglish.com/tools/hn-popularity/">the highest-ranking personal blogs of Hacker News</a>” since HN’s inception in 2007. According to Lynch’s all-time listing, Daring Fireball ranks #5, which I have to say surprised me, given its years of inexplicable (or at the very least, unexplained) shitlisting status. But Lynch’s tool lets you select date ranges. If you look at <a href="https://refactoringenglish.com/tools/hn-popularity/?start=2006-10-09&amp;end=2021-03-26&amp;limit=100">2007 through 2021</a>, Daring Fireball ranked #3, behind only <a href="https://paulgraham.com/">Paul Graham’s renowned eponymous blog</a> and Brian Krebs’s excellent (and also eponymous) <a href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/">Krebs on Security</a>. From <a href="https://refactoringenglish.com/tools/hn-popularity/?start=2006-10-09&amp;end=2013-03-26&amp;limit=100">2007 though 2013</a>, DF ranked #2, behind only Graham (who created Hacker News). But if you look at the last four years, from <a href="https://refactoringenglish.com/tools/hn-popularity/?start=2021-10-09&amp;end=2025-03-26&amp;limit=100">2021 through 2025</a>, Daring Fireball ranks #72.</p>

<p>Maybe I’ve lost my fastball, and I just don’t write so good no more. Or maybe it’s not me, but the Hacker News audience that has changed in recent years.<sup id="fnr1-2025-03-26"><a href="#fn1-2025-03-26">1</a></sup> But it seems to me <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=34626587">there’s something fishy going on</a>. What bothers me isn’t so much that Daring Fireball is shitlisted at Hacker News — even though I really did enjoy reading the commentary on my posts back when they regularly surfaced there, and <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/user?id=jgruber">still do</a> when one slips through the cracks. What bothers me is that it’s unexplained. Which, ultimately, seems not so much censorial as just cowardly.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1-2025-03-26">
<p>You’d think there’d be a certain kinship between decades-old websites, typeset in small-point Verdana, which stubbornly refuse to update their general layout and design.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-03-26"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ The Website That Hacker News Is Afraid to Discuss (You’re Reading It)</title></entry></feed><!-- THE END -->
