<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>Daring Fireball</title>
<subtitle>By John Gruber</subtitle>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/" />
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main" />
<id>https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main</id>


<updated>2025-07-16T16:40:20Z</updated><rights>Copyright © 2025, John Gruber</rights><entry>
	<title>More on Commodore, Apple, and the Inchoate Personal Computer Era</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sixcolors.com/link/2025/07/commodore-apple-and-the-early-computer-days/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgl" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/16/snell-commodore-apple" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42069</id>
	<published>2025-07-16T16:39:24Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-16T16:40:20Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jason Snell:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>If you find yourself walking down the street in the 1980s and you
see someone coming who prefers the VIC-20 to the Apple II, cross
to the other side of the street. (That said, the VIC-20 really was
revolutionary. It was by far the most affordable home computer
anyone had ever seen at that point. It was laughably underpowered
… but: it was only $300! They sold a million of ’em.)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Snell takes issue (correctly!) with <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/15/saur-c64">Drew Saur’s framing</a> of the Apple II <a href="https://theprogressivecio.com/the-commodore-64-made-a-difference/">as “corporate”</a>. As Snell points out, Commodore was founded by a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack_Tramiel">suit</a> — Apple was founded by <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/how-steve-jobs-met-steve-wozniak-2014-12">two guys</a> whose first collaboration was <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2013/02/the-definitive-story-of-steve-wozniak-steve-jobs-and-phone-phreaking/273331/">making phone-phreaking blue boxes</a>.</p>

<p>But a more pertinent point was made <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@drdrang/114860309297062759">by Dr. Drang on Mastodon</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I don’t want to get on the bad side of @gruber and @jsnell, but
when they say the Commodore 64 cost $600, that’s misleading. Yes,
it cost $600 when it was released, but its price dropped quickly.
By the time I bought one in late ’83 or early ’84, it was selling
for $200 at Kmart. To recognize that it was a great computer for
the price, you have to know what that price really was.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>When <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/14/commodore-64-ultimate">I wrote the other day</a> that the C64 cost $600, it didn’t jibe with my memory. But my thinking is too set in the ways of Apple, where a computer debuts at a price and then stays at that price. A price around $200 is more what I remember for the C64, at a time when a bare-bones IIe cost $1,400. Inflation-adjusted, $200 in 1984 is about $620 today, and $1,400 is about $4,300. <em>That’s</em> why so many more kids of my era got their parents to spring for a Commodore 64 but not an Apple II. They were rivals in some sense, but really, the Apple II was a different class of computer, and cost nearly an order of magnitude more.</p>

<p>(Me, I didn’t own a computer until I went to college. My parents wouldn’t buy me one because they feared if they did, I’d never leave the house. I resented it at the time, but in hindsight, they might have been right. I didn’t fight too hard because we had an Atari 2600 and a generous budget for game cartridges. Plus, my grade school had a few Apple IIe’s (alongside a bunch of cheap <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TI-99/4A\">TI-99/4A</a>’s), and my middle/high school had an entire lab of Apple IIe’s and IIc’s.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘More on Commodore, Apple, and the Inchoate Personal Computer Era’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/16/snell-commodore-apple">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Drew Saur’s Ode to the Commodore 64</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://theprogressivecio.com/the-commodore-64-made-a-difference/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgk" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/15/saur-c64" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42068</id>
	<published>2025-07-15T23:29:47Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-16T15:34:38Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Drew Saur, pushing back on <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/14/commodore-64-ultimate">my post</a> slagging on the Commodore 64:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I cannot argue with your nostalgia. It is uniquely yours.</p>

<p>That said: The Commodore 64 as cheap-feeling and inelegant! Oh my.</p>

<p>I was fourteen when the Commodore 64 came out, and I want to
convey — in as brief a form as I can — why it captured so many
hearts during the 8-bit era.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>What a great post. Fond memories all the way down the stack with that whole era of computing. As I told Saur in email, my fondest memory of the Commodore 64 is that they sold them at Kmart, and for years had a working model on display. And every time I’d go to Kmart with my mom, I’d swing by the electronics department and type:</p>

<pre><code>10 PRINT "KMART SUCKS!!!!"
20 GOTO 10
RUN
</code></pre>

<p>Sometimes I’d be clever and do something like add an incrementing number of spaces to make the lines go diagonally. Something like:</p>

<pre><code>5 LET X = 0
10 PRINT SPC(X); "KMART SUCKS!"
20 X = X + 1
30 IF X &gt; 28 THEN X = 0
35 FOR T = 0 TO 100 : NEXT : REM SLOW DOWN
40 GOTO 10
RUN
</code></pre>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/07/kmart-sucks.png">This</a> never got old for me. <a href="https://c64online.com/c64-online-emulator/">Try it yourself</a>. (And of course I never actually commented my code at Kmart — that <code>REM</code> is for you, if you’re wondering what that do-nothing <code>FOR</code> loop is for.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Drew Saur’s Ode to the Commodore 64’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/15/saur-c64">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://workos.com/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wgj" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/07/workos_scalable_secure_authent_6" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.42067</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-07-15T19:33:53Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-15T19:33:53Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>With WorkOS you can start selling to enterprises with just a few lines of code. It provides a complete User Management solution along with SSO, SCIM, and FGA. The APIs are modular and easy-to-use, allowing integrations to be completed in minutes instead of months.</p>

<p>Today, some of the fastest growing startups are already powered by WorkOS, including Perplexity, Vercel, and Webflow.</p>

<p>For SaaS apps that care deeply about design and user experience, WorkOS is the perfect fit. From high-quality documentation to self-serve onboarding for your customers, it removes all the unnecessary complexity for your engineering team.</p>

<p>Check out our <a href="https://workos.com/launch-week/summer-2025">Summer Launch Week announcements</a> to see our latest.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘WorkOS: Scalable, Secure Authentication’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/07/workos_scalable_secure_authent_6">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] WorkOS: Scalable, Secure Authentication</title></entry><entry>
	<title>The Party of ‘Free Speech’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theatlantic.com/newsletters/archive/2025/07/trump-rosie-odonnell-citizenship-free-speech/683530/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgi" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/15/party-of-free-speech" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42066</id>
	<published>2025-07-15T17:52:49Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-15T17:52:49Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>David A. Graham, writing at The Atlantic:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Not that long ago, believe it or not, Donald Trump ran for
president as the candidate who would defend the First Amendment.</p>

<p>He <a href="https://www.donaldjtrump.com/agenda47/president-donald-j-trump-free-speech-policy-initiative">warned</a> that a “sinister group of Deep State
bureaucrats, Silicon Valley tyrants, left-wing activists, and
depraved corporate news media” was “conspiring to manipulate and
silence the American people,” and promised that “by restoring free
speech, we will begin to reclaim our democracy, and save our
nation.” On his first day back in office, Trump signed an
<a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/presidential-actions/2025/01/restoring-freedom-of-speech-and-ending-federal-censorship/">executive order</a> affirming the “right of the American
people to engage in constitutionally protected speech.”</p>

<p>If anyone believed him at the time, they should be disabused by
now. One of his most brazen attacks on freedom of speech thus far
came this past weekend, when the president said that he was
thinking about stripping a comedian of her citizenship — for no
apparent reason other than that she regularly criticizes him.</p>

<p>“Because of the fact that Rosie O’Donnell is not in the best
interests of our Great Country, I am giving serious consideration
to taking away her Citizenship. She is a Threat to Humanity, and
should remain in the wonderful Country of Ireland, if they want
her,” he posted on <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/114840552173805537">Truth Social</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The people who griped that the Biden Administration was anti-free-speech because they ... <em>checks notes</em> ... applied soft pressure on companies like Meta to clamp down on algorithmically promoting disinformation are pretty quiet these days.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Party of ‘Free Speech’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/15/party-of-free-speech">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Elon Musk Gives Himself Another Handshake’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://pxlnv.com/linklog/musk-xai-spacex/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgh" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/14/musk-gives-himself-a-handshake" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42065</id>
	<published>2025-07-15T00:31:29Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-15T15:46:44Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Nick Heer, Pixel Envy on <a href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/spacex-to-invest-2-billion-into-elon-musks-xai-413934de?st=XZYChT&amp;reflink=desktopwebshare_permalink">the news</a> that SpaceX “invested” $2 billion in the <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2025-06-17/musk-s-xai-burning-through-1-billion-a-month-as-costs-pile-up">xAI money pit</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This comes just a few months after <a href="https://pxlnv.com/linklog/musk-x-xai/">xAI acquired X</a>, one
year after Musk <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/06/04/elon-musk-told-nvidia-to-ship-ai-chips-reserved-for-tesla-to-x-xai.html">shifted</a> a bunch of Tesla-bound Nvidia GPUs
to xAI, and just a few years after he <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/tech/tech-news/elon-musk-pulled-50-tesla-employees-twitter-takeover-rcna54946">used staff</a> from
Tesla to work on Twitter. So, to recap: he has moved people and
resources from two publicly traded companies to two privately
owned ones, has used funds from one of his privately owned
companies to buy another one of his privately owned companies, and
is now using one of his <s>publicly traded</s> privately owned
companies to give billions of dollars to (another) one of his
privately owned ones.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Musk can and should be able to do whatever he wants with his privately held companies, like X Corp and SpaceX. But the way he treats Tesla Motors, which is publicly traded, as though it’s just part of his personal fiefdom is absurd. And the European Commission <a href="https://fortune.com/europe/2024/10/17/musk-empire-risks-being-targeted-by-eu-for-potential-x-fines/">isn’t fooled</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Elon Musk Gives Himself Another Handshake’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/14/musk-gives-himself-a-handshake">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Lee Elia, Former Major League Manager, Dies at 87</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/athletic/6486807/2025/07/10/lee-elia-obituary-cubs-phillies/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgg" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/14/lee-elia-rip" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42064</id>
	<published>2025-07-14T22:53:05Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-14T22:55:51Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Steve Berman, The Athletic:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Lee Elia, who managed the Philadelphia Phillies and Chicago Cubs
for two seasons apiece but is perhaps best known for a profane
postgame rant critical of Chicago fans, died on Wednesday. He was
87. The Phillies announced his death in a statement on Thursday,
though they did not say where he died or cite a cause. [...]</p>

<p>The team noted that Elia was a Philadelphia native who signed with
the Phillies in 1958. He was in the organization on and off
throughout the decades, including as a minor league player,
manager, scout and director of instruction. He was the third-base
coach for the Phillies team that won the 1980 World Series.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You’ll never hear a better example of how to talk like a Philadelphian than <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uiVVbYK9HXw">Elia’s famed 1983 rant</a>, after the Cubs opened the season 5-14. Earmuffs for any (non-Philadelphian) children in the room.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Lee Elia, Former Major League Manager, Dies at 87’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/14/lee-elia-rip">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Elmore Leonard’s Perfect Pitch</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2025/07/07/elmore-leonards-perfect-pitch" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgf" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/14/elmore-leonard-perfect-pitch" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42063</id>
	<published>2025-07-14T21:15:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-14T21:46:08Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Anthony Lane, in a crackerjack piece for The New Yorker on the writing and work of Elmore Leonard:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>So, when does Leonard become himself? Is it possible to specify
the moment, or the season, when he crosses the border? I would
nominate “The Big Bounce,” from 1969 — which, by no coincidence,
is the first novel of his to be set in the modern age. As the
prose calms down, something quickens in the air, and the plainest
words and deeds make easy music: “They discussed whether beer was
better in bottles or cans, and then which was better, bottled or
draft, and both agreed, finally, that it didn’t make a hell of a
lot of difference. Long as it was cold.”</p>

<p>What matters here is what isn’t there. Grammatically, by rights,
we ought to have an “As” or a “So” before “long.” If the beer
drinkers were talking among themselves, however, or <em>to</em>
themselves, they wouldn’t bother with such nicety, and Leonard
heeds their example; he does them the honor of flavoring his
registration of their chatter with that perfect hint of them. The
technical term for this trick, as weary students of literature
will recall, is <em>style indirect libre</em>, or free indirect
discourse. It has a noble track record, with Jane Austen and
Flaubert as front-runners, but seldom has it proved so
democratically wide-ranging — not just <em>libre</em> but liberating,
too, as Leonard tunes in to regular citizens. He gets into their
heads, their palates, and their plans for the evening. Listen to a
guy named Moran, in “<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Cat-Chaser-Novel-Elmore-Leonard/dp/0062190954/?tag=df-amzn-20">Cat Chaser</a>” (1982), watching
Monday-night football and trying to decide “whether he should have
another beer and fry a steak or go to Vesuvio’s on Federal Highway
for spaghetti marinara and eat the crisp breadsticks with hard
butter, Jesus, and have a bottle of red with it, the house salad
... or get the chicken cacciatore and slock the bread around in
the gravy ...”</p>

<p>The ellipses are Leonard’s, or, rather, they are Moran’s musings,
reproduced by Leonard as a kind of Morse code. We join in with the
dots. But it’s the “Jesus” that does the work, yielding up a
microsecond of salivation, and inviting us to slock around in the
juice of the character’s brain.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The genius in the second example is the verb choice: <em><a href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/slock">slock</a></em>. There are dozens of verbs that could have worked there, but none better.</p>

<p>Leonard is probably tops on the list of authors whose work I love, but of which I haven’t read nearly as much as I should. There are novelists who are good at creating (and voicing) original vivid characters, novelists who are good at plot, and novelists who are just great at <em>writing</em>. Leonard hits the trifecta.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Elmore Leonard’s Perfect Pitch’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/14/elmore-leonard-perfect-pitch">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Experts Said This Was a Damn Clever Post by Jason Kottke</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://kottke.org/25/07/journalisms-experts-said-conclusion" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wge" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/14/kottke-experts-said" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42062</id>
	<published>2025-07-14T20:58:07Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-14T20:58:07Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jason Kottke:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Large media companies, and the NY Times in particular these days,
like to use the phrase “experts said” instead of simply stating
facts. The thing is, many other statements of plain truth in that
brief Times post lack the confirmation of expertise. To aid the
paper in steering their readers away from notions of objective
truth, here’s a suggested rewrite of that Bluesky post.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Experts Said This Was a Damn Clever Post by Jason Kottke’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/14/kottke-experts-said">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Reborn Commodore Is Taking Pre-Orders for New Commodore 64 Models</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.commodore.net/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgd" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/14/commodore-64-ultimate" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42061</id>
	<published>2025-07-14T19:29:56Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-14T19:32:29Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Last year, retro computing YouTuber Christian “Peri Fractic” Simpson <a href="https://tedium.co/2025/06/19/peri-fractic-retro-recipes-commodore-profile/">bought the branding rights and some of the IP</a> belonging to Commodore (which rights have been transferred five times since the original company went bankrupt in 1994). Last week they launched their first product:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This is the first real Commodore computer in over 30 years, and
it’s picked up a few new tricks.</p>

<p>Not an emulator. Not a PC. Retrogaming heaven in three dimensions:
<em>silicon, nostalgia, and light</em>. Powered by a FPGA recreation of the
original motherboard, wrapped in glowing game-reactive LEDs (or
classic beige of course).</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://tedium.co/2025/07/12/commodore-revival-community/">Via Ernie Smith</a>, who has been <a href="https://tedium.co/2025/06/19/peri-fractic-retro-recipes-commodore-profile/">following this saga thoughtfully</a>.</p>

<p>This is, no question, a fun and cool project, and I hope it succeeds wildly. But personally, the Commodore 64 holds almost no nostalgic value for me. The Commodore 64 — which came out in 1982, when I was 9 — always struck me as cheap-feeling and inelegant. Like using some weird computer from the Soviet Union. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/07/commodore-64-keyboard.jpeg">Just look at its keyboard</a>. It’s got a bunch of odd keys, like “Run Stop” and “Restore”, and all sorts of drawing-related glyphs (used when programming) printed on the sides of the keycaps. Now compare that to the keyboards from <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/07/apple-IIplus-keyboard.jpeg">the Apple II Plus</a> (1979), which has just one weird key, “REPT” (<a href="https://www.duxburysystems.org/downloads/library/texas/apple/history/museum/computers/a2_plusclose.html">for Repeat</a> — you needed to press and hold REPT to get other keys to auto-repeat), and to <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/07/apple-IIe-keyboard.jpeg">the Apple IIe</a> (1983), which has no weird keys and whose keyboard looks remarkably modern lo these 42 intervening years.</p>

<p>That said, while both systems came with 64 kilobytes of RAM, the Apple IIe cost $1,400 when it debuted (~$4,600 today, inflation adjusted); the Commodore 64 cost $600 (~$2,000 today). Some things haven’t changed about the computer industry in my lifetime.</p>

<p>The most interesting computers Commodore ever made, by far, were the Amigas. The Amiga brand and IP were cleaved from Commodore long ago, and alas, the new Commodore doesn’t have them. But they’ve expressed interest in buying them. Something like this Commodore 64 Ultimate but for an Amiga — now <em>that</em> might get me to reach for my credit card.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Reborn Commodore Is Taking Pre-Orders for New Commodore 64 Models’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/14/commodore-64-ultimate">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Classic Web’ on Mastodon</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://indieweb.social/@classicweb" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgc" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/13/classic-web" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42060</id>
	<published>2025-07-14T00:17:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-14T00:18:25Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Classic Web is a fun account to follow on Mastodon. Curator Richard MacManus posts half a dozen or so screenshots per day of, well, classic websites from the late 1990s and 2000s. Makes me feel old and young at the same time.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Classic Web’ on Mastodon’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/13/classic-web">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Drata</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://drata.com/daring/?utm_source=Daring_Fireball&amp;utm_medium=display&amp;utm_campaign=18991230_fy26_comm_DG_COMM_&amp;utm_content=demo_request" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgb" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/13/drata" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42059</id>
	<published>2025-07-13T19:26:31Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-13T19:26:32Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to Drata for sponsoring this last week at DF. Their message is short and sweet: Automate compliance. Streamline security. Manage risk. Drata delivers the world’s most advanced Trust Management platform.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Drata’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/13/drata">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Grok 4 System Prompt Shenanigans</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Jul/12/grok-4-heavy/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wga" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/12/grok-4-system-prompt-shenanigans" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42058</id>
	<published>2025-07-12T21:55:27Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-13T03:11:14Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Simon Willison:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Grok 4 Heavy is the “think much harder” version of Grok 4 that’s
currently only available on their $300/month plan. Jeremy Howard
relays a report from a Grok 4 Heavy user who wishes to remain
anonymous: it turns out that Heavy, <a href="https://grok.com/share/bGVnYWN5_fb5f16af-9590-4880-9d96-58573c7e1293">unlike regular Grok 4</a>, has
measures in place to prevent it from sharing its system prompt.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Most big LLMs do not share their system prompts, but xAI has <a href="https://x.com/jeremyphoward/status/1943871257134739866">made a show out of being transparent</a> in that regard.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In related prompt transparency news, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Jul/12/grok/">Grok’s retrospective</a>
on why Grok started spitting out antisemitic tropes last week
included the text “You tell it like it is and you are not afraid
to offend people who are politically correct” as part of the
system prompt blamed for the problem. That text isn’t present in
<a href="https://github.com/xai-org/grok-prompts/commits/main/">the history</a> of their previous published system prompts.</p>

<p>Given the <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Jul/12/grok/">past week of mishaps</a> I think xAI would be wise to
reaffirm their dedication to prompt transparency and set things up
so the <a href="https://github.com/xai-org/grok-prompts">xai-org/grok-prompts</a> repository updates
automatically when new prompts are deployed — their current manual
process for that is clearly not adequate for the job!</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Transparently publishing system prompt changes to GitHub was xAI’s main “trust us” argument after <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/08/grok-praises-hitler">the “white genocide in South Africa” fiasco mid-May</a>. Turns out they don’t publish all of them.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Grok 4 System Prompt Shenanigans’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/12/grok-4-system-prompt-shenanigans">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple and Masimo Faced Off in US Appeals Court This Week</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.reuters.com/legal/government/apple-masimo-spar-over-apple-watch-import-ban-us-appeals-court-2025-07-07/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wg9" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/11/apple-masimo-appeals-court" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42057</id>
	<published>2025-07-12T01:46:49Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-13T18:29:00Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Blake Brittain, reporting for Reuters:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple asked a U.S. appeals court on Monday to overturn a trade
tribunal’s decision which forced it to remove blood-oxygen reading
technology from its Apple Watches, in order to avoid a ban on its
U.S. smartwatch imports.</p>

<p>A three-judge panel of the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Federal
Circuit heard arguments from the tech giant, medical monitoring
technology company Masimo, and the U.S. International Trade
Commission over the ITC’s 2023 ruling that Apple Watches violated
Masimo’s patent rights in pulse oximetry technology. [...]</p>

<p>Apple attorney Joseph Mueller of WilmerHale told the court on
Monday that the decision had wrongly “deprived millions of Apple
Watch users” of Apple’s blood-oxygen feature. A lawyer for Masimo,
Joseph Re of Knobbe Martens Olson &amp; Bear, countered that Apple was
trying to “rewrite the law” with its arguments.</p>

<p>The judges questioned whether Masimo’s development of a competing
smartwatch justified the ITC’s ruling. Apple has told the appeals
court that the ban was improper because a Masimo wearable device
covered by the patents was “purely hypothetical” when Masimo filed
its ITC complaint in 2021. [...]</p>

<p>Mueller told the court on Monday that the ban was unjustified
because Masimo only had prototypes of a smartwatch with pulse
oximetry features when it had filed its ITC complaint. Re
responded that Apple was wrong to argue that a “finished product”
was necessary to justify the ITC’s decision.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This whole thing started with the Apple Watch Series 9 and Ultra 2 in 2023. I’m very surprised that we’re just two months away from the Series 11 and Ultra 3 in 2025 and it still isn’t settled. And to be clear, while it’s technically an “import ban”, all Apple Watch Series 9, Series 10, and Ultra 2 have the blood oxygen sensors. Units sold in the US after December 2023 simply have the feature disabled in software.</p>

<p>(<a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/07/07/apple-and-masimo-back-in-court-over-apple-watch-import-ban-appeal/">Via Chance Miller at 9to5Mac</a>.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple and Masimo Faced Off in US Appeals Court This Week’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/11/apple-masimo-appeals-court">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Moft’s MagSafe-Compatible Snap-On iPhone Stand and Wallet</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.moft.us/products/iphone-stand-wallet-magsafe-compatible" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wg8" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/11/moft-snap-on-iphone-stand-wallet" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42056</id>
	<published>2025-07-11T23:51:55Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-11T23:55:44Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Here’s a product recommendation long in the making. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2021/07/21/ep-318">Four years ago this month</a>, Matthew Panzarino was my guest on The Talk Show and at one point he recommended Moft’s Snap-On iPhone Stand/Wallet. It uses a very clever origami-style folding design. Folded flat it kind of just looks like a leather MagSafe wallet. But folded open it works as a stand — and as a stand, it works both horizontally and vertically. Borrowing images from Moft’s website:</p>

<p><img
  src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/07/moft-vertical.jpeg"
  alt = "A blue Moft Snap-On iPhone Stand, propping an iPhone vertically."
/></p>

<p><img
  src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/07/moft-horizontal.jpeg"
  alt = "A blue Moft Snap-On iPhone Stand, propping an iPhone vertically."
/></p>

<p>You can also use it with the stand oriented vertically but the phone horizontally.</p>

<p>I bought one of these right after that episode of the show, and I’ve been using it ever since. And every so often when I use it, I think to myself that I should write a post recommending it. I’ve waited so long that Panzarino has been back on The Talk Show five times since the episode in which he recommended it, but here we are. The thing is, I use it both in my kitchen <em>and</em> while travelling, and so I’ll often find myself in the kitchen, rooting around the drawer in which I keep it stashed, only to realize it’s downstairs in my office in my laptop bag. Or, worse, I’ll find myself looking for it in my laptop bag while I’m sitting on an airplane 35,000 feet in the air, only to realize it’s back home in my kitchen. So I ordered a second one today — which I should have done like 3.5 years ago.</p>

<p>I own a few similar/competing products, like these PopSocket-y rings from <a href="https://amzn.to/3Imv8sx">Anker</a> and <a href="https://amzn.to/4lhshj0">Belkin</a>. I have no idea why I own both of those rings when I don’t like either of them as much as the Moft foldable stand. The problem with these rings is that they’re only able to prop the phone horizontally. Watching video is almost certainly the most common use case for these stands, but I do often use my iPhone propped up vertically, like for FaceTime calls and when I’m writing on it using a Bluetooth keyboard. I’m going to give both of these rings away — there’s nothing they do better than the Moft stand. The Moft stand even works better as a hand-holding grip.</p>

<p>I’ve never used the Moft stand as a wallet, but if you want to, it holds two cards. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/07/make_me_rich_on_amazon_prime_day">Prime “Day”</a> lasts a week and it’s still running until midnight Pacific tonight, but the Moft stand doesn’t have a Prime Day discount: <a href="https://amzn.to/4eLcTJn">it’s the same price at Amazon</a> as it is <a href="https://www.moft.us/products/iphone-stand-wallet-magsafe-compatible">from Moft’s website</a>: $30. Well worth it. I love this thing. (Buy yours wherever you want, of course, but the Amazon link a few sentences back will throw some filthy affiliate lucre my way.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Moft’s MagSafe-Compatible Snap-On iPhone Stand and Wallet’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/11/moft-snap-on-iphone-stand-wallet">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Linda Yaccarino Resigns as ‘CEO’ of X</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://x.com/lindayaX/status/1942957094811951197" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wg7" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/10/yaccarino-out" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42055</id>
	<published>2025-07-10T22:21:24Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-10T22:21:25Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Linda Yaccarino, in a post on X yesterday:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>After two incredible years, I’ve decided to step down as CEO of X.</p>

<p>When @elonmusk and I first spoke