<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>Daring Fireball</title>
<subtitle>By John Gruber</subtitle>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/" />
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main" />
<id>https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main</id>


<updated>2025-07-23T21:08:09Z</updated><rights>Copyright © 2025, John Gruber</rights><entry>
	<title>Yours Truly With David Barnard on the Sub Club Podcast</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://subclub.com/episode/the-past-present-and-future-of-building-on-apple-john-gruber-daring-fireball" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wha" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/23/yours-truly-with-david-barnard-on-the-sub-club-podcast" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42094</id>
	<published>2025-07-23T21:08:08Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-23T21:08:09Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>David Barnard:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>On the podcast I talk with John about the fascinating 40-year
history of Apple’s developer relations, how almost going bankrupt
in the 1990s shaped today’s control-focused approach, and why we
might need an “App Store 3.0” reset.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Yet <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/19/cortex-hurley-interview-with-yours-truly">another</a> fun appearance on a podcast. There’s a good transcript too, if you’re more of a reader than a listener.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Yours Truly With David Barnard on the Sub Club Podcast’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/23/yours-truly-with-david-barnard-on-the-sub-club-podcast">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Financial Times Reports the UK Is Backing Down From Its Demand for Apple to Grant It an iCloud Encryption Backdoor</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2025/07/uk-backing-down-on-apple-encryption-backdoor-after-pressure-from-us/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wh9" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/22/uk-backing-down-on-apple-encryption-backdoor" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42093</id>
	<published>2025-07-22T17:34:09Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-22T17:54:50Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Anna Gross, Tim Bradshaw, and Lauren Fedor, reporting for the Financial Times (syndicated without paywall at Ars Technica):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Sir Keir Starmer’s government is seeking a way out of a clash with
the Trump administration over the UK’s demand that Apple provide
it with access to secure customer data, two senior British
officials have told the Financial Times. The officials both said
the Home Office, which ordered the tech giant in January to grant
access to its most secure cloud storage system, would probably
have to retreat in the face of pressure from senior leaders in
Washington, including Vice President JD Vance.</p>

<p>“This is something that the vice president is very annoyed about
and which needs to be resolved,” said an official in the UK’s
technology department. “The Home Office is basically going to have
to back down.”</p>

<p>Both officials said the UK decision to force Apple to break its
end-to-end encryption — which has been raised multiple times by
top officials in Donald Trump’s administration — could impede
technology agreements with the US.</p>

<p>“One of the challenges for the tech partnerships we’re working on
is the encryption issue,” the first official said. “It’s a big red
line in the US — they don’t want us messing with their tech
companies.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>One dystopian element of the UK’s Investigatory Powers Act is that when companies are issued demands under the law — which critics in the UK call “the Snoopers’ Charter” — it’s a criminal offense subject to imprisonment to reveal to anyone that the UK government issued the demand. You will recall that after receiving this demand, in February this year <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/02/apple_pulls_advanced_data_protection_from_the_uk">Apple pulled iCloud Advanced Data Protection from users in the UK</a>.</p>

<p>What I don’t like about the Financial Times’s framing of this is that they describe it only in terms of politics between the Trump administration and Starmer’s. This is not merely about a foreign government “messing with their tech companies”. It’s fundamentally about privacy and security. It is a human rights and civil liberties issue, first and foremost. The Trump administration is on the correct and just side of this issue. Whether they’re on the correct side for the right reasons, I don’t know, but that’s what’s most important here. A secret backdoor is abhorrent from all perspectives: privacy, security, civil liberties. (Not to mention impossible cryptographically with E2EE — mandating a backdoor is effectively banning E2EE, which is why Apple pulled Advanced Data Protection from the UK.)</p>

<p>Conversely, one reason the UK went through with this demand is that <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/02/26/wapo-biden-justice-department-backdoor">the Biden administration was, disgracefully, on the wrong side of this</a>, choosing to look the other way and lie to Congress about what the UK was planning to do.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Financial Times Reports the UK Is Backing Down From Its Demand for Apple to Grant It an iCloud Encryption Backdoor’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/22/uk-backing-down-on-apple-encryption-backdoor">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>OS 26 Beta 4’s Are Out</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/07/22/apple-seeds-ios-26-beta-4/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wh8" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/22/os-26-beta-4" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42092</id>
	<published>2025-07-22T17:07:53Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-23T01:23:17Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Juli Clover, MacRumors:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple today provided developers with the fourth betas of <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/roundup/ios-26/">iOS
26</a> and <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/roundup/ipados-26/">iPadOS 26</a> for testing purposes, with the
updates coming two weeks after Apple <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/07/07/apple-seeds-ios-26-beta-3/">seeded the third
betas</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/07/22/apple-seeds-macos-tahoe-beta-4/">MacOS</a>, <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/07/22/apple-seeds-watchos-26-beta-4/">WatchOS, tvOS, and VisionOS</a> too, all in lockstep. Also, a <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/07/22/ios-26-beta-4-features/">good first look at what’s changed in iOS 26 beta 4 from beta 3</a>. Some of the things Apple is tweaking between betas <a href="https://mastodon.social/@gruber/114899907908341231">need more than minor tweaking</a>. Also: Apple Intelligence summaries for news notifications <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/07/22/ios-26-beta-4-notification-summaries/">are back</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘OS 26 Beta 4’s Are Out’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/22/os-26-beta-4">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Computer History Museum’s Vintage Computer Festival: August 1–2</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://computerhistory.org/events/vintage-computer-festival-3/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wh7" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/22/chm-vintage-computer-festival" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42091</id>
	<published>2025-07-22T16:12:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-22T16:15:01Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>CHM:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Come and explore an extraordinary showcase of historical
computers, from pristine originals to ingenious modern hacks.
Computer enthusiasts around the world look forward to the annual
Vintage Computer Festival.</p>

<p>Experience hands-on demos of historical systems from the 1960s
through the 1990s, learn preservation tips, and try out brands
like Apple, Atari, Commodore, Tandy/Radio Shack, and more.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s in Mountain View, so I can’t make it, but given <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/14/commodore-64-ultimate">all</a> <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/15/saur-c64">the</a> <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/16/snell-commodore-apple">recent</a> <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/20/dont-forget-atari">nostalgia</a> that’s been in the air regarding the early PC era, I wish I could.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Computer History Museum’s Vintage Computer Festival: August 1–2’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/22/chm-vintage-computer-festival">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Hackers Exploit Zero-Day Microsoft SharePoint Exploit, Attacking Governments and Businesses Around the World</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2025/07/20/microsoft-sharepoint-hack/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wh6" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/22/zero-day-microsoft-sharepoint-exploit" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42090</id>
	<published>2025-07-22T15:41:21Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-22T15:41:22Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Ellen Nakashima, Yvonne Wingett Sanchez and Joseph Menn, reporting for The Washington Post:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The U.S. government and partners in Canada and Australia are
investigating the compromise of SharePoint servers, which provide
a platform for sharing and managing documents. Tens of thousands
of such servers are at risk, experts said, and Microsoft has
issued no patch for the flaw, leaving victims around the world
scrambling to respond.</p>

<p>The “zero-day” attack, so called because it targeted a previously
unknown vulnerability, is only the latest cybersecurity
embarrassment for Microsoft. Last year, the company was faulted by
a panel of U.S. government and industry experts for lapses that
enabled a <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/national-security/2024/04/02/microsoft-cyber-china-hack-report/">2023 targeted Chinese hack of U.S. government
emails</a>, including those of then-Commerce Secretary Gina
Raimondo.</p>

<p>This most recent attack compromises only those servers housed
within an organization — not those in the cloud, such as
Microsoft 365, officials said. After first suggesting that users
make modifications to or simply unplug SharePoint server programs
from the internet, the company on Sunday evening released a patch
for one version of the software. Two other versions remain
vulnerable and Microsoft said it is continuing to work to develop
a patch.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>“Just pull the plug” — classic Microsoft security.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>With access to these servers, which often connect to Outlook
email, Teams and other core services, a breach can lead to theft
of sensitive data as well as password harvesting,
Netherlands-based research company <a href="https://research.eye.security/sharepoint-under-siege/">Eye Security noted</a>.
What’s also alarming, researchers said, is that the hackers have
gained access to keys that may allow them to regain entry even
after a system is patched. “So pushing out a patch on Monday or
Tuesday doesn’t help anybody who’s been compromised in the past 72
hours,” said one researcher, who spoke on the condition of
anonymity because a federal investigation is ongoing.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Sounds bad.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The nonprofit Center for Internet Security, which staffs an
information-sharing group for state and local governments,
notified about 100 organizations that they were vulnerable and
potentially compromised, said Randy Rose, the organization’s vice
president. Those warned included public schools and universities.
The process took six hours Saturday night — much longer than it
otherwise would have, because the threat-intelligence and
incident-response teams have been cut by 65 percent as CISA
slashed funding, Rose said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/16/dingalings-cut-off-funding-for-cve">Another</a> DOGE success story.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Hackers Exploit Zero-Day Microsoft SharePoint Exploit, Attacking Governments and Businesses Around the World’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/22/zero-day-microsoft-sharepoint-exploit">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Reuters: ‘Meta, X, and LinkedIn Appeal Unprecedented VAT Claim by Italy’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.reuters.com/world/europe/meta-x-linkedin-appeal-unprecedented-vat-claim-by-italy-2025-07-21/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wh5" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/22/italy-meta-x-linkedin-tax" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42089</id>
	<published>2025-07-22T15:31:57Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-22T17:09:53Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Reuters:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Italian tax authorities argue that free user registrations with X,
LinkedIn and Meta platforms should be seen as taxable transactions
as they imply the exchange of a membership account in return for a
user’s personal data.</p>

<p>The issue is especially sensitive given wider trade tensions
between the EU and the administration of U.S. President Donald
Trump. Italy is claiming 887.6 million euros ($1.03 billion) from
Meta, 12.5 million euros from X and around 140 million euros from
LinkedIn. [...]</p>

<p>According to several experts consulted by Reuters, the Italian
approach could affect almost all companies, from airlines to
supermarkets to publishers, who link access to free services on
their sites to users’ acceptance of profiling cookies.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Charging a VAT on free account signups does not strike me as a good idea.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Reuters: ‘Meta, X, and LinkedIn Appeal Unprecedented VAT Claim by Italy’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/22/italy-meta-x-linkedin-tax">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Google Solves Its Pixel 10 Leaks by Just Showing Us the Phone’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/news/711033/google-pixel-10-design-tease-reveal" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wh4" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/22/google-pixel-10" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42088</id>
	<published>2025-07-22T15:25:06Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-22T15:25:07Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jay Peters, The Verge:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Google’s Pixel 10 launch event is just under a month away, but the
company is already revealing the official design of the base
phone. You can currently see a video of the phone <a href="https://store.google.com/magazine/google_pixel_10">on Google’s
website</a> (and below). It looks just like the official renders that
<a href="https://www.theverge.com/news/710809/google-pixel-10-leaked-official-renders-third-telephoto-camera">leaked earlier today</a>, which showed that the phone will have a
third back camera (which is rumored to be a telephoto sensor).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That’s certainly one way to deal with leaks. It looks like a Pixel 9, which looks like an iPhone 12–16 with a different (but cool) camera mesa.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Google Solves Its Pixel 10 Leaks by Just Showing Us the Phone’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/22/google-pixel-10">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Will Wonders Never Cease?</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2025-07-21/oracle-in-talks-for-100-million-skydance-paramount-cloud-deal" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wh3" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/21/skydance-oracle-deal" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42087</id>
	<published>2025-07-22T00:59:53Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-22T00:59:53Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Brody Ford and Hannah Miller, reporting for Bloomberg:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Oracle Corp. is in discussions with Skydance Media LLC for a major
software deal once the media company’s acquisition of Paramount
Global is complete. The new arrangement is expected to be worth
about $100 million per year, according to people familiar with the
matter who asked not to be named speaking about the private
discussions. The agreement would see Paramount and its
subsidiaries using Oracle’s cloud software, the people said.</p>

<p>Skydance was founded by David Ellison, the son of Oracle Chairman
Larry Ellison.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Reminiscent of <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/14/musk-gives-himself-a-handshake">SpaceX’s $2 billion “investment” in xAI</a>. (<a href="https://x.com/pkafka/status/1947444354659787026">Via Peter Kafka</a>.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Will Wonders Never Cease?’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/21/skydance-oracle-deal">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Commanders : Goofus :: Guardians : Gallant</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nbcsports.com/nfl/profootballtalk/rumor-mill/news/as-guardians-dig-in-commanders-remain-mum-on-president-trumps-name-change-demand" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wh2" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/21/commanders-goofus-guardians-gallant" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42086</id>
	<published>2025-07-22T00:24:03Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-22T02:53:25Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Mike Florio, NBC Sports:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>And while the Guardians <a href="https://x.com/ZackMeisel/status/1946961807198875727">stood up and responded to Trump</a>, the
Commanders are hiding under the bed. With the NFL right next
to them.</p>

<p>We’ve sent multiple emails to both the team and the league seeking
comment on one of the biggest stories in all of sports. No one has
responded. It’s a common, low-tech, P.R. play. Ignore the request,
and maybe the reporter will forget about it. Force the reporter to
remember, and to ask again. And maybe again.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Here’s the statement from Guardians team president Chris Antonetti:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“I understand there are very different perspectives on the
decision we made a few years ago, but it’s a decision we made and
we’ve gotten the opportunity to build the brand as the Guardians
over the last four years and we’re excited about the future that’s
in front of us.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’d recommend going a little further and saying that everyone in the organization loves the new brand, but that’s quibbling. What the Commanders and the NFL are doing is cowardice.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Commanders : Goofus :: Guardians : Gallant’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/21/commanders-goofus-guardians-gallant">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://safebase.io/lp/why-safebase/?utm_source=daring_fireball&amp;utm_medium=display&amp;utm_campaign=18991230_sb_tc_campaign_DG_ENT_" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wh1" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/07/safebase_by_drata" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.42085</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-07-21T21:44:46Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-21T21:44:47Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Eliminate the friction of inbound security reviews. SafeBase helps you automate inbound requests, use AI to answer questionnaires, and share your security posture proactively — all through a centralized Trust Center.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘SafeBase by Drata’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/07/safebase_by_drata">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] SafeBase by Drata</title></entry><entry>
	<title>‘CBS: The Tiffany Network’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7Rv36XkQojM" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wh0" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/21/cbs-the-tiffany-network" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42084</id>
	<published>2025-07-21T20:41:02Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-21T20:41:03Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Letterman: “You can’t spell CBS without BS.”</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘CBS: The Tiffany Network’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/21/cbs-the-tiffany-network">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>HRW Report Documents Abusive Practices at Three Florida Immigration Detention Centers Since January 2025</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.hrw.org/report/2025/07/21/you-feel-like-your-life-is-over/abusive-practices-at-three-florida-immigration" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgz" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/21/hrw-ice-detention-abuse" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42083</id>
	<published>2025-07-21T18:05:36Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-21T18:05:37Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>John Holmes for Human Rights Watch (<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2025/jul/21/migrants-miami-ice-jail-abuses">via The Guardian</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>One woman described arriving at Krome — a facility that typically
<a href="https://www.oig.dhs.gov/sites/default/files/assets/2024-04/OIG-24-21-Apr24.pdf">only holds men</a> — late at night on January 28. Officers then
confined her for days with dozens of other women without bedding
or privacy, in a cell normally used only during incarceration
intake procedures. “There was only one toilet, and it was covered
in feces,” she said. “We begged the officers to let us clean it,
but they just said sarcastically, ‘Housekeeping will come soon.’
No one ever came.”</p>

<p>A man recalled the frigid conditions in the intake cell where he
was detained: “They turned up the air conditioning... You could
not fall asleep because it was so cold. I thought I was going to
experience hypothermia.”</p>

<p>This report documents serious violations of medical standards.
Detention facility staff routinely denied individuals with
diabetes, asthma, kidney conditions, and chronic pain their
prescribed medications and access to doctors. In one case at
Krome, a woman with gallstones began vomiting and lost
consciousness after being denied care for several days. Officers
returned her to the same cell after emergency surgery to remove
her gallbladder — still without medication. [...]</p>

<p>Staff were dismissive or abusive even when detainees were
undergoing a visibly obvious medical crisis. For example, staff
ignored a detained immigrant who began coughing blood in a crowded
holding cell for hours. In that case, unrest ensued, and a
Disturbance Control Team stormed the cell, forcing the men in it
to lie face down on the wet, dirty floor while officers zip-tied
their hands behind their backs. A detainee said he heard an
officer order the cell’s CCTV camera feed to be turned off.
Another detainee said a team member slapped him while shouting,
“Shut the fuck up.”</p>

<p>During another incident, officers made men eat while shackled with
their hands behind their backs after forcing the group to wait
hours for lunch: “We had to bend over and eat off the chairs with
our mouths, like dogs,” one man said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://constitution.congress.gov/constitution/amendment-8/">The Eighth Amendment of the US Constitution</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Excessive bail shall not be required, nor excessive fines imposed,
nor cruel and unusual punishments inflicted.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘HRW Report Documents Abusive Practices at Three Florida Immigration Detention Centers Since January 2025’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/21/hrw-ice-detention-abuse">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>WorkOS: Summer Launch Week</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://workos.com/launch-week/summer-2025" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgv" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/20/workos-summer-launch-week" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42079</id>
	<published>2025-07-21T02:04:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-21T02:04:09Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to WorkOS for sponsoring last week at DF to promote their summer launch week. You may recall their previous launch week <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/21/workos-launch-week">back in spring</a>, when I emphasized that their launch week announcements were worth checking out just to admire the retro-modern design of the web page. Well, they’ve done it again, with all-new retro pixel-art design. It’s so fun and well done, with a bunch of UI elements that you can play with.</p>

<p>Amidst the fun of the presentation, they once again have a slew of great new features, including:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://workos.com/blog/authkit-custom-css">Custom CSS for AuthKit</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://workos.com/blog/feature-flags">Feature Flags</a> — “Assign flags, expose them in JWTs, and roll out features with targeted control.”</li>
<li><a href="https://workos.com/blog/supabase-integration">Supabase Native Auth Integration</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://workos.com/blog/cli-auth">CLI Auth</a> — “Log in from the command line with OAuth 2.0 device grant flow”.</li>
</ul>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘WorkOS: Summer Launch Week’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/20/workos-summer-launch-week">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Mad King Watch: Trump Threatens to Interfere With Stadium Deal Unless Washington Commanders Change Name Back to ‘Redskins’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.reuters.com/sports/trump-threatens-washington-stadium-deal-unless-nfl-team-readopts-redskins-name-2025-07-20/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgy" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/20/trump-threatens-commanders" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42082</id>
	<published>2025-07-21T02:03:20Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-21T02:03:21Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Reuters, with a headline that truly could have come from The Onion, “Trump Threatens Washington Stadium Deal Unless NFL Team Readopts Redskins Name”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>U.S. President Donald Trump threatened on Sunday to interfere with
a deal to build a new football stadium in Washington, D.C., unless
the local NFL team, now known as the Commanders, changes its name
back to Redskins. The American football team dropped the name
Redskins in 2020 after decades of criticism that it was a racial
slur with links to the U.S. genocide of the Indigenous population.</p>

<p>Trump had called for a return to the name Redskins - and for the
Cleveland Guardians baseball team to once again adopt the name
Indians — on other occasions, but on Sunday he added that he may
take official action.</p>

<p>“I may put a restriction on them that if they don’t change the
name back to the original ‘Washington Redskins,’ and get rid of
the ridiculous moniker, ‘Washington Commanders,’ I won’t make a
deal for them to build a Stadium in Washington,” Trump said in a
post on his Truth Social platform.</p>

<p>The team moved from Washington to suburban Landover, Maryland, in
1997, but earlier this year reached an agreement with the local
District of Columbia government to return to the city with a new
stadium expected to open in 2030.</p>

<p>Trump has limited authority to intervene under the current
home-rule law governing federal oversight of the District of
Columbia, but he has raised the prospect of taking more control,
telling reporters in February, “I think we should take over
Washington, D.C.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It should be emphasized — and shame on Reuters for not doing so — that Trump can’t just “take control” of the District of Columbia. Per <a href="https://constitution.congress.gov/browse/article-1/section-8/">Article I, Section 8</a> of the Constitution, it’s Congressional authority that oversees the district, not the Executive branch.</p>

<p>Here are the <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/114885987478070699">two</a> <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/114887236310446076">posts</a> from his blog that got this obvious attempt to distract from his involvement with Jeffrey Epstein. (“<em>Look at me, I’m a crazy old angry racist, not a creepy old pedophile!</em>”)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Mad King Watch: Trump Threatens to Interfere With Stadium Deal Unless Washington Commanders Change Name Back to ‘Redskins’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/20/trump-threatens-commanders">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Don’t Forget About Atari</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cory.news/posts/2025-07-17-atari/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgx" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/20/dont-forget-atari" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42081</id>
	<published>2025-07-21T00:18:36Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-21T00:34:50Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Cory Ondrejka joins in on the 40-year-old retro computing reminiscing:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>For being otherwise bright folks, it’s remarkable how completely
wrong they all are. The Atari was the best computer to have.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This whole friendly debate reminds me of the oft-cited adage that the best camera is the one you have with you: The best computer in the 1980s was whichever one your parents bought you. I honestly don’t remember anyone I knew who had an Atari computer. Atari game consoles, sure — almost <em>everyone</em> I knew had a 2600, and we all coveted the 5200. <a href="https://appdot.net/@morrick/114866268850615377">But they sure were cool-looking</a>.</p>

<p>Oddly enough, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack_Tramiel">Jack Tramiel</a><sup>*</sup> — who founded and named Commodore in 1953 as a typewriter company and was running the company when it launched the PET (1977), VIC-20 (1980), and Commodore 64 (1982) — left the company after a dispute with the board in 1984 (a <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/1985/09/19/business/apple-computer-entrepreneur-s-rise-and-fall.html">common</a> industry occurrence in those days, seemingly), founded a new company briefly named Tramel Technology (not “Tramiel”, for ease of spelling), which bought the then-failing consumer business of Atari from Warner Communications and took the Atari name for its own. In 1985 Tramiel <a href="https://www.goto10retro.com/p/atari-st-40th-anniversary">launched the Atari ST line at CES</a>. To me the 16-bit Atari ST barely registers in my memory — I don’t think I ever encountered one anywhere, including in a store. When I think of Atari personal computers I think of the <a href="https://www.goto10retro.com/p/atari-st-40th-anniversary">8-bit Atari 800</a> (pretty cool!) and 400 (horrible — perhaps <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7CnYI0E_6mk">the worst keyboard ever shipped</a>) from 1979.</p>

<p>(Anyway, neither of those aforecited adages are really true, though. Some cameras are much better than others. And the best computers back then were the Apple II’s.)</p>

<p><small>* Just me or was <a href="https://duckduckgo.com/?t=h_&amp;q=jack+tramiel&amp;ia=images&amp;iax=images">Tramiel a dead ringer</a> for character actor <a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0432410/">Gordon Jump</a>, of <em>WKRP in Cincinnati</em> fame?</small></p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Don’t Forget About Atari’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/20/dont-forget-atari">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The WSJ on Late Night TV’s Ad Revenue Decline, and CBS’s Decision to Cancel The Late Show</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.wsj.com/business/media/stephen-colbert-late-show-canceled-profit-3dcc48a2?st=TT3iun" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgw" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/20/wsj-late-night-ad-revenue" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42080</id>
	<published>2025-07-20T20:59:37Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-21T00:36:35Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Joe Flint and John Jurgensen, reporting for The Wall Street Journal (gift link):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>But digital advertising revenue hasn’t made up for the fall in ad
dollars going to traditional broadcast programming. Spending on
linear advertising for the late-night segment on ABC, CBS and NBC
fell from $439 million in 2018 to $221 million in 2024, according
to Guideline, an ad-tracking platform.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That’s a precipitous decline, if accurate. But still, given that Colbert’s <em>The Late Show</em> has consistently been the highest-rated overall and tied with ABC’s <em>Jimmy Kimmel Live</em> for the 18–49 year-old demographic, it feels very safe to presume that it generated at least a full third — say, $75–80 million — of that $221 million total. It’s reported that Colbert’s salary is $20 million per year, and Colbert himself said the other night the show employs 200 staff.</p>

<p>If, as anonymous CBS sources are claiming to multiple outlets, the show lost $40 million last year, that means it costs something on the order of $120 million per year to produce, or $100 million after Colbert’s salary. With a staff of 200 people, that’s an <em>average</em> salary of $500,000. I know it costs money to heat and cool the Ed Sullivan theater, and I’m sure there are other costs. But there is no way the average salary of a staff member on the show is half a million per year.</p>

<p>And, even if somehow <em>The Late Show</em> <em>did</em> lose money last year, it seems implausible that CBS wouldn’t first ask for budget cuts — staff reductions, a salary cut for Colbert, whatever else might possibly be running up a $120 million/year budget — before just shutting the whole thing down. NBC’s <em>Late Night With Seth Meyers</em> <a href="https://variety.com/2024/tv/news/seth-meyers-late-night-8g-band-budget-cuts-1236034409/">sadly cut the live studio band last year</a>, for example. $75 million per year in ad revenue is way down from its <a href="https://nypost.com/2015/08/23/colberts-late-show-ready-to-challenge-fallons-ad-revenue/">Letterman era heyday</a>, but that’s surely more than enough to produce a talk show. Also, all of this back-of-the-napkin budget analysis neglects to assign any promotional value to the show. CBS gets to promote everything else on the network to over 2 million people per night with house ads during commercial breaks and guests on the show from other CBS programs.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The WSJ on Late Night TV’s Ad Revenue Decline, and CBS’s Decision to Cancel The Late Show’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/20/wsj-late-night-ad-revenue">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Myke Hurley Interviews Yours Truly for the Cortex ‘State of the Workflow’ Series</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theenthusiast.net/john-gruber-state-of-the-workflow/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgt" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/19/cortex-hurley-interview-with-yours-truly" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42077</id>
	<published>2025-07-19T16:25:18Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-19T16:25:18Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Myke Hurley:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>For this episode, I took a slightly different approach for the
main section, following step-by-step how John writes and publishes
an article. I think this is a template I want to follow with
future guests, taking a detailed look at what they do from
beginning to end.</p>

<p>I’m so pleased with how this interview turned out — I actually
think it may be one of the best of my career. I’ve never had the
chance to have a one-on-one podcast with John before, and I’m
happy we waited until now to make it happen.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We spoke for a long time, and at some point like halfway through, it really hit me that Hurley was asking <em>really</em> good questions. If you’re interested in how I work and the tools I use, you should enjoy listening to this interview as much as I enjoyed participating in it.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Myke Hurley Interviews Yours Truly for the Cortex ‘State of the Workflow’ Series’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/19/cortex-hurley-interview-with-yours-truly">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Puck: ‘Was Colbert’s Cancellation Really “Economic” for CBS?’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://puck.news/was-colberts-cancellation-really-economic-for-cbs/?sharer=167184&amp;token=9a8ea7a6fea9e13d6d23eaf8102f68d3" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgs" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/19/belloni-colbert-economic" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42076</id>
	<published>2025-07-19T16:17:18Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-21T00:37:19Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Matthew Belloni, writing at Puck (paywall-busting gift link) regarding the claim from anonymous CBS sources that <em>The Late Show</em> lost $40 million last year:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Nobody can know for sure. All I can tell you is what I’m hearing.
Several sources at both CBS and Skydance insist the decision was
based on economics, not politics. After all, if this was about
appeasing Trump, they argue, Cheeks would have pulled Colbert off
the air ASAP rather than giving him 10 more months in the chair.
“Trust me, there’s no conspiracy,” a very good source close to
Colbert told me tonight. Still, two other people with deep ties to
CBS and <em>Late Show</em> suspect otherwise. After all, when a network
decides that a show is too expensive, executives typically go to
the key talent and ask them to take pay cuts, fire people, or
otherwise slash costs. That didn’t happen here — though with
Colbert said to be making between $15 million and $20 million per
year, a pay cut wouldn’t have solved the problem on its own. And
given the company’s willingness to fold to Trump, there’s no
reason for you or me to think they would stand up to any political
pressure, or resist any specific demand (which, of course, is the
reason to not settle frivolous litigation…). If Chris McCarthy,
Cheeks’s counterpart on the cable TV side, cancels <em>The Daily
Show</em> in the next couple weeks, I think we’ll have a good idea
what’s going on. But for now, I cautiously (and skeptically)
believe that this was mostly an economic decision.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Puck: ‘Was Colbert’s Cancellation Really “Economic” for CBS?’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/19/belloni-colbert-economic">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>ChatGPT Agent</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://openai.com/index/introducing-chatgpt-agent/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgr" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/18/chatgpt-agent" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42075</id>
	<published>2025-07-19T01:03:34Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-19T01:03:34Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>OpenAI:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You can now ask ChatGPT to handle requests like “look at my
calendar and brief me on upcoming client meetings based on recent
news,” “plan and buy ingredients to make Japanese breakfast for
four,” and “analyze three competitors and create a slide deck.”
ChatGPT will intelligently navigate websites, filter results,
prompt you to log in securely when needed, run code, conduct
analysis, and even deliver editable slideshows and spreadsheets
that summarize its findings.</p>

<p>At the core of this new capability is a unified agentic system. It
brings together three strengths of earlier breakthroughs:
<a href="https://openai.com/index/introducing-operator/"><em>Operator’s</em> </a> ability to interact with websites, <a href="https://openai.com/index/introducing-deep-research/"><em>deep
research’s</em> </a> skill in synthesizing information, and ChatGPT’s
intelligence and conversational fluency.</p>

<p>ChatGPT carries out these tasks using its own virtual computer,
fluidly shifting between reasoning and action to handle complex
workflows from start to finish, all based on your instructions.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Impressive examples in the embedded videos in the post.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘ChatGPT Agent’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/18/chatgpt-agent">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Billionaire Jackass Bill Ackman Bought His Way Into Playing in a Legit Professional Tennis Tournament and, Shockingly, He Embarrassed Himself and Everyone Involved With Letting Him Play</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.youtube.com/shorts/L7NqTpnSQWo" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgq" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/18/ackman-tennis-jackass" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42074</id>
	<published>2025-07-18T23:59:11Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-18T23:59:55Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Real athletes get <em>30 For 30</em> documentaries; fake athletes get fake ones. Not sure which are more enjoyable.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Billionaire Jackass Bill Ackman Bought His Way Into Playing in a Legit Professional Tennis Tournament and, Shockingly, He Embarrassed Himself and Everyone Involved With Letting Him Play’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/18/ackman-tennis-jackass">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/07/curse_not_the_king_cbs_colbert_trump" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wgp" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42073</id>
	<published>2025-07-18T23:28:19Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-21T03:06:37Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Why CBS’s cancellation of “The Late Show With Stephen Colbert” stinks to high hell.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<h2>Why CBS’s Cancellation of “The Late Show With Stephen Colbert” Stinks to High Hell</h2>

<p>Even back in the now-comparatively-sane Trump 1.0 administration, it seemed palpably true to me that the best check against Trump’s authoritarian instincts wasn’t legal or Constitutional, but rather cultural. The culture of free speech, of being able to criticize — in no uncertain terms, with no held punches — anyone in authority is fundamental to the American mindset. It’s like the opening of David Foster Wallace’s “This Is Water” 2005 commencement address to Kenyon College:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Greetings parents and congratulations to Kenyon’s graduating class
of 2005. There are these two young fish swimming along and they
happen to meet an older fish swimming the other way, who nods at
them and says “Morning, boys. How’s the water?” And the two young
fish swim on for a bit, and then eventually one of them looks over
at the other and goes “What the hell is water?”</p>

<p>This is a standard requirement of US commencement speeches, the
deployment of didactic little parable-ish stories. The story thing
turns out to be one of the better, less bullshitty conventions of
the genre, but if you’re worried that I plan to present myself
here as the wise, older fish explaining what water is to you
younger fish, please don’t be. I am not the wise old fish. The
point of the fish story is merely that the most obvious, important
realities are often the ones that are hardest to see and talk
about. Stated as an English sentence, of course, this is just a
banal platitude, but the fact is that in the day to day trenches
of adult existence, banal platitudes can have a life or death
importance, or so I wish to suggest to you on this dry and lovely
morning.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In the way that fish take water for granted, Americans take <a href="https://xkcd.com/1357/">true freedom of speech</a> and freedom of the press for granted. It’s the culture we were born into, the air we breathe. And to my mind, the fiercest and most effective form of criticism — especially political — is mockery. Mark Twain, America’s first great (and perhaps still greatest) humorist, said, “Against the assault of laughter, nothing can stand.”</p>

<p>No one in Russian media mocks Vladimir Putin, lest they find themselves falling out one of <a href="https://www.newsweek.com/full-list-russians-fall-windows-putin-ukraine-war-1781790">Russia’s easily-fallen-out-of windows</a>. No one in Chinese media mocks Xi Jinping. Back in 2017 the CCP went as far as to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Censorship_of_Winnie-the-Pooh_in_China">censor images of Winnie the Pooh</a>, because Xi resembles Pooh so clearly, and people naturally find that amusing. Trump, clearly, has authoritarian instincts and desires, but US media — print, web, podcasts, YouTube, social, and TV — has been replete with unrelenting mockery aimed at him. There’s no better example of that than late night talk shows: Colbert on CBS, Jimmy Kimmel on ABC, Seth Meyers on NBC, Jon Stewart and his fellow hosts on <em>The Daily Show</em> at Comedy Central, John Oliver and Bill Maher on HBO. Vociferous, unrelenting critics of Trump, all of them. (And it works both ways: Greg Gutfield’s <em>Gutfield!</em> is <a href="https://www.tvinsider.com/1202434/late-night-ratings-2025-gutfeld-kimmel-colbert-fallon/">a ratings success at 10:00pm for Fox News</a>.)</p>

<p>That’s been one of the canaries I’ve been monitoring in the Trump 2.0 drift-into-authoritarianism coal mine. So long as Trump is getting skewered by comedians on major TV channels nightly, in some sense, we’re doing OK.</p>

<p>But while our Constitution and cultural fabric protect our media from <em>government</em> interference, there’s no such protection from <em>ownership</em> interference. Trump can’t dictate what a newspaper prints — proven again, just last night, by The Wall Street Journal, which added significant fuel to the Epstein fire that’s rupturing MAGAland with <a href="https://www.wsj.com/politics/trump-jeffrey-epstein-birthday-letter-we-have-certain-things-in-common-f918d796?mod=hp_lead_pos7">a scoop on a dirty birthday letter Trump wrote to his friend Epstein in 2003</a>, despite Trump trying to quash the story by <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2025/07/17/media/trump-rupert-murdoch-wsj-epstein-story-lawsuit-threat">directly calling Journal owner Rupert Murdoch</a>. Trump can’t dictate who hosts late-night TV shows or censor the jokes they tell, and we still seem far from a world where Jimmy Kimmel might mysteriously “fall” from a high window.</p>

<p>But the owners, they can do what they want. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2024/10/profiles_in_cowardice_bezos_lewis_washington_post">Jeff Bezos kiboshed The Washington Post’s already-written endorsement of Kamala Harris</a> — on the cusp of the election — and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2024/12/journalism_requires_owners_committed_to_the_cause">torched the paper’s previously sterling reputation</a> of independence and journalistic integrity. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2024/12/13/soon-shiong-la-times">Patrick Soon-Shiong has done similar</a> to the LA Times.</p>

<p>CBS is owned by Paramount, and Paramount is controlled by Shari Redstone. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Proposed_merger_of_Skydance_Media_and_Paramount_Global">Redstone has a deal to sell Paramount to Skydance</a>, a company controlled by David Ellison (son of Oracle gazillionaire Larry Ellison) for $8 billion, but the deal needs approval from the FCC, and the FCC answers to Trump. That’s why CBS settled a bullshit lawsuit by Trump against <em>60 Minutes</em> for $16 million. As former <em>60 Minutes</em> correspondent <a href="https://www.tvinsider.com/1201084/trump-cbs-news-60-minutes-steve-kroft-jon-stewart-daily-show/">Steve Kroft told Jon Stewart</a> (righteously, on Paramount-owned Comedy Central) regarding the “settlement”: “They never said, ‘We screwed up.’ They just paid the money. It was a shakedown, that’s what I call it. Some people call it extortion, that’s a legal term.”</p>

<p><a href="https://nypost.com/2025/07/02/media/how-secret-side-deal-helped-seal-paramounts-16m-settlement-with-trump/">The New York Post reported two weeks ago</a> that the official settlement is only half the deal, however:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Shari Redstone’s Paramount received an unusual assist to settle
its controversial lawsuit with President Trump, which should now
clear the way for its long-awaited sale to independent studio
Skydance, On The Money has learned.</p>

<p>Skydance boss David Ellison, the son of Trump friend and
billionaire Oracle co-founder Larry Ellison, stepped up and agreed
that once he takes control of the Tiffany Network, currently part
of Redstone’s flailing media empire, it will run between $15
million and $20 million of public service ads to promote causes
supported by the president, a source with knowledge of the
negotiations said.</p>

<p>“There is an anticipation of a mid-eight-figure sum that will be
allocated by the network to PSA advertisements and other broadcast
transmissions that support conservative causes supported by
President Trump,” the source said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It made no sense journalistically or financially for CBS to settle Trump’s lawsuit. <em>60 Minutes</em> clearly did nothing ethically wrong, let alone illegal, with its editing of Kamala Harris’s interview.<sup id="fnr1-2025-07-18"><a href="#fn1-2025-07-18">1</a></sup> It only makes sense as a de facto payoff to Trump to help secure approval of Skydance’s acquisition of Paramount. Likewise with CBS’s decision not just to part ways with Colbert as host, but to cease production of <em>The Late Show</em> entirely. It makes no TV sense. <em>The Late Show</em> isn’t just doing OK in the ratings, it’s the top show in the 11:30 timeslot. Here’s Jed Rosenzweig, <a href="https://latenighter.com/news/ratings/late-night-tv-ratings-q2-2025/">writing for LateNighter just four days ago</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>As the second quarter of 2025 wrapped, late-night’s pecking order
held mostly steady — with The Late Show with Stephen Colbert
topping the 11:35 PM hour in total viewers, and Late Night with
Seth Meyers leading at 12:37 AM across both key ratings metrics.</p>

<p>CBS’s <em>Late Show</em> was the only show among the nine tracked by
LateNighter to draw more total viewers in Q2 than it had in the
first quarter of 2025 — although just barely, with the show
growing its audience by 1% quarter over quarter. All told, the
Stephen Colbert-hosted show averaged 2.42 million viewers across
41 first-run episodes, comfortably outpacing ABC’s <em>Jimmy Kimmel
Live</em> (1.77 million) and NBC’s <em>The Tonight Show Starring Jimmy
Fallon</em> (1.19 million). In the advertiser-coveted 18–49 demo,
however, Kimmel surged ahead with 220,000 viewers — his strongest
performance in a year — edging out Colbert (219,000) and leaving
Fallon (at 157,000) in a distant third.</p>

<p>At 12:37 AM, <em>Late Night With Seth Meyers</em> continued its quiet
reign. The NBC mainstay averaged 900,000 total viewers and
111,000 in the demo across 35 episodes — easily topping both
metrics in the late-late slot. ABC’s <em>Nightline</em> held second
place with 810,000 total viewers and 108,000 in the demo, putting
it ahead of CBS’s <em>After Midnight</em>, which ended its two-year run
in early June with an average of 591,000 total viewers and 89,000
in the 18–49 demo.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So Colbert’s <em>Late Show</em> is the highest-rated overall, and effectively tied with Kimmel in the advertiser-coveted 18–49 demo.<sup id="fnr2-2025-07-18"><a href="#fn2-2025-07-18">2</a></sup> Like all of traditional TV, late night viewership — and thus revenue — isn’t what it used to be. (For context, through the end of the 1990s and into the 2000s, Letterman and Leno <a href="https://www.deseret.com/2000/1/23/19487374/late-show-scores-ratings-victory-vs-leno/">each drew around 4–6 million viewers per night</a>. Johnny Carson averaged over 10 million viewers per night in the 1970s and 80s.) CBS declaring in its announcement that “This is purely a financial decision against a challenging backdrop in late night” is obvious bullshit — and, <a href="https://politicalwire.com/2025/07/18/trump-gets-a-win-in-the-culture-wars/">in light of its timing</a>, extra stinky bullshit at that. Surely the top-rated show in late night isn’t just at least profitable, but almost certainly more profitable than whatever CBS might replace it with in that time slot. (CBS sources suddenly claim <em>The Late Show</em> <a href="https://puck.news/was-colberts-cancellation-really-economic-for-cbs/">lost $40 million last year</a>; <a href="https://latenighter.com/features/cbs-cites-costs-in-colbert-cancellation-the-timing-tells-a-different-story/">Bill Carter isn’t buying that</a> and neither should you.)</p>

<p>The TV industry has always been obsessed with ratings and obsessed with advertising revenue. I can’t recall the top-rated show in any category being cancelled. Again, it makes no TV sense. It doesn’t pass the sniff test. Back in December, regarding the Bezos-driven upheaval at The Washington Post, I wrote a piece titled “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2024/12/journalism_requires_owners_committed_to_the_cause">Journalism Requires Owners Committed to the Cause</a>”, which title sort of says it all. The only proper way to run a serious newspaper is for the work and reputation of the newspaper itself to be the topmost priority of everyone in leadership, right up to the owner. That’s just clearly not true for Bezos. And part of it too is that the entire business of The Washington Post just doesn’t matter to Bezos. Jeff Bezos has a net worth of around $230 <em>billion</em>. He bought the Post from its longtime owners, the Graham family (who <em>were</em> <a href="https://www.nyhistory.org/blogs/lets-go-lets-publish-katharine-graham-and-the-pentagon-papers">owners committed to the cause</a>) in 2013 for just $250 <em>million</em>. Financially, the entire Washington Post Company represents like one-thousandth of Bezos’s wealth. Trashing the paper’s reputation and the trust of its readers meant less to him than cozying up to Trump for potential trade policy favors for Amazon and <a href="https://www.wsj.com/business/jeff-bezos-trump-blue-origin-9f5ac75b?st=jo2tkC">rocketry deals for Blue Origin</a>.</p>

<p>It’s exactly the same for David Ellison. His father, Larry Ellison, is even wealthier than Bezos, with <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/dereksaul/2025/06/13/larry-ellison-40-billion-richer---surpassing-bezos-and-zuckerberg---as-oracle-stock-mounts-big-rally/">Forbes estimating his worth above $250 billion</a> after recent Oracle stock price gains. In normal times, with a normal US president (that is to say, not crooked), and a normal incoming buyer of a major television network (that is to say, concerned with ratings and ad revenue) it would be insane for the network to cancel the top-rated late night show just before the deal is finalized. But David Ellison doesn’t give a shit how much money CBS makes at 11:30 and doesn’t care about the three-decade legacy of The Late Show or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ed_Sullivan_Theater">the storied history</a> of the theater in which it’s produced each night. Cancelling this particular hit show isn’t poison to the deal for Skydance to buy Paramount — it’s a sweetener. I missed this at the time, but Oliver Darcy, media reporter extraordinaire, called it at Status (paywalled, alas) <a href="https://www.status.news/p/skydance-colbert-stewart-ellison">just over a week ago</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Jon Stewart opened Monday’s episode of <em>The Daily Show</em> not
mincing words, calling Paramount’s settlement with Donald Trump
“shameful.” Just as he was digging in, a fake Arby’s ad suddenly
appeared on screen, as if to cut him off mid-rant for criticizing
Comedy Central’s parent company. “Did they? Son of a bitch!”
Stewart exclaimed, playing along with the bit — yet nodding to a
deeper fear that his commentary might soon be silenced amid all
the corporate upheaval.</p>

<p>Later in the episode, Stewart continued to needle Paramount,
sitting down with former <em>60 Minutes</em> correspondent Steve Kroft
for a candid and unsparing conversation. Kroft described the
settlement in clear terms: “It was a shakedown.” Inside “The Daily
Show,” I’m told staffers have taken pride that Stewart showed once
again he is willing to stand up to powerful interests, even if it
potentially risks his future employment. And while they may not
yet know it, inside certain power circles, there is an open
question: How much longer will Stewart have this platform?</p>

<p>Indeed, the reality is that the ground under not only Stewart, but
also Stephen Colbert, is shifting fast. Skydance, led by Larry and
David Ellison, now believes its merger with Paramount will close
in the next several weeks, I’m told. Much of the attention has
focused on how the Ellisons will reshape <em>60 Minutes</em> and CBS
News. We first reported that David Ellison met with Bari Weiss
about a possible role at CBS News, and it is clear the Ellisons
want to rid the network of what they see as a liberal taint. But
little has been said about the futures of Colbert and Stewart, who
have been two of Trump’s most consistent comedic antagonists,
under the new corporate leadership. [...]</p>

<p>As one media insider put it to me this week, “What better gift
could [the Ellisons] give Trump than to get rid of Colbert and
Stewart?”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The first shoe dropped at CBS last night. TV-wise, it’d be crazy for Paramount to drop Jon Stewart too. But dropping Colbert is even crazier, and they already did that. It’s not tyranny or the threat of state violence that is taking <em>The Late Show With Stephen Colbert</em> off the air, but rather oligarchy and unchecked cronyism and corruption. The breathtaking abdication we’re seeing at CBS — first news with <em>60 Minutes</em>, now commentary and humor with <em>The Late Show</em> — signals a decidedly American descent into <a href="https://www.biblegateway.com/verse/en/Ecclesiastes%2010%3A20">curse-not-the-king</a> mass media acquiescence to Trump’s authoritarian hostility to criticism and dissent.</p>

<h2>Postscript</h2>

<p><a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/114874422468516376">Here’s Trump on his blog this morning</a>, heralding the news with his usual grace, equanimity, and factual accuracy:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I absolutely love that Colbert’ [<em>sic</em>] got fired. His talent was even
less than his ratings. I hear Jimmy Kimmel is next. Has even less
talent than Colbert! Greg Gutfeld is better than all of them
combined, including the Moron on NBC who ruined the once great
Tonight Show.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I will admit that it’s kind of funny that he didn’t even deign to address Fallon by name, especially since Fallon is the one who <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kIGcosb22_Y">did the most</a> to normalize Trump’s aberrant candidacy in 2016.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>

<li id="fn1-2025-07-18">
<p>If any interview with a 2024 presidential candidate was edited deceptively to help the candidate in question, it was <a href="https://www.yahoo.com/news/fox-news-trump-interview-resurfaces-164913528.html">this Fox News interview with Trump</a>, which resurfaced this month amidst the Jeffrey Epstein imbroglio. Fox grossly truncated a glaringly evasive answer from Trump regarding whether, if re-elected, he would release all DOJ files related to Epstein.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-07-18"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>

<li id="fn2-2025-07-18">
<p>Which hurts slightly to write about, insofar as I’ve aged out of the demo personally. Now I’m a non-coveted TV watcher — but one who’s skipped all the commercials on late night shows for 25 years anyway.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr2-2025-07-18"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
</li>

</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Curse Not the King</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Apple Sues Jon Prosser Over iOS 26 Leaks</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/07/17/apple-sues-jon-prosser-ios-26-leaks/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgo" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/18/apple-sues-prosser" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42072</id>
	<published>2025-07-18T20:36:52Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-18T21:34:15Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Eric Slivka, reporting last night for MacRumors:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>While the Camera app redesign didn’t exactly match what Apple
unveiled for iOS 26, the general idea was correct and much of
what else Prosser showed was pretty close to spot on, and Apple
clearly took notice as the company filed a lawsuit today (<a href="https://www.scribd.com/document/889709146/Apple-v-Ramacciotti-and-Prosser">Scribd
link</a>) against Prosser and Michael Ramacciotti for
misappropriation of trade secrets.</p>

<p>Apple’s complaint outlines what it claims is the series of events
that led to the leaks, which centered around a development iPhone
in the possession of Ramacciotti’s friend and Apple employee Ethan
Lipnik. According to Apple, Prosser and Ramacciotti plotted to
access Lipnik’s phone, acquiring his passcode and then using
location-tracking to determine when he “would be gone for an
extended period.” Prosser reportedly offered financial
compensation to Ramacciotti in return for assisting with accessing
the development iPhone.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Lipnik, the Apple employee, was fired, but isn’t named in the lawsuit because seemingly all he did was improperly secure his device running an early build of iOS 26. That’s against company policy, but not against the law.</p>

<p>Prosser, on X, <a href="https://x.com/jon_prosser/status/1946056858474525097">disputes the description of his involvement in Apple’s lawsuit</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>For the record: This is not how the situation played out on my
end. Luckily have receipts for that.</p>

<p>I did not “plot” to access anyone’s phone. I did not have any
passwords. I was unaware of how the information was obtained.</p>

<p>Looking forward to speaking with Apple on this.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Prosser also shared <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/07/prosser-signal-screenshot.jpeg">one screenshot</a> of his Signal message correspondence with Ramacciotti.</p>

<p>(MacRumors’s copy of Apple’s lawsuit is <a href="https://www.scribd.com/document/889709146/Apple-v-Ramacciotti-and-Prosser">hosted at Scribd</a>, which is free to read in a browser, but requires a paid account to download the original PDF. I’m <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/07/889709146-Apple-v-Ramacciotti-and-Prosser.pdf">hosting a copy of the PDF here</a>.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Sues Jon Prosser Over iOS 26 Leaks’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/18/apple-sues-prosser">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Network Pinheads at CBS Are Ending ‘The Late Show’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.instagram.com/reel/DMOhWKsxT_G/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgn" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/17/cbs-pinheads-colbert-ending" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42071</id>
	<published>2025-07-18T00:39:15Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-21T00:38:33Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The above links to an Instagram reel with Colbert breaking the news at the start of his show airing tonight. Here’s <a href="https://twitter.com/latenightercom/status/1945993251938549803">the same clip on X</a>, if you prefer. He, apparently, was as surprised as anyone.</p>

<p><a href="https://latenighter.com/news/cbs-cancels-the-late-show-with-stephen-colbert-show-to-end-in-may-2026/">Here’s Jed Rosenzweig’s story at (the excellent) LateNighter</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“<em>The Late Show with Stephen Colbert</em> will end its historic run in
May 2026 at the end of the broadcast season,” the network said in
a statement. “We consider Stephen Colbert irreplaceable and will
retire <em>The Late Show</em> franchise at that time. We are proud that
Stephen called CBS home. He and the broadcast will be remembered
in the pantheon of greats that graced late night television.”</p>

<p>The statement was issued jointly by George Cheeks (Co-CEO of
Paramount Global and President and CEO of CBS), Amy Reisenbach
(President of CBS Entertainment), and David Stapf (President of
CBS Studios).</p>

<p>CBS emphasized that the decision was not related to performance or
content: “This is purely a financial decision against a
challenging backdrop in late night. It is not related in any way
to the show’s performance, content or other matters happening at
Paramount.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This stinks to high hell. Colbert has the best ratings in late night TV.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Network Pinheads at CBS Are Ending ‘The Late Show’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/17/cbs-pinheads-colbert-ending">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Rare Earth Magnet Maker MP Materials Is Having a Big Week</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/07/10/pentagon-to-become-largest-shareholder-in-rare-earth-magnet-maker-mp-materials.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgm" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/16/mp-materials-big-week" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42070</id>
	<published>2025-07-16T19:14:27Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-16T19:30:42Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Spencer Kimball, reporting for CNBC one week ago:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The Defense Department will become the largest shareholder in rare
earth miner MP Materials after <a href="https://investors.mpmaterials.com/investor-news/news-details/2025/MP-Materials-Announces-Transformational-Public-Private-Partnership-with-the-Department-of-Defense-to-Accelerate-U-S--Rare-Earth-Magnet-Independence/default.aspx">agreeing to buy $400 million of
its preferred stock</a>, the company said Thursday.</p>

<p>MP Materials owns the only operational rare earth mine in the U.S.
at Mountain Pass, California, about 60 miles outside Las Vegas.
Proceeds from the Pentagon investment will be used to expand MP’s
rare earths processing capacity and magnet production, the company
said. Shares of MP Materials soared about 50% to close at $45.23.
Its market capitalization grew to $7.4 billion, an increase of
about $2.5 billion from the previous trading session. [...]</p>

<p>MP Materials CEO James Litinsky described the Pentagon investment
as a public-private partnership that will speed the buildout of an
end-to-end rare earth magnet supply chain in the U.S.</p>

<p>“I want to be very clear, this is not a nationalization,” Litinsky
told CNBC’s “Squawk on the Street” on Thursday. “We remain a
thriving public company. We now have a great new partner in our
economically largest shareholder, DoD, but we still control our
company. We control our destiny. We’re shareholder driven.” U.S.
miners are facing a unique threat from “Chinese mercantilism,”
Litinsky said. The Pentagon investment in MP could serve as a
model for similar deals with other U.S. companies, the CEO said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This news caught my eye when Taegan Goddard <a href="https://politicalwire.com/2025/07/15/pentagon-buys-into-rare-earth-miner/">linked to it from Political Wire</a> yesterday (quipping, “I’m old enough to remember when this was called ‘socialism’”), because yesterday MP Materials landed a $500 million deal from Apple. <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2025/07/apple-expands-us-supply-chain-with-500-million-usd-commitment/">Apple Newsroom</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Today Apple announced a new commitment of $500 million with MP
Materials, the only fully integrated rare earth producer in the
United States. With this multiyear deal, Apple is committed to
buying American-made rare earth magnets developed at MP Materials’
flagship Independence facility in Fort Worth, Texas. The two
companies will also work together to establish a cutting-edge rare
earth recycling line in Mountain Pass, California, and develop
novel magnet materials and innovative processing technologies to
enhance magnet performance. The commitment is part of Apple’s
pledge to spend more than $500 billion in the U.S. over the next
four years, and builds on the company’s long history of investment
in American innovation, advanced manufacturing, and
next-generation recycling technologies. [...]</p>

<p>When complete, the new recycling facility in Mountain Pass,
California will enable MP Materials to take in recycled rare earth
feedstock — including material from used electronics and
post-industrial scrap — and reprocess it for use in Apple
products. For nearly five years, Apple and MP Materials have been
piloting advanced recycling technology that enables recycled rare
earth magnets to be processed into material that meets Apple’s
exacting standards for performance and design. The companies will
continue to innovate together to improve magnet production, as
well as end-of-life recovery.</p>

<p>Apple pioneered the use of recycled rare earth elements in
consumer electronics, first introducing them in the Taptic Engine
of iPhone 11 in 2019. Today, nearly all magnets across Apple
devices are made with 100 percent recycled rare earth elements.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The timing of these two announcements could be purely coincidental, but I can’t help but wonder if both moves were fueled by concerns about China cornering the market on rare earth magnets. Conversely, I wonder if this deal (and promotion of it) from Apple is aimed just to placate the Trump administration. A $500 million commitment is surely a big deal for MP Materials. It’s not that big a deal for Apple. What makes it interesting is that it’s with an American company.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Rare Earth Magnet Maker MP Materials Is Having a Big Week’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/16/mp-materials-big-week">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>More on Commodore, Apple, and the Inchoate Personal Computer Era</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sixcolors.com/link/2025/07/commodore-apple-and-the-early-computer-days/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgl" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/16/snell-commodore-apple" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42069</id>
	<published>2025-07-16T16:39:24Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-16T20:12:06Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jason Snell:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>If you find yourself walking down the street in the 1980s and you
see someone coming who prefers the VIC-20 to the Apple II, cross
to the other side of the street. (That said, the VIC-20 really was
revolutionary. It was by far the most affordable home computer
anyone had ever seen at that point. It was laughably underpowered
… but: it was only $300! They sold a million of ’em.)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Snell takes issue (correctly!) with <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/15/saur-c64">Drew Saur’s framing</a> of the Apple II <a href="https://theprogressivecio.com/the-commodore-64-made-a-difference/">as “corporate”</a>. As Snell points out, Commodore was founded by a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack_Tramiel">suit</a> — Apple was founded by <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/how-steve-jobs-met-steve-wozniak-2014-12">two guys</a> whose first collaboration was <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2013/02/the-definitive-story-of-steve-wozniak-steve-jobs-and-phone-phreaking/273331/">making phone-phreaking blue boxes</a>.</p>

<p>But a more pertinent point was made <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@drdrang/114860309297062759">by Dr. Drang on Mastodon</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I don’t want to get on the bad side of @gruber and @jsnell, but
when they say the Commodore 64 cost $600, that’s misleading. Yes,
it cost $600 when it was released, but its price dropped quickly.
By the time I bought one in late ’83 or early ’84, it was selling
for $200 at Kmart. To recognize that it was a great computer for
the price, you have to know what that price really was.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>When <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/14/commodore-64-ultimate">I wrote the other day</a> that the C64 cost $600, it didn’t jibe with my memory. But my thinking is too set in the ways of Apple, where a computer debuts at a price and then stays at that price. A price around $200 is more what I remember for the C64, at a time when a bare-bones IIe cost $1,400. Inflation-adjusted, $200 in 1984 is about $620 today, and $1,400 is about $4,300. <em>That’s</em> why so many more kids of my era got their parents to spring for a Commodore 64 but not an Apple II. They were rivals in some sense, but really, the Apple II was a different class of computer, and cost nearly an order of magnitude more. Inflation-adjusted, it’s very similar to the difference in both price and capabilities of the Meta Quest versus Vision Pro.</p>

<p>(Me, I didn’t own a computer until I went to college. My parents wouldn’t buy me one because they feared if they did, I’d never leave the house. I resented it at the time, but in hindsight, they might have been right. I didn’t fight too hard because we had an Atari 2600 and a generous budget for game cartridges. Plus, my grade school had a few Apple IIe’s (alongside a bunch of cheap <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TI-99/4A">TI-99/4A</a>’s), and my middle/high school had an entire lab of Apple IIe’s and IIc’s.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘More on Commodore, Apple, and the Inchoate Personal Computer Era’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/16/snell-commodore-apple">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Drew Saur’s Ode to the Commodore 64</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://theprogressivecio.com/the-commodore-64-made-a-difference/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgk" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/15/saur-c64" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42068</id>
	<published>2025-07-15T23:29:47Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-22T16:13:01Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Drew Saur, pushing back on <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/14/commodore-64-ultimate">my post</a> slagging on the Commodore 64:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I cannot argue with your nostalgia. It is uniquely yours.</p>

<p>That said: The Commodore 64 as cheap-feeling and inelegant! Oh my.</p>

<p>I was fourteen when the Commodore 64 came out, and I want to
convey — in as brief a form as I can — why it captured so many
hearts during the 8-bit era.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>What a great post. Fond memories all the way down the stack with that whole era of computing. As I told Saur in email, my fondest memory of the Commodore 64 is that they sold them at Kmart, and for years had a working model on display. And every time I’d go to Kmart with my mom, I’d swing by the electronics department and type:</p>

<pre><code>10 PRINT "KMART SUCKS!!!!"
20 GOTO 10
RUN
</code></pre>

<p>Sometimes I’d be clever and do something like add an incrementing number of spaces to make the lines go diagonally. Something like:</p>

<pre><code>5 LET X = 0
10 PRINT SPC(X); "KMART SUCKS!"
20 X = X + 1
30 IF X &gt; 28 THEN X = 0
35 FOR T = 0 TO 100 : NEXT : REM SLOW DOWN
40 GOTO 10
RUN
</code></pre>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/07/kmart-sucks.png">This</a> never got old for me. <a href="https://c64online.com/c64-online-emulator/">Try it yourself</a>. (And of course I never actually commented my code at Kmart — that <code>REM</code> is for you, if you’re wondering what that do-nothing <code>FOR</code> loop is for.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Drew Saur’s Ode to the Commodore 64’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/15/saur-c64">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://workos.com/?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wgj" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/07/workos_scalable_secure_authent_6" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.42067</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-07-15T19:33:53Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-15T19:33:53Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>With WorkOS you can start selling to enterprises with just a few lines of code. It provides a complete User Management solution along with SSO, SCIM, and FGA. The APIs are modular and easy-to-use, allowing integrations to be completed in minutes instead of months.</p>

<p>Today, some of the fastest growing startups are already powered by WorkOS, including Perplexity, Vercel, and Webflow.</p>

<p>For SaaS apps that care deeply about design and user experience, WorkOS is the perfect fit. From high-quality documentation to self-serve onboarding for your customers, it removes all the unnecessary complexity for your engineering team.</p>

<p>Check out our <a href="https://workos.com/launch-week/summer-2025">Summer Launch Week announcements</a> to see our latest.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘WorkOS: Scalable, Secure Authentication’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/07/workos_scalable_secure_authent_6">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] WorkOS: Scalable, Secure Authentication</title></entry><entry>
	<title>The Party of ‘Free Speech’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theatlantic.com/newsletters/archive/2025/07/trump-rosie-odonnell-citizenship-free-speech/683530/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgi" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/15/party-of-free-speech" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42066</id>
	<published>2025-07-15T17:52:49Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-15T17:52:49Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>David A. Graham, writing at The Atlantic:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Not that long ago, believe it or not, Donald Trump ran for
president as the candidate who would defend the First Amendment.</p>

<p>He <a href="https://www.donaldjtrump.com/agenda47/president-donald-j-trump-free-speech-policy-initiative">warned</a> that a “sinister group of Deep State
bureaucrats, Silicon Valley tyrants, left-wing activists, and
depraved corporate news media” was “conspiring to manipulate and
silence the American people,” and promised that “by restoring free
speech, we will begin to reclaim our democracy, and save our
nation.” On his first day back in office, Trump signed an
<a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/presidential-actions/2025/01/restoring-freedom-of-speech-and-ending-federal-censorship/">executive order</a> affirming the “right of the American
people to engage in constitutionally protected speech.”</p>

<p>If anyone believed him at the time, they should be disabused by
now. One of his most brazen attacks on freedom of speech thus far
came this past weekend, when the president said that he was
thinking about stripping a comedian of her citizenship — for no
apparent reason other than that she regularly criticizes him.</p>

<p>“Because of the fact that Rosie O’Donnell is not in the best
interests of our Great Country, I am giving serious consideration
to taking away her Citizenship. She is a Threat to Humanity, and
should remain in the wonderful Country of Ireland, if they want
her,” he posted on <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/114840552173805537">Truth Social</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The people who griped that the Biden Administration was anti-free-speech because they ... <em>checks notes</em> ... applied soft pressure on companies like Meta to clamp down on algorithmically promoting disinformation are pretty quiet these days.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Party of ‘Free Speech’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/15/party-of-free-speech">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Elon Musk Gives Himself Another Handshake’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://pxlnv.com/linklog/musk-xai-spacex/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgh" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/14/musk-gives-himself-a-handshake" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42065</id>
	<published>2025-07-15T00:31:29Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-15T15:46:44Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Nick Heer, Pixel Envy on <a href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/spacex-to-invest-2-billion-into-elon-musks-xai-413934de?st=XZYChT&amp;reflink=desktopwebshare_permalink">the news</a> that SpaceX “invested” $2 billion in the <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2025-06-17/musk-s-xai-burning-through-1-billion-a-month-as-costs-pile-up">xAI money pit</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This comes just a few months after <a href="https://pxlnv.com/linklog/musk-x-xai/">xAI acquired X</a>, one
year after Musk <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/06/04/elon-musk-told-nvidia-to-ship-ai-chips-reserved-for-tesla-to-x-xai.html">shifted</a> a bunch of Tesla-bound Nvidia GPUs
to xAI, and just a few years after he <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/tech/tech-news/elon-musk-pulled-50-tesla-employees-twitter-takeover-rcna54946">used staff</a> from
Tesla to work on Twitter. So, to recap: he has moved people and
resources from two publicly traded companies to two privately
owned ones, has used funds from one of his privately owned
companies to buy another one of his privately owned companies, and
is now using one of his <s>publicly traded</s> privately owned
companies to give billions of dollars to (another) one of his
privately owned ones.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Musk can and should be able to do whatever he wants with his privately held companies, like X Corp and SpaceX. But the way he treats Tesla Motors, which is publicly traded, as though it’s just part of his personal fiefdom is absurd. And the European Commission <a href="https://fortune.com/europe/2024/10/17/musk-empire-risks-being-targeted-by-eu-for-potential-x-fines/">isn’t fooled</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Elon Musk Gives Himself Another Handshake’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/14/musk-gives-himself-a-handshake">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Lee Elia, Former Major League Manager, Dies at 87</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/athletic/6486807/2025/07/10/lee-elia-obituary-cubs-phillies/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgg" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/14/lee-elia-rip" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42064</id>
	<published>2025-07-14T22:53:05Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-14T22:55:51Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Steve Berman, The Athletic:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Lee Elia, who managed the Philadelphia Phillies and Chicago Cubs
for two seasons apiece but is perhaps best known for a profane
postgame rant critical of Chicago fans, died on Wednesday. He was
87. The Phillies announced his death in a statement on Thursday,
though they did not say where he died or cite a cause. [...]</p>

<p>The team noted that Elia was a Philadelphia native who signed with
the Phillies in 1958. He was in the organization on and off
throughout the decades, including as a minor league player,
manager, scout and director of instruction. He was the third-base
coach for the Phillies team that won the 1980 World Series.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You’ll never hear a better example of how to talk like a Philadelphian than <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uiVVbYK9HXw">Elia’s famed 1983 rant</a>, after the Cubs opened the season 5-14. Earmuffs for any (non-Philadelphian) children in the room.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Lee Elia, Former Major League Manager, Dies at 87’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/14/lee-elia-rip">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Elmore Leonard’s Perfect Pitch</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2025/07/07/elmore-leonards-perfect-pitch" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgf" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/14/elmore-leonard-perfect-pitch" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42063</id>
	<published>2025-07-14T21:15:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-14T21:46:08Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Anthony Lane, in a crackerjack piece for The New Yorker on the writing and work of Elmore Leonard:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>So, when does Leonard become himself? Is it possible to specify
the moment, or the season, when he crosses the border? I would
nominate “The Big Bounce,” from 1969 — which, by no coincidence,
is the first novel of his to be set in the modern age. As the
prose calms down, something quickens in the air, and the plainest
words and deeds make easy music: “They discussed whether beer was
better in bottles or cans, and then which was better, bottled or
draft, and both agreed, finally, that it didn’t make a hell of a
lot of difference. Long as it was cold.”</p>

<p>What matters here is what isn’t there. Grammatically, by rights,
we ought to have an “As” or a “So” before “long.” If the beer
drinkers were talking among themselves, however, or <em>to</em>
themselves, they wouldn’t bother with such nicety, and Leonard
heeds their example; he does them the honor of flavoring his
registration of their chatter with that perfect hint of them. The
technical term for this trick, as weary students of literature
will recall, is <em>style indirect libre</em>, or free indirect
discourse. It has a noble track record, with Jane Austen and
Flaubert as front-runners, but seldom has it proved so
democratically wide-ranging — not just <em>libre</em> but liberating,
too, as Leonard tunes in to regular citizens. He gets into their
heads, their palates, and their plans for the evening. Listen to a
guy named Moran, in “<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Cat-Chaser-Novel-Elmore-Leonard/dp/0062190954/?tag=df-amzn-20">Cat Chaser</a>” (1982), watching
Monday-night football and trying to decide “whether he should have
another beer and fry a steak or go to Vesuvio’s on Federal Highway
for spaghetti marinara and eat the crisp breadsticks with hard
butter, Jesus, and have a bottle of red with it, the house salad
... or get the chicken cacciatore and slock the bread around in
the gravy ...”</p>

<p>The ellipses are Leonard’s, or, rather, they are Moran’s musings,
reproduced by Leonard as a kind of Morse code. We join in with the
dots. But it’s the “Jesus” that does the work, yielding up a
microsecond of salivation, and inviting us to slock around in the
juice of the character’s brain.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The genius in the second example is the verb choice: <em><a href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/slock">slock</a></em>. There are dozens of verbs that could have worked there, but none better.</p>

<p>Leonard is probably tops on the list of authors whose work I love, but of which I haven’t read nearly as much as I should. There are novelists who are good at creating (and voicing) original vivid characters, novelists who are good at plot, and novelists who are just great at <em>writing</em>. Leonard hits the trifecta.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Elmore Leonard’s Perfect Pitch’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/14/elmore-leonard-perfect-pitch">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Experts Said This Was a Damn Clever Post by Jason Kottke</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://kottke.org/25/07/journalisms-experts-said-conclusion" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wge" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/14/kottke-experts-said" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42062</id>
	<published>2025-07-14T20:58:07Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-14T20:58:07Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jason Kottke:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Large media companies, and the NY Times in particular these days,
like to use the phrase “experts said” instead of simply stating
facts. The thing is, many other statements of plain truth in that
brief Times post lack the confirmation of expertise. To aid the
paper in steering their readers away from notions of objective
truth, here’s a suggested rewrite of that Bluesky post.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Experts Said This Was a Damn Clever Post by Jason Kottke’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/14/kottke-experts-said">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Reborn Commodore Is Taking Pre-Orders for New Commodore 64 Models</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.commodore.net/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgd" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/14/commodore-64-ultimate" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42061</id>
	<published>2025-07-14T19:29:56Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-19T22:10:29Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Last year, retro computing YouTuber Christian “Peri Fractic” Simpson <s>bought</s> <a href="https://tedium.co/2025/06/19/peri-fractic-retro-recipes-commodore-profile/">licensed the branding rights and some of the IP</a> belonging to Commodore (which rights have been transferred five times since the original company went bankrupt in 1994). Last week they launched their first product:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This is the first real Commodore computer in over 30 years, and
it’s picked up a few new tricks.</p>

<p>Not an emulator. Not a PC. Retrogaming heaven in three dimensions:
<em>silicon, nostalgia, and light</em>. Powered by a FPGA recreation of the
original motherboard, wrapped in glowing game-reactive LEDs (or
classic beige of course).</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://tedium.co/2025/07/12/commodore-revival-community/">Via Ernie Smith</a>, who has been <a href="https://tedium.co/2025/06/19/peri-fractic-retro-recipes-commodore-profile/">following this saga thoughtfully</a>.</p>

<p>This is, no question, a fun and cool project, and I hope it succeeds wildly. But personally, the Commodore 64 holds almost no nostalgic value for me. The Commodore 64 — which came out in 1982, when I was 9 — always struck me as cheap-feeling and inelegant. Like using some weird computer from the Soviet Union. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/07/commodore-64-keyboard.jpeg">Just look at its keyboard</a>. It’s got a bunch of odd keys, like “Run Stop” and “Restore”, and all sorts of drawing-related glyphs (used when programming) printed on the sides of the keycaps. Now compare that to the keyboards from <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/07/apple-IIplus-keyboard.jpeg">the Apple II Plus</a> (1979), which has just one weird key, “REPT” (<a href="https://www.duxburysystems.org/downloads/library/texas/apple/history/museum/computers/a2_plusclose.html">for Repeat</a> — you needed to press and hold REPT to get other keys to repeat, which, admittedly, seems inexplicable in hindsight), and to <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/07/apple-IIe-keyboard.jpeg">the Apple IIe</a> (1983), which has no weird keys and whose keyboard looks remarkably modern lo these 42 intervening years.</p>

<p>That said, while both systems came with 64 kilobytes of RAM, the Apple IIe cost $1,400 when it debuted (~$4,600 today, inflation adjusted); the Commodore 64 cost $600 (~$2,000 today). Some things haven’t changed about the computer industry in my lifetime.</p>

<p>The most interesting computers Commodore ever made, by far, were the Amigas. The Amiga brand and IP were cleaved from Commodore long ago, and alas, the new Commodore doesn’t have them. But they’ve expressed interest in buying them. Something like this Commodore 64 Ultimate but for an Amiga — now <em>that</em> might get me to reach for my credit card.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Reborn Commodore Is Taking Pre-Orders for New Commodore 64 Models’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/14/commodore-64-ultimate">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Classic Web’ on Mastodon</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://indieweb.social/@classicweb" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgc" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/13/classic-web" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42060</id>
	<published>2025-07-14T00:17:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-14T00:18:25Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Classic Web is a fun account to follow on Mastodon. Curator Richard MacManus posts half a dozen or so screenshots per day of, well, classic websites from the late 1990s and 2000s. Makes me feel old and young at the same time.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Classic Web’ on Mastodon’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/13/classic-web">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Drata</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://drata.com/daring/?utm_source=Daring_Fireball&amp;utm_medium=display&amp;utm_campaign=18991230_fy26_comm_DG_COMM_&amp;utm_content=demo_request" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgb" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/13/drata" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42059</id>
	<published>2025-07-13T19:26:31Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-13T19:26:32Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to Drata for sponsoring this last week at DF. Their message is short and sweet: Automate compliance. Streamline security. Manage risk. Drata delivers the world’s most advanced Trust Management platform.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Drata’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/13/drata">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Grok 4 System Prompt Shenanigans</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Jul/12/grok-4-heavy/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wga" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/12/grok-4-system-prompt-shenanigans" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42058</id>
	<published>2025-07-12T21:55:27Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-13T03:11:14Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Simon Willison:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Grok 4 Heavy is the “think much harder” version of Grok 4 that’s
currently only available on their $300/month plan. Jeremy Howard
relays a report from a Grok 4 Heavy user who wishes to remain
anonymous: it turns out that Heavy, <a href="https://grok.com/share/bGVnYWN5_fb5f16af-9590-4880-9d96-58573c7e1293">unlike regular Grok 4</a>, has
measures in place to prevent it from sharing its system prompt.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Most big LLMs do not share their system prompts, but xAI has <a href="https://x.com/jeremyphoward/status/1943871257134739866">made a show out of being transparent</a> in that regard.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In related prompt transparency news, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Jul/12/grok/">Grok’s retrospective</a>
on why Grok started spitting out antisemitic tropes last week
included the text “You tell it like it is and you are not afraid
to offend people who are politically correct” as part of the
system prompt blamed for the problem. That text isn’t present in
<a href="https://github.com/xai-org/grok-prompts/commits/main/">the history</a> of their previous published system prompts.</p>

<p>Given the <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Jul/12/grok/">past week of mishaps</a> I think xAI would be wise to
reaffirm their dedication to prompt transparency and set things up
so the <a href="https://github.com/xai-org/grok-prompts">xai-org/grok-prompts</a> repository updates
automatically when new prompts are deployed — their current manual
process for that is clearly not adequate for the job!</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Transparently publishing system prompt changes to GitHub was xAI’s main “trust us” argument after <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/08/grok-praises-hitler">the “white genocide in South Africa” fiasco mid-May</a>. Turns out they don’t publish all of them.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Grok 4 System Prompt Shenanigans’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/12/grok-4-system-prompt-shenanigans">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple and Masimo Faced Off in US Appeals Court This Week</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.reuters.com/legal/government/apple-masimo-spar-over-apple-watch-import-ban-us-appeals-court-2025-07-07/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wg9" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/11/apple-masimo-appeals-court" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42057</id>
	<published>2025-07-12T01:46:49Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-13T18:29:00Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Blake Brittain, reporting for Reuters:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple asked a U.S. appeals court on Monday to overturn a trade
tribunal’s decision which forced it to remove blood-oxygen reading
technology from its Apple Watches, in order to avoid a ban on its
U.S. smartwatch imports.</p>

<p>A three-judge panel of the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Federal
Circuit heard arguments from the tech giant, medical monitoring
technology company Masimo, and the U.S. International Trade
Commission over the ITC’s 2023 ruling that Apple Watches violated
Masimo’s patent rights in pulse oximetry technology. [...]</p>

<p>Apple attorney Joseph Mueller of WilmerHale told the court on
Monday that the decision had wrongly “deprived millions of Apple
Watch users” of Apple’s blood-oxygen feature. A lawyer for Masimo,
Joseph Re of Knobbe Martens Olson &amp; Bear, countered that Apple was
trying to “rewrite the law” with its arguments.</p>

<p>The judges questioned whether Masimo’s development of a competing
smartwatch justified the ITC’s ruling. Apple has told the appeals
court that the ban was improper because a Masimo wearable device
covered by the patents was “purely hypothetical” when Masimo filed
its ITC complaint in 2021. [...]</p>

<p>Mueller told the court on Monday that the ban was unjustified
because Masimo only had prototypes of a smartwatch with pulse
oximetry features when it had filed its ITC complaint. Re
responded that Apple was wrong to argue that a “finished product”
was necessary to justify the ITC’s decision.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This whole thing started with the Apple Watch Series 9 and Ultra 2 in 2023. I’m very surprised that we’re just two months away from the Series 11 and Ultra 3 in 2025 and it still isn’t settled. And to be clear, while it’s technically an “import ban”, all Apple Watch Series 9, Series 10, and Ultra 2 have the blood oxygen sensors. Units sold in the US after December 2023 simply have the feature disabled in software.</p>

<p>(<a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/07/07/apple-and-masimo-back-in-court-over-apple-watch-import-ban-appeal/">Via Chance Miller at 9to5Mac</a>.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple and Masimo Faced Off in US Appeals Court This Week’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/11/apple-masimo-appeals-court">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Moft’s MagSafe-Compatible Snap-On iPhone Stand and Wallet</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.moft.us/products/iphone-stand-wallet-magsafe-compatible" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wg8" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/11/moft-snap-on-iphone-stand-wallet" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42056</id>
	<published>2025-07-11T23:51:55Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-11T23:55:44Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Here’s a product recommendation long in the making. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2021/07/21/ep-318">Four years ago this month</a>, Matthew Panzarino was my guest on The Talk Show and at one point he recommended Moft’s Snap-On iPhone Stand/Wallet. It uses a very clever origami-style folding design. Folded flat it kind of just looks like a leather MagSafe wallet. But folded open it works as a stand — and as a stand, it works both horizontally and vertically. Borrowing images from Moft’s website:</p>

<p><img
  src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/07/moft-vertical.jpeg"
  alt = "A blue Moft Snap-On iPhone Stand, propping an iPhone vertically."
/></p>

<p><img
  src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/07/moft-horizontal.jpeg"
  alt = "A blue Moft Snap-On iPhone Stand, propping an iPhone vertically."
/></p>

<p>You can also use it with the stand oriented vertically but the phone horizontally.</p>

<p>I bought one of these right after that episode of the show, and I’ve been using it ever since. And every so often when I use it, I think to myself that I should write a post recommending it. I’ve waited so long that Panzarino has been back on The Talk Show five times since the episode in which he recommended it, but here we are. The thing is, I use it both in my kitchen <em>and</em> while travelling, and so I’ll often find myself in the kitchen, rooting around the drawer in which I keep it stashed, only to realize it’s downstairs in my office in my laptop bag. Or, worse, I’ll find myself looking for it in my laptop bag while I’m sitting on an airplane 35,000 feet in the air, only to realize it’s back home in my kitchen. So I ordered a second one today — which I should have done like 3.5 years ago.</p>

<p>I own a few similar/competing products, like these PopSocket-y rings from <a href="https://amzn.to/3Imv8sx">Anker</a> and <a href="https://amzn.to/4lhshj0">Belkin</a>. I have no idea why I own both of those rings when I don’t like either of them as much as the Moft foldable stand. The problem with these rings is that they’re only able to prop the phone horizontally. Watching video is almost certainly the most common use case for these stands, but I do often use my iPhone propped up vertically, like for FaceTime calls and when I’m writing on it using a Bluetooth keyboard. I’m going to give both of these rings away — there’s nothing they do better than the Moft stand. The Moft stand even works better as a hand-holding grip.</p>

<p>I’ve never used the Moft stand as a wallet, but if you want to, it holds two cards. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/07/make_me_rich_on_amazon_prime_day">Prime “Day”</a> lasts a week and it’s still running until midnight Pacific tonight, but the Moft stand doesn’t have a Prime Day discount: <a href="https://amzn.to/4eLcTJn">it’s the same price at Amazon</a> as it is <a href="https://www.moft.us/products/iphone-stand-wallet-magsafe-compatible">from Moft’s website</a>: $30. Well worth it. I love this thing. (Buy yours wherever you want, of course, but the Amazon link a few sentences back will throw some filthy affiliate lucre my way.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Moft’s MagSafe-Compatible Snap-On iPhone Stand and Wallet’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/11/moft-snap-on-iphone-stand-wallet">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Linda Yaccarino Resigns as ‘CEO’ of X</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://x.com/lindayaX/status/1942957094811951197" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wg7" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/10/yaccarino-out" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42055</id>
	<published>2025-07-10T22:21:24Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-10T22:21:25Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Linda Yaccarino, in a post on X yesterday:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>After two incredible years, I’ve decided to step down as CEO of X.</p>

<p>When @elonmusk and I first spoke of his vision for X, I knew it
would be the opportunity of a lifetime to carry out the
extraordinary mission of this company. I’m immensely grateful to
him for entrusting me with the responsibility of protecting free
speech, turning the company around, and transforming X into the
Everything App.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/2022/10/everything">I thought it couldn’t be done</a>, but here we are today, using X for everything: news, banking, shopping, payments, messaging. It’s the only app most people use.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2025/jul/10/linda-yaccarino-resigns-x-elon-musk">The Guardian, reporting on her departure</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>After more than two years of Yaccarino running damage control for
her boss and the platform’s myriad issues, Musk issued only a
brief statement acknowledging she was stepping down.</p>

<p>“Thank you for your contributions,” Musk responded to Yaccarino’s
post announcing her resignation. Minutes later, he began sending
replies to other posts about SpaceX, artificial intelligence and
how his chatbot became a Nazi.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Linda Yaccarino Resigns as ‘CEO’ of X’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/10/yaccarino-out">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Yours Truly on Crossword, With Jonathan Wold and Luke Carbis</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://crossword.fm/s09/e13/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wg6" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/10/yours-truly-on-crossword" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42054</id>
	<published>2025-07-10T19:46:24Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-11T01:11:32Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jonathan Wold and Luke Carbis cohost a podcast called Crossword, focusing mainly on WordPress and the open web. They occasionally invite guests to join them, and it was my pleasure to join them on their latest episode:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>John Gruber’s Dithering podcast with Ben Thompson was the original
inspiration for Crossword’s 15-minute format. Five years later,
John joins Luke and Jonathan for a wide-ranging conversation
covering open versus closed platforms, the history and impact of
Markdown, and a missed opportunity in WordPress. Luke goes on
about the good old days, Jonathan starts thinking about a rival
platform, and John makes a prediction for the ten-year follow-up
episode.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>While their usual format is a <a href="https://dithering.fm/">Dithering</a>-esque 15 minutes, these special “perspectives” interviews run long. And unsurprisingly, mine ran long. I don’t write about the open web as much as I used to but I care about it as much as ever. I express some of my deep concerns <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2024/11/regarding_and_well_against_substack">about Substack in particular</a> in this interview.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Yours Truly on Crossword, With Jonathan Wold and Luke Carbis’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/10/yours-truly-on-crossword">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Mark Gurman Got a Slew of Interesting Quotes Regarding Jeff Williams’s Retirement</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2025-07-08/apple-operating-chief-jeff-williams-to-pass-role-to-lieutenant" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wg5" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/09/gurman-jeff-williams" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42053</id>
	<published>2025-07-09T21:10:57Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-09T21:13:34Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Mark Gurman got some interesting quotes from interesting former Apple employees for his report at Bloomberg on Jeff Williams’s retirement:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Jeff’s importance and contributions to Apple have been enormous,
although perhaps not always obvious to the general public,” said
Tony Blevins, a former Apple operations vice president who
reported to Williams until the end of 2022. “As a shareholder, I
am saddened. Time takes its toll, and it’s almost as if the band
is dissolving. Jeff will be sorely missed.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Blevins is a fascinating character. A hard-charging negotiator nicknamed “the Blevinator”, Blevins was somewhat ignominiously <a href="https://nypost.com/2022/09/29/tony-blevins-leaving-apple-over-vulgar-tiktok-video/">run out of Apple</a> in 2022 after he appeared in a TikTok video that went viral making a joke that, out of context, seemed very crude, but was in fact just a quote from the mildly crude 1981 Dudley Moore hit movie <em>Arthur</em>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Clearly he wasn’t destined to be the Tim Cook replacement,” Bob
Mansfield, the company’s former chief of hardware engineering
under both Cook and co-founder Steve Jobs, said of Williams. “He’s
about the same age as Tim, so that wouldn’t make much sense. The
operations team at Apple is really going to miss Jeff.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Mansfield is the only ex-Apple person I’ve seen quoted who addressed the succession issue. (And of course, no current Apple people are quoted anywhere, other than in <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2025/07/apple-announces-chief-operating-officer-transition/">Apple’s PR announcement of Williams’s retirement</a>.)</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Myoung Cha, who reported to Williams in the health group until
2021, said the outgoing COO’s “personal passion for health” helped
shape the Apple Watch and that his presence on the team will be
“hugely missed.”</p>

<p>“Sabih is very much cut from the Tim Cook cloth,” said Matthew
Moore, a former Apple operations engineer. “Jeff was a little more
product minded; Sabih is just a really brilliant operator and
methodical in the same way that Tim would operate.” Moore added
that Khan has already been running Apple’s operations group and
that the team “won’t miss a beat.” “The concerns will be in the
other areas” that Williams currently oversees, he said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I wrote about <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/07/jeff_williams_is_retiring_as_coo">Williams’s “overseeing” of design yesterday</a>. Design — software at least — has already become a concern in the six years since Jony Ive left Apple, which is when design teams started reporting to Williams. And, frankly, it’s been a concern for many of us ever since <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2012/10/forstall_out">Scott Forstall was fired and Ive put all design — HI and ID — under the same roof</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2025/07/apple-announces-chief-operating-officer-transition/">Apple did announce yesterday</a> that after Williams fully retires at the end of this year, design leaders will start reporting to Tim Cook directly. Left unsaid in Apple’s announcement is who will take over Williams’s roles overseeing Apple Watch and Health. I presume Watch will simply fall under John Ternus (SVP hardware) and that Sumbul Desai, who already has the title VP of health and frequently (always?) appears during the Health segments of Apple keynotes, will report directly to Cook.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Mark Gurman Got a Slew of Interesting Quotes Regarding Jeff Williams’s Retirement’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/09/gurman-jeff-williams">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/07/make_me_rich_on_amazon_prime_day" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wg4" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42052</id>
	<published>2025-07-09T19:33:52Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-10T05:14:00Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">You can support Daring Fireball and save yourself a veritable bundle through some Prime Day discounts.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>It’s Amazon’s annual Prime Day sale, and if you <a href="https://www.amazon.com/primeday/?tag=df-amzn-20">click through this link</a>, or any of the ones below, you can show your support for Daring Fireball by throwing the referral revenue from any purchases you make my way. You don’t pay a penny more but I get a few percentage points of your purchases. Prime Day discounts are no joke either — we need an outdoor TV for our sun-drenched deck, and I’d been putting off purchasing one out of indecision, but I pulled the trigger and <a href="https://amzn.to/40wWYZp">saved $500</a> with a Prime Day discount last night. (Sometimes my procrastination pays off.)</p>

<p>Just about everything Amazon sells from Apple is being offered at significant discounts. Just a handful of popular ones:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Apple-11-inch-Intelligence-Display-All-Day/dp/B0DZ76BN5D/?tag=df-amzn-20">11-inch M3 iPad Air for $480</a> (regularly $600).</li>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/4lemIlr">iPad Mini (A17 Pro) for $380</a> (regularly $500).</li>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/44lQIG5">AirPods 4 With Active Noise Cancellation for $120</a> (regularly $180) and the ones without ANC <a href="https://amzn.to/46vrJS4">are just $90</a>. (You should definitely get the ones with ANC, though — I never did write a proper review, but I tested a pair with ANC for <em>months</em> and they’re quite amazing given their price and non-sealed ear fit.)</li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Apple-Cancellation-Transparency-Personalized-High-Fidelity/dp/B0D1XD1ZV3/?tag=df-amzn-20">AirPods Pro 2 are just $150</a> (regularly $250).</li>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/3Gt8EFE">13-inch M4 MacBook Airs starting at just $850</a> (regularly $1,000) and the sweet configuration <a href="https://amzn.to/3TrhB5c">with 24 GB RAM and 512 GB storage for $1,250</a> (regularly $1,400). It seems like you save $150 on any MacBook Amazon sells.</li>
</ul>

<p>Even small items like Apple’s <a href="https://amzn.to/4lPsuKh">woven USB-C cables</a> and wired EarPods (<a href="https://amzn.to/4kw3lD8">USB-C</a> or <a href="https://amzn.to/3U0PvxI">old-school 3.5mm</a>) are a few bucks off. (I keep a pair of the old 3.5mm EarPods in my laptop bag for use with my <a href="https://play.date/">Playdate</a>, along with Apple’s <a href="https://amzn.to/4f00O3f">$9 USB-C headphone jack adapter</a> (one of the few products I saw that’s not discounted for Prime day, but, come on, it’s $9) in case I ever find myself needing wired buds.)</p>

<p>It’s called Prime Day for a reason: you need to be <a href="https://www.amazon.com/amazonprime/?tag=df-amzn-20">a Prime subscriber</a> to get these deals. We’ve been members since forever, and the $140/year fee pays for itself in shipping fees alone. But for some high-priced items like MacBooks and iPads, you can make up the entire annual fee in one purchase today.</p>

<p>I don’t post a ton of affiliate links here on DF, but when I do, they sometimes work out to a nice windfall. As the media industry moves more and more toward subscriptions and memberships — and, alas, paywalled content — I’m still freely publishing the entirety of my work other than <a href="https://dithering.fm/">Dithering</a>. I really do get asked by readers on a regular basis how they can support Daring Fireball directly. I’ll do a new round of t-shirts and maybe some other merch soon. That’s one way. I might someday offer a membership tier with bonus content (<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2004/06/something_daring">again</a>), but that day is not today. But one way you can support DF directly today is by buying anything — anything at all — from Amazon after clicking through any of the above links.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Save Yourself Some Dough on Apple Kit and Make Me Rich on Amazon Prime Day</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Apple TV+ Renews ‘Slow Horses’ for a Seventh Season</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.apple.com/tv-pr/news/2025/07/apple-tv-announces-seventh-season-for-celebrated-emmy-and-bafta-award-winning-spy-drama-slow-horses-starring-academy-award-winner-sir-gary-oldman/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wg3" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/09/slow-horses-renewed-for-7th-season" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42051</id>
	<published>2025-07-09T17:56:12Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-09T17:59:24Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Apple TV+:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Today, Apple TV+ announced a new, six-episode seventh season for
the widely hailed, darkly comedic spy drama <em>Slow Horses</em>. The
Emmy and BAFTA Award-winning series stars Academy Award winner Sir
Gary Oldman, who has been honored with Golden Globe, Emmy and
BAFTA Award nominations for his outstanding performance as the
beloved, irascible Jackson Lamb. The complete first four seasons
of <em>Slow Horses</em> are now streaming on Apple TV+, with the premiere
of season five slated for September 24, 2025. Season six was
announced last year.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s always good news when a show you love is renewed for another season. It’s almost too good to be true that <em>Slow Horses</em> has been renewed so far into the future already. It’s so good. </p>

<p>Maybe I’m just lucky that the Apple TV shows I like best have proven broadly popular, but it feels like <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/08/19/amazon-peripheral-season-2">quite the difference</a> from <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/05/02/onion-netflix-wga">other</a> streaming services.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple TV+ Renews ‘Slow Horses’ for a Seventh Season’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/09/slow-horses-renewed-for-7th-season">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>OpenAI Officially Acquires ‘io Products Inc.’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://openai.com/sam-and-jony/?asset=video" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wg2" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/09/openai-officially-acquires-io-products-inc" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42050</id>
	<published>2025-07-09T17:15:26Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-09T17:21:31Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>OpenAI’s page for io, <em>minus</em> the “Sam and Jony” short film that introduced the partnership, is back up, with a brief announcement that the deal has officially closed:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We’re thrilled to share that the io Products, Inc. team has
officially merged with OpenAI. Jony Ive and LoveFrom remain
independent and have assumed deep design and creative
responsibilities across OpenAI.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Referring to the company as “io Products Inc.” rather than just “io” is seemingly their stopgap workaround for <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/23/io-iyo-aye-aye-aye">the trademark injunction they faced from rival startup iyO two weeks ago</a>, which led them to temporarily take down this web page and the video. The video remains unavailable, presumably because of the ongoing trademark dispute.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘OpenAI Officially Acquires ‘io Products Inc.’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/09/openai-officially-acquires-io-products-inc">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/07/jeff_williams_is_retiring_as_coo" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wfz" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42047</id>
	<published>2025-07-08T23:26:53Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-10T19:35:30Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Post-Williams, Apple’s operations will clearly remain under excellent, experienced leadership under Sabih Khan. But the company will be left with its design teams reporting directly to Cook, leaving it less clear whose taste, [ultimately], is steering the work of the company into the future.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2025/07/apple-announces-chief-operating-officer-transition/">Apple Newsroom, this afternoon</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple today announced Jeff Williams will transition his role as
chief operating officer later this month to Sabih Khan, Apple’s
senior vice president of Operations as part of a long-planned
succession. Williams will continue reporting to Apple CEO Tim Cook
and overseeing Apple’s world class design team and Apple Watch
alongside the company’s Heath initiatives. Apple’s design team
will then transition to reporting directly to Cook after Williams
retires late in the year.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Apple’s executive ranks have been so remarkably stable for so long that any change feels surprising. But Williams is 62 years old and has been at Apple for 27 years. Tim Cook is 64, and Khan <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sabih_Khan">is 58</a>. The whole thing seems amicable and orderly, and thus completely in line with everything we know about Williams’s and Cook’s seemingly similar personalities. After a long and successful career, Apple’s COO is retiring and his longtime lieutenant is being promoted to replace him this month. Apple’s operations aren’t just world-class, they’re almost certainly world-best. Even their leadership transitions are operationally smooth. <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2019/06/apple-names-sabih-khan-senior-vice-president-of-operations/">Khan was promoted in 2019</a> to the title of senior vice president of operations. Williams was promoted from that title (SVP of operations) to COO in 2015, four years after Cook took over as CEO from Steve Jobs.</p>

<p>But that’s the operations part. </p>

<p>What’s intriguing about the announcement is the design part — a functional area where, especially on the software side, Apple’s current stature is subject to much debate. While Williams is staying on until “late in the year” to continue his other responsibilities — Watch, Health, and serving as the senior executive Apple’s design teams report to — Khan isn’t taking over those roles when Williams leaves. And so by the end of the year, Apple’s design teams will go from reporting to Williams to reporting directly to Tim Cook. </p>

<p>I’ve long found it curious, if not downright dubious, that Apple’s design leaders have reported to Williams ever since it was announced in 2019 (<a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2019/06/jony-ive-to-form-independent-design-company-with-apple-as-client/">the very same day</a> that <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2019/06/apple-names-sabih-khan-senior-vice-president-of-operations/">Khan was promoted to SVP</a> of operations) that Jony Ive would be stepping down as chief design officer and leaving Apple to found the (as-yet-unnamed) design firm LoveFrom. Williams had no background in design at all. Apple’s design teams reporting to an operations executive makes no more sense than it would for Apple’s operations teams to report to, say, Alan Dye. Well, maybe it made a little more sense than that — having design report to Williams sort of felt like a way to give Williams experience across the breadth of the company in the case that he ever needed to step in to replace Cook as CEO, either temporarily or permanently, as Cook was asked to for Jobs. </p>

<p>But when that was announced in 2019, I expected it to be temporary, while Apple took its time to properly identify a new senior design leader. Someone with, you know, design leadership experience, and strong opinions about and deep knowledge of the craft of design. That was six years ago, and Apple has seemingly made not one move toward naming a new chief design officer or (the more likely title) SVP of design. It seems like time for that now.</p>

<p>I get the impression — from multiple sources — that <em>overseeing</em>, not <em>leading</em>, is in fact exactly the right word for Williams’s role regarding design since 2019. Williams oversaw design the same way Tim Cook, ultimately, oversees everything the company does. It was in no way a token role. Williams was <em>there</em>. He asked insightful questions about product designs and experiences. But he didn’t push back or offer opinions. There’s much to like about Liquid Glass, for example, but there’s also a lot of <a href="https://lmnt.me/blog/ive-got-better-things-to-do-than-this-and-yet.html">shitty UI functionality</a> and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/24/sorry-macos-tahoe-b2-finder-icon">just plain bad</a> design that makes you wonder how numerous aspects even escaped the drawing board, let alone made their way into the WWDC keynote and various OS 26 betas. Looking back at the last six years of Apple design — hardware, software, packaging, architecture — I detect not one fingerprint of style or taste that belongs to Jeff Williams. Given that Williams is not a designer, that’s not a surprise. But it’s a problem for the company if its products don’t ultimately have a distinctive <em>voice</em>.</p>

<p>I’m of the mind that, in hindsight, it was a mistake for Jony Ive to bring HI (software human interface design) under the same roof as ID (hardware industrial design). That arrangement made sense for Ive’s unique role in the company, and the unique period in the wake of Steve Jobs’s too-young demise. But it might have ultimately made Ive more difficult to replace than Steve Jobs. Williams’s combination of authority, mild-mannered-ness, and equanimity might have made him uniquely suited to either finding another Ive-like design leader whom all sides could have agreed to (even if begrudgingly), or, perhaps, to the task of unwinding the intermingling of HI and ID that occurred during the Jony-as-CDO era. But neither of those things happened.</p>

<p>Post-Williams, Apple’s operations will clearly remain under excellent, experienced leadership under Sabih Khan. But the company will be left with its design teams reporting directly to Cook — who is three years older than Williams. Six years after Jony Ive’s departure, today’s announcements leave it less clear than ever whose taste, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xk3UcgbbmxQ">ultimately</a>, is steering the work of the company into the future. Perhaps, I hope, Williams is staying until the end of the year to help answer that question.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Jeff Williams, 62, Is Retiring as Apple’s COO</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/07/full-screen_ad_for_f1_the_movie_in_apples_tv_app_linked_directly_to_the_web" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wfv" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42043</id>
	<published>2025-07-07T18:26:38Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-08T00:34:32Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">I can see the argument that Apple’s answer is “Yes, it’s potentially confusing for many users”. But I can’t see the argument that the answer is “Yes, it’s potentially confusing for many users, but only if they’re trying to buy in-app content or subscriptions, but not confusing at all if they’re trying to buy, say, movie tickets.”</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://www.threads.com/@mgsiegler/post/DLdXyO6otsI">MG Siegler, on Threads last week</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We’re already beyond ridiculous with the full-on ad assault from
Apple as everyone is well aware by now. But the wild thing here — in this <em>full screen</em> pop-up in the Apple TV app — is that it’s
not in-app but links out to the web to pay?!</p>
</blockquote>

<p>At least here in the US, if you just opened the TV app on iOS 18 last week, you were presented with <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/06/f1-tv-app-tickets-via-web.jpeg">this full-screen ad</a> (replete with all those dumb ®’s, despite Apple’s <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/06/f1-appstore-via-fandango.jpeg">ads for the same thing in the App Store</a> omitting them).</p>

<p>There were two buttons to choose from: “Not Now” and “Buy Tickets ↗︎”. If you tapped the “Buy Tickets ↗︎” button, boom, you just jumped to <a href="https://www.f1themovie.com/">the F1 The Movie website</a> in your default browser. <a href="https://www.threads.com/@kylealden/post/DLdhE1JhpeL">Kyle Alden, on Threads</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>That’s weird, Apple’s new full screen F1 ad in the TV app links
out to the browser to compete the transaction, but for some reason
doesn’t include any full screen interstitials warning of the big
scary web, nor a confirmation dialog that it would open in the
browser? Must be an oversight.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The hypocrisy isn’t that Apple didn’t show a full-screen scare sheet for this link-out to the web. It’s that they require other developers, who are doing it to sell digital content, to show a scare sheet/confirmation.</p>

<p>One of the subtle differences with this particular promotion is that buying movie tickets is not “digital content” — even if they’re just passes in Apple Wallet or saved QR codes in an app like Fandango. You’re purchasing a real-world experience, so it’s not eligible for Apple’s In-App Purchase (IAP) system. This is why when you buy theater tickets in the Fandango app, Fandango charges your credit or debit card directly. Same when you pay for rides in Uber or Lyft. It’s really subtle for something like a movie. Pay for a movie to watch on your TV at home? That’s a digital purchase. Pay for a movie to watch in a theater? <em>Not</em> a digital purchase.</p>

<p>I understand the distinction between digital content (that’s consumed on your Apple device) and real-world goods and experiences (even if you pay for them in apps on your Apple device). But how many iPhone users understand this distinction? Like, if you polled 1,000 U.S. iPhone users who (a) purchase in-game content in games like Candy Crush, and (b) hail rides in Uber or Lyft, what percentage of those iPhone users do you think could give a coherent answer as to why their in-game purchases <em>must</em> use Apple’s IAP system, and why Uber not only <em>doesn’t</em> use IAP to charge for rides, but is not <em>allowed</em> to use IAP for that? I’d bet fewer than 1 percent. (I’d also bet that fewer than 1 percent <em>care</em>, which is why they don’t know.)</p>

<p>Is it inherently confusing to have a button in an app that jumps you out of the app to your default web browser (probably Safari, especially for people who might be confused) to complete a transaction, without a scare sheet or even a confirmation alert? I can see the argument that Apple’s answer is “Yes, it’s potentially confusing for many users”. But I can’t see the argument that the answer is “Yes, it’s potentially confusing for many users, but only if they’re trying to buy in-app content or subscriptions, but not confusing at all if they’re trying to buy, say, movie tickets.”</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Full-Screen Ad for ‘F1 The Movie’ in Apple’s TV App Linked Directly to the Web, and Nothing Bad Seemed to Happen</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/06/apple_app_store_policy_updates_dma" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wfo" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42036</id>
	<published>2025-06-28T21:00:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-07T23:32:39Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">It’s a natural consequence that an overly complicated law (the DMA) has resulted in an ever-more-complicated set of guidelines and policies (from Apple). It’s all downright byzantine.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Let’s start with <a href="https://developer.apple.com/news/?id=awedznci">Apple’s own announcement at Apple Developer News</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The European Commission has required Apple to make a series of
additional changes under the Digital Markets Act:</p>

<h2>Communication and Promotion of Offers</h2>

<ul>
<li>Today, we’re introducing updated terms that let developers with
apps in the European Union storefronts of the App Store
communicate and promote offers for purchase of digital goods or
services available at a destination of their choice. The
destination can be a website, alternative app marketplace, or
another app, and can be accessed outside the app or within the
app via a web view or native experience.</li>
<li>App Store apps that communicate and promote offers for digital
goods or services will be subject to new business terms for
those transactions — an initial acquisition fee, store services
fee, and for apps on the StoreKit External Purchase Link
Entitlement (EU) Addendum, the Core Technology Commission (CTC).
The CTC reflects value Apple provides developers through ongoing
investments in the tools, technologies, and services that enable
them to build and share innovative apps with users. [...]</li>
</ul>

<h2>Update to Business Terms for Apps in the European Union</h2>

<ul>
<li>By January 1, 2026, Apple plans to move to a single business
model in the EU for all developers. Under this single business
model, Apple will transition from the Core Technology Fee (CTF)
to the CTC on digital goods or services. The CTC will apply to
digital goods or services sold by apps distributed from the App
Store, Web Distribution, and/or alternative marketplaces.</li>
<li>Apps currently under the Alternative Terms Addendum for Apps in
the EU continue to be subject only to the CTF until the
transition to the CTC is fully implemented next year. At that
time, qualifying transactions will be subject to the CTC, and
the CTF will no longer apply. Additional details regarding this
transition will be provided at a later date.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>Amongst other policy and API changes, Apple also announced a new, seemingly simplified, experience on iOS/iPadOS <a href="https://developer.apple.com/support/alt-distribution-ux-in-the-eu/">for installing apps and alternative app marketplaces in the EU</a>.</p>

<p>As for the other policy changes, <a href="https://sixcolors.com/link/2025/06/apple-makes-big-app-store-changes-in-the-eu/">here’s Jason Snell’s summary</a>, which I think captures the gist as well as possible:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>Tiered App Store fees.</em> For today’s full-service App Store,
developers will now pay 13% on sales, reduced to 10% for Small
Business Program members. Or developers can opt into “Tier One”,
which comes with a 5% fee but does not support a raft of App Store
features we’ve come to expect, like automatic app updates, App
Store promotions, placement in search suggestions, ratings and
reviews on product listings (!), and more.</p>

<p><em>Core Technology Commission.</em> Apple is going to move all
developers over to a new tax called the Core Technology
Commission, in which developers who opt to sell apps outside the
App Store will pay 5% of sales made through in-app promotions. The
€0.50-per-install Core Technology Fee will be dropped as of
January 1.</p>

<p><em>Free linking.</em> Developers can promote offers broadly, are no
longer limited to a single static URL without tracking parameters,
and can freely design the interfaces for those links and
promotions.</p>

<p><em>New business terms.</em> Developers have to pay a 2% fee for digital
goods and services purchased by new users for the first six months
after a user first downloads an app; members of the Small Business
Program don’t have to pay this fee.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/06/26/apple-announces-sweeping-app-store-changes-in-the-eu/">here’s Chance Miller’s summary at 9to5Mac</a>, which includes the following statement from Apple (which statement was provided to me, as well):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The European Commission is requiring Apple to make a series of
additional changes to the App Store. We disagree with this outcome
and plan to appeal.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The new fee structure is undeniably convoluted, and I think downright confusing. <a href="https://x.com/rjonesy/status/1938354627155501219">Seemingly no one can figure out</a> exactly what commissions apps that use alternative payments or distribution are going to pay. It’s a natural consequence that an overly complicated law (the DMA) has resulted in an ever-more-complicated set of guidelines and policies (from Apple): byzantine compliance with a byzantine law.</p>

<p>Because it’s so complicated and hard to understand, it’s difficult even to summarize with a headline describing what’s new. Even if you understand it enough to just want to express anger at Apple for spiteful compliance and greed, it’s hard to sum up why you’re angry in a succinct headline or tweet.</p>

<hr />

<p>The bottom line, as I understand it, is the following (but I could be wrong about some of this<sup id="fnr1-2025-06-28"><a href="#fn1-2025-06-28">1</a></sup> — if I am, let me know, and I’ll try to correct it):</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Developers who just do the simplest thing possible — distribute through the App Store and process all payments using Apple’s IAP — will continue to pay the same commissions, 30% by default, or 15% for Small Business Program developers and recurring subscriptions after the first year. Of course this is what Apple would prefer developers do.</p></li>
<li><p>Big developers, distributing through the App Store but processing their own payments, will still owe Apple a commission of around 20% on non-IAP purchases: 13% for “store services”, 5% for the new Core Technology Commission (replacing the €0.50 per-download Core Technology Fee), and 2% for “initial acquisition”. Small Developer Program members and recurring subscriptions after the first year pay 15% — no “initial acquisition fee” and a reduced “store services” fee of 10%. But everyone’s on the hook for the 5% CTC.</p></li>
<li><p>Apps distributed through the App Store can pay a reduced rate of 5% for “store services” (down from 13%) by opting into a reduced “Tier 1”. Rather than this “Tier 1” being an appealing choice for any developers, I think the point of it is for Apple to assert that those App Store features justify 8 percent of Apple’s commission on purchases: automatic software updates, reviews and ratings, surfacing through search for anything other than an exact name match, <a href="https://developer.apple.com/help/app-store-connect/reference/store-services-tiers/">and a whole lot more</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>One consequence of the €0.50 per-download Core Technology Fee (CTF) being replaced by a 5% Core Technology Commission (CTC) is that there will no longer be a penalty for small developers who have a free-to-download app that hits over one million EU downloads. That was a legitimate problem with the CTF — an app with 5 million EU downloads would owe Apple €2 million for the CTF, but might be generating far less than that (or even nothing at all) in revenue. But another consequence of switching to the CTC from the CTF is that super-popular apps from super-big companies that don’t sell digital goods from their apps will continue to pay nothing at all. E.g. unless Meta starts selling digital goods from within their apps, they’ll continue to pay nothing at all to Apple for zillion-download apps like Instagram, Facebook, and WhatsApp. That was a shortcoming with the App Store’s model that the CTF was designed to correct.</p></li>
<li><p>All of this additional complication is, I believe, just for apps distributed through the App Store. Feel free to blame Apple as much as you want for spiteful compliance (especially when it comes to payments made on the web, from links in apps), but part of this is on the European Commission for demanding not only that Apple allow apps to be distributed outside the App Store (which is somewhat reasonable), but also for requiring Apple to allow outside payments for apps distributed through the App Store. Apps and games distributed through alternative EU app marketplaces or web downloads are only on the hook for the 5% CTC (by the end of the year, when it replaces the CTF). But there is no free lunch — iOS apps and games distributed outside the App Store that require a purchase, or offer digital content for sale, must pay the 5% CTC.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>There are a lot of people <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/06/26/tim-sweeney-slams-apples-unlawful-eu-app-store-changes/">who think</a> what Apple is “supposed” to do is collect no commission or fees at all on anything other than IAP from apps and games that are distributed through the App Store. That Apple should collect no commission or fees from apps distributed outside the App Store, nor any commission or fees from apps in the App Store that offer their own payment processing — and, thus, that Apple should set their own IAP commission accordingly, as something akin to Stripe or PayPal, in the single-digit percentage range. That’s obviously not in Apple’s interest. But it’s also <em>not</em> what the European Commission has suggested the DMA demands.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1-2025-06-28">
<p>One thing I might be wrong about is that these new terms could be read to suggest that developers who stick with the App Store and Apple’s IAP now pay just 20 percent commission under the new EU terms. That’d be really weird, insofar as it would mean that developers in the EU get an 80/20 split for App Store distribution + IAP, but apps everywhere else in the world still get 70/30 for the same thing. That doesn’t make sense unless there’s another shoe to drop, and Apple is going to reduce IAP to 80/20 worldwide soon. (Which would be a great move on Apple’s part — something that would actually earn them back some developer goodwill.)&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-06-28"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Apple Announces Sweeping but Complicated Policy Changes for Apps in the EU, Attempting to Comply With the Latest Dictums Regarding the DMA</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/06/more_on_apples_trust-eroding_f1_the_movie_wallet_ad" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wfi" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42030</id>
	<published>2025-06-27T17:28:19Z</published>
	<updated>2025-06-28T22:46:34Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Sending this ad is completely destructive to all the hard work other teams at Apple have done to make Apple Wallet actually private — and, more importantly, *to get users to believe that it’s private*.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://mastodon.social/@czeins/114739403773350112">This is a funny gag from Claude Zeins</a>, but if you think about it, it shows just how destructive Apple’s decision was <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/26/apple-wallet-sends-push-notification-ad-pushing-f1-the-movie">to send a push notification from the Wallet app promoting <em>F1 The Movie</em></a>.</p>

<!-- Backup: https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/06/claude-zeins-f1-wallet-gag.jpeg -->

<p>It’s a fact that no company can inject an ad into your physical wallet. It just can’t happen. So if Apple’s message to users is that they should trust Apple Wallet, and move more of their “shit that goes in your wallet” life from their traditional analog wallet into their digital Apple Wallet, that’s the bar. No ads, ever. They’re competing against the privacy and intimacy of one of the most personal things people carry with them.</p>

<p>It’s not just that many people find ads annoying, no matter where they appear. It’s that Apple Wallet ought to be sacrosanct — like the Passwords and Journal apps. Apple is asking us to trust this app with our finances, our <a href="https://learn.wallet.apple/id">identity cards</a>, and our keys. I’m 99.9 percent certain this <em>F1</em> ad was just blasted out to zillions of Wallet users indiscriminately, but some number of users who got it — especially people who know they’re in the demographic for the movie — surely think they got the ad because Wallet is tracking their interests and activities. Like, what if you recently bought tickets to see another summer blockbuster movie? Using Apple Wallet? And then you got this ad? It’d be completely sensible to be spooked by that, and conclude that Apple Wallet is tracking you.</p>

<p>Sending this ad is completely destructive to all the hard work other teams at Apple have done to make Apple Wallet actually private — and, more importantly, <em>to get users to believe that it’s private</em>. That Apple can be trusted in ways that other “big tech” companies cannot. The perception of privacy is just as important as the technical details that make something actually private. I try very seldom to call for anyone to be fired, but I think whoever authorized this movie ad through Wallet push notifications ought to be canned.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ More on Apple’s Trust-Eroding ‘F1 The Movie’ Wallet Ad</title></entry></feed><!-- THE END -->
