<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>Daring Fireball</title>
<subtitle>By John Gruber</subtitle>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/" />
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main" />
<id>https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main</id>


<updated>2025-12-16T19:41:16Z</updated><rights>Copyright © 2025, John Gruber</rights><entry>
	<title>Zara Picken’s ‘Modern Illustration’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.modernillustration.org/?ref=simplebits.com" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ws6" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/16/modern-illustration" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42486</id>
	<published>2025-12-16T19:39:44Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-16T19:41:16Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<blockquote>
  <p>Modern Illustration is a project by illustrator <a href="https://www.zarapicken.com/">Zara Picken</a>,
featuring print artefacts from her extensive personal collection.
Her aim is to preserve and document outstanding examples of
mid-20th century commercial art, creating an accessible resource
for understanding illustration history.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Glorious collection of mid-century illustrations and graphic design. (<a href="https://simplebits.com/notebook/studio-notes-60/">Via Dan Cederholm</a>.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Zara Picken’s ‘Modern Illustration’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/16/modern-illustration">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/12/apple_tv_new_fanfare" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/ws5" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42485</id>
	<published>2025-12-16T19:08:56Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-16T19:08:56Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Netflix’s “tadum” is so iconic that it’s the name of their company blog. HBO’s static + chanted om is the OG standard-setter. I suspect the new Apple TV fanfare will be seen in that class. The old one was not.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Tim Nudd, <a href="https://adage.com/creativity/work/aa-apple-tv-mnemonic-visual-branding/">writing at Ad Age a few weeks ago</a> (paywalled, alas):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>As we <a href="https://adage.com/creativity/campaigns-commercials/aa-creative-ads-today-apple-kraft-mac-cheese-lexus-philadelphia-cream-cheese/">mentioned in roundup</a> yesterday, Finneas (aka, Finneas
O’Connell) has developed a new sonic logo for Apple TV, the
streaming service previously known as Apple TV+. However, the
rebrand, created with Apple agency TBWA\Media Arts Lab, goes
beyond the audio mnemonics to include a striking new visual look
as well.</p>

<p>The visual branding centers on layers of shifting colored light, a
metaphor for the range of genres and emotions that Apple TV has
cultivated since its 2019 debut.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I held off on posting about this new Apple TV fanfare (a.k.a. <em>sonic logo</em>, a.k.a. <em>mnemonic</em> ) until I’d experienced it a few times, and after a few weeks, watching a bunch of episodes from a few Apple TV series — <em><a href="https://tv.apple.com/us/show/mr-scorsese/umc.cmc.4a06j5lm5pxny9nx505zo5g0y">Mr. Scorsese</a></em>, a 5-star five-part documentary by Rebecca Miller, absolutely riveting; <em><a href="https://tv.apple.com/us/show/pluribus/umc.cmc.37axgovs2yozlyh3c2cmwzlza">Pluribus</a></em>, Vince Gilligan’s excellent new the-less-you-know-about-it-before-you-start-watching-<a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/21/pluribus-carol-sturka-ama">the-better</a> series starring Rhea Seehorn; and <em><a href="https://tv.apple.com/us/show/the-morning-show/umc.cmc.25tn3v8ku4b39tr6ccgb8nl6m">The Morning Show</a></em> season 4, a series that’s skirting <em>just</em> above the good-enough-to-keep-watching line for me — I’m willing to render a verdict.</p>

<p>I love it.</p>

<p>The old one was not bad. But “not bad” should never be good enough for Apple. I can’t find anyone from Apple stating so explicitly, but it seems pretty obvious that the piano chord accompanying the old fanfare was meant to evoke the Macintosh startup chime. That’s a neat idea. And no one is more a fan of the Macintosh than me. I’d argue that the Mac remains <em>the</em> definitive Apple product, the one that best exemplifies everything the company does and should stand for. So harking back to the Macintosh was an interesting idea for the Apple TV fanfare/sonic logo/mnemonic.</p>

<p>But: it just wasn’t great. What makes that chord great for a computer booting up doesn’t make it great for a cinematic sonic logo. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GV3HUDMQ-F8">Netflix’s “tadum”</a> is so iconic that it’s <a href="https://www.netflix.com/tudum">the name of their company blog</a>. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=O08PQRA6MLo">HBO’s static + chanted om</a> is the OG standard-setter. I suspect the new Apple TV fanfare will be seen in that class. The old one was not.</p>

<p>The new one feels like a branding stroke unto itself. Sonically, it doesn’t evoke anything else. It just sounds rich and cool. Visually, with its rotating prism effect, it does evoke the classic six-color Apple logo. Thus, despite moving away from a sonic callback to the Macintosh, the overall effect feels <em>more</em> rooted to Apple’s on-the-cusp-of-a-half-century history. The change makes Apple TV original content feel more like a part of Apple, less like a possible passing fancy (which is what <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/10/17/belloni-cue-interview">many in Hollywood fear</a>).</p>

<p>That prism effect was created practically. From <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/tbwamedia-arts-lab_at-mal-we-partnered-with-apple-tv-to-reimagine-activity-7391899271060582400-8OW9/">a LinkedIn post from Apple’s longtime agency partner TBWA Media Arts Lab</a> (no clue why they posted this on LinkedIn, of all places):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Built from real glass and captured entirely in camera, the new
identity explores reflection, color, and light to express the
cinematic spirit at the heart of Apple TV. Every shimmer was made
for real, no CG shortcuts, a nod to Apple’s belief that craft
should be felt, not faked.</p>

<p>The work spans the entire platform, from a sharp five-second show
open to a full-length cinematic version for films, paired with a
new sonic logo composed by Oscar winner Finneas and a custom
typeface, SF TV, developed with Apple’s design team.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>They include a very short video showing behind the scenes of its creation. It matters not to me that they photographed this practically, rather than via computer-generated graphics, but the bottom line is that it looks cool, timeless, and Apple-y.</p>

<p><a href="https://variety.com/2025/music/news/finneas-discusses-apple-tv-originals-mnemonic-intro-1236568433/">Chris Willman at Variety has an interview with Finneas</a> (O’Connell) regarding the music:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>Mnemonic</em>, Finneas says, “is sort of a beautiful word for a
logo” accompanied by sound. “The things that I think of as real
classic mnemonics are NBC — you can hear that in your head — or
HBO has its static.” Finneas is well aware of how modern
streaming consumption might make this especially ubiquitous,
household by household. “If you’re binge-ing the whole season of
<em>Ted Lasso</em> or <em>Severance</em> or <em>Disclaimer</em>” (the last of those
being the limited series that he composed the score for himself),
“you’re going to hear the mnemonic 10 times in one day. So it’s
gotta be something that’s like the bite of ginger between rolls
or something, you know?”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>See and hear for yourself. Here’s the old Apple TV mnemonic:</p>

<p><video
    width = 500
    controls
    src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/12/Apple-TV-Plus-Mnemonic-Old.mp4">
</video></p>

<p>Here’s the new 5-second version, shown at the beginning of each episode of Apple TV original series:</p>

<p><video
    width = 500
    controls
    src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/12/Apple-TV-Mnemonic-New-5s.mp4">
</video></p>

<p>And here’s the full 12-second version, shown before Apple Original Films:</p>

<p><video
    width = 500
    controls
    src = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/12/Apple-TV-Mnemonic-New-12s.mp4">
</video></p>

<p>Bravo.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Apple TV’s New Fanfare</title></entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://finalist.works/df" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/ws4" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/12/finalist_daily_planner_for_ios" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.42484</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-12-16T02:52:31Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-16T02:52:31Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Finalist is an iOS planner rooted in paper. Originally an index card system, it grew into a love letter to paper planners. You know the kind, leather folders with colored tabs and translucent dividers.</p>

<p>Unlike those old binders, Finalist fills itself with your calendars, reminders and weather forecast. Minimalist? Maybe not, but it’s become a UI playground designed to inspire, and looks great on iPad and Mac too.</p>

<p>Like the gorgeous new Year Planner for roughing in plans with the Highlighter (“intention paintbrush”).</p>

<p>iOS has tons of cool productivity apps. Finalist is a different take, and it might just end up in your dock.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Finalist Daily Planner for iOS’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/12/finalist_daily_planner_for_ios">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] Finalist Daily Planner for iOS</title></entry><entry>
	<title>‘A Brief History of Times New Roman’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://typographyforlawyers.com/a-brief-history-of-times-new-roman.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ws3" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/15/a-brief-history-of-timesnewroman" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42483</id>
	<published>2025-12-16T01:03:17Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-16T05:28:11Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/10/butterick-times-new-roman">One more</a> from Matthew Butterick, from his <em>Typography for Lawyers</em>, and a good <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/15/the-scourge-of-arial">pairing</a> with Mark Simonson’s “<a href="https://www.marksimonson.com/notebook/view/the-scourge-of-arial/">The Scourge of Arial</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Yet it’s an open question whether its longevity is attributable to
its quality or merely its ubiquity. Helvetica still inspires
enough affection to have been the subject of a 2007 documentary
feature. Times New Roman, meanwhile, has not attracted similar
acts of homage.</p>

<p>Why not? Fame has a dark side. When Times New Roman appears in a
book, document, or advertisement, it connotes apathy. It says, “I
submitted to the font of least resistance.” Times New Roman is not
a font choice so much as the absence of a font choice, like the
blackness of deep space is not a color. To look at Times New Roman
is to gaze into the void.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>As Simonson mentions in “The Scourge of Arial”, regarding Helvetica’s enduring popularity:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>As it spread into the mainstream in the ’70s, many designers tired
of it and moved on to other typographic fashions, but by then it
had become a staple of everyday design and printing. So in the
early ’80s when Adobe developed the PostScript page description
language, it was no surprise that they chose Helvetica as one of
the basic four fonts to be included with every PostScript
interpreter they licensed (along with Times, Courier, and Symbol).
Adobe licensed its fonts from the original foundries,
demonstrating their respect and appreciation for the integrity of
type, type foundries and designers. They perhaps realized that if
they had used knock-offs of popular typefaces, the professional
graphic arts industry — a key market — would not accept them.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>To my mind, Helvetica, Times, and Courier are <em>the</em> three canonical “default” fonts. One modern sans, one modern serif, and one for “typewriter”/code. (When I see Courier in print, at display sizes, my mind immediately wonders if the printer was missing the font that the designer specified in the document file.)</p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Symbol_(typeface)">The Symbol font</a> is a different story. It existed and was included with PostScript as one of just four defaults because the 8-bit character encodings of the time only had space for 255 characters. You needed a special font like Symbol to access “exotic” characters like Greek letters, math symbols (e.g. × or ÷), or arrows (↑ ↓ ← →). So there were really only three regular “fonts”, for prose, included with PostScript: Helvetica, Courier, and Times.</p>

<p>Courier and Times were eventually superseded in popular use by rivals that Microsoft licensed for inclusion in Windows: Courier New and Times New Roman, respectively. Times was from Linotype, Times New Roman from Monotype. Both versions of Times are legitimate digital interpretations of the 1929 hot metal design of Times Roman, and <a href="https://creativepro.com/times-roman-vs-times-new-roman/">their differences are minor</a>. Courier New, on the other hand, is <a href="http://www.identifont.com/differences?first=Courier+New&amp;second=Courier">so ugly</a> — anemically thin and weak — that it hurts my teeth whenever I encounter it.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘A Brief History of Times New Roman’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/15/a-brief-history-of-timesnewroman">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘The Scourge of Arial’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.marksimonson.com/notebook/view/the-scourge-of-arial/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ws1" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/15/the-scourge-of-arial" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42481</id>
	<published>2025-12-16T00:05:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-16T00:24:26Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Typographer Mark Simonson, all the way back in 2001:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Arial is everywhere. If you don’t know what it is, you don’t
use a modern personal computer. Arial is a font that is
familiar to anyone who uses Microsoft products, whether on a PC
or a Mac. It has spread like a virus through the typographic
landscape and illustrates the pervasiveness of Microsoft’s
influence in the world.</p>

<p>Arial’s ubiquity is not due to its beauty. It’s actually rather
homely. Not that homeliness is necessarily a bad thing for a
typeface. With typefaces, character and history are just as
important. Arial, however, has a rather dubious history and not
much character. In fact, Arial is little more than a shameless
impostor.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is <em>the</em> exegesis on Arial. There’s also an exemplary illustrated sidebar, “<a href="https://www.marksimonson.com/notebook/view/how-to-spot-arial/">How to Spot Arial</a>”, which shows in detail how to tell the fucking bastard from Helvetica. If you want to be like me, cursed to notice Arial each time it appears in life, study that, and take note how every single way that it’s different from Helvetica is in the direction of making it uglier.</p>

<p>I’ve <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2007/07/iphone_fonts">referenced</a> “The Scourge of Arial” a few times over the years here at DF, but the <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/10/state-department-times-new-roman">recent</a> <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/12/full_text_of_marco_rubio_state_dept_directive_times_new_roman">contretemps</a> over Times New Roman’s return at the US State Department has the general topic of “default fonts” at top of mind. For me, at least.</p>

<p>One of the old posts in which I linked to “The Scourge of Arial” was this gem from September 2007: “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2007/09/hacking_the_iphone_notes_app">Hacking the iPhone Notes App for the Admittedly Nit-Picky Purpose of Changing the Text Font to Helvetica</a>”. This was so early in the iPhone era — just three months after the original iPhone shipped — that we were calling its operating system “mobile OS X”, and none of it was protected in any way, so you could do what I did and delete the Marker Felt font (<a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2007/07/11/marker-felt">Merlin Mann</a>: “Comic Sans with a shave and a breath mint”) and then use a hex editor to modify the Mobile Notes app so it would fall back to Helvetica instead of cursed Arial after Marker Felt was deleted. Good times.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘The Scourge of Arial’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/15/the-scourge-of-arial">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>A Note on Current SMS Marketing Practices</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/15/note-on-sms-marketing" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ws2" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/15/note-on-sms-marketing" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42482</id>
	<published>2025-12-16T00:02:08Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-16T00:23:50Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Back on November 28, I bought a new cap from <a href="https://www.neweracap.com/pages/our-story">New Era</a>’s web store. They offered a discount of some sort if I gave them a phone number and permitted them to send me marketing messages. That got me curious about what they’d do with my number, and it was a $50-some dollar cap, so I took the discount and gave them my Google Voice number. That was 17 days ago. They sent me 19 SMS marketing messages since then, before I’d seen enough today and called it quits on this experiment. (Or called “STOP”, perhaps, which was the magic word to opt out.) They didn’t send a text every day, and on some days, they sent more than one. But the overall effect was relentlessly annoying.</p>

<p>I’m sure some of the people who sign up for these texts in exchange for a discount code wind up clicking at least one of the offers sent via SMS and buying more stuff, and the marketing team running this points to those sales as proof that it “works”. You can measure that. It shows up as a number. Some people in business only like arguments that can be backed by numbers. 3 is more than 2. That is indeed a fact.</p>

<p>But there are an <em>infinite</em> number of things in life that cannot be assigned numeric values. Many of these things matter too. Like the fact that in my mind, after experiencing this, the New Era company smells like a sweaty hustler in a cheap polyester suit. If their brand were a man, I’d check my pants pocket for my wallet after interacting with him.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘A Note on Current SMS Marketing Practices’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/15/note-on-sms-marketing">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Disney, Immediately After Partnering With OpenAI for Sora, Sends Google a Cease-and-Desist Letter Accusing Them of Copyright Infringement on ‘Massive Scale’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://variety.com/2025/digital/news/disney-google-ai-copyright-infringement-cease-and-desist-letter-1236606429/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ws0" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/15/disney-google-cease-and-desist" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42480</id>
	<published>2025-12-15T21:13:40Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-15T21:14:10Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Todd Spangler, reporting last week for Variety:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>As Disney has <a href="https://variety.com/2025/digital/news/disney-openai-deal-200-characters-to-sora-video-invests-1-billion-1236606401/">gone into business with OpenAI</a>, the Mouse
House is accusing Google of copyright infringement on a “massive
scale” using AI models and services to “commercially exploit and
distribute” infringing images and videos. On Wednesday evening,
attorneys for Disney sent a cease-and-desist letter to Google,
demanding that Google stop the alleged infringement in its AI
systems. [...]</p>

<p>According to the letter, which Variety has reviewed, Disney
alleges that Google’s AI systems and services infringe Disney
characters including those from “Frozen,” “The Lion King,”
“Moana,” “The Little Mermaid,” “Deadpool,” “Guardians of the
Galaxy,” “Toy Story,” “Brave,” “Ratatouille,” “Monsters Inc.,”
“Lilo &amp; Stich,” “Inside Out” and franchises such as Star Wars, the
Simpsons, and Marvel’s Avengers and Spider-Man. In its letter,
Disney included examples of images it claims were generated by
text prompts in Google’s AI apps, including of Darth Vader
(<em>pictured above</em>).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s very Disney-esque to embrace a new medium. Alone among the major movie studios in the 1950s, Disney embraced television. TV <em>was</em> a threat to the cinema, but it was also an enormous opportunity. The other studios only saw the threat. Walt Disney focused on the opportunity. But Disney did this not by giving their content to television on the cheap or for free. They did it by getting paid. That’s what they’re doing with generative AI.</p>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/12/disney-google-ai-cease-and-desist-darth-vader.png">Here’s the Gemini-generated Darth Vader image</a>. Note the blood splatter — which was un-<em>Star Wars</em>-like even before Disney’s purchase of Lucasfilm. Also, even worse, his lightsaber is totally wrong.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Disney, Immediately After Partnering With OpenAI for Sora, Sends Google a Cease-and-Desist Letter Accusing Them of Copyright Infringement on ‘Massive Scale’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/15/disney-google-cease-and-desist">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Roomba Maker iRobot Declares Bankruptcy, Falls Into Chinese Hands</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.wsj.com/business/roomba-maker-declares-bankruptcy-but-tries-to-ease-bricking-fears-fe73dff2?st=XATuAs" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wrz" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/15/roomba-maker-irobot-declares-bankruptcy" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42479</id>
	<published>2025-12-15T18:50:21Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-15T18:50:21Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>John Keilman, reporting for The Wall Street Journal (gift link):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The company that makes Roomba robotic vacuums declared bankruptcy
Sunday but said its devices will continue to function normally
while the company restructures.</p>

<p>Massachusetts-based iRobot has struggled financially for
years, beset by foreign competition that made cheaper and, in the
opinion of some buyers, technologically superior autonomous
vacuums. When a proposed sale to Amazon.com fell through in 2024
<a href="https://www.wsj.com/business/retail/amazon-irobot-scrap-acquisition-deal-7072122f">because of regulatory concerns</a>, the company’s share price
plummeted.</p>

<p>Founded in 1990, iRobot’s autonomous vacuum cleaners helped
pioneer robotics for consumers. Many recent versions of the Roomba
have features that are controlled through the brand’s app. Some
owners have worried that, similar to other products tied to the
internet, their Roombas could “brick” — or stop working — if the
company went under. iRobot said it anticipates no disruptions to
its product support or app functionality.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Matt Stoller, author of the (generally excellent) website <a href="https://www.thebignewsletter.com/">Big</a>, <a href="https://x.com/matthewstoller/status/2000567118207828114">on Twitter/X today</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>iRobot is selling itself to Chinese manufacturers, a result of
hedge fund attack a decade ago that gutted the company. Wall
Street is a threat to our national sovereignty.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Matt Stoller, author of the (generally knee-jerk anti-acquisition) website Big, <a href="https://x.com/matthewstoller/status/1555530144407867392">on Twitter back in 2022</a>, when Amazon announced its intended acquisition:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Amazon just bought iRobot, which has immense amounts of data about
people’s physical homes. It never ends. Congress should have
passed <a href="https://x.com/TomCottonAR">@TomCottonAR</a>’s bill to bar big tech mergers.</p>

<p>[Press release: “<a href="https://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/amazon-and-irobot-sign-an-agreement-for-amazon-to-acquire-irobot-301600720.html">Amazon and iRobot sign an agreement for Amazon to acquire iRobot</a>”]</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You can’t have it both ways. If Amazon’s proposed acquisition would have gone through, iRobot, an American company, would now be a (small) subsidiary of Amazon, another American company. The acquisition did not go through, which is what Stoller wanted, and now here we are with iRobot — which in Stoller’s own description “has immense amounts of data about people’s physical homes” — in the hands of a Chinese company.</p>

<p>iRobot’s demise wasn’t caused by hedge fund investments a decade ago. The hedge fund vultures swooped in after the Amazon acquisition collapsed in early 2024. Here’s Connie Loizos, writing yesterday for TechCrunch:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It seemed like a fairy tale ending — the scrappy MIT spinoff
absorbed into the Everything Store’s sprawling empire.</p>

<p>Except European regulators had other ideas. Indeed, amid threats
they would block the deal — they believed Amazon could foreclose
rivals by restricting or degrading access to its marketplace — Amazon and iRobot agreed to <a href="https://www.wsj.com/business/retail/amazon-irobot-scrap-acquisition-deal-7072122">kill the deal</a> in January 2024,
with Amazon paying a $94 million breakup fee and walking away.
Angle resigned. The company’s shares nosedived. It shed 31% of its
workforce.</p>

<p>What followed afterward was a slow-motion collapse. Earnings had
been declining since 2021 thanks to supply chain chaos and Chinese
competitors flooding the market with cheaper robot vacuums.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>iRobot didn’t get big enough on its own quickly enough. It was under fierce competitive pressure from Chinese robot vacuums. Roombas seemed groundbreaking and innovative at first, but technical progress stalled. Amazon’s hands aren’t exactly clean in terms of putting the squeeze on iRobot: the primary place where the cheaper Chinese robot vacuums were being sold was, of course, Amazon.</p>

<p>By 2022, the Amazon acquisition was iRobot’s lifeline. <a href="https://www.wsj.com/business/retail/amazon-irobot-scrap-acquisition-deal-7072122f">EU regulators wanted it shot down</a>, and despite the fact that it was one American company trying to acquire another, the anti-big-tech Biden administration clearly preferred to let the deal collapse. The US should have told the EU to mind their own companies.</p>

<p>Now iRobot is in Chinese hands, the worst possible outcome. The Amazon acquisition wasn’t anti-competitive — it was iRobot’s last chance to remain competitive.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Roomba Maker iRobot Declares Bankruptcy, Falls Into Chinese Hands’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/15/roomba-maker-irobot-declares-bankruptcy">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Jaho Coffee Roaster</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.jaho.com/s/df" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wry" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/15/jaho-coffee-roaster" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42478</id>
	<published>2025-12-15T05:17:23Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-15T05:17:33Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to Jaho Coffee Roaster for sponsoring last week at DF. Great coffee changes the day. Since 2005, Jaho’s family-owned roastery has taken the slow and careful approach, sourcing small-lot coffees, roasting in small batches and shipping every bag fresh. Award-winning coffee delivered to your home or office, shipped fresh nationwide.</p>

<p>Jaho was kind enough to send me a few bags of their beans, and I can vouch that they roast <em>excellent</em> coffee — the kind of tasty beans where, when I finish my last morning cup, I’m tempted to brew a little more even though I know I’m fully caffeinated.</p>

<p>Holiday gifts? Fresh coffee is a gift that never misses, easy to give, even better to receive. Give better coffee this season. Even better: DF readers get 20 percent off with code <strong>DF</strong>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Jaho Coffee Roaster’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/15/jaho-coffee-roaster">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Rob Reiner and Wife Found Stabbed to Death at Home</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://deadline.com/2025/12/rob-reiner-two-reported-dead-at-home-lapd-1236648185/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wrx" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/14/rob-reiner-stabbed-to-death" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42477</id>
	<published>2025-12-15T03:50:02Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-15T04:09:05Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Deadline:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The bodies of Rob Reiner and his wife Michele Reiner have been found in their Brentwood home, sources confirmed to Deadline.</p>

<p>It appears the acclaimed director and his wife were slain by knife wounds.</p>

<p>The LAPD are on the scene, but have not issued an official confirmation yet. A press conference is expected to take place tonight.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://people.com/rob-reiner-wife-michele-were-killed-by-son-sources-11868856">People</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Rob Reiner and his wife, Michele Singer Reiner, were killed by their son, Nick, multiple sources confirm to People.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So it goes.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Rob Reiner and Wife Found Stabbed to Death at Home’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/14/rob-reiner-stabbed-to-death">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Pluribus’ Becomes Apple TV’s Most Watched Show Ever</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/12/12/pluribus-most-watched-show-ever-on-apple-tv/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wrw" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/13/pluribus-most-watched" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42476</id>
	<published>2025-12-13T22:59:22Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-15T17:07:14Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Marcus Mendes, 9to5Mac:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Now, on the same day that <em>F1 The Movie</em> debuted at the top of
Apple TV’s movie rankings, the company confirmed that <em>Pluribus</em>
has reached another, even more impressive milestone: it is the
most watched show in the service’s history. Busy day. [...]</p>

<p>Apple doesn’t share viewership numbers, so it is hard to quantify
what exactly this means.</p>

<p>However, considering that Apple TV has had quite a few hit
shows, including <em>Ted Lasso</em>, <em>Severance</em>, <em>The Morning Show</em>,
<em>Slow Horses</em>, and, more recently, <em>The Studio</em>, it is still
notable that Pluribus has managed to top them all in just a few
short weeks.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/21/pluribus-carol-sturka-ama">love</a> <em>Pluribus</em>. I’d rank it behind <em>Severance</em> and <em>Slow Horses</em>, but it’s a close call between <em>Pluribus</em> and <em>The Studio</em> for third place on my Apple TV favorites list. Great shows all four of them. I don’t think there’s any question that when it comes to prestige series, Apple TV had the best 2025. Which other streamer had four shows of that caliber this year?</p>

<p><a href="https://kottke.org/25/11/whats-all-the-fuss-about-pluribus">Jason Kottke is iffy on it</a>, though, because he’s not seeing the appeal of Rhea Seehorn’s protagonist Carol Sturka. Count me <a href="https://maxfrequency.net/2025/12/02/pluribus-very-good-jason-kottke">with Max Roberts</a> — I find Carol very compelling, and uncomfortably realistic. She feels to me like a real person, not a “character”. It’s one of the best cinematic explorations of loneliness since Tom Hanks in <em><a href="https://www.themoviedb.org/movie/8358-cast-away">Cast Away</a></em>, or <em><a href="https://www.themoviedb.org/movie/10681-wall-e">WALL-E</a></em>. <strong>Update:</strong> A few more that come to mind: <em><a href="https://www.themoviedb.org/movie/286217-the-martian">The Martian</a></em> and <em><a href="https://www.themoviedb.org/movie/17431-moon">Moon</a></em>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Pluribus’ Becomes Apple TV’s Most Watched Show Ever’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/13/pluribus-most-watched">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Lucas de Groot, Designer of Calibri, on the State Department’s Switch Back to Times New Roman</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46229533" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wrv" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/13/de-groot-calibri-times-new-roman" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42475</id>
	<published>2025-12-13T20:38:18Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-13T20:38:19Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>From the LucasFonts account, in a comment on Hacker News:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Professional typography can be achieved with both serif and
sans-serif fonts. However, Times New Roman — a typeface older
than the current president — presents unique challenges.
Originally crafted in Great Britain for newspaper printing, Times
was optimised for paper, with each letterform meticulously cut and
tested for specific sizes. In the digital era, larger size
drawings were repurposed as models, resulting in a typeface that
appears too thin and sharp when printed at high quality.</p>

<p>Serif fonts are often perceived as more traditional, but they are
also more demanding to use effectively. While a skilled
typographer can, in theory, produce excellent results with Times,
using it in its default digital form is not considered
professional practice.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This echoes my thoughts: the State Department should use a traditional-looking serif typeface, but they should choose — or even better, commission — something far better than Times New Roman.</p>

<p>Also from that Hacker News thread, comes <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46244661">this</a> delightful Easter egg: <a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=Lucas+de+Groot">do a Google search for “Lucas de Groot”</a>, and the results will be set in Calibri. Same thing for common fonts like, yes, <a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=Times+New+Roman">Times New Roman</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Lucas de Groot, Designer of Calibri, on the State Department’s Switch Back to Times New Roman’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/13/de-groot-calibri-times-new-roman">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Pondering Middle East Petrostates as American Media Owners</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.businessinsider.com/paramount-warner-discovery-larry-ellison-saudi-arabia-qatar-wbd-deal-2025-12" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wru" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/13/pondering-middle-east-petrostates-as-american-media-owners" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42474</id>
	<published>2025-12-13T17:16:28Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-13T17:16:28Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Peter Kafka, writing at Business Insider:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>And last: It’s possible that Middle Eastern countries are
investing in an American media conglomerate solely for a financial
return, and would have zero interest in the content that
conglomerate makes and distributes. But that’s an assertion that
many folks would have a hard time taking at face value. And while
lots of American companies have sought Middle Eastern funding for
years, there was a pause after 2018, following the murder and
dismemberment of Washington Post contributor Jamal Khashoggi — a
shocking act <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/cia-assessment-mohammed-bin-salman-khashoggi-murder-trump-russia-2018-11">the CIA concluded was ordered by Saudi Arabia’s
Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman himself</a>. (He has denied
involvement.)</p>

<p>Now bin Salman might end up owning a piece of major American news
outlets and other media arms. How’s that going to go over?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>David Ellison’s hostile takeover proposal <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/09/paramount-hostile-takeover-warner-bros">reportedly would have these Middle East partners owning “non-voting” shares</a>, but regardless of their rights in the corporate by-laws, their mere ownership would give them influence. These are profoundly fucked-up countries, where <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Women%27s_rights_in_Saudi_Arabia">women are a repressed underclass</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LGBTQ_rights_in_the_Middle_East">LGBT activity is punishable <em>by death</em></a>, and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Women%27s_rights_in_Saudi_Arabia">their word is worth nothing</a> when they promise to abide by Western norms.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Pondering Middle East Petrostates as American Media Owners’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/13/pondering-middle-east-petrostates-as-american-media-owners">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Infinite Loop of One LLM Talking to Another</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.instagram.com/reel/DRd2ldWkQYr" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wrt" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/13/llm-infinite-loop" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42473</id>
	<published>2025-12-13T16:26:23Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-13T16:26:23Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>This is very funny, but also a good indication of just how far away these things are from actual intelligence. First, a reasonable human being would never get caught in a loop like this. Second, only humans can not only recognize what’s going on here, but also see the humor in it.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Infinite Loop of One LLM Talking to Another’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/13/llm-infinite-loop">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Paris Buttfield-Addison’s Apple Account Is in Kafka Mode</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://hey.paris/posts/appleid/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wrs" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/13/buttfield-addison-apple-account" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42472</id>
	<published>2025-12-13T15:09:39Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-13T16:41:54Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Paris Buttfield-Addison:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A major brick-and-mortar store sold an Apple Gift Card that Apple
seemingly took offence to, and locked out my entire Apple ID,
effectively bricking my devices and my iCloud Account, Apple
Developer ID, and everything associated with it, and I have no
recourse. [...]</p>

<p>I am not a casual user. I have <a href="https://hey.paris/books-and-events/books/#books">literally written the book on
Apple development (taking over the <em>Learning Cocoa with
Objective-C</em> series, which Apple themselves used to write, for
O’Reilly Media, and then 20+ books following that)</a>. I
help run the longest-running Apple developer event not run by
Apple themselves, <a href="https://devworld.au/index.php">/dev/world</a>. I have effectively been
an evangelist for this company’s technology for my entire
professional life. We had an app on the App Store on Day 1 in
every sense of the world.</p>

<p>I am asking for a human at Apple to review this case. I suspect an
automated fraud flag regarding the bad gift card triggered a
nuclear response that frontline support cannot override. I have
escalated this through my many friends in WWDR and SRE at Apple,
with no success.</p>

<p>I am desperate to resolve this and restore my digital life.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The triggering event, as best he can determine, was his failed attempt to redeem a $500 Apple gift card purchased from a major retail chain. There’s <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46252114">a very active thread on Hacker News</a> about his plight, where Buttfield-Addison himself is <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/threads?id=parisidau">commenting</a>. That thread pointed to <a href="https://www.ozbargain.com.au/node/937339">this description</a> of one form of gift card thievery, in which thieves tamper with the cards in-store to steal the codes, tamper with the code, and then some unsuspecting victim buys the tampered card and the thieves get the credit.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Paris Buttfield-Addison’s Apple Account Is in Kafka Mode’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/13/buttfield-addison-apple-account">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Daring Fireball Weekly Sponsorships, End of Year and Q1 2026</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wrq" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/12/df-sponsorships-end-of-year" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42470</id>
	<published>2025-12-13T04:00:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-13T21:18:08Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Weekly sponsorships have been the top source of revenue for Daring Fireball ever since I started selling them <a href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/archive">back in 2007</a>. They’ve succeeded, I think, because they make everyone happy. They generate good money. There’s only one sponsor per week and the sponsors are always relevant to at least some sizable portion of the DF audience, so you, the reader, are never annoyed and hopefully often intrigued by them. And, from the sponsors’ perspective, they work. My favorite thing about them is how many sponsors <a href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/archive">return for subsequent weeks</a> after seeing the results.</p>

<p>After a solid run in the second half of 2025 with sponsorships sold out weeks, if not months, in advance, we’ve arrived at the end of the year with the last three weeks still open — starting this coming Monday. I’m offering those weeks at a discount.</p>

<ul>
<li>December 15–21 (next week)</li>
<li>December 22–28</li>
<li>December 29–January 4</li>
</ul>

<p>Traffic at DF tends not to ebb over holidays, and while I slow down, I don’t stop posting. If <em>you</em> still check DF when you’re bored over the holidays, think about how many other people do too.</p>

<p>I’m also booking sponsorships for Q1 2026, and six of those weeks are already sold.</p>

<p>If you’ve got a product or service you think would be of interest to DF’s audience of people obsessed with high quality and good design, <a href="mailto:sponsors@daringfireball.net?subject=Feed%20Sponsorship">get in touch</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Daring Fireball Weekly Sponsorships, End of Year and Q1 2026’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/12/df-sponsorships-end-of-year">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple at the AWS re:Invent 2025 Keynote</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=O46695Y7ab8" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wrr" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/12/apple-aws-reinvent-keynote" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42471</id>
	<published>2025-12-12T23:22:39Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-13T00:06:53Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Six-minute segment from Amazon’s AWS re:Invent keynote last week:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Payam Mirrashidi, VP, Cloud Systems &amp; Platforms, Apple, explains
how AWS Graviton helps improve developer velocity at scale. Hear
Swift’s journey from the premier programming language for the
Apple ecosystem to adoption by millions of developers around the
world building apps for everything from devices to data centers.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>(Graviton is AWS’s ARM-in-the-cloud initiative.)</p>

<p>Nothing earth-shaking in this brief presentation, but it’s not often you see an Apple VP on stage at another company’s keynote, or see Apple so very publicly declare their reliance on someone else’s infrastructure. It speaks to Apple and Amazon being more allies than competitors amongst the big tech companies. And of course, you even less often see anyone from Apple speak live on stage at Apple’s own keynotes, which, alas, are no longer live nor on stages.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple at the AWS re:Invent 2025 Keynote’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/12/apple-aws-reinvent-keynote">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Special Dyslexia Fonts Are Based on Voodoo Pseudoscience</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.edutopia.org/article/do-dyslexia-fonts-actually-work" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wrp" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/12/dyslexia-fonts-pseudoscience" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42469</id>
	<published>2025-12-12T18:37:47Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-12T18:37:48Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Youki Terada, writing for Edutopia in 2022 (via <a href="https://typo.social/@jenskutilek/115701215633708390">Jens Kutílek</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Under close scrutiny, the evidence for dyslexia-friendly fonts
falls apart. In a <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11881-016-0127-1">2017 study</a>, for example, researchers tested
whether OpenDyslexic, a popular font with thicker lines near the
bottom of the letters, could improve the reading rate and accuracy
for young children with dyslexia. According to the developers of
the font, which is open-source and free of charge, the “heaviness”
of the letters prevented them from turning upside down for readers
with dyslexia, which they claimed would improve reading accuracy
and speed.</p>

<p>Researchers put the font to the test, comparing it with two other
popular fonts designed for legibility — Arial and Times New Roman — and discovered that the purportedly dyslexia-friendly font
actually reduced reading speed and accuracy. In addition, none of
the students preferred to read material in OpenDyslexic, a
surprising rebuke for a font specifically designed for the task.</p>

<p>In a separate <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11881-017-0154-6">2018 study</a>, researchers compared another popular
dyslexia font — Dyslexie, which charges a fee for usage — with
Arial and Times New Roman and found no benefit to reading
accuracy and speed. As with the previous dyslexia font, children
expressed a preference for the mainstream fonts. “All in all, the
font Dyslexie, developed to facilitate the reading of dyslexic
people, does not have the desired effect,” the researchers
concluded. “Children with dyslexia do not read better when text
is printed in the font Dyslexie than when text is printed in
Arial or Times New Roman.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Quoting from the abstract of <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11881-016-0127-1">the first study cited above</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Results from this alternating treatment experiment show no
improvement in reading rate or accuracy for individual students
with dyslexia, as well as the group as a whole. While some
students commented that [OpenDyslexic] was “new” or “different”,
none of the participants reported preferring to read material
presented in that font. These results indicate there may be no
benefit for translating print materials to this font.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The problem isn’t dyslexia if you don’t notice that <a href="https://opendyslexic.org/">OpenDyslexic</a> is  “different”.</p>

<p>Quoting from <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11881-017-0154-6">the second cited study</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Words written in Dyslexie font were not read faster or more
accurately. Moreover, participants showed a preference for the
fonts Arial and Times New Roman rather than Dyslexie, and again,
preference was not related to reading performance. These
experiments clearly justify the conclusion that the Dyslexie font
neither benefits nor impedes the reading process of children with
and without dyslexia.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>OpenDyslexic’s website has <a href="https://opendyslexic.org/related-research">a “related research” page</a> but of the four articles they link to, three are 404s, and the other one only studied “extra-large letter spacing”. I chased down <a href="https://vtechworks.lib.vt.edu/server/api/core/bitstreams/d2aff585-f8a5-4152-b9c8-a177f84a3979/content">the correct link</a> to one of the other articles they cite, and the only fonts it studied were Verdana, Arial, Georgia, and Times.</p>

<p>Some people claim to prefer reading text set with OpenDyslexic. Some people like Comic Sans, too. But I was unaware that these typefaces that purport to be designed specifically to benefit people with dyslexia are based on misguided beliefs that dyslexia is a visual problem, and that actual research shows they do not provide the benefits they claim to. They’re just ugly fonts.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Special Dyslexia Fonts Are Based on Voodoo Pseudoscience’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/12/dyslexia-fonts-pseudoscience">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>iMessage Doesn’t Use APNs for Attachments</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://support.apple.com/guide/security/how-imessage-sends-and-receives-messages-sec70e68c949/web" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wro" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/12/imessage-apns-attachments" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42468</id>
	<published>2025-12-12T17:29:02Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-12T17:30:14Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Small follow-up point re: <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/12/imessage_push_notifications_hard_to_block">my post this week</a> on iMessage’s delivery architecture being built atop the Apple Push Notification service:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>APNs can only relay messages up to 4 or 16 KB in size, depending
on the iOS or iPadOS version. If the message text is too long or
if an attachment such as a photo is included, the attachment is
encrypted using AES in CTR mode with a randomly generated 256-bit
key and uploaded to iCloud. The AES key for the attachment, its
Uniform Resource Identifier (URI), and an SHA-1 hash of its
encrypted form are then sent to the recipient as the contents of
an iMessage, with their confidentiality and integrity protected
through normal iMessage encryption, as shown in the following
diagram.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This explains why you can often text, but not send or receive images, with iMessage over in-flight Wi-Fi. (<a href="https://infosec.exchange/@adamshostack/115696265565038136">Thanks to Adam Shostack</a> for flagging this detail.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘iMessage Doesn’t Use APNs for Attachments’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/12/imessage-apns-attachments">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>OpenAI Releases GPT-5.2</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://openai.com/index/introducing-gpt-5-2/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wrn" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/12/gpt-5-2" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42467</id>
	<published>2025-12-12T15:53:32Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-12T15:53:33Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>OpenAI:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In ChatGPT, GPT‑5.2 Instant, Thinking, and Pro will begin rolling
out today, starting with paid plans. In the API, they are
available now to all developers.</p>

<p>Overall, GPT‑5.2 brings significant improvements in general
intelligence, long-context understanding, agentic tool-calling,
and vision — making it better at executing complex, real-world
tasks end-to-end than any previous model.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>5.1 was released just <a href="https://openai.com/index/gpt-5-1/">one month ago</a>, but 5.2 delivers a slew of measurable improvements across the board. Where 5.1 was <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/11/chatgpt_5-1_with_renamed_and_new_personalities">seemingly more about the <em>feel</em> of responses</a>, the personality, 5.2 was clearly focused on tangible and benchmarkable gains.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘OpenAI Releases GPT-5.2’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/12/gpt-5-2">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Trump’s Dogshit White House Signage Typography</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.yahoo.com/news/articles/white-house-just-revealed-another-210003798.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wrm" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/10/trumps-dogshit-white-house-signage-typography" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42466</id>
	<published>2025-12-11T02:25:42Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-11T20:41:46Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Before anyone starts patting the Trump administration on its back for <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/12/full_text_of_marco_rubio_state_dept_directive_times_new_roman">one good typographic decision</a>, take a gander at the hard-to-believe-this-is-real new signage at (and alas, on) the White House. This is the sort of signage that typically spells “Business Center” across from the check-in desk at a Courtyard Marriott. The Biden State Department replacing Times New Roman with Calibri was a typographic misdemeanor. Festooning the White House with signage set in gold-plated <a href="https://www.myfonts.com/collections/shelley-script-font-linotype/">Shelley Script</a> ought to land Trump in The Hague.</p>

<p>(The idea that the Oval Office ought to be explicitly labeled “The Oval Office” — whatever the typeface or signage style — brings to mind <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/12/far-side-a-few-things-around-here-mono.png">this classic <em>Far Side</em> cartoon</a>, which I think aptly illustrates the president’s mental faculties.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Trump’s Dogshit White House Signage Typography’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/10/trumps-dogshit-white-house-signage-typography">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Those Fonts Are Favored Only by the Apathetic and Sloppy’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://practicaltypography.com/typography-in-ten-minutes.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wrl" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/10/butterick-times-new-roman" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42465</id>
	<published>2025-12-11T02:01:56Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-11T02:07:34Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The fifth of five rules in Matthew Butterick’s “Typography in Ten Minutes”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>And finally, font choice. The fastest, easiest, and most visible
improvement you can make to your typography is to ignore the fonts
already loaded on your computer (known as <a href="https://practicaltypography.com/system-fonts.html">system fonts</a>)
and the <a href="https://practicaltypography.com/free-fonts.html">free fonts</a> that inundate the internet. Instead,
buy a professional font (like those found in <a href="https://practicaltypography.com/font-recommendations.html">font
recommendations</a>). A professional font gives you the benefit
of a professional designer’s skills without having to hire one.</p>

<p>If that’s impossible, you can still make good typography with
system fonts. But choose wisely. And never choose <a href="https://practicaltypography.com/times-new-roman-alternatives.html">Times New
Roman</a> or <a href="https://practicaltypography.com/helvetica-and-arial-alternatives.html">Arial</a>, as those fonts are favored only by
the apathetic and sloppy. Not by typographers. Not by you.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>(<a href="https://typo.social/@verbosus/115696232964814142">Via Antonio Cavedoni</a>.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Those Fonts Are Favored Only by the Apathetic and Sloppy’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/10/butterick-times-new-roman">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/12/full_text_of_marco_rubio_state_dept_directive_times_new_roman" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wrk" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42464</id>
	<published>2025-12-10T23:53:51Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-11T22:10:36Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Good on Rubio for rescinding a bad decision, and even better for doing so with a fair and informative explanation.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>I’m a big believer in reading original source material. For example, when Apple provided me, <a href="https://www.techmeme.com/250307/p12#a250307p12">alongside only a handful of other outlets</a>, with a statement regarding their decision to delay the “more personalized Siri” back in March, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/apple_is_delaying_the_more_personalized_siri_apple_intelligence_features">I ran the full statement</a>, verbatim. I added my own commentary, but I wanted to let Apple’s own statement speak for itself first. It drives me nuts when news sites in possession of a statement or original document do not make the full original text available, even if only in a link at the bottom, and choose only to quote short excerpts.</p>

<p>With regard to <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/10/state-department-times-new-roman">today’s news</a> regarding Marco Rubio’s directive re-establishing Times New Roman as the default font for U.S. State Department documents (rescinding the Biden administration’s 2023 change to Calibri), I very much wanted to read the original. The New York Times broke the news, stated that they had obtained the memo, and quoted phrases and words from it, but they did not provide a copy of the original. </p>

<p>The State Department has not made this document publicly available, and to my knowledge, no one else has published it. I have obtained a copy from a source, and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/12/state-department-return-to-tradition.text">have made it available here in plain text format</a>. The only change I’ve made is to replace non-breaking spaces (<code>U+00A0</code>) with regular spaces.<sup id="fnr1-2025-12-10"><a href="#fn1-2025-12-10">1</a></sup></p>

<p>Please do <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/12/state-department-return-to-tradition.text">read it yourself</a>, and do so with an open mind.</p>

<p>It seems clear to me that The New York Times did Rubio dirty in their characterization of the directive. The Times story, credited to reporters Michael Crowley and Hamed Aleaziz, ran under the headline “<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/12/09/us/politics/rubio-state-department-font.html?unlocked_article_code=1.7k8.NI-S.Il8KdkMKKnGV">At State Dept., a Typeface Falls Victim in the War Against Woke</a>”, and opens thus:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Secretary of State Marco Rubio waded into the surprisingly fraught
politics of typefaces on Tuesday with an order halting the State
Department’s official use of Calibri, reversing a 2023 Biden-era
directive that Mr. Rubio called a “wasteful” sop to diversity.</p>

<p>While mostly framed as a matter of clarity and formality in
presentation, Mr. Rubio’s directive to all diplomatic posts around
the world blamed “radical” diversity, equity, inclusion and
accessibility programs for what he said was a misguided and
ineffective switch from the serif typeface Times New Roman to sans
serif Calibri in official department paperwork.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Rubio’s memo ran about 950 words. Here are the full quotes the Times pulled from it, consisting of just 56 words, aside from the memo’s subject line (“Return to Tradition: Times New Roman 14-Point Font Required for All Department Paper”):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“wasteful”</p>

<p>“radical”</p>

<p>“restore decorum and professionalism to the department’s
written work.”</p>

<p>“informal”</p>

<p>“clashes”</p>

<p>“was not among the department’s most illegal, immoral, radical or
wasteful instances of D.E.I.A.”</p>

<p>“accessibility-based document remediation cases”</p>

<p>“Switching to Calibri achieved nothing except the degradation of
the department’s official correspondence.”</p>

<p>“generally perceived to connote tradition, formality and ceremony”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Rubio’s memo wasn’t merely “mostly framed as a matter of clarity and formality in presentation”. That’s entirely what the memo is about. Serif typefaces like Times New Roman <em>are</em> more formal. It was the Biden administration and then-Secretary of State Antony Blinken who categorized the 2023 change to Calibri as driven by accessibility. I do not have access to Blinken’s memo making that change (under the cringe-inducing subject line “The Times (New Roman) are a-Changin”), but it was <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/world/2023/01/18/state-department-times-new-roman-calibri/">first reported by John Hudson and Annabelle Timsit at The Washington Post</a>, where they wrote:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The secretary’s decision was motivated by accessibility issues and
not aesthetics, said a senior State Department official familiar
with the change.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Rubio’s memo makes the argument — correctly — that aesthetics matter, and that the argument that Calibri was in any way more accessible than Times New Roman was bogus. Rubio’s memo does not lash out against accessibility as a concern or goal. He simply makes the argument that Blinken’s order mandating Calibri in the name of accessibility was an empty gesture. Purely performative, at the cost of aesthetics. Going back to that 2023 story at the Post, they quote from Blinken’s memo thus:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In its cable, the State Department said it was choosing to shift
to 14-point Calibri font because serif fonts like Times New Roman
“can introduce accessibility issues for individuals with
disabilities who use Optical Character Recognition technology or
screen readers. It can also cause visual recognition issues for
individuals with learning disabilities,” it said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The bit here about OCR <a href="https://mastodon.social/@pesh/115696514979388477">is utter nonsense</a>, a voodoo belief. No OCR or screen-reader software in use today has any problem whatsoever with Times New Roman. That’s just made-up nonsense, and I’d like to see sources for the claim about “visual recognition issues for individuals with learning disabilities”. I don’t think it’s true, and citing it alongside a provably wrong claim about OCR software makes me even more skeptical.</p>

<p>Rubio brings actual numbers to make his case, which is more than can be said for anyone I’ve found arguing that Calibri is somehow more accessible than Times New Roman. Rubio’s argument is alluded to in the Times’s article thus:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>But Mr. Rubio called it a failure by its own standards, saying
that “accessibility-based document remediation cases” at the
department had not declined.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Here’s the full passage from Rubio’s memo:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>And although switching to Calibri was not among the Department’s
most illegal, immoral, radical, or wasteful instances of DEIA
(see, e.g., Executive Orders 14151, 14173, 14281, and Memorandum
on Removing Discrimination and Discriminatory Equity Ideology From
the Foreign Service (DCPD202500375)) it was nonetheless cosmetic:
the switch was promised to mitigate “accessibility issues for
individuals with disabilities,” and employees were promised, “Your
adoption supports the Department’s commitment to create a more
accessible workplace,” but these promises were false. In fact, the
number of accessibility-based document remediation cases at the
Department of State was the same in the year after adopting
Calibri as in the year before (1,192 cases in FY2024 versus 1,193
cases in FY2022). And the costs of remediation actually increased
by $145,000 in that period — nearly a 20% jump. Switching to
Calibri achieved nothing except the degradation of the
Department’s official correspondence.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>2024 was a Biden year, not a Trump year, so there’s no reason to think the remediation numbers were counted differently. The change to Calibri was the worst kind of accessibility effort: one that was founded on nothing more than feel-good performance. It was a change everyone could see and notice, but one that had no practical benefit whatsoever. Good on Rubio for rescinding a bad decision, and even better for doing so with a fair and informative explanation.<sup id="fnr2-2025-12-10"><a href="#fn2-2025-12-10">2</a></sup> (His memo even explains, “Fonts are specific variations of a typeface....  Through common use, the word font has come to mean both typeface and font.”)</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>

<li id="fn1-2025-12-10">
<p>The memo, per State Department standards perhaps, uses two spaces after sentences and colons. In the original copy I received, those double-spaces were sometimes in the sequence <em>NON-BREAK-SPACE + SPACE</em>, and other times the other way around: <em>SPACE + NON-BREAK-SPACE</em>. There were also a handful of seemingly random non-breaking space characters between words, mid-sentence. All of them, I suspect, just invisible-to-the-eye detritus from Microsoft Word. I replaced all of them with regular spaces, preserving, in plain text, two spaces wherever two spaces were intended.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-12-10"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>

<li id="fn2-2025-12-10">
<p>Do I think it was “fair and informative” to describe all of the Biden State Department’s DEIA initiatives as “illegal, immoral, radical, or wasteful”? No. Did I bother reading any of the documents Rubio referenced as proving such? No. Do I think this particular memorandum, specific to changing State’s font back to Times New Roman, would have been stronger without that line, leaving his defenestration of the Calibri font change to speak for itself? Yes. But that line was just one aside in an otherwise focused, sober, and, yes, fair and informative memo.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr2-2025-12-10"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
</li>

</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ The Full Text of Marco Rubio’s Directive on State Department Typography, Re-Establishing Times New Roman</title></entry><entry>
	<title>U.S. State Department Changes Back to Times New Roman From Calibri</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/12/09/us/politics/rubio-state-department-font.html?unlocked_article_code=1.7k8.NI-S.Il8KdkMKKnGV" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wrj" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/10/state-department-times-new-roman" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42463</id>
	<published>2025-12-10T17:04:43Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-13T00:05:50Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Michael Crowley and Hamed Aleaziz, reporting for The New York Times:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>While mostly framed as a matter of clarity and formality in
presentation, Mr. Rubio’s directive to all diplomatic posts around
the world blamed “radical” diversity, equity, inclusion and
accessibility programs for what he said was a misguided and
ineffective switch from the serif typeface Times New Roman to sans
serif Calibri in official department paperwork.</p>

<p>In an “Action Request” memo obtained by The New York Times, Mr.
Rubio said that switching back to the use of Times New Roman would
“restore decorum and professionalism to the department’s written
work.” Calibri is “informal” when compared to serif typefaces like
Times New Roman, the order said, and “clashes” with the
department’s official letterhead. [...]</p>

<p>Then-Secretary of State Antony J. Blinken ordered the 2023
typeface shift on the recommendation of the State Department’s
office of diversity and inclusion, which Mr. Rubio has since
abolished. The change was meant to improve accessibility for
readers with disabilities, such as low vision and dyslexia,
and people who use assistive technologies, such as screen
readers. [...]</p>

<p>But Mr. Rubio’s order rejected the grounds for the switch. The
change, he allowed, “was not among the department’s most illegal,
immoral, radical or wasteful instances of D.E.I.A.,” the acronym
for diversity, equity, inclusion and accessibility. But Mr. Rubio
called it a failure by its own standards, saying that
“accessibility-based document remediation cases” at the department
had not declined.</p>

<p>“Switching to Calibri achieved nothing except the degradation of
the department’s official correspondence,” Mr. Rubio said. He
noted that Times New Roman had been the department’s official
typeface for nearly 20 years until the 2023 change. (Before 2004,
the State Department used Courier New.)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>When Blinken ordered the change to Calibri in 2023, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/01/26/state-dept-font">I wrote</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It is correct for the State Department to have a house style for
documents. I’m not sure what font they should use, but it wasn’t
Times, and it shouldn’t be Calibri. Off the top of my head, I’d
suggest Caslon — a sturdy, serious typeface <a href="https://www.mcsweeneys.net/articles/caslon-baskerville-and-franklin-revolutionary-types">that looked good 250
years ago</a>, looks good now, and should look good 250 years
from now.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>While neither is a good choice, between the two, Times New Roman is clearly better. Unstated in my post from 2023 is acknowledgement that the choice might be limited to the default fonts in Microsoft Office. Limited to those fonts, Times New Roman might be the best choice. I just think it’s stupid for an institution with the resources of the U.S. State Department to shrug its shoulders at the notion that they should license and install whatever fonts they want on all of their computers. Anyone making excuses that they “can’t” do that should be fired. It’s the job of IT to serve the needs of the organization, not the organization’s job to limit itself to what makes IT easiest.</p>

<p>Calibri does convey a sense of casualness — and more so, modernity — that is not appropriate for the U.S. State Department. And I do not buy the argument that Calibri is somehow more accessible for those with low vision or reading disabilities. People with actual accessibility needs should be catered to, but they need more than a sans serif typeface, and their needs should not primarily motivate the choice for the default typeface. <s>Dyslexics need typefaces like OpenDyslexic.</s> [<strong>Update:</strong> Actually, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/12/dyslexia-fonts-pseudoscience">they don’t</a>.] People with low vision need font sizes much larger than 14-point. Those would make for terrible defaults for everyone.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘U.S. State Department Changes Back to Times New Roman From Calibri’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/10/state-department-times-new-roman">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/12/imessage_push_notifications_hard_to_block" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wri" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42462</id>
	<published>2025-12-09T22:42:45Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-12T17:23:12Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Draw your own conclusions about cellular carriers and enterprise network administrators being similar to authoritarian governments.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>From Apple’s <a href="https://support.apple.com/guide/security/imessage-security-overview-secd9764312f/web">iMessage Security Overview</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple iMessage is a messaging service for iPhone, iPad, Mac, Apple
Watch, and Apple Vision Pro. Relying on the Apple Push
Notification service (APNs), iMessage lets users send texts and
attachments like photos, contacts, locations, links, and emoji.
Messages sync across all devices, enabling seamless conversations.
Apple doesn’t store message content or attachments, which are all
secured with end-to-end encryption so that no one but the sender
and receiver can access them. Apple canʼt decrypt the data.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://mastodon.social/@magebarf/115686285616651788">This thread on Mastodon</a>, prompted by <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/07/russia-blocks-facetime-and-snapchat">my wondering why Russia is blocking FaceTime but not iMessage</a>, suggests that because iMessage messages are sent via APNs, a network (or entire nation) seeking to block iMessage could only do so by blocking all push notifications for iOS. That’s why on airplanes with “free messaging” on in-flight Wi-Fi, you usually also get all incoming push notifications, even for services that aren’t available on the free Wi-Fi. (It also explains why, on in-flight Wi-Fi and similar restricted networks, text-only messages go through, <a href="https://infosec.exchange/@adamshostack/115696265565038136">but images and other attachments do not</a>.)</p>

<p><a href="https://support.gfi.com/article/107782-when-blocking-imessage-push-notifications-are-blocked">Here’s a support document from GFI Software</a>, which makes network appliances for enterprises and schools:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The Exinda appliance gives administrators multiple options to stop
or throttle applications that can use a lot of bandwidth in the
network. An application that many would consider discardable or
able to be easily limited in bandwidth is iMessage. When blocking
or discarding iMessage traffic, users may experience an issue
where all push notifications on iOS devices that have traffic
going through the Exinda, i.e., on WiFi, will stop displaying.</p>

<p>Root Cause: Apple uses the Apple Push Notification Service (APNS)
to allow application creators to push out information to iOS
devices. This includes mail servers being able to push out
notifications of calendar and email, or app creators to be able to
push text-based messages straight to the device.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Apple might have architected iMessage this way to make iMessage veto-proof with cellular carriers, who, at the time of <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2011/06/06New-Version-of-iOS-Includes-Notification-Center-iMessage-Newsstand-Twitter-Integration-Among-200-New-Features/">iMessage’s announcement in June 2011</a>, were already promoting iPhone push notifications as a reason to upgrade from a dumb phone to an iPhone with a more expensive plan. The carriers might have been tempted to block iMessage over cell networks to keep people using SMS, but they couldn’t without blocking all push notifications, which wouldn’t be tenable. But this architecture also makes iMessage hard to block in authoritarian countries where iPhones are even vaguely popular. (Maybe this helps explain why iMessage isn’t blocked in China, too?)</p>

<p>Draw your own conclusions about cellular carriers and enterprise network administrators being similar to authoritarian governments.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ iMessage’s Delivery Architecture Makes It Hard to Block Without Blocking All iOS Push Notifications</title></entry><entry>
	<title>The Real Problem of Humanity</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.harvardmagazine.com/2009/09/james-watson-edward-o-wilson-intellectual-entente" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wrh" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/09/the-real-problem-of-humanity" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42461</id>
	<published>2025-12-09T22:17:20Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-09T22:17:21Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Sociobiologist Edward O. Wilson, back in 2009:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The real problem of humanity is the following: we have paleolithic
emotions; medieval institutions; and god-like technology.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A related adage I heard, and internalized, recently: “We’re not thinking creatures who feel; we’re feeling creatures who think.” (<a href="https://kottke.org/25/11/0047871-edward-o-wilson-in-2009">Via Jason Kottke</a>.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Real Problem of Humanity’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/09/the-real-problem-of-humanity">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>ProPublica: ‘Trump’s Own Mortgages Match His Description of Mortgage Fraud, Records Reveal’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.propublica.org/article/trump-mortgage-fraud-florida-principal-residences" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wrg" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/09/trump-mortgages" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42460</id>
	<published>2025-12-09T21:17:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-09T21:17:01Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Justin Elliott, Robert Faturechi, and Alex Mierjeski, reporting for ProPublica:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>For months, the Trump administration has been accusing its
political enemies of mortgage fraud for claiming more than one
primary residence. President Donald Trump <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115092130707196133">branded one foe who did
so</a> “deceitful and potentially criminal.” He called another
“<a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/114857687712359546">CROOKED</a>” on Truth Social and pushed the attorney general
to take action.</p>

<p>But years earlier, Trump did the very thing he’s accusing his
enemies of, records show.</p>

<p>In 1993, Trump <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/26342753-trump-mortgage-1993/">signed a mortgage</a> for a “Bermuda style”
home in Palm Beach, Florida, pledging that it would be his
principal residence. Just seven weeks later, he got <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/26342754-trump-mortgage-1994/">another
mortgage</a> for a seven-bedroom, marble-floored neighboring
property, attesting that it too would be his principal residence.</p>

<p>In reality, Trump, then a New Yorker, does not appear to have ever
lived in either home, let alone used them as a principal
residence.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://slate.com/business/2022/06/wilhoits-law-conservatives-frank-wilhoit.html">Frank Wilhoit’s axiom</a> comes to mind: “Conservatism consists of exactly one proposition, to wit: There must be in-groups whom the law protects but does not bind, alongside out-groups whom the law binds but does not protect.”</p>

<p>The difference between traditional conservatism — which hadn’t yet been washed away in 2018, <a href="https://crookedtimber.org/2018/03/21/liberals-against-progressives/#comment-729288">when Wilhoit wrote it</a> — and today’s MAGA Republican cult is that in Trumpism, the in-group is just Trump, and whoever he sees as serving allegiance to him personally. It’s not men, not white people, not rich people, and not even rich white men, as a class. It’s just Donald Trump and those who pay personal fealty to him. Especially rich white men who pay subservient <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/09/trump-fifa-peace-prize">fealty to him</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘ProPublica: ‘Trump’s Own Mortgages Match His Description of Mortgage Fraud, Records Reveal’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/09/trump-mortgages">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Wall Street Journal: ‘Behind Paramount’s Relentless Campaign to Woo Warner Discovery and President Trump’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.wsj.com/business/media/paramount-netflix-warner-bros-battle-ellisons-a86fe15c?st=gwekR4&amp;reflink=desktopwebshare_permalink" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wrf" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/09/wsj-paramount-warner-bros-behind-the-scenes" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42459</id>
	<published>2025-12-09T20:59:19Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-09T21:00:51Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Joe Flint, Brian Schwartz, and Natalie Andrews, reporting for The Wall Street Journal (<a href="https://www.wsj.com/business/media/paramount-netflix-warner-bros-battle-ellisons-a86fe15c?st=gwekR4&amp;reflink=desktopwebshare_permalink">gift link</a>, also <a href="https://apple.news/ARdvLmsUMRyeLXShmkooSYQ">in News+</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Just tried calling you about new bid we have submitted,” Ellison
texted Zaslav. “I heard you on all your concerns and believe we
have addressed them in our new proposal. Please give me a call
back when you can to discuss in detail.”</p>

<p>He didn’t hear back.</p>

<p>Sensing trouble, Ellison followed up, saying Paramount had offered
a package that covered all the issues Warner had raised, including
the need for “strong cash value” and “speed to close.”</p>

<p>“It would be the honor of a lifetime to be your partner and to be
the owner of these iconic assets,” he texted, according to a
regulatory filing.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Desperation is never a good look.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>During a visit to Washington in recent days, David Ellison offered
assurances to Trump administration officials that if he bought
Warner, he’d make sweeping changes to CNN, a common target of
President Trump’s ire, people familiar with the matter said. Trump
has told people close to him that he wants new ownership of CNN as
well as changes to CNN programming.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Lickspittling is never a good look, either. David Ellison cuts the figure of a pathetic little man, a mere shadow of his father. (I’ll bet he gets along well with Don Jr. and Eric.) And Trump is now already <a href="https://www.wsj.com/business/media/paramount-netflix-warner-bros-battle-ellisons-a86fe15c?st=gwekR4&amp;reflink=desktopwebshare_permalink">pissed that Ellison hasn’t turned</a> <em>60 Minutes</em> into <em>Fox and Friends</em>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Wall Street Journal: ‘Behind Paramount’s Relentless Campaign to Woo Warner Discovery and President Trump’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/09/wsj-paramount-warner-bros-behind-the-scenes">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>You’ll Never Guess Who Won the Newly Created ‘Peace Prize’ From FIFA, the World’s Most Corrupt Sports Body</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2025/dec/05/trump-peace-prize-fifa-world-cup" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wre" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/09/trump-fifa-peace-prize" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42458</id>
	<published>2025-12-09T20:28:21Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-09T20:48:28Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The Guardian:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>There on a plinth, with “Donald J Trump” emblazoned on it in
capital letters, was the uncoveted trophy: a golden globe resting
on five golden hands big enough to compensate any tiny-handed
recipient feeling sore about the Nobel peace prize.</p>

<p>But wait, there was more. “There is also a beautiful medal for you
that you can wear everywhere you want to go,” added Infantino,
knowing that with Trump there is no such thing as too much.</p>

<p>Glowing oranger than usual under the stage lights, Trump eagerly
put the medal around his neck without waiting for Infantino to do
the honours. He told the audience of 2,000 people: “This is truly
one of the great honours of my life.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s just perfect that <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2025/dec/09/donald-trump-finally-won-peace-prize-fifa-five-other-awards-he-should-win">Trump put the medal around his own neck</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/12/09/arts/television/late-night-trump-prize.html">The jokes</a> practically wrote themselves.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘You’ll Never Guess Who Won the Newly Created ‘Peace Prize’ From FIFA, the World’s Most Corrupt Sports Body’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/09/trump-fifa-peace-prize">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>You Can’t Please a Madman</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/115684406134734247" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wrd" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/09/you-cant-please-a-madman" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42457</id>
	<published>2025-12-09T19:58:52Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-09T21:03:30Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Donald Trump, on his blog:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The only reason Marjorie “Traitor” Brown (Green turns Brown under
stress!) went BAD is that she was JILTED by the President of the
United States (Certainly not the first time she has been jilted!).
Too much work, not enough time, and her ideas are, NOW, really BAD — She sort of reminds me of a Rotten Apple! Marjorie is not
AMERICA FIRST or MAGA, because nobody could have changed her views
so fast, and her new views are those of a very dumb person. That
was proven last night when washed up, Trump hating, 60 Minutes
“correspondent,” Lesley Stahl, who still owes me an apology from
when she attacked me on the show (with serious conviction!), that
Hunter Biden’s LAPTOP FROM HELL was produced by Russia, not Hunter
himself (TOTALLY PROVEN WRONG!), interviewed a very poorly
prepared Traitor, who in her confusion made many really stupid
statements. My real problem with the show, however, wasn’t the low
IQ traitor, it was that the new ownership of 60 Minutes,
Paramount, would allow a show like this to air. THEY ARE NO BETTER
THAN THE OLD OWNERSHIP, who just paid me millions of Dollars for
FAKE REPORTING about your favorite President, ME! Since they
bought it, 60 Minutes has actually gotten WORSE! Oh well, far
worse things can happen. P.S. I hereby demand a complete and total
APOLOGY, though far too late to be meaningful, from Lesley Stahl
and 60 Minutes for her incorrect and Libelous statements about
Hunter’s Laptop!!! President DJT</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Trump’s expectation isn’t that <em>60 Minutes</em>, along with the entirety of CBS News, along with <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/07/curse_not_the_king_cbs_colbert_trump">the entirety of CBS TV programming</a>, would tilt in Trump’s direction after its acquisition (as part of Paramount) by David Ellison’s Skydance. Trump’s expectation is that all of CBS, every minute of the broadcast day, should appeal to and appease him.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘You Can’t Please a Madman’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/09/you-cant-please-a-madman">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Netflix and the Hollywood End Game’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stratechery.com/2025/netflix-and-the-hollywood-end-game/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wrc" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/09/netflix-and-the-hollywood-end-game" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42456</id>
	<published>2025-12-09T18:45:19Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-09T20:31:23Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Ben Thompson at Stratechery yesterday:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It’s important to note that the President does not have final say
in the matter: President Trump directed the DOJ to oppose AT&amp;T’s
acquisition of Time Warner, but the DOJ <a href="https://stratechery.com/2018/the-need-for-neutrality/">lost in federal
court</a>, much to AT&amp;T’s detriment. Indeed, the irony of mergers
and regulatory review is that the success of the latter is often
inversely correlated to the wisdom of the former: the AT&amp;T deal
for Time Warner never made much sense, which is directly related
to why it (correctly) was approved. It would have been
economically destructive for AT&amp;T to, say, limit Time Warner
content to its networks, so suing over that theoretical
possibility was ultimately unsuccessful.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Thompson also makes clear that Paramount itself couldn’t possibly launch a credible bid for Warner Bros.:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Paramount’s bid, it should be noted, was for the entire Warner
Bros. Discovery business, including the TV and cable networks that
will be split off next year; Netflix is only buying the Warner
Bros. part. <a href="https://puck.news/will-paramount-challenge-netflix-wbd-deal/">Puck</a> reported that the stub Netflix is leaving
behind is being valued at $5/share, which would mean that Netflix
outbid Paramount.</p>

<p>And, it should be noted, that Paramount money wouldn’t be from the
actual business, which is valued at a mere $14 billion; new owner
David Ellison is the son of Oracle founder Larry Ellison, who is
worth $275 billion. Netflix, meanwhile, is worth $425 billion and
generated $9 billion in cash flow over the last year. Absent
family money this wouldn’t be anywhere close to a fair fight.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s not illegal or even sketchy for an acquisition to be backed by family money from an entirely separate source (in the Ellisons’ case, Oracle), but it certainly makes more business sense for Netflix to make this acquisition than Paramount. There’s a strong argument that David Ellison doesn’t really know what the fuck he’s doing in the media racket; no one would argue that Netflix doesn’t know exactly what they’re doing.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Netflix and the Hollywood End Game’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/09/netflix-and-the-hollywood-end-game">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Paramount Skydance Makes Hostile Takeover Bid for Warner Bros. Discovery</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.wsj.com/business/media/paramount-skydance-warner-bros-hostile-takeover-bid-f03c6f3f" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wrb" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/09/paramount-hostile-takeover-warner-bros" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42455</id>
	<published>2025-12-09T18:37:33Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-09T18:37:34Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The Wall Street Journal yesterday:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Paramount launched a $77.9 billion hostile takeover offer for
Warner Bros. Discovery Monday, taking its case for acquiring the
storied entertainment company directly to shareholders just days
after Warner agreed to a deal with Netflix.</p>

<p>Paramount, run by David Ellison, is arguing that its all-cash
$30-a-share offer for all of Warner, owner of networks such as
CNN, TBS and HGTV as well as the HBO Max streaming service, is
a better deal for shareholders and more likely to pass
regulatory muster.</p>

<p>“We’re really here to finish what we started,” Ellison said on
CNBC Monday morning.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The “more likely to pass regulatory muster” bit is a euphemism for the Ellisons (David, and the real player here, his $250+-billion-dollar-net-worth father Larry) being on the inside of the Trump administration oligarchy. It’s so transparent that Trump’s son-in-law Jared Kushner is part of the hostile bid, along with sovereign wealth funds from Saudi Arabia, Abu Dhabi, and Qatar.</p>

<p>That said, while the Executive Branch is influential in such regulatory approvals, it’s <em>not</em> completely under their control. The U.S. court system, while under duress from this administration, remains independent, and <a href="https://www.rawstory.com/jack-smith-2674262772/">with admittedly notable exceptions</a>, remains largely on the up-and-up.</p>

<p>And CNN’s Brian Stelter reports that <a href="https://x.com/brianstelter/status/1998112063902691718">Netflix was prepared for this</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Today’s move was entirely expected,” Netflix co-CEO Ted Sarandos
said on stage at a UBS conference just now, waving off Paramount’s
hostile play for WBD. “We have a deal done, and we are incredibly
happy with the deal... We’re super confident we’re going to get it
across.”</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Paramount Skydance Makes Hostile Takeover Bid for Warner Bros. Discovery’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/09/paramount-hostile-takeover-warner-bros">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Johny Srouji, in Memo Responding to Gurman Report: ‘I Love My Team, and I Love My Job at Apple, and I Don’t Plan on Leaving Anytime Soon’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/12/08/apple-chips-johny-srouji.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wra" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/08/srouji" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42454</id>
	<published>2025-12-09T00:52:37Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-09T16:12:24Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>CNBC:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple chip leader Johny Srouji addressed rumors of his impending
exit in a memo to staff on Monday, saying he doesn’t plan on
leaving the company anytime soon. “I love my team, and I love my
job at Apple, and I don’t plan on leaving anytime soon,” he wrote.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2025-12-06/apple-rocked-by-executive-departures-with-johny-srouji-at-risk-of-leaving-next">Bloomberg reported</a> on Saturday that Srouji had told CEO Tim
Cook that he was considering leaving, citing people with knowledge
of the matter.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It wasn’t <em>rumors</em>, plural. It was one report, on Saturday, from Mark Gurman at Bloomberg, and Srouji just called bullshit on it.</p>

<p>What a colossal fuck-up for Gurman and Bloomberg. There’s no possible scenario where Srouji was threatening to leave Apple for a competitor on Saturday and telling his staff (in a memo meant to leak to the press) “I love my job at Apple, and I don’t plan on leaving anytime soon” Monday morning.</p>

<p>The most gracious interpretation for Gurman and Bloomberg is that Srouji <em>had</em> expressed this to Cook, at some point in the recent past, and Cook addressed whatever it took to keep Srouji on board. But even in that scenario, they ran a story Saturday that was wrong at the time it was published.</p>

<p>The more likely scenario is <a href="https://x.com/neilcybart/status/1998143342786515351">the one suggested by Neil Cybart</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>If someone wanted to sow seeds of doubt among Apple employees in
an effort to help their own poaching efforts, there are at least
three publications who would have no problem offering an anonymous
microphone to that person.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I.e., the source for this story about Srouji being unhappy at Apple and considering leaving for a competitor was aligned with one of those competitors, and Gurman and his editors at Bloomberg said “Sure, we’ll print that.” Meta, of course, is the competitor that comes to mind.</p>

<p>It speaks to Gurman’s personal and Bloomberg’s institutional influence that Srouji and Apple saw the need to shoot the bogus narrative down in public like this. I can’t remember the last time an Apple executive saw the need to send an intended-to-leak memo like this to shoot down one bogus story. After <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/05/apple-announces-a-few-other-executive-transitions">last week</a>, though, this one couldn’t be ignored.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Johny Srouji, in Memo Responding to Gurman Report: ‘I Love My Team, and I Love My Job at Apple, and I Don’t Plan on Leaving Anytime Soon’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/08/srouji">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.jaho.com/s/df" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wr9" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/12/jaho_coffee_roaster_1" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.42453</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-12-09T00:43:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-09T00:43:00Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Great coffee changes the day. Since 2005, our family-owned roastery has taken the slow and careful approach, sourcing small-lot coffees, roasting in small batches and shipping every bag fresh. Award-winning coffee delivered to your home or office.</p>

<p>Holiday gifts? Fresh coffee is a gift that never misses, easy to give, even better to receive.</p>

<p>DF readers get 20% off with code <strong>DF</strong>.</p>

<p>Fresh beans shipped nationwide.</p>

<p>Give better coffee this season.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Jaho Coffee Roaster’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/12/jaho_coffee_roaster_1">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] Jaho Coffee Roaster</title></entry><entry>
	<title>EU Court Rules That Apple Must Face Dutch Antitrust Lawsuit Regarding App Store Commission Rates</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/12/02/dutch-app-store-antitrust-case-proceeds/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wr8" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/08/dutch-app-store-antitrust-suit" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42452</id>
	<published>2025-12-08T23:13:43Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-09T16:17:38Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Juli Clover, writing at MacRumors (regarding a <a href="https://www.reuters.com/sustainability/boards-policy-regulation/eu-court-rules-dutch-courts-can-handle-anti-trust-case-against-apples-app-store-2025-12-02/">report at Reuters</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple could ultimately have to pay up to an estimated 637 million
euros to address the damage suffered by 14 million iPhone and iPad
users in the Netherlands.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That’s about €45/user.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The lawsuit dates back to 2022, when two Dutch consumer
foundations (Right to Consumer Justice and App Store Claims)
accused Apple of abusing its dominant market position and charging
developers excessive fees. The lawsuit was filed on behalf of
Dutch iPhone and iPad users, and it claimed that Apple’s 30
percent commission inflated prices for apps and in-app purchases.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’m curious what these consumer foundations would consider a “fair” (and thus legal) commission rate.</p>

<p>This all comes back to the argument that Apple’s App Store commission inflates prices. <a href="https://developer.apple.com/download/files/DMA-Study-Nov-2025.pdf">A recent Apple-funded (and Apple-promoted) study</a> suggests this is not true — that with lower commissions mandated by the DMA, prices paid by consumers stayed the same and the difference went to the developers. That’s <a href="https://pxlnv.com/linklog/apple-dma-commission-study/">good if you’re a developer</a>, but it’s not the argument being made by these consumer advocate groups.</p>

<p>That said, <a href="https://pxlnv.com/linklog/apple-dma-commission-study/">I pointed out just the other day</a> that Tiimo, a to-do app that Apple just named as the iPhone app of the year in the 2025 App Awards, charges about 20 percent less for subscriptions on its website compared to its in-app subscriptions. An Apple-funded, Apple-promoted study showing that the App Store’s commissions don’t raise prices ought to be taken with a few grains of salt.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple argued that the Dutch court did not have jurisdiction to
hear the case because the EU App Store is run from Ireland, and
therefore the claims should be litigated in Ireland. Apple said
that if the Dutch court was able to hear the case, it could lead
to fragmentation with multiple similar cases across the EU, plus
it argued that customers in the Netherlands could have downloaded
apps while in other EU member states.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I know Apple wants this litigated in Ireland because the Irish government <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apple%27s_EU_tax_dispute">sees Apple as an ally, not an adversary</a>, but it does seem contrary to the idea of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/European_single_market">a single market</a> if a company doing business in the EU is subject to different antitrust laws from each of the EU’s 27 member states.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘EU Court Rules That Apple Must Face Dutch Antitrust Lawsuit Regarding App Store Commission Rates’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/08/dutch-app-store-antitrust-suit">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>WorkOS Radar</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://workos.com/radar?utm_source=daringfireball&amp;utm_medium=RSS&amp;utm_campaign=q12025" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wr6" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/07/workos-radar" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42450</id>
	<published>2025-12-07T21:24:01Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-07T21:24:20Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to WorkOS for sponsoring last week at DF. Does your app get fake signups, throwaway emails, or users abusing your free tier? Or worse, bot attacks and brute force attempts?</p>

<p>WorkOS Radar can block all this and more. A simple API gives you advanced device fingerprinting that can detect bad actors, bots, and suspicious behavior. Your users trust you. WorkOS Radar lets you keep it that way.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘WorkOS Radar’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/07/workos-radar">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Russia Blocks FaceTime and Snapchat</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://apnews.com/article/russia-internet-crackdown-facetime-restrictions-06301be480510b18ae02039c6524cd80" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wr7" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/07/russia-blocks-facetime-and-snapchat" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42451</id>
	<published>2025-12-07T21:19:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-08T23:34:03Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Dasha Litvinova, reporting for the AP:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Russian authorities said Thursday they have imposed restrictions
on Apple’s video calling service FaceTime, the latest step in an
effort to tighten control over the internet and communications
online. State internet regulator Roskomnadzor alleged in a
statement that the service is being “used to organize and conduct
terrorist activities on the territory of the country, to recruit
perpetrators (and) commit fraud and other crimes against our
citizens.” Apple did not respond to an emailed request for
comment.</p>

<p>The Russian regulator also announced that it has blocked Snapchat,
a messaging app for sharing photos, videos and text messages,
citing the same grounds it gave for restricting FaceTime. It said
that it took the action Oct. 10 even though it only reported the
move on Thursday.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’m sure the crime rate in Russia will soon plummet. (I’m curious why iMessage isn’t blocked too.)</p>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> A DF reader in Russia, who has sent me feedback before, told me that iMessage still works (and in fact told me via iMessage), but that it likely hasn’t been blocked because it isn’t widely used there. (He said that his chat with me is his one and only iMessage thread.) FaceTime, on the other hand, is quite popular in Russia. Or at least it was.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Russia Blocks FaceTime and Snapchat’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/07/russia-blocks-facetime-and-snapchat">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/12/meta_says_fuck_that_metaverse_shit" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wr5" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42449</id>
	<published>2025-12-07T21:18:13Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-09T16:53:51Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Joz might want to use the word now, just to make jokes.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Mike Isaac, reporting for The New York Times, “<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/12/04/technology/meta-cuts-metaverse-unit.html?unlocked_article_code=1.608.XuJW.cN8SImoOdegY">Meta Weighs Cuts to Its Metaverse Unit</a>” (gift link):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Meta is considering making cuts to a division in its Reality Labs
unit that works on the so-called metaverse, said three employees
with knowledge of the matter.</p>

<p>The cuts could come as soon as next month and amount to 10 to 30
percent of employees in the Metaverse unit, which works on virtual
reality headsets and a V.R.-based social network, the people said.
The numbers of potential layoffs are still in flux, they said.
Other parts of the Reality Labs division develop smart glasses,
wristbands and other wearable devices. The total number of
employees in Reality Labs could not be learned.</p>

<p>Meta does not plan to abandon building the metaverse, the people
said. Instead, executives expect to shift the savings from the
cuts into investments in its augmented reality glasses, the
people said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Meta confirmed the cuts <a href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/ai/meta-plans-to-shift-spending-away-from-the-metaverse-d0ac3b7f">to the Wall Street Journal</a>, and <a href="https://www.techmeme.com/251204/p27#a251204p27">Bloomberg’s Kurt Wagner broke the news Thursday</a>.</p>

<p>I’m so old that I remember ... checks notes ... four years ago, when Facebook renamed itself Meta in late 2021 with <a href="https://about.fb.com/news/2021/10/facebook-company-is-now-meta/">this statement</a>: “Meta’s focus will be to bring the metaverse to life and help people connect, find communities and grow businesses.” And <a href="https://about.fb.com/news/2021/10/founders-letter/">Mark Zuckerberg, announcing the change, wrote</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>But all of our products, including our apps, now share a new
vision: to help bring the metaverse to life. And now we have a
name that reflects the breadth of what we do.</p>

<p>From now on, we will be metaverse-first, not Facebook-first. That
means that over time you won’t need a Facebook account to use our
other services. As our new brand starts showing up in our
products, I hope people around the world come to know the Meta
brand and the future we stand for.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Many of us never fell for this metaverse nonsense. For example, I’m also old enough to remember just one year later, near the end of Joanna Stern’s on-stage interview with Craig Federighi and Greg Joswiak at a 2022 WSJ event, seven months before Vision Pro was announced (<a href="https://youtu.be/m-ugwoEOMvg?t=1770">at the 29:30 mark</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Stern:</strong> You have to finish this sentence, both of you. The
metaverse is...</p>

<p><strong>Joz:</strong> A word I’ll never use.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>He might want to use the word now, just to make jokes.</p>

<p>Om Malik, <a href="https://blog.om.co/2025/04/28/no-gruber-this-is-why-facebook-renamed-itself/">writing in April this year</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Some of us are old enough to remember that the reason Mark renamed
the company is because the Facebook brand was becoming toxic, and
associated with misinformation and global-scale crap. It was
viewed as a tired, last-generation company. Meta allowed the
company to rebrand itself <a href="https://om.co/2021/10/31/facebook-is-now-meta/">as something amazing and fresh</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Lastly, yours truly, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/28/om-malik-facebook-rename">linking to Malik’s post</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>And so while “Meta” will never be remembered as the company that
spearheaded the metaverse — because the metaverse never was or
will be an actual thing — it’s in truth the perfect name for a
company that believes in nothing other than its own success.</p>
</blockquote>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Meta Says Fuck That Metaverse Shit</title></entry><entry>
	<title>One Last Note on Tiimo: What’s the Deal With That Icon?</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/12/2025_app_store_award_winners" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wr4" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/07/tiimo-icon" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42448</id>
	<published>2025-12-07T20:38:16Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-07T20:38:17Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>One small update I just appended to my piece Friday taking a look at the winning apps from this year’s App Store Awards:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Lastly, I have questions — some really hard questions — regarding <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/12/tiimo-icon.png">Tiimo’s app icon</a>. Such as, “What is that?”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Perhaps it got picked because it makes <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/07/tahoes-terrible-icons">Apple’s new OS 26 icons</a> look good by comparison?</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘One Last Note on Tiimo: What’s the Deal With That Icon?’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/07/tiimo-icon">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Dithering: ‘Alan Dye Leaves Apple’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://dithering.passport.online/member/episode/alan-dye-leaves-apple" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wr3" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/05/dithering-alan-dye" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42447</id>
	<published>2025-12-05T23:25:09Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-05T23:28:42Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://dithering.passport.online/member/episode/alan-dye-leaves-apple" class="noborder">
  <img
    src   = "https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/12/dithering-cover-dec-2025.jpeg"
    alt   = "The December 2025 cover art for Dithering, showing a man dressed as Santa Claus getting a kiss on the cheek under some mistletoe."
    width = 525
  /></a></p>

<p>Dithering is my and Ben Thompson’s twice-a-week podcast — 15 minutes per episode, not a minute less, not a minute more. It’s a $7/month or $70/year subscription, and included in the Stratechery Plus bundle (a bargain). This year our CMS (<a href="https://passport.online/">Passport</a> — check it out) gained a feature that lets us make some episodes free for everyone to listen to on the website. Today’s episode, regarding Alan Dye leaving Apple for Meta, seems like a good one to do that with. (And, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/16/dithering-being-real-points">once again</a>, this month’s album art serendipitously captures my mood.)</p>

<p>Give it a listen. <a href="https://dithering.fm/">Subscribe if you enjoy it</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Dithering: ‘Alan Dye Leaves Apple’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/05/dithering-alan-dye">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple’s Succession Intrigue Isn’t Strange at All</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theinformation.com/articles/silicon-valley-buzzing-apple-ceo-succession" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wr2" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/05/apple-succession-the-information" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42446</id>
	<published>2025-12-05T23:08:12Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-13T18:07:18Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Aaron Tilley and Wayne Ma, in a piece headlined “Why Silicon Valley is Buzzing About Apple CEO Succession” at the paywalled-up-the-wazoo The Information:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Prediction site Polymarket <a href="https://polymarket.com/event/next-ceo-of-apple">places Ternus’ odds of getting the
job</a> at nearly 55%, ahead of other current Apple executives
such as software head Craig Federighi, Chief Operating Officer
Sabih Khan and marketing head Greg Joswiak. But some people close
to Apple don’t believe Ternus is ready to take on such a
high-profile role, and that could make a succession announcement
unlikely anytime soon, said people familiar with the company.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Nothing in the rest of the article backs up that “some people close
to Apple don’t believe Ternus is ready” claim, other than this, several paragraphs later:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>And while his fans believe Ternus has the temperament to be CEO,
many of them say he isn’t a charismatic leader in the mold of a
Jobs. He has also had little involvement in the geopolitical and
government affairs issues that dominate most of Cook’s time these
days. On a recent trip to China, for example, Apple’s new COO,
Sabih Khan, accompanied Cook to some of his meetings.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>No one else in the history of the industry, let alone the company, has the charisma of Steve Jobs. And while I think Polymarket has the shortlist of candidates right, I also think they have them listed in the right order. Sabih Khan probably should be considered an outside-chance maybe, but the fact that he accompanied Cook to China doesn’t make me think, for a second, that it’s in preparation to name him CEO. If Khan were being groomed to become CEO, he’d have started appearing in keynotes already. It’s silly to slag Ternus for not having the charisma of Steve Jobs, when Ternus has been a strong presence in keynotes since 2018, and <em>in the same paragraph</em> suggest Khan as a better option, when Khan has never once appeared in a keynote or public appearance representing Apple.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Some former Apple executives hope a dark-horse candidate emerges.
For example, Tony Fadell, a former Apple hardware executive who
coinvented [<em>sic</em>] the iPod, has told associates recently that he
would be open to replacing Cook as CEO, according to people who
have heard his remarks. (Other people close to Apple consider
Fadell an unlikely candidate, in part because he was a polarizing
figure when he worked at the company. Fadell left Apple in 2010.)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The parenthetical undersells the unlikelihood of Fadell returning to Apple, ever, in any role, let alone the borderline insanity of suggesting he’d come back as Cook’s successor.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It has become one of the strangest succession spectacles in tech.
Typically, the kind of buzz that is swirling around Cook occurs
when companies are performing badly or a CEO has dropped hints
that they’re getting ready to hang up their spurs. Neither applies
in Cook’s case, though.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There’s nothing strange about it. Apple has a unique company culture, but <a href="https://ritholtz.com/2013/07/organizational-charts-of-amazon-apple-facebook-microsoft/">so too do its peers</a>, like Microsoft, Amazon, and Google. And just like at those companies, it’s therefore a certainty that Cook’s replacement will come from within the company’s current ranks. Polymarket doesn’t even list anyone other than Ternus, Federighi, Joswiak, and Khan.</p>

<p>As for hints, there is not much need for any hint beyond the fact that Cook is now 65 years old and has been in the job since 2011. But the high-profile multi-source <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/11/15/ft-apple-tim-cook-succession">leak to the Financial Times</a> is a pretty obvious fucking additional hint.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple’s Succession Intrigue Isn’t Strange at All’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/05/apple-succession-the-information">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Lisa Jackson on The Talk Show Back in 2017</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2017/04/21/ep-188" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wr1" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/05/lisa-jackson-the-talk-show" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42445</id>
	<published>2025-12-05T22:37:35Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-05T22:37:36Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>This interview was both interesting and a lot of fun. Worth a listen or re-listen.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Lisa Jackson on The Talk Show Back in 2017’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/05/lisa-jackson-the-talk-show">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Apple Announces a Few Other Executive Transitions</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2025/12/apple-announces-executive-transitions/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wr0" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/05/apple-announces-a-few-other-executive-transitions" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42444</id>
	<published>2025-12-05T22:18:12Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-05T23:53:40Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Apple Newsroom, yesterday:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple today announced that Jennifer Newstead will become Apple’s
general counsel on March 1, 2026, following a transition of duties
from Kate Adams, who has served as Apple’s general counsel since
2017. She will join Apple as senior vice president in January,
reporting to CEO Tim Cook and serving on Apple’s executive team.</p>

<p>In addition, Lisa Jackson, vice president for Environment, Policy,
and Social Initiatives, will retire in late January 2026. The
Government Affairs organization will transition to Adams, who will
oversee the team until her retirement late next year, after which
it will be led by Newstead. Newstead’s title will become senior
vice president, General Counsel and Government Affairs, reflecting
the combining of the two organizations. The Environment and Social
Initiatives teams will report to Apple chief operating officer
Sabih Khan. [...]</p>

<p>Newstead was most recently chief legal officer at Meta and
previously served as the legal adviser of the U.S. Department of
State, where she led the legal team responsible for advising the
Secretary of State on legal issues affecting the conduct of U.S.
foreign relations.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Monday’s announcement <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/01/giannandrea-out">that AI head John Giannandrea is retiring</a> and the hierarchy for AI related projects being further reshuffled under software head Craig Federighi was significant, but not surprising, given <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/03/something_is_rotten_in_the_state_of_cupertino">how things went this year</a> for Apple with AI.</p>

<p>Wednesday’s announcement that VP of design and Liquid Glass frontman Alan Dye is leaving Apple for Meta was a shock, both inside and outside the company. As I wrote this week, I think <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/12/bad_dye_job">it’s great news for Apple</a>, but <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/12/dye_cook_blind_spot">not by plan</a>.</p>

<p>This news yesterday is just typical planned retirements. The timing is slightly unfortunate though. In the eyes of observers unfamiliar with the company, they might be misconstrued as signs of executive upheaval, occurring on the heels of the minor and major dramas of Giannandrea’s and Dye’s departures. The Jackson / Adams / Newstead transitions announced yesterday are nothing of the sort.</p>

<p>Jackson had a very nice run at Apple and carved out a rather unique position within the company. Apple’s environmental efforts expanded tremendously under her leadership. I’ve never met anyone with a bad word to say about her, and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2017/04/21/ep-188">in my own interactions</a>, found her downright delightful.</p>

<p>As for Adams, the responsibilities of Apple’s general counsel are generally far afield from my interests. The only two times I’ve mentioned her at DF were <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2017/10/06/sewell-adams">when she got the job in 2017</a>, and a passing reference when the FBI sent <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2020/01/08/fbi-apple-pensacola-shooter">a letter to Apple, addressed to Adams, in 2020</a> regarding the locked phone of a mass shooter in Pensacola, Florida. That’s a sign of a good run for a general counsel — it’s a job where no news is good news.</p>

<p>Lastly, I wouldn’t read anything into Newstead coming to Apple by way of Meta. But it is a bit funny that it was announced the day after Dye left Apple <em>for</em> Meta. She seems to have <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jennifer_Gillian_Newstead">an excellent wide-ranging background</a> to spearhead Apple’s government affairs. Her stint in the State Department was during the first (now seemingly sane) Trump administration, but she clerked for liberal Supreme Court Justice Stephen Breyer.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Announces a Few Other Executive Transitions’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/05/apple-announces-a-few-other-executive-transitions">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/12/2025_app_store_award_winners" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wqz" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42443</id>
	<published>2025-12-05T21:46:12Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-12T17:18:46Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">I did not enjoy them as much as Apple did.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Apple, today: “<a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/story/id1849728503">Announcing the 2025 App Store Awards</a>”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This year’s winners represent the best-in-class apps and games
we returned to again and again. We hope you enjoy them as much
as we do.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I did not enjoy all of them as much as Apple did.</p>

<h2>Tiimo</h2>

<p>iPhone app of the year <a href="https://www.tiimoapp.com/">Tiimo</a> bills itself as an “AI Planner &amp; To-do” app that is designed with accommodations for people with ADHD and other neurodivergences. Subscription plans cost $12/month ($144/year) or $54/year ($4.50/month). It does not offer a native Mac app, and at the end of onboarding/account setup, it suggests <a href="https://webapp.tiimoapp.com/home">their web app</a> for use on desktop computers. When I went to the web app, after signing in with the “Sign in With Apple” account I created on the iPhone app, Tiimo prompted me to sign up for an annual subscription for $42/year ($3.50/month), or monthly for $10 ($120/year). The in-app subscriptions offer a 30-day free trial; the less expensive pay-on-the-web subscriptions only offer a 7-day free trial. The web app doesn’t let you do anything without a paid account (or at least starting a trial); the iOS app offers quite a bit of basic functionality free of charge.</p>

<p><a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/story/id1847760015">From Apple’s own description for why it gave Tiimo the award</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Built to support people who are neurodivergent (and anyone
distracted by the hum of modern life), Tiimo brought clarity to our
busy schedules using color-coded, emoji-accented blocks. The
calming visual approach made even the most hectic days feel
manageable.</p>

<p>It starts by syncing everything in Calendar and Reminders, pulling
in doctor’s appointments, team meetings, and crucial prompts to
walk the dog or stand up and stretch. Instead of dumping it all
into a jumbled list, the app gives each item meaning by
automatically assigning it a color and an emoji. (Tiimo gave us the
option to change the weightlifter emoji it added to our workout
reminders, but its pick was spot on.)</p>

<p>While on the move with coffee in one hand and keys in the other,
we sometimes talked to Tiimo with the Al chatbot feature to add new
tasks or shift appointments. When we felt overwhelmed by our to-do
list, Tiimo kept us laser-focused by bubbling up just high-priority
tasks, while its built-in Focus timer (accessible from any to-do
with a tap) saved us from the pitfalls of multitasking.</p>

<p>But Tiimo really stood out when we faced a big personal project,
like getting our Halloween decorations up before Thanksgiving.
With the help of Al, the app suggested all the smaller tasks
that would get us there: gathering the decorations from the
garage, planning the layout, securing the cobwebs, and doing a
safety check.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Aside from the web app, <a href="https://www.tiimoapp.com/faq">Tiimo is iOS exclusive</a>, with apps only for iPhone, iPad, and Apple Watch. No Android version. It seems to do a good job with native platform integration (Calendar integration is free; Reminders integration requires a subscription). Animations in the app feel slow to me, which makes the app itself feel slow. And, personally, I find Tiimo’s emphasis on decorating everything with emoji <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/11/chatgpt_5-1_with_renamed_and_new_personalities">distracting and childish</a>, not clarifying.</p>

<p>The app seems OK, but not award-worthy to me. But, admittedly, I’m not in the target audience for Tiimo’s ADHD/neurodivergent focus. I don’t need reminders to have coffee in the morning, start work, have dinner, or to watch TV at night, which are all things Tiimo prefilled on my Today schedule after I went through onboarding. As I write this sentence, I’ve been using Tiimo for five minutes, and it’s already prompted me twice to rate it on the App Store. Nope, wait, I just got a third prompt. That’s thirsty, and a little gross. (And, although I’m not an ADHD expert, three prompts to rate and review the app in the first 10 minutes of use strikes me as contrary to the needs of the easily distracted.)</p>

<p>Lastly, I have questions — some really hard questions — regarding <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/12/tiimo-icon.png">Tiimo’s app icon</a>. Such as, “What is that?”</p>

<h2>Essayist</h2>

<p>Mac app of the year <a href="https://www.essayist.app/">Essayist</a> bills itself as “The Word Processor designed for Academic Writing” (capitalization verbatim). Subscriptions cost $80/year ($6.67/month) or $10/month ($120/year). Its <em>raison d’être</em> is managing citations and references, and automatically formatting the entire document, including citations, according to a variety of standards (MLA, Chicago, etc.). Quoting from <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/story/id1848945161">Apple’s own description of Essayist</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Essayist gives you an easy way to organize a dizzying array of
primary sources. Ebooks, podcasts, presentations, and even direct
messages and emails can be cataloged with academic rigor. Using
macOS Foundation Models, Essayist extracts all the key info needed
to use it as a source.</p>

<p>For example, paste a YouTube URL into an entry and Essayist
automatically fills in the name of the video, its publication
date, and the date you accessed it. Drag in an article as a PDF to
have Essayist fill in the title, author, and more — and store the
PDF for easy access. You can also search for the books and journal
articles you’re citing right in the app.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Essayist is a document-based (as opposed to library-based) app, and its custom file format is a <a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/archive/documentation/CoreFoundation/Conceptual/CFBundles/AboutBundles/AboutBundles.html">package</a> with the adorable file extension “.essay”. The default font for documents is Times New Roman, and the only other option is, of all fonts, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/search/arial">Arial</a> — and you need an active subscription to switch the font to Arial. (<em>Paying money for the privilege to use Arial... Jiminy fucking christ. I might need a drink.</em>) I appreciate the simplicity of severely limiting font choices to focus the user’s attention on the writing, but offering Times New Roman and Arial as the only options means you’re left with the choice between “the default font’s default font” and “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2020/10/02/when-the-clients-specs-arial">font crime</a>”. The Essayist app itself <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/12/essayist-app-menu.png">has no Settings</a>; instead, it offers only <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/12/essayist-document-window-menu.png">per-document settings</a>.</p>

<p>The app carries a few whiffs of non-Mac-likeness (e.g. the aforementioned lack of Settings, and some <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/12/essayist-alerts.png">lame-looking custom alerts</a>). The document settings window refers to a new document, even after it has been saved with a name, as “Untitled” until you close and reopen the document. Reopened documents do not remember their window size and position. But <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=32113754">poking around with <code>otool</code></a>, it appears to be written using AppKit, not Catalyst. I suspected the app might be Catalyst because there are companion iOS apps for iPhone and iPad, which seem to offer identical feature sets as the Mac app. Essayist uses a clever system where, unless you have a subscription, documents can <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/12/essayist-unlock-access.png">only be edited on the device on which they were created</a>, but you can open them read-only on other devices. That feels like a good way to encourage paying while giving you a generous way to evaluate Essayist free of charge. There is no Android, Windows, or web app version — it’s exclusive to Mac and iOS.</p>

<p>I’ve never needed to worry about adhering to a specific format for academic papers, and that’s the one and only reason I can see to use Essayist. In all other aspects, it seems a serviceable but very basic, almost primitive, word processor. <s>There’s no support for embedding images or figures of any kind in a document, for example.</s> [Correction: <a href="https://www.essayist.app/guides/figures---tables">Essayist does support figures</a>, but I missed the UI for how to insert them.]</p>

<h2>Detail</h2>

<p>iPad app of the year <a href="https://detail.co/">Detail</a> bills itself, simply and to the point, as an “AI Video Editor”. The default subscription is $70/year ($5.83/month) with a 3-day free trial; the other option is to pay $12/month ($144/year) with no free trial. After a quick test drive, Detail seems like an excellent video editing app, optimized for creating formats common on social media, like reel-style vertical videos where you, the creator, appear as a cutout in the corner, in front of the video or images that you’re talking about. The iPhone version seems equally good. The iPad version of Detail will install and run on MacOS, but it’s one of those “Designed for iPad / Not verified for macOS” no-effort direct conversions. But they do offer a standalone Mac app, <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/detail-video-studio/id6443923358">Detail Studio</a>, which is a real Mac app, written using AppKit, which requires a separate subscription to unlock pro features ($150/year or $22/month). Detail only offers apps for iOS and MacOS — no  Windows, Android, or web.</p>

<p><a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/ipad/story/id1847760011">From Apple’s own acclaim for Detail</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>When we used Detail to record a conversation of two people sitting
side by side, the app automatically created a cut that looked like
it was captured with two cameras. It zoomed in on one speaker,
then cut away to the other person’s reaction. The app also made it
easy to unleash our inner influencer. We typed a few key points,
and the app’s AI wrote a playful script that it loaded into its
teleprompter so we could read straight to the camera.</p>

<p>Most importantly, Detail helped us memorialize significant life
moments all while staying present. At a birthday party, we propped
an iPad on a table and used Detail to record with the front and
back cameras simultaneously. The result was a split-screen video
with everyone singing “Happy Birthday” on the left and the guest
of honor blowing out the candles on the right. (No designated
cameraperson needed.)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Detail has a bunch of seemingly genuinely useful AI-based features. But putting all AI features aside, it feels like a thoughtful, richly featured <em>manual</em> video editor. I suspect that’s why the AI features might work well — they’re an ease-of-use / automation layer atop a professional-quality non-AI foundation. Basically, Detail seems like what Apple’s own Clips — <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/10/13/clips-eol">recently end-of-life’d</a> — should have been. It turns your iPad (or iPhone) into a self-contained video studio. Cool.</p>

<hr />

<p>Of these three apps — Tiimo on iPhone, Essayist on Mac, and Detail on iPad — Detail appeals to me the most, and strikes me as the most deserving of this award. If I were to start making videos for modern social media, I’d strongly evaluate Detail as my primary tool.</p>

<p>Apple still has no standalone category for AI apps, but all three of these apps emphasize AI features, and Apple itself calls out those AI features in its praise for them. It’s an obvious recurring theme shared by all three, along with their shared monetization strategies of being free to download with in-app subscriptions to unlock all features, and the fact that all three winners are exclusive to iOS and Mac (and, in Tiimo’s case, the web).</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ 2025 App Store Award Winners: Tiimo, Essayist, and Detail</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Netflix Agrees to Buy Warner Bros., Including HBO, for $83 Billion</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/business/story/2025-12-05/netflix-prevails-in-warner-bros-discovery-bidding-opponents" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wqy" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/05/netflix-buying-warner-bros" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42442</id>
	<published>2025-12-05T16:47:44Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-05T16:47:45Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Meg James, reporting for The Los Angeles Times (<a href="https://apple.news/Ak1molISkQ4GGq7cNQtPOSw">News+ link</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The two companies announced the blockbuster deal early Friday
morning. The takeover would give Netflix such beloved characters
as Batman, Harry Potter and Fred Flintstone.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Fred Flintstone?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Our mission has always been to entertain the world,” Ted
Sarandos, co-CEO of Netflix, said in a statement. “By combining
Warner Bros.’ incredible library of shows and movies — from
timeless classics like <em>Casablanca</em> and <em>Citizen Kane</em> to modern
favorites like <em>Harry Potter</em> and <em>Friends</em> — with our
culture-defining titles like <em>Stranger Things</em>, <em>KPop Demon
Hunters</em> and <em>Squid Game</em>, we’ll be able to do that even better.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Not sure <em>Squid Game</em> belongs in the same comparison as <em>Citizen Kane</em>, but the Warners library is incredibly deep. Stanley Kubrick’s post-<em>2001: A Space Odyssey</em> films were all for Warner Bros.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Netflix’s cash and stock transaction is valued at about $27.75 per
Warner Bros. Discovery share. Netflix also agreed to take on more
than $10 billion in Warner Bros. debt, pushing the deal’s value to
$82.7 billion. [...] Warner’s cable channels, including CNN, TNT
and HGTV, are not included in the deal. They will form a new
publicly traded company, Discovery Global, in mid-2026.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I don’t know if this deal makes sense for Netflix, but Netflix has earned my trust. Netflix is a product-first company. They care about the quality of their content, their software, their service, and their brand. If you care about the Warner/HBO legacy, an acquisition by Netflix is a much, much better outcome than if David Ellison had bought it to merge with Paramount.</p>

<p>The LA Times article goes on to cite concerns from the movie theater industry, based on Netflix’s historic antipathy toward theatrical releases for its films. Netflix is promising to keep Warner Bros.’s film studio a separate operation, maintaining the studio’s current support for theatrical releases. I hope they do. I grew up loving going to the movies. I still enjoy it, but the truth is I go far less often as the years go on. Movie theaters shouldn’t be a protected class of business just because there’s so much affection and nostalgia for them. If they continue sliding into irrelevance, so be it. That’s how disruption, progress, and competition work.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Netflix Agrees to Buy Warner Bros., Including HBO, for $83 Billion’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/05/netflix-buying-warner-bros">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/12/dye_cook_blind_spot" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wqx" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42441</id>
	<published>2025-12-05T01:53:12Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-05T01:53:12Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">How could someone who would even *consider* leaving Apple for Meta rise to a level of such prominence at Apple, including as one of the few public faces of the company?</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/tech/tech-news/apple-ceo-tim-cook-slams-facebook-privacy-human-right-it-n860816">NBC News, back in March 2018</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Speaking at a town hall event hosted by MSNBC’s Chris Hayes and
Recode’s Kara Swisher, Cook said Facebook put profits above all
else when it allegedly allowed user data to be taken through
connected apps. [...]</p>

<p>When asked what he would do if he were in Zuckerberg’s position,
Cook replied: “What would I do? I wouldn’t be in this situation.”</p>

<p>“The truth is we could make a ton of money if we monetized our
customer, if our customer was our product,” Cook said. “We’ve
elected not to do that.”</p>

<p>“Privacy to us is a human right. It’s a civil liberty, and
something that is unique to America. This is like freedom of
speech and freedom of the press,” Cook said. “Privacy is right up
there with that for us.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Perhaps Cook now needs to define “us”.</p>

<p>This was a rather memorable interview. Cook’s “What would I do? I wouldn’t be in this situation” is one of the stone-coldest lines he’s ever zinged at a rival company. (In public, that is.) That was just ice cold. Cook is a consummate diplomat. Most non-founder big company CEOs are. Satya Nadella, Sundar Pichai, Andy Jassy — none of them are known for throwing shade, let alone sharp elbows, at competitors. Cook has made an exception, <a href="https://time.com/5433499/tim-cook-apple-data-privacy/">multiple</a> <a href="https://www.reuters.com/article/technology/apples-tim-cook-criticizes-social-media-practices-intensifying-facebook-confli-idUSKBN29X2NB/">times</a>, when it comes to Facebook/Meta (and to a lesser degree, Google).</p>

<p>So it’s not just that Alan Dye jumped ship from Apple for the chief designer officer role at another company.<sup id="fnr1-2025-12-04"><a href="#fn1-2025-12-04">1</a></sup> It’s not just that he left for a <em>rival</em> company. It’s that he left Apple for <em>Meta</em>, of all companies. Given what Cook has said about Meta publicly, one can only imagine what he thinks about them privately. Apple executives tend to stay at Apple. The stability of its executive team is unparalleled. But Dye is a senior leader who not only left for a rival, but the one rival that Cook and the rest of Apple’s senior leadership team consider the most antithetical to Apple’s ideals.</p>

<p>It would have been surprising if Dye had jumped ship to Google or Microsoft. It would have been a little more surprising if he’d left for Amazon, if only because Amazon seemingly places no cultural value whatsoever on design, as Apple practices it. But maybe with Amazon it would have been seen as Andy Jassy deciding to get serious about design, and thus, in a way, less surprising after the fact. But leaving Apple for <em>Meta</em>, of all companies, feels shocking. How could someone who would even <em>consider</em> leaving Apple for Meta rise to a level of such prominence at Apple, including as one of the few <a href="https://www.printmag.com/podcasts/2025/design-matters-craig-federighi-and-alan-dye/">public faces of the company</a>?</p>

<p>So it’s not just that Alan Dye is a fraud of a UI designer and leader, and that Apple’s senior leadership had a blind spot to the ways Dye’s leadership was steering Apple’s interface design deeply astray. That’s problem enough, as I emphasized <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/12/bad_dye_job">in my piece yesterday</a>. It’s also that it’s now clear that Dye’s moral compass was not aligned with Apple’s either. Tim Cook and the rest — or at least most? — of Apple’s senior leadership apparently couldn’t see that, either.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1-2025-12-04">
<p>I’d have thrown OpenAI in that list of companies where it would have been surprising, but not shocking, for Dye to leave Apple for. But that simply wasn’t possible given Jony Ive’s relationship with Sam Altman, LoveFrom’s collaboration with OpenAI with the io project, and Ive’s utter disdain for Dye’s talent, leadership, and personality.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-12-04"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Alan Dye Was in Tim Cook’s Blind Spot</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Alan Dye Comments on His Career Move in an Instagram Story</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://x.com/sdw/status/1996431428561822093?s=46" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wqw" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/04/alan-dye-instagram-story" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42440</id>
	<published>2025-12-04T16:31:34Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-04T16:31:59Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Straight/dumb quotation marks. Some default Instagram typeface. That period just hanging there, outside the closing quote. This is the post from the man who led Apple’s software design for a decade.</p>

<p>Not to mention the gall to use <em>any</em> quote from Steve Jobs, let alone <em>this</em> particular one, which is <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2012/01/29/steve-jobs-legacy-lives-on-at-apple-campus-with-posters-and-quotes/">enshrined by Apple on the wall outside Town Hall</a> at the old Infinite Loop campus in Cupertino, and provides the title for the splendid book published (<a href="https://book.stevejobsarchive.com/">in a delightful interactive version on the web</a>, and in <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2023/04/14/make-something-wonderful-ebay">gorgeous limited print editions</a>) by the Steve Jobs Archive and LoveFrom.</p>

<p>“Just figure out what’s next” for Alan Dye, after his supposedly wonderful accomplishments at Apple, is ... going to work for Meta? Jiminy H. Christ, that takes stones.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Alan Dye Comments on His Career Move in an Instagram Story’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/04/alan-dye-instagram-story">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Louie Mantia on The Talk Show in July, Talking About Alan Dye and Liquid Glass</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2025/07/31/ep-428" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wqu" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/03/mantia-the-talk-show-dye" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42438</id>
	<published>2025-12-03T22:30:35Z</published>
	<updated>2025-12-03T22:30:35Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Back in July, I was lucky enough to have my friend Louie Mantia <a href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2025/07/31/ep-428">on The Talk Show</a> to talk about Liquid Glass and (as I wrote in the show notes) “the worrisome state of Apple’s UI design overall”. This was probably my favorite episode of the show all year, and I think it holds up extremely well now that we’re all using Liquid Glass, across Apple’s platforms, in release versions.</p>

<p>Included in the show notes was a link to Mantia’s essay making his case against Dye’s decade-long stint leading Apple’s UI design teams, “<a href="https://lmnt.me/blog/a-responsibility-to-the-industry.html">A Responsibility to the Industry</a>”, which began thus:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Firstly, I maintain that it makes absolutely no sense that Alan
Dye has the power he has, because he simply has no taste. But
what’s worse is that he wields that power so clumsily, so
carelessly. And because it goes unchallenged, unchecked by someone
higher than him, the entire industry suffers the consequences.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://pdx.social/@louie/115657549705092757">Here’s Mantia today</a>, regarding the news of Dye leaving Apple for Meta:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>And good riddance!!</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Louie Mantia on The Talk Show in July, Talking About Alan Dye and Liquid Glass’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/12/03/mantia-the-talk-show-dye">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry></feed><!-- THE END -->
