<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>Daring Fireball</title>
<subtitle>By John Gruber</subtitle>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/" />
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main" />
<id>https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main</id>


<updated>2025-07-30T18:17:13Z</updated><rights>Copyright © 2025, John Gruber</rights><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/07/tea_number_3_app_store" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/whv" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42115</id>
	<published>2025-07-30T18:17:13Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-30T18:17:13Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Tea remains a chart-topping app in the App Store, but isn’t listed at all in Play Store top lists.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Tea remains <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/charts/iphone/top-free-apps/36">#3 overall in the US iPhone App Store</a>. Here’s a <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/07/us-iphone-app-store-top-10-2025-07-30.png">screenshot of the top free iPhone apps today</a>, and a list of the current top 10, using the full names the apps choose to display:</p>

<ol>
<li>ChatGPT</li>
<li>Wingstop</li>
<li>Tea Dating Advice</li>
<li>Threads</li>
<li>Google</li>
<li>Google Maps</li>
<li>WhatsApp Messenger</li>
<li>ParentSquare</li>
<li>CapCut - Video Editor
<ol><li>TikTok - Videos, Shop &amp; LIVE</li></ol></li>
</ol>

<p>I might be forgetting or unaware of previous similar situations, but I can’t recall anything like this before, where an app riddled with <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/28/tea-breach-worsens">outrageous security/privacy vulnerabilities</a> remains virally popular. A Hacker News thread from earlier today <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=44732995">debates why the app is even still available on the App Store</a>.</p>

<p>So is it Apple’s place to yank the app? It feels wrong to me that Apple should completely remove Tea from the App Store, but it’s also true that one of Apple’s fundamental pitches for the App Store — and the App Store’s exclusivity for app distribution in most of the world — is that iOS users can trust any and all apps in the App Store because they’re vetted by Apple. But here’s Tea, sitting at #3, providing a service that many woman want, and the entire thing is shockingly untrustworthy. (I fully expect more vulnerabilities to be found and exploited.)</p>

<p>Tea, unsurprisingly, has almost nothing on <a href="https://www.teaforwomen.com/">their website</a> about the security violations their users have suffered, nor any mention in their App Store listing. Their only public acknowledgement of the fiasco is a series of three Instagram posts on July <a href="https://www.instagram.com/theteapartygirls/p/DMjRl4CPE0z/">26</a>, <a href="https://www.instagram.com/theteapartygirls/p/DMl3E0TvoML/">27</a>, and <a href="https://www.instagram.com/theteapartygirls/p/DMrGSlrJA-e/">29</a> (the most recent of which acknowledges that they’ve completely disabled the DM feature “temporarily”), and <a href="https://www.teaforwomen.com/cyberincident">this FAQ</a> on their website, that, as far as I can tell, is only discoverable through the “links in bio” on their Instagram profile. Their FAQ only addresses the initial discovery from last week, not <a href="https://www.404media.co/a-second-tea-breach-reveals-users-dms-about-abortions-and-cheating/">the more significant one that 404 Media publicized Monday</a> that included the exposure of DMs.</p>

<p>Also fascinating to me is that Tea, though available on both iOS <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.tea.tea&amp;hl=en_US&amp;gl=US">and Android</a>, is seemingly not popular at all on Android. It’s not even listed <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps?hl=en_US">in the Play Store’s top free apps</a>. (The Play Store website lists only the top 45, but I scrolled through the entire top 200 on my Pixel.) The current Play Store top 10:</p>

<ol>
<li>ChatGPT</li>
<li>TikTok - Videos, Shop &amp; LIVE</li>
<li>Threads</li>
<li>WhatsApp Messenger</li>
<li>Temu: Shop Like a Billionaire</li>
<li>Instagram</li>
<li>TikTok Lite - Faster TikTok</li>
<li>DramaBox - Stream Drama Shorts</li>
<li>Cash App</li>
<li>Snapchat</li>
</ol>

<p>More tellingly, Tea doesn’t even crack the Play Store top 200 list for the “Dating” category. (On iOS, it’s in the “Lifestyle” category, but on the Play Store it’s in the “Dating” and “Casual” categories. Perhaps Apple requires apps in the “Dating” category to be full-fledged dating app services, not dating-app-adjacent like Tea.)</p>

<p>I’m not sure what explains the disparity in Tea’s popularity by platform. One assumption is that dating is more of a young person’s game, and young people skew slightly more toward iPhone than the US population overall. But from what I can tell, that skew is only about 10 percent. Also, surveys suggest <a href="https://www.sci-tech-today.com/stats/iphone-vs-android-user-statistics/">women are more likely to be iPhone users</a>. But I can’t believe that age or gender demographics alone explain why Tea is #3 in the App Store but doesn’t even crack the top 200 on Android.</p>

<p>I strongly suspect that while Google hasn’t removed Tea from the Play Store, that they’ve delisted it from discovery other than by searching for it by name or following a direct link to its listing. That both jibes with what I’m seeing on the Play Store top lists, and strikes me as a thoughtful balance between the responsibilities of an app store provider. As egregious as Tea’s security exploits have been, removing the app entirely doesn’t seem called for. But delisting it from popularity lists seems like a measured way to discourage new users from trying it unless they’re specifically looking for it. If this is what Google is doing, Apple should follow their lead. (I’ve put in a question to Google’s PR inquiring about this; if/when I get an answer, I’ll update this article.)</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Tea, the Women’s Dating Gossip App Riddled With Security Vulnerabilities, Remains #3 on the US iPhone App Store</title></entry><entry>
	<title>YouTube Is Rolling Out an Age-Estimation Algorithm to Identify US Teens</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/07/29/youtube-rolls-out-age-estimatation-tech-to-identify-u-s-teens-and-apply-additional-protections/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/whu" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/30/youtube-teen-age-estimation" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42114</id>
	<published>2025-07-30T15:24:39Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-30T15:24:39Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Sarah Perez, TechCrunch:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>YouTube on Tuesday announced it’s beginning to roll out
age-estimation technology in the U.S. to identify teen users in
order to provide a more age-appropriate experience. The company
says it will use a variety of signals to determine the users’
possible age, regardless of what the user entered as their
birthday when they signed up for an account.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Well-intentioned though I think this is, it still feels more than a little dystopian.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘YouTube Is Rolling Out an Age-Estimation Algorithm to Identify US Teens’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/30/youtube-teen-age-estimation">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Sony Sues Tencent for Allegedly Ripping Off ‘Horizon’ Video Games</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.reuters.com/legal/litigation/sony-sues-tencent-allegedly-ripping-off-horizon-video-games-2025-07-28/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wht" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/29/sony-sues-tencent" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42113</id>
	<published>2025-07-29T20:41:18Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-29T20:41:18Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Reuters:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Sony released the first game in the <em>Horizon</em> series, <em>Horizon:
Zero Dawn</em>, on its PlayStation 4 in 2017. The games follow a
red-headed woman named Aloy as she navigates a post-apocalyptic
world populated by human tribes and robotic animals.</p>

<p>Sony said in its complaint that it declined an offer from Tencent
to collaborate on a new <em>Horizon</em> game last year. Tencent later
announced <em>Light of Motiram</em>, which Sony said features identical
gameplay, story themes and artistic elements to <em>Horizon</em> as well
as many other similarities.</p>

<p>Sony said that video game journalists have characterized <em>Light of
Motiram</em> as a “knock-off” of <em>Horizon</em>, including one who called
the game <em>Horizon Zero Originality</em>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Tencent is the Chinese software giant behind, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tencent">amongst many other things</a>, WeChat, China’s “everything app”.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Sony Sues Tencent for Allegedly Ripping Off ‘Horizon’ Video Games’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/29/sony-sues-tencent">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The E-Book Editions of Timothy Snyder’s ‘On Tyranny’ Are Just $2</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://books.apple.com/us/book/on-tyranny/id1195458571" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/whs" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/29/snyder-on-tyranny-two-bucks" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42112</id>
	<published>2025-07-29T20:09:43Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-29T20:09:58Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Back in March <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/24/on-tyranny">I linked to and recommended</a> Timothy Snyder’s <em><a href="https://timothysnyder.org/on-tyranny/">On Tyranny</a></em>, a cogent collection of 20 short essays. I was never a big e-book reader, both because I love printed books so much and because I welcome any respite from reading on screens of any sort. But if e-books are your thing, note that <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/24/on-tyranny">Apple Books currently has it for just $2</a>. Amazon’s <a href="https://amzn.to/3UypaaG">Kindle edition is also $2</a> — and the paperback edition, which is the lovely little thing I own, <a href="https://amzn.to/4mizwHA">is an oddly but low-priced $7.31</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The E-Book Editions of Timothy Snyder’s ‘On Tyranny’ Are Just $2’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/29/snyder-on-tyranny-two-bucks">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Amazon Is Selling M4 MacBook Airs for $200 Off</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://amzn.to/4fdd0gN" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/whr" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/29/amazon-m4-macbook-airs" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42111</id>
	<published>2025-07-29T16:32:11Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-29T16:32:36Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>These prices — which I presume are a back-to-school season promotion — are even lower than those during the weeklong “Prime Day” <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/07/make_me_rich_on_amazon_prime_day">earlier this month</a>, and you don’t need to be a Prime subscriber to get them:</p>

<ul>
<li>The pretty-good base configuration (16 GB RAM, 256 GB storage) <a href="https://amzn.to/4fdd0gN">is just $800</a>.</li>
<li>The configuration with <a href="https://amzn.to/40HrhfR">16 GB RAM and 512 GB is $1,000</a>, the normal price for the base model.</li>
<li>You can splurge and get <a href="https://amzn.to/3U4PgSC">24 GB RAM with 512 GB storage for just $1,200</a>.</li>
</ul>

<p>These are make-me-rich affiliate links, as is <a href="https://amzn.to/456bngj">this link for AirPods Pro 2 for just $200</a>, $50 off.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Amazon Is Selling M4 MacBook Airs for $200 Off’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/29/amazon-m4-macbook-airs">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Microsoft Introduces ‘Copilot Mode’ in Edge</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://blogs.windows.com/msedgedev/2025/07/28/introducing-copilot-mode-in-edge-a-new-way-to-browse-the-web/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/whq" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/29/copilot-mode-in-microsoft-edge" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42110</id>
	<published>2025-07-29T16:05:06Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-29T16:08:42Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Sean Lyndersay, general manager of Edge at Microsoft:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>For decades, the way we’ve used browsers has remained linear: open
a tab (or 20), search for something, read a page, repeat. It’s a
model that’s worked well, but it hasn’t fundamentally changed.
Until now. As AI begins to reshape nearly every facet of digital
life, we’re witnessing a turning point in how we interact with the
web. Now, it’s worth asking: is your browser working for you as
much as it should?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Color me skeptical about the idea that my web browser should be “working for me”, rather than serving as a tool for me to work with. The AI hype cycle is pointing to a future where automated agentic web browsers surf automated AI-generated websites. Robots consuming robot-generated content — an infinite loop of AI onanism.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This is why today we’re excited to launch Copilot Mode, a new
experimental mode in Microsoft Edge, and our next step towards
building a more powerful way to pilot the web.</p>

<p>With Copilot Mode on, you enable innovative AI features in Edge
that enhance your browser. It doesn’t just wait idly for you to
click but anticipates what you might want to do next. It doesn’t
just give you endless tabs to sift through but works with you as a
collaborator that makes sense of it all. It keeps you browsing,
cuts through clutter and removes friction to unlock your flow — all built to the highest Microsoft standards of security, privacy
and performance trusted by billions of people and businesses
worldwide — with you as the user always in control.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Microsoft is famously known for presenting interfaces that “cut through clutter” and “remove friction”. I’m sure this will be great.</p>

<p>I am reminded of the decade-ago <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2013/01/29/hbo-netflix">Netflix strategy espoused by Ted Sarandos</a>: “The goal is to become HBO faster than HBO can become us.” I think something similar is behind Microsoft trying to make Copilot front-and-center in Edge, and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/29/chrome-ai-shopping">Google’s concurrent move to junk up Chrome</a> with AI-generated suggestions. Their goal is to make their web browsers chatbots faster than OpenAI can make ChatGPT a web browser.</p>

<p>HBO is still around. It even just <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/05/14/hbo-max-again">got its name back</a>. But Netflix won that race.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Microsoft Introduces ‘Copilot Mode’ in Edge’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/29/copilot-mode-in-microsoft-edge">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Google Chrome Adds AI-Generated Store Summaries</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/07/28/google-chrome-adds-ai-powered-store-summaries-to-help-u-s-shoppers/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/whp" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/29/chrome-ai-shopping" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42109</id>
	<published>2025-07-29T15:10:01Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-29T16:57:07Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Sarah Perez, writing for TechCrunch:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Google on Monday announced an update to its Chrome web browser
that will introduce AI-generated store reviews to U.S. shoppers
with the aim of helping to determine the best places to make a
purchase. The feature, which will be available by clicking an icon
just to the left of the web address in the browser, will display a
pop-up that informs consumers about the store’s reputation for
things like product quality, shopping, pricing, customer service,
and returns.</p>

<p>The feature, which is currently available only in English, will
generate the summaries based on reviews from partners, including
Bazaarvoice, Bizrate Insights, Reputation.com, Reseller Ratings,
ScamAdviser, Trustpilot, TurnTo, Yotpo, Verified Reviews, <a href="https://support.google.com/merchants/answer/190657?hl=en#Supported_Review_Partners">and
others</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I have never heard of a single one of these “partners”. It’s bad enough that so many web pages themselves are increasingly covered with distracting junk, much of it AI-generated slop. But now browsers themselves will be adding their own layers of distracting cruft atop the websites. The entire premise of Chrome — the reason for its name — is that it was originally designed to simplify the UI of the browser app itself, the “chrome”, at a time when Internet Explorer and even Firefox were increasingly cluttered and confusing. I feel like this is a sign that Chrome is completely losing its way — AI-generated slop from the browser layered atop AI-generated slop in the underlying web pages.</p>

<p>Dare Obasanjo, on Bluesky, <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/carnage4life.bsky.social/post/3lv2vvzlbd22o">takes this news credulously</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Google Chrome is now going to provide AI generated summaries of
online stores covering topics like customer service, product
quality, shipping, pricing and return policy.</p>

<p>This is on the heels of Microsoft Edge announcing Copilot mode
earlier today. Apple’s Safari is being left behind in the AI wars.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I would argue that Safari is looking ever more like a proverbial glass of ice water in hell. These Chrome AI overviews (Chrome is also, for example, going to start presenting its own <a href="https://www.seroundtable.com/google-business-profiles-menu-ai-summaries-39838.html">AI-generated menu summaries for restaurants</a>) don’t seem like user-centric features to me. They seem like features designed to turn the dial up on Google’s slice of commissions from web transactions.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Google Chrome Adds AI-Generated Store Summaries’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/29/chrome-ai-shopping">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Security Breach at Tea Worsens, Revealing Users’ DMs About Abortions and Cheating</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.404media.co/a-second-tea-breach-reveals-users-dms-about-abortions-and-cheating/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/who" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/28/tea-breach-worsens" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42108</id>
	<published>2025-07-29T02:09:10Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-30T15:39:13Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Emanuel Maiberg and Joseph Cox, reporting <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/26/4chan-tea-breach">again</a> for 404 Media:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Despite Tea’s initial statement that “the incident involved a
legacy data storage system containing information from over two
years ago,” the second issue impacting a separate database is much
more recent, affecting messages up until last week, according to
the researcher’s findings that 404 Media verified. The researcher
said they also found the ability to send a push notification to
all of Tea’s users.</p>

<p>It’s hard to overstate how sensitive this data is and how it could
put Tea’s users at risk if it fell into the wrong hands. When
signing up, Tea encourages users to choose an anonymous
screenname, but it was trivial for 404 Media to find the real
world identities of some users given the nature of their messages,
which Tea has led them to believe were private. Users could be
easily found via their social media handles, phone numbers, and
real names that they shared in these chats. These conversations
also frequently make damning accusations against people who are
also named in the private messages and in some cases are easy to
identify. [...]</p>

<p>Some of the private messages viewed by 404 Media include:</p>

<ul>
<li>One user tells another they just discovered their husband on the
app being discussed. “I am his wife,” many of the messages say.</li>
<li>Another appears to show a woman contacting others about a man
she is engaged to.</li>
<li>Multiple messages which appear to show women discussing their
abortions.</li>
<li>Chat logs between women discovering they are dating the same
man, exchanging information such as what car he drives for
verification.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>When <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/26/4chan-tea-breach">I linked to 404 Media’s coverage</a> of the initial breach at Tea the other day, I wrote, “I’m not accusing Tea in particular of being vibe-coded”. Well, I still don’t know if Tea’s service architecture was vibe-coded, but it’s now clear that whoever made it was shamefully incompetent. They shouldn’t have made <em>any</em> sort of services backend, let alone one like Tea’s that’s intended to carry incredibly sensitive personal information and messages.</p>

<p>This is an outright privacy — and quite possibly, personal security — disaster. With the abortion discussions and the current bifurcation of women’s rights here in the US, it could be a legal disaster, too. 4chan clowns have taken the images and data and <a href="https://knowyourmeme.com/editorials/guides/whats-going-on-with-the-tea-app-data-leak-the-tea-app-map-and-memes-about-ranking-foids-on-teaspill-explained">created</a> maps of Tea users’ addresses, and a Mark-Zuckerberg-“Facemash”-style site for ranking users’ appearance.</p>

<p>For women who’ve already signed up and started using Tea, I doubt there’s anything that can be done to remove them from exposure. Even if Tea offers a “delete your account” feature, I wouldn’t trust that it actually deletes <em>anything</em> from their database, let alone everything. And the cat’s already out of the bag for any bad actors who figured out this second exploit before Tea was alerted.</p>

<p>Yet another data point for the argument that any “private messaging” feature that doesn’t use E2EE isn’t actually private at all.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Security Breach at Tea Worsens, Revealing Users’ DMs About Abortions and Cheating’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/28/tea-breach-worsens">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://helloweather.com/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/whn" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/07/hello_weather" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.42107</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-07-28T21:11:43Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-28T21:11:44Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>One of the best indie weather apps just got a major overhaul for 2025, and it’s worth checking out.</p>

<p>Hello Weather is well known for its simple, friendly design, but the new update rounds it out with more depth and customization.</p>

<p>You’ll get beautiful new visuals for wind, UV, future forecasts, and more, all powered by the finest data on Earth. With its excellent widgets, Watch app, and notifications, you’ll always stay up to date.</p>

<p>Hello Weather also respects your privacy, with no tracking or ads in sight. It’s a customer-focused app, made with care.</p>

<p><a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/hello-weather/id978393692">Download Hello Weather</a> and start a 7-day free trial.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Hello Weather’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/07/hello_weather">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] Hello Weather</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Republican Election Group Is Attempting to Organize Against Text Message Filtering in iOS 26</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://politicalwire.com/2025/07/28/republicans-say-apple-update-will-hurt-fundraising/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/whm" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/28/nrsc-letter-ios-26" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42106</id>
	<published>2025-07-28T20:46:59Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-28T22:44:01Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>From <a href="https://punchbowl.news/article/senate/nrsc-apple-ios-fundraising/">this paywalled report at Punchbowl News</a>, as quoted by Taegan Goddard at Political Wire:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The Senate GOP campaign arm <a href="https://punchbowl.news/nrsc-letter/">is warning</a> that Apple’s new
iOS update could cost them $25 million in fundraising revenue, as
well as priceless GOTV opportunities,” <a href="https://punchbowl.news/archive/72825-midday-2/">Punchbowl News</a>
reports.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/07/nrsc-letter-ios-26.jpeg">Here’s a copy of the original memo from the NRSC</a> (National Republican Senatorial Committee). What they’re freaking out about is the new iOS 26 Messages feature (which will be available in Messages on iPadOS and MacOS 26 too — but because these messages are sent as SMS and because the iPhone is so many people’s primary or sole messaging device, it’s the platform they’re focusing on) <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2025/07/03/ios-26s-messages-app-has-a-solution-coming-for-unwanted-texts/">that will automatically sort messages from unknown senders</a> into a new “Unknown Sender” inbox.</p>

<p>Quoting from <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/07/nrsc-letter-ios-26.jpeg">the NRSC letter</a> (emphasis in original):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple’s iOS 26 update introduces aggressive message filtering.
Political texts — even from verified and compliant senders-will
be treated as spam by default, silently sent to an “Unknown” inbox
with no alerts or notifications. That change has profound
implications for our ability to fundraise, mobilize voters, and
run digital campaigns.</p>

<p><em>It’s important to understand: Apple isn’t just targeting cold
outreach or spammy actors.</em> Every political message — shortcode,
long code, doesn’t matter-gets pushed into the dark. The only
workaround-getting a voter to reply — is increasingly rare and
entirely at the mercy of Apple’s unclear rules. How will a voter
reply if they never get the message?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Apple’s “rules” for this new feature aren’t unclear at all. If a sender is not in your saved contacts and you’ve never sent or responded to a text message from them, they’re considered “unknown”. That’s it. The feature isn’t even really new — you’ve been able to <a href="https://support.apple.com/guide/iphone/block-filter-and-report-messages-iph203ab0be4/ios">filter messages like this in Messages for years now</a>, but what iOS 26 changes is that it now <s>will be on by default and</s> has a new more prominent — better, IMO — interface for switching between filter views. <strong>Update:</strong> I was wrong that this filtering will be on by default in iOS 26 — I was fooled because I had previously enabled “Filter Unknown Senders” in Settings → Apps → Messages → Unknown &amp; Spam (which you need to scroll down quite a bit to get to). I do think, though, that many more iOS users will be using this feature starting with iOS 26 — it’s both better designed and less hidden.</p>

<p>Back to the NRSC letter:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Here’s the shift in practice. Today, a voter with an iPhone gets
our message just like a normal text. In iOS 26, unless that
person has already replied, our message is silently sent to the
“Unknown” inbox. No ping, no badge, just buried in an inbox few
people ever check.</p>

<p>We’ve spent years complying with rigorous standards — providing full
documentation, opt-in proof, and message samples via Campaign
Verify and The Campaign Registry — yet Apple ignores that. <em>Carriers
respect it. Apple doesn’t.</em></p>

<p>Estimated prospecting losses: <em>NRSC alone could see a $25M+
revenue hit</em>. Since 70% of small-dollar donations come via text,
and iPhones make up 60% of US mobile devices, <em>the macro effect
could be over $500M in lost GOP revenue</em>. [...]</p>

<p>Unfortunately, K St and trade groups are asleep at the wheel.
Apple isn’t engaging. But we have only a few weeks left before the
public release. <em>If we’re going to push back, it has to be now. We
have a very narrow window to fix this.</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>“Unknown Senders” isn’t spam. It’s for ... unknown senders. Which these political texts are. I don’t know anyone who enjoys getting these texts in their primary timeline of messages. What the NRSC is asserting here is that they have a right to put political solicitations in your primary Messages view, and to have them appear as notifications, which is ridiculous.</p>

<p>Also, there’s no reason to believe that Republican candidates and groups will be more affected by this than Democratic ones. There’s no filtering by message content. It’s just a change to stop sending notifications for texts from unknown senders, and to put those messages in a separate timeline by default. People <em>will</em> check the Unknown Senders timeline occasionally too — all sorts of text messages from bots will go there, including some you want or need.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Republican Election Group Is Attempting to Organize Against Text Message Filtering in iOS 26’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/28/nrsc-letter-ios-26">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Adam Aaronson Drank Every Cocktail</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://aaronson.org/blog/i-drank-every-cocktail" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/whl" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/28/aaronson-cocktails" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42105</id>
	<published>2025-07-28T16:35:31Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-28T16:35:31Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Adam Aaronson:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The <a href="https://iba-world.com/">International Bartenders Association</a>, or IBA,
maintains a list of official cocktails, ones they deem to be
“the most requested recipes” at bars all around the world. It’s
the closest thing the bartending industry has to a canonical
list of cocktails, akin to the American Kennel Club’s registry
of <a href="https://www.akc.org/dog-breeds/">dog breeds</a> or a jazz musician’s <a href="https://99percentinvisible.org/episode/the-real-book/">Real Book</a> of
standards. [...]</p>

<p>As of 2025, there are 102 IBA official cocktails, and as of July
12, 2025, <a href="https://aaronson.org/cocktails/">I’ve had every one of them</a>.</p>

<p>The journey has taken me to some interesting places, and now that
it’s done, I have a little story to tell for each cocktail. I’m
not gonna tell you all 102 stories, but I do want to debrief the
experience. Drinking all 102 cocktails turned out to be
unexpectedly tricky, and for reasons you’ll soon understand, I
might be one of the first people in the world to do it.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Fun story, copiously documented with details, locations, photos, and sidenotes. Truly a blogger’s blog post.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Adam Aaronson Drank Every Cocktail’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/28/aaronson-cocktails">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>SafeBase by Drata</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://safebase.io/lp/why-safebase/?utm_source=daring_fireball&amp;utm_medium=display&amp;utm_campaign=18991230_sb_tc_campaign_DG_ENT_" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/whj" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/26/safebase-by-drata" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42103</id>
	<published>2025-07-26T20:20:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-26T20:26:09Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to Drata for sponsoring this week at DF to promote SafeBase. SafeBase eliminates the friction of inbound security reviews. It helps you automate inbound requests, use AI to answer questionnaires, and share your security posture proactively — all through a centralized Trust Center.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘SafeBase by Drata’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/26/safebase-by-drata">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>To Trust ICEBlock’s Anonymity, You Have to Trust Apple</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/cyber-security/707116/iceblock-data-privacy-security-android-version" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/whk" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/26/iceblock-trust-apple" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42104</id>
	<published>2025-07-26T20:18:46Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-26T20:24:19Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Dominic Preston, writing at The Verge, regarding Android fans’ bristling at ICEBlock developer Joshua Aaron’s claims that an Android (or web) version of ICEBlock couldn’t provide the same level of privacy as the iOS version:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Aaron told The Verge ICEBlock is built around a single database in
iCloud. When a user taps on the map to report ICE sightings, the
location data is added to that database, and users within five
miles are automatically sent a push notification alerting them.
Push notifications require developers to have some way of
designating which devices receive them, and while Aaron declined
to say precisely how the notifications function, he said alerts
are sent through Apple’s system, not ICEBlock’s, letting him avoid
keeping his own database of users or their devices. “We utilized
iCloud in kind of a creative way,” Aaron said. [...]</p>

<p>But you might have spotted the problem: ICEBlock isn’t collecting
device data on iOS, but only because similar data is stored with
Apple instead.</p>

<p>Apple maintains a database of which devices and accounts have
installed a given app, and Carlos Anso from GrapheneOS told me
that it likely also tracks device registrations for push
notifications. For either ICEBlock’s iOS app or a hypothetical
Android app, law enforcement could demand information directly
from the company, cutting ICEBlock out of the loop. Aaron told me
that he has “no idea what Apple would store,” and it “has nothing
to do with ICEBlock.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2025/07/security-vulnerabilities-in-iceblock.html">Bruce Schneier linked to this story</a> saying “the ICEBlock tool has vulnerabilities”, but I don’t think that’s a fair description. As far as we know, ICEBlock is as private as possible while still enabling push notifications, and a hypothetical Android version couldn’t be as private. But that privacy does depend on trust in Apple.</p>

<p><strong>Also worth a note:</strong> Aaron’s wife, Carolyn Feinstein, was an auditor at the Department of Justice but <a href="https://www.newsweek.com/iceblock-app-founder-wife-fired-doj-carolyn-feinstein-2102214">was fired last month because of her husband’s app</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘To Trust ICEBlock’s Anonymity, You Have to Trust Apple’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/26/iceblock-trust-apple">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>New York Times’ Style Guide Substitutions for ‘The President Violated the Constitution’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.mcsweeneys.net/articles/new-york-times-style-guide-substitutions-for-the-president-violated-the-constitution" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/whi" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/26/nyt-style-guide-president-violated-constitution" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42102</id>
	<published>2025-07-26T19:48:26Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-26T20:53:19Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Carlos Greaves, writing for McSweeney’s:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The president remained steadfast in his novel interpretation of
constitutional law.”</p>

<p>“Faced with the choice between clinging to the letter of the law
and marching to the beat of his own legal drum, the president
chose the latter.”</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘New York Times’ Style Guide Substitutions for ‘The President Violated the Constitution’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/26/nyt-style-guide-president-violated-constitution">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Obsoless’ — Ken Pillonel’s Small-Batch Cases Bring USB-C Charging to Lightning iPhones</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KUXQzVD1TdI" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/whh" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/26/obsoless-pillonel-iphone-cases" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42101</id>
	<published>2025-07-26T19:29:52Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-26T19:29:52Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Back in 2021 a young engineering student named Ken Pillonel <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SAekbJf4Gsw">modified his own iPhone X</a> to replace the Lightning port with USB-C, <a href="https://appleinsider.com/articles/21/10/11/iphone-gets-usb-c-thanks-to-creative-robotics-engineer">which became a small viral sensation</a>. He’s back at it, with a far more ambitious project: iPhone cases with USB-C  ports for the last five or so years of models with Lightning ports. He’s produced three batches of cases so far, but is <a href="https://obsoless.com/products/iph0n3-usb-c-protection-case">currently sold out</a>.</p>

<p>Even if you’re not interested in buying one of these cases, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KUXQzVD1TdI">Pillonel’s video documenting how he brought the concept to fruition</a> is quite clever and fun.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Obsoless’ — Ken Pillonel’s Small-Batch Cases Bring USB-C Charging to Lightning iPhones’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/26/obsoless-pillonel-iphone-cases">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Intel Needs a Big Customer for Foundry Business to Survive</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.reuters.com/world/asia-pacific/intels-foundry-future-depends-securing-customer-next-gen-chipmaking-tech-2025-07-25/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/whg" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/26/intel-needs-a-big-customer" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42100</id>
	<published>2025-07-26T18:00:37Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-26T20:43:00Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Max A. Cherney and Stephen Nellis, reporting for Reuters:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Those customers for the company’s so-called 14A manufacturing
process are crucial to the success of the technology — so much so
that if it fails to secure a big one, it could shut down its
cutting-edge manufacturing business altogether, according to
Intel’s quarterly filing on Thursday.</p>

<p>The possibility that Intel could drop out of the cutting-edge
manufacturing business would be a historic shift for a company
that has described itself as a steward of Moore’s Law — an
observation by Intel co-founder Gordon Moore about the fast rate
of development of the chip industry that held true for decades.
Intel is the only U.S. chipmaker capable of making advanced
computing chips.</p>

<p>Intel has struggled for years due to <a href="https://www.reuters.com/technology/inside-intel-ceo-pat-gelsinger-fumbled-revival-an-american-icon-2024-10-29/">management missteps</a>,
missing out on the AI race and losing market share to its longtime
rival AMD.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The beginning of the end for Intel was long before the AI race or the market share they’ve lost to AMD. It was missing out on mobile. From <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2013/05/paul-otellinis-intel-can-the-company-that-built-the-future-survive-it/275825/">a 2013 profile of then-CEO Paul Otellini</a>, by Alexis Madrigal for The Atlantic:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>But, oh, what could have been! Even Otellini betrayed a profound
sense of disappointment over a decision he made about a
then-unreleased product that became the iPhone. Shortly after
<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JkUpQZxLv4g">winning Apple’s Mac business</a>, he decided against doing what it
took to be the chip in Apple’s paradigm-shifting product.</p>

<p>“We ended up not winning it or passing on it, depending on how you
want to view it. And the world would have been a lot different if
we’d done it,” Otellini told me in a two-hour conversation during
his last month at Intel. “The thing you have to remember is that
this was before the iPhone was introduced and no one knew what the
iPhone would do... At the end of the day, there was a chip that
they were interested in that they wanted to pay a certain price
for and not a nickel more and that price was below our forecasted
cost. I couldn’t see it. It wasn’t one of these things you can
make up on volume. And in hindsight, the forecasted cost was wrong
and the volume was 100× what anyone thought.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That was it, the beginning of the end. It’s not just that mobile computing, as defined by the iPhone, became the largest market, by far, for chips, but that the needs of mobile devices defined the future of leading edge chipmaking across all industries: performance-per-watt, not merely sheer performance. As mobile grew, so went the economies of scale, which resulted in Apple Silicon eventually beating x86 chips not just in performance-per-watt but also in single-core performance.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Intel Needs a Big Customer for Foundry Business to Survive’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/26/intel-needs-a-big-customer">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>goo.gl, Google’s Link Shortener, Will Stop Working Next Month</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/news/713125/google-url-shortener-links-shutdown-deadline" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/whf" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/26/google-link-shortener" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42099</id>
	<published>2025-07-26T17:30:22Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-28T15:45:44Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Emma Roth, The Verge:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Google will officially deprecate links generated with its URL
shortening tool next month. On August 25th, 2025, all links in the
<code>https://goo.gl/*</code> format will no longer work and return a 404
error message.</p>

<p>Google <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2018/3/31/17184164/google-alphabet-url-shortening-service-closed">shut down its URL shortener in 2019</a>, citing “changes
we’ve seen in how people find content on the internet.” Links
created with the tool continued to work since then, but Google
<a href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/7/19/24201734/google-url-link-shortening-service-shut-down-support">announced last year</a> that it would begin deprecating them as
traffic to the shortened URLs declined. “In fact more than 99% of
them had no activity in the last month,” Google said in its <a href="https://developers.googleblog.com/en/google-url-shortener-links-will-no-longer-be-available/">July
2024 blog post</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The heyday for link shorteners was the era when Twitter (a) was still Twitter, (b) had a 140-character post limit, and (c) counted characters such that each character of a URL counted toward the 140-character limit. None of those things are true anymore. But, still. <a href="https://www.w3.org/Provider/Style/URI">Cool URLs don’t change</a>.</p>

<p>I’m sure it is true that 99 percent of goo.gl links had no activity in the past month. But I’m just as sure that it would cost next to nothing for Google to keep goo.gl up and running in perpetuity. I mean, 99 percent of <em>all</em> URLs probably had no activity in the last month. 99 percent of all books ever written weren’t read in the last month either, I bet — but that’s no excuse for libraries to throw them in the trash.</p>

<p>It’s fine that Google stopped allowing for the creating of new links a while back, but there’s no reason they should ever stop redirecting existing links. The whole reason anyone might have used goo.gl instead of something like <a href="https://bit.ly/">bit.ly</a> is misplaced trust in Google. I trust Google with almost nothing long-term. Mark my words, they’re going to do this with Gmail accounts eventually.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘goo.gl, Google’s Link Shortener, Will Stop Working Next Month’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/26/google-link-shortener">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>4chan Clowns Find Open Database of Images From Viral Women’s Dating Safety App ‘Tea’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.404media.co/women-dating-safety-app-tea-breached-users-ids-posted-to-4chan/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/whe" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/26/4chan-tea-breach" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42098</id>
	<published>2025-07-26T14:35:12Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-29T01:49:30Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Emanuel Maiberg and Joseph Cox, reporting for 404 Media:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Users from 4chan claim to have discovered an exposed database
hosted on Google’s mobile app development platform, Firebase,
belonging to the newly popular women’s dating safety app Tea.
Users say they are rifling through peoples’ personal data and
selfies uploaded to the app, and then posting that data online,
according to screenshots, 4chan posts, and code reviewed by 404
Media. In a statement to 404 Media, Tea confirmed the breach also
impacted some direct messages but said that the data is from two
years ago.</p>

<p>Tea, which claims to have more than 1.6 million users, reached the
top of the App Store charts this week and has tens of thousands of
reviews there. The app aims to provide a space for women to
exchange information about men in order to stay safe, and verifies
that new users are women by asking them to upload a selfie.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/tea-dating-advice/id6444453051">Tea</a> jumped to the top spot in the App Store (it’s still at #4 as I type this, trailing only ChatGPT, Netflix, and Amazon Prime Video) and has been getting a lot of <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/tea-app-women-share-anonymous-dating-reviews-goes-viral-2025-7">coverage this week</a>. A wide open, publicly accessible database of users’ driver’s licenses and self portraits is, to say the least, pretty egregious.</p>

<p>I’m not accusing Tea in particular of being vibe-coded, but I do wonder if this sort of thing is going to become commonplace as more apps and services come online after being developed in slapdash AI-assisted manners.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘4chan Clowns Find Open Database of Images From Viral Women’s Dating Safety App ‘Tea’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/26/4chan-tea-breach">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Talk Show: ‘The Shift-2 Crowd’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2025/07/25/ep-427" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/whd" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/25/the-talk-show-427" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42097</id>
	<published>2025-07-25T23:47:04Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-25T23:47:04Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jason Snell returns to the show to talk about the early PC platform rivalries of the 1980s, iOS 26 leaks (and Apple suing YouTuber Jon Prosser), the various Apple OS 26 public betas and the state of Liquid Glass, and more. (Where by “more” I mean a little baseball and keyboard nerdery.)</p>

<p><audio
    src = "https://traffic.libsyn.com/secure/daringfireball/thetalkshow-427-jason-snell.mp3"
    controls
    preload = "none"
/></p>

<p><strong>Sponsored by:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://factormeals.com/talkshow50off">Factor</a>: Healthy eating, made easy. Get 50% off plus free shipping on your first box.</li>
<li><a href="https://sentry.io/signup/?utm_source=twist&amp;utm_medium=paid-community&amp;utm_campaign=seer-fy26q2-evergreen&amp;utm_content=recording-twist-tryfree">Sentry</a>: The real-time error monitoring and tracing platform that helps dev teams and tech companies build better, more reliable products. Use code <strong>talkshow</strong> for 3 months free and 150,000 errors.</li>
<li><a href="https://squarespace.com/talkshow">Squarespace</a>: Save 10% off your first purchase of a website or domain using code <strong>talkshow</strong>.</li>
</ul>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Talk Show: ‘The Shift-2 Crowd’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/25/the-talk-show-427">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Public Betas for Apple OSes 26</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2025/07/first-look-ios-26-public-beta/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/whc" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/24/public-betas-for-apple-oses-26" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42096</id>
	<published>2025-07-24T22:39:20Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-26T17:42:39Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The public betas are out for iOS/iPadOS/WatchOS/MacOS 26, and Dan Moren and Jason Snell cover them all at Six Colors. Here’s Moren on iOS 26:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple’s new design language, dubbed Liquid Glass, applies across
all their platforms, but unsurprisingly, it feels most at home on
the iPhone and iPad. That’s in part because of the touch
interface; the literal hands-on nature makes the feel responsive
and more like physical things that you’re interacting with. For
example, dragging the new magnifying loupe across the screen,
watching the way it magnifies and distorts text and images as it
passes over them — this interaction has always been unique to iOS
for practical reasons, but the way it feels here doesn’t have a
direct analogue on other platforms.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>For it now being late July, though, there remain a lot of <a href="https://mastodon.social/@gruber/114909122813996684">glaring problems</a>. I hope to be proven wrong, but I think the legibility/usability problems are going to make the 26.0 versions of Apple’s OSes unpopular. Functionally, iOS and iPadOS 26 betas 4 are solid. MacOS 26 Tahoe really adds some great productivity features. But visually, not so much for any of these OSes (especially MacOS) — and that, to me, is a serious problem.</p>

<p>Anyway, public beta commentary:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2025/07/first-look-ios-26-public-beta/">Dan Moren on iOS 26</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2025/07/first-look-ipados-26-public-beta/">Jason Snell on iPadOS 26</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2025/07/first-look-watchos-26-public-beta/">Moren on WatchOS 26</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://sixcolors.com/post/2025/07/first-look-macos-tahoe-public-beta/">Snell on MacOS 26 Tahoe</a>.</li>
</ul>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Public Betas for Apple OSes 26’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/24/public-betas-for-apple-oses-26">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/07/iceblock" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/whb" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42095</id>
	<published>2025-07-24T16:15:12Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-26T20:11:16Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">To maintain anonymity and store zero user data, there is and can be no web app version of ICEBlock. There is and can be no Android version. Only iOS supports the security and privacy features for ICEBlock to offer what it does, the way it does.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://www.iceblock.app/">ICEBlock</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>ICEBlock is an innovative, completely anonymous crowdsourced
platform that allows users to report Immigration and Customs
Enforcement (ICE) activity with just two taps on their phone. In
recent years, ICE has faced criticism for alleged civil rights
abuses and failures to adhere to constitutional principles and due
process, making it crucial for communities to stay informed about
its operations.</p>

<p>Modeled after Waze but for ICE sightings, the app ensures user
privacy by storing no personal data, making it impossible to trace
reports back to individual users. Available exclusively for iOS
devices, ICEBlock empowers communities to stay informed about ICE
presence within a 5-mile radius while maintaining their anonymity
through real-time updates and automatic deletion of sightings
after four hours.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The ICEBlock app is interesting in and of itself (and from my tire-kicking test drive, appears to be a well-crafted and designed app), as will be Apple’s response if (when?) the Trump administration takes offense to the app’s existence. Back in 2019, kowtowing to tacit demands from China, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2019/10/10/apple-pulls-hkmaps">Apple removed from the App Store an app called HKmap.live</a> which helped pro-democracy activists in Hong Kong know the location of police and protest activity. The app broke no Hong Kong laws, but <a href="https://www.npr.org/2019/10/10/768841864/after-china-objects-apple-removes-app-used-by-hong-kong-protesters">scared the thin-skinned skittish lickspittles in the Chinese Communist Party</a>. (Remember too that in 2019, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2019/10/07/taiwan-flag-emoji">Apple removed the Taiwan flag emoji</a> (🇹🇼) from the iOS 13 keyboard for users in Hong Kong and Macau.)</p>

<p>One defense from Apple regarding HKmap.live, however, was that the iOS app was a thin wrapper around the website, which website remained fully functional and could be saved to an iPhone user’s home screen. Removing the app from the App Store thus did not prevent Hong Kongers from accessing it. (<a href="https://hkmap.live/">That website</a> today <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HKmap.live">seems to be defunct</a>.)</p>

<p>ICEBlock is different. It is <em>only</em> available as a native iOS app. According to the developers, this is for technical reasons. From their web page explaining <a href="https://www.iceblock.app/android">why they <em>can’t</em> offer an Android version</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>At ICEBlock, user privacy and security are paramount. Our
application is designed to provide as much anonymity as possible
without storing any user data or creating accounts. While we
understand the desire for an Android version of ICEBlock,
achieving this level of anonymity on Android is not feasible due
to the inherent requirements of push notification services.</p>

<p>To send push notifications on Android, it is necessary to use a
mechanism that requires storing device IDs. This means that we
would need to maintain a privately hosted database to store these
identifiers. Storing such data, even if it’s anonymized,
introduces significant privacy risks. [...]</p>

<p>In contrast, iOS offers us the flexibility to deliver push
notifications while adhering strictly to our design philosophy.
Apple’s ecosystem allows for push notifications to be sent without
requiring us to store any user-identifiable information. This
ensures that ICEBlock remains completely anonymous and secure.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>To deliver push notifications on Android, the developers claim they would need to maintain a database of device IDs, create a user account system to manage those device IDs, and all of that server-stored data would be susceptible to law enforcement subpoenas and pro-ICE red hat hackers. (What “brown shirts” were to the Nazis, we should make “red hats” to MAGA.)</p>

<p>To maintain anonymity and store zero user data, there is and can be no web app version of ICEBlock. There is and can be no Android version. Only iOS supports the security and privacy features for ICEBlock to offer what it does, the way it does. Here’s to hoping that Apple will proudly defend it if push comes to shove.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ ICEBlock, an iOS Exclusive</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Yours Truly With David Barnard on the Sub Club Podcast</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://subclub.com/episode/the-past-present-and-future-of-building-on-apple-john-gruber-daring-fireball" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wha" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/23/yours-truly-with-david-barnard-on-the-sub-club-podcast" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42094</id>
	<published>2025-07-23T21:08:08Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-23T21:08:09Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>David Barnard:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>On the podcast I talk with John about the fascinating 40-year
history of Apple’s developer relations, how almost going bankrupt
in the 1990s shaped today’s control-focused approach, and why we
might need an “App Store 3.0” reset.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Yet <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/19/cortex-hurley-interview-with-yours-truly">another</a> fun appearance on a podcast. There’s a good transcript too, if you’re more of a reader than a listener.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Yours Truly With David Barnard on the Sub Club Podcast’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/23/yours-truly-with-david-barnard-on-the-sub-club-podcast">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Financial Times Reports the UK Is Backing Down From Its Demand for Apple to Grant It an iCloud Encryption Backdoor</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2025/07/uk-backing-down-on-apple-encryption-backdoor-after-pressure-from-us/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wh9" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/22/uk-backing-down-on-apple-encryption-backdoor" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42093</id>
	<published>2025-07-22T17:34:09Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-22T17:54:50Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Anna Gross, Tim Bradshaw, and Lauren Fedor, reporting for the Financial Times (syndicated without paywall at Ars Technica):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Sir Keir Starmer’s government is seeking a way out of a clash with
the Trump administration over the UK’s demand that Apple provide
it with access to secure customer data, two senior British
officials have told the Financial Times. The officials both said
the Home Office, which ordered the tech giant in January to grant
access to its most secure cloud storage system, would probably
have to retreat in the face of pressure from senior leaders in
Washington, including Vice President JD Vance.</p>

<p>“This is something that the vice president is very annoyed about
and which needs to be resolved,” said an official in the UK’s
technology department. “The Home Office is basically going to have
to back down.”</p>

<p>Both officials said the UK decision to force Apple to break its
end-to-end encryption — which has been raised multiple times by
top officials in Donald Trump’s administration — could impede
technology agreements with the US.</p>

<p>“One of the challenges for the tech partnerships we’re working on
is the encryption issue,” the first official said. “It’s a big red
line in the US — they don’t want us messing with their tech
companies.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>One dystopian element of the UK’s Investigatory Powers Act is that when companies are issued demands under the law — which critics in the UK call “the Snoopers’ Charter” — it’s a criminal offense subject to imprisonment to reveal to anyone that the UK government issued the demand. You will recall that after receiving this demand, in February this year <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/02/apple_pulls_advanced_data_protection_from_the_uk">Apple pulled iCloud Advanced Data Protection from users in the UK</a>.</p>

<p>What I don’t like about the Financial Times’s framing of this is that they describe it only in terms of politics between the Trump administration and Starmer’s. This is not merely about a foreign government “messing with their tech companies”. It’s fundamentally about privacy and security. It is a human rights and civil liberties issue, first and foremost. The Trump administration is on the correct and just side of this issue. Whether they’re on the correct side for the right reasons, I don’t know, but that’s what’s most important here. A secret backdoor is abhorrent from all perspectives: privacy, security, civil liberties. (Not to mention impossible cryptographically with E2EE — mandating a backdoor is effectively banning E2EE, which is why Apple pulled Advanced Data Protection from the UK.)</p>

<p>Conversely, one reason the UK went through with this demand is that <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/02/26/wapo-biden-justice-department-backdoor">the Biden administration was, disgracefully, on the wrong side of this</a>, choosing to look the other way and lie to Congress about what the UK was planning to do.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Financial Times Reports the UK Is Backing Down From Its Demand for Apple to Grant It an iCloud Encryption Backdoor’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/22/uk-backing-down-on-apple-encryption-backdoor">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>OS 26 Beta 4’s Are Out</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/07/22/apple-seeds-ios-26-beta-4/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wh8" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/22/os-26-beta-4" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42092</id>
	<published>2025-07-22T17:07:53Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-23T01:23:17Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Juli Clover, MacRumors:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple today provided developers with the fourth betas of <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/roundup/ios-26/">iOS
26</a> and <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/roundup/ipados-26/">iPadOS 26</a> for testing purposes, with the
updates coming two weeks after Apple <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/07/07/apple-seeds-ios-26-beta-3/">seeded the third
betas</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/07/22/apple-seeds-macos-tahoe-beta-4/">MacOS</a>, <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/07/22/apple-seeds-watchos-26-beta-4/">WatchOS, tvOS, and VisionOS</a> too, all in lockstep. Also, a <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/07/22/ios-26-beta-4-features/">good first look at what’s changed in iOS 26 beta 4 from beta 3</a>. Some of the things Apple is tweaking between betas <a href="https://mastodon.social/@gruber/114899907908341231">need more than minor tweaking</a>. Also: Apple Intelligence summaries for news notifications <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/07/22/ios-26-beta-4-notification-summaries/">are back</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘OS 26 Beta 4’s Are Out’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/22/os-26-beta-4">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Computer History Museum’s Vintage Computer Festival: August 1–2</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://computerhistory.org/events/vintage-computer-festival-3/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wh7" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/22/chm-vintage-computer-festival" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42091</id>
	<published>2025-07-22T16:12:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-22T16:15:01Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>CHM:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Come and explore an extraordinary showcase of historical
computers, from pristine originals to ingenious modern hacks.
Computer enthusiasts around the world look forward to the annual
Vintage Computer Festival.</p>

<p>Experience hands-on demos of historical systems from the 1960s
through the 1990s, learn preservation tips, and try out brands
like Apple, Atari, Commodore, Tandy/Radio Shack, and more.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s in Mountain View, so I can’t make it, but given <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/14/commodore-64-ultimate">all</a> <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/15/saur-c64">the</a> <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/16/snell-commodore-apple">recent</a> <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/20/dont-forget-atari">nostalgia</a> that’s been in the air regarding the early PC era, I wish I could.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Computer History Museum’s Vintage Computer Festival: August 1–2’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/22/chm-vintage-computer-festival">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Hackers Exploit Zero-Day Microsoft SharePoint Exploit, Attacking Governments and Businesses Around the World</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2025/07/20/microsoft-sharepoint-hack/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wh6" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/22/zero-day-microsoft-sharepoint-exploit" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42090</id>
	<published>2025-07-22T15:41:21Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-22T15:41:22Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Ellen Nakashima, Yvonne Wingett Sanchez and Joseph Menn, reporting for The Washington Post:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The U.S. government and partners in Canada and Australia are
investigating the compromise of SharePoint servers, which provide
a platform for sharing and managing documents. Tens of thousands
of such servers are at risk, experts said, and Microsoft has
issued no patch for the flaw, leaving victims around the world
scrambling to respond.</p>

<p>The “zero-day” attack, so called because it targeted a previously
unknown vulnerability, is only the latest cybersecurity
embarrassment for Microsoft. Last year, the company was faulted by
a panel of U.S. government and industry experts for lapses that
enabled a <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/national-security/2024/04/02/microsoft-cyber-china-hack-report/">2023 targeted Chinese hack of U.S. government
emails</a>, including those of then-Commerce Secretary Gina
Raimondo.</p>

<p>This most recent attack compromises only those servers housed
within an organization — not those in the cloud, such as
Microsoft 365, officials said. After first suggesting that users
make modifications to or simply unplug SharePoint server programs
from the internet, the company on Sunday evening released a patch
for one version of the software. Two other versions remain
vulnerable and Microsoft said it is continuing to work to develop
a patch.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>“Just pull the plug” — classic Microsoft security.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>With access to these servers, which often connect to Outlook
email, Teams and other core services, a breach can lead to theft
of sensitive data as well as password harvesting,
Netherlands-based research company <a href="https://research.eye.security/sharepoint-under-siege/">Eye Security noted</a>.
What’s also alarming, researchers said, is that the hackers have
gained access to keys that may allow them to regain entry even
after a system is patched. “So pushing out a patch on Monday or
Tuesday doesn’t help anybody who’s been compromised in the past 72
hours,” said one researcher, who spoke on the condition of
anonymity because a federal investigation is ongoing.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Sounds bad.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The nonprofit Center for Internet Security, which staffs an
information-sharing group for state and local governments,
notified about 100 organizations that they were vulnerable and
potentially compromised, said Randy Rose, the organization’s vice
president. Those warned included public schools and universities.
The process took six hours Saturday night — much longer than it
otherwise would have, because the threat-intelligence and
incident-response teams have been cut by 65 percent as CISA
slashed funding, Rose said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/04/16/dingalings-cut-off-funding-for-cve">Another</a> DOGE success story.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Hackers Exploit Zero-Day Microsoft SharePoint Exploit, Attacking Governments and Businesses Around the World’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/22/zero-day-microsoft-sharepoint-exploit">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Reuters: ‘Meta, X, and LinkedIn Appeal Unprecedented VAT Claim by Italy’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.reuters.com/world/europe/meta-x-linkedin-appeal-unprecedented-vat-claim-by-italy-2025-07-21/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wh5" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/22/italy-meta-x-linkedin-tax" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42089</id>
	<published>2025-07-22T15:31:57Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-22T17:09:53Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Reuters:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Italian tax authorities argue that free user registrations with X,
LinkedIn and Meta platforms should be seen as taxable transactions
as they imply the exchange of a membership account in return for a
user’s personal data.</p>

<p>The issue is especially sensitive given wider trade tensions
between the EU and the administration of U.S. President Donald
Trump. Italy is claiming 887.6 million euros ($1.03 billion) from
Meta, 12.5 million euros from X and around 140 million euros from
LinkedIn. [...]</p>

<p>According to several experts consulted by Reuters, the Italian
approach could affect almost all companies, from airlines to
supermarkets to publishers, who link access to free services on
their sites to users’ acceptance of profiling cookies.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Charging a VAT on free account signups does not strike me as a good idea.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Reuters: ‘Meta, X, and LinkedIn Appeal Unprecedented VAT Claim by Italy’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/22/italy-meta-x-linkedin-tax">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Google Solves Its Pixel 10 Leaks by Just Showing Us the Phone’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/news/711033/google-pixel-10-design-tease-reveal" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wh4" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/22/google-pixel-10" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42088</id>
	<published>2025-07-22T15:25:06Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-22T15:25:07Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jay Peters, The Verge:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Google’s Pixel 10 launch event is just under a month away, but the
company is already revealing the official design of the base
phone. You can currently see a video of the phone <a href="https://store.google.com/magazine/google_pixel_10">on Google’s
website</a> (and below). It looks just like the official renders that
<a href="https://www.theverge.com/news/710809/google-pixel-10-leaked-official-renders-third-telephoto-camera">leaked earlier today</a>, which showed that the phone will have a
third back camera (which is rumored to be a telephoto sensor).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That’s certainly one way to deal with leaks. It looks like a Pixel 9, which looks like an iPhone 12–16 with a different (but cool) camera mesa.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Google Solves Its Pixel 10 Leaks by Just Showing Us the Phone’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/22/google-pixel-10">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Will Wonders Never Cease?</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2025-07-21/oracle-in-talks-for-100-million-skydance-paramount-cloud-deal" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wh3" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/21/skydance-oracle-deal" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42087</id>
	<published>2025-07-22T00:59:53Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-22T00:59:53Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Brody Ford and Hannah Miller, reporting for Bloomberg:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Oracle Corp. is in discussions with Skydance Media LLC for a major
software deal once the media company’s acquisition of Paramount
Global is complete. The new arrangement is expected to be worth
about $100 million per year, according to people familiar with the
matter who asked not to be named speaking about the private
discussions. The agreement would see Paramount and its
subsidiaries using Oracle’s cloud software, the people said.</p>

<p>Skydance was founded by David Ellison, the son of Oracle Chairman
Larry Ellison.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Reminiscent of <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/14/musk-gives-himself-a-handshake">SpaceX’s $2 billion “investment” in xAI</a>. (<a href="https://x.com/pkafka/status/1947444354659787026">Via Peter Kafka</a>.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Will Wonders Never Cease?’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/21/skydance-oracle-deal">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Commanders : Goofus :: Guardians : Gallant</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nbcsports.com/nfl/profootballtalk/rumor-mill/news/as-guardians-dig-in-commanders-remain-mum-on-president-trumps-name-change-demand" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wh2" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/21/commanders-goofus-guardians-gallant" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42086</id>
	<published>2025-07-22T00:24:03Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-22T02:53:25Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Mike Florio, NBC Sports:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>And while the Guardians <a href="https://x.com/ZackMeisel/status/1946961807198875727">stood up and responded to Trump</a>, the
Commanders are hiding under the bed. With the NFL right next
to them.</p>

<p>We’ve sent multiple emails to both the team and the league seeking
comment on one of the biggest stories in all of sports. No one has
responded. It’s a common, low-tech, P.R. play. Ignore the request,
and maybe the reporter will forget about it. Force the reporter to
remember, and to ask again. And maybe again.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Here’s the statement from Guardians team president Chris Antonetti:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“I understand there are very different perspectives on the
decision we made a few years ago, but it’s a decision we made and
we’ve gotten the opportunity to build the brand as the Guardians
over the last four years and we’re excited about the future that’s
in front of us.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’d recommend going a little further and saying that everyone in the organization loves the new brand, but that’s quibbling. What the Commanders and the NFL are doing is cowardice.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Commanders : Goofus :: Guardians : Gallant’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/21/commanders-goofus-guardians-gallant">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://safebase.io/lp/why-safebase/?utm_source=daring_fireball&amp;utm_medium=display&amp;utm_campaign=18991230_sb_tc_campaign_DG_ENT_" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wh1" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/07/safebase_by_drata" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/feeds/sponsors//11.42085</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2025-07-21T21:44:46Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-21T21:44:47Z</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Eliminate the friction of inbound security reviews. SafeBase helps you automate inbound requests, use AI to answer questionnaires, and share your security posture proactively — all through a centralized Trust Center.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘SafeBase by Drata’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2025/07/safebase_by_drata">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] SafeBase by Drata</title></entry><entry>
	<title>‘CBS: The Tiffany Network’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7Rv36XkQojM" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wh0" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/21/cbs-the-tiffany-network" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42084</id>
	<published>2025-07-21T20:41:02Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-21T20:41:03Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Letterman: “You can’t spell CBS without BS.”</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘CBS: The Tiffany Network’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/21/cbs-the-tiffany-network">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>HRW Report Documents Abusive Practices at Three Florida Immigration Detention Centers Since January 2025</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.hrw.org/report/2025/07/21/you-feel-like-your-life-is-over/abusive-practices-at-three-florida-immigration" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgz" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/21/hrw-ice-detention-abuse" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42083</id>
	<published>2025-07-21T18:05:36Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-21T18:05:37Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>John Holmes for Human Rights Watch (<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2025/jul/21/migrants-miami-ice-jail-abuses">via The Guardian</a>):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>One woman described arriving at Krome — a facility that typically
<a href="https://www.oig.dhs.gov/sites/default/files/assets/2024-04/OIG-24-21-Apr24.pdf">only holds men</a> — late at night on January 28. Officers then
confined her for days with dozens of other women without bedding
or privacy, in a cell normally used only during incarceration
intake procedures. “There was only one toilet, and it was covered
in feces,” she said. “We begged the officers to let us clean it,
but they just said sarcastically, ‘Housekeeping will come soon.’
No one ever came.”</p>

<p>A man recalled the frigid conditions in the intake cell where he
was detained: “They turned up the air conditioning... You could
not fall asleep because it was so cold. I thought I was going to
experience hypothermia.”</p>

<p>This report documents serious violations of medical standards.
Detention facility staff routinely denied individuals with
diabetes, asthma, kidney conditions, and chronic pain their
prescribed medications and access to doctors. In one case at
Krome, a woman with gallstones began vomiting and lost
consciousness after being denied care for several days. Officers
returned her to the same cell after emergency surgery to remove
her gallbladder — still without medication. [...]</p>

<p>Staff were dismissive or abusive even when detainees were
undergoing a visibly obvious medical crisis. For example, staff
ignored a detained immigrant who began coughing blood in a crowded
holding cell for hours. In that case, unrest ensued, and a
Disturbance Control Team stormed the cell, forcing the men in it
to lie face down on the wet, dirty floor while officers zip-tied
their hands behind their backs. A detainee said he heard an
officer order the cell’s CCTV camera feed to be turned off.
Another detainee said a team member slapped him while shouting,
“Shut the fuck up.”</p>

<p>During another incident, officers made men eat while shackled with
their hands behind their backs after forcing the group to wait
hours for lunch: “We had to bend over and eat off the chairs with
our mouths, like dogs,” one man said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://constitution.congress.gov/constitution/amendment-8/">The Eighth Amendment of the US Constitution</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Excessive bail shall not be required, nor excessive fines imposed,
nor cruel and unusual punishments inflicted.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘HRW Report Documents Abusive Practices at Three Florida Immigration Detention Centers Since January 2025’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/21/hrw-ice-detention-abuse">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>WorkOS: Summer Launch Week</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://workos.com/launch-week/summer-2025" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgv" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/20/workos-summer-launch-week" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42079</id>
	<published>2025-07-21T02:04:00Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-21T02:04:09Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to WorkOS for sponsoring last week at DF to promote their summer launch week. You may recall their previous launch week <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/03/21/workos-launch-week">back in spring</a>, when I emphasized that their launch week announcements were worth checking out just to admire the retro-modern design of the web page. Well, they’ve done it again, with all-new retro pixel-art design. It’s so fun and well done, with a bunch of UI elements that you can play with.</p>

<p>Amidst the fun of the presentation, they once again have a slew of great new features, including:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://workos.com/blog/authkit-custom-css">Custom CSS for AuthKit</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://workos.com/blog/feature-flags">Feature Flags</a> — “Assign flags, expose them in JWTs, and roll out features with targeted control.”</li>
<li><a href="https://workos.com/blog/supabase-integration">Supabase Native Auth Integration</a>.</li>
<li><a href="https://workos.com/blog/cli-auth">CLI Auth</a> — “Log in from the command line with OAuth 2.0 device grant flow”.</li>
</ul>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘WorkOS: Summer Launch Week’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/20/workos-summer-launch-week">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Mad King Watch: Trump Threatens to Interfere With Stadium Deal Unless Washington Commanders Change Name Back to ‘Redskins’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.reuters.com/sports/trump-threatens-washington-stadium-deal-unless-nfl-team-readopts-redskins-name-2025-07-20/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgy" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/20/trump-threatens-commanders" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42082</id>
	<published>2025-07-21T02:03:20Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-24T18:59:31Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Reuters, with a headline that truly could have come from The Onion, “Trump Threatens Washington Stadium Deal Unless NFL Team Readopts Redskins Name”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>U.S. President Donald Trump threatened on Sunday to interfere with
a deal to build a new football stadium in Washington, D.C., unless
the local NFL team, now known as the Commanders, changes its name
back to Redskins. The American football team dropped the name
Redskins in 2020 after decades of criticism that it was a racial
slur with links to the U.S. genocide of the Indigenous population.</p>

<p>Trump had called for a return to the name Redskins — and for the
Cleveland Guardians baseball team to once again adopt the name
Indians — on other occasions, but on Sunday he added that he may
take official action.</p>

<p>“I may put a restriction on them that if they don’t change the
name back to the original ‘Washington Redskins,’ and get rid of
the ridiculous moniker, ‘Washington Commanders,’ I won’t make a
deal for them to build a Stadium in Washington,” Trump said in a
post on his Truth Social platform.</p>

<p>The team moved from Washington to suburban Landover, Maryland, in
1997, but earlier this year reached an agreement with the local
District of Columbia government to return to the city with a new
stadium expected to open in 2030.</p>

<p>Trump has limited authority to intervene under the current
home-rule law governing federal oversight of the District of
Columbia, but he has raised the prospect of taking more control,
telling reporters in February, “I think we should take over
Washington, D.C.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It should be emphasized — and shame on Reuters for not doing so — that Trump can’t just “take control” of the District of Columbia. Per <a href="https://constitution.congress.gov/browse/article-1/section-8/">Article I, Section 8</a> of the Constitution, it’s Congressional authority that oversees the district, not the Executive branch.</p>

<p>Here are the <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/114885987478070699">two</a> <a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/114887236310446076">posts</a> from his blog that got this obvious attempt to distract from his involvement with Jeffrey Epstein. (“<em>Look at me, I’m a crazy old angry racist, not a creepy old pedophile!</em>”)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Mad King Watch: Trump Threatens to Interfere With Stadium Deal Unless Washington Commanders Change Name Back to ‘Redskins’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/20/trump-threatens-commanders">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Don’t Forget About Atari</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://cory.news/posts/2025-07-17-atari/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgx" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/20/dont-forget-atari" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42081</id>
	<published>2025-07-21T00:18:36Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-21T00:34:50Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Cory Ondrejka joins in on the 40-year-old retro computing reminiscing:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>For being otherwise bright folks, it’s remarkable how completely
wrong they all are. The Atari was the best computer to have.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This whole friendly debate reminds me of the oft-cited adage that the best camera is the one you have with you: The best computer in the 1980s was whichever one your parents bought you. I honestly don’t remember anyone I knew who had an Atari computer. Atari game consoles, sure — almost <em>everyone</em> I knew had a 2600, and we all coveted the 5200. <a href="https://appdot.net/@morrick/114866268850615377">But they sure were cool-looking</a>.</p>

<p>Oddly enough, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jack_Tramiel">Jack Tramiel</a><sup>*</sup> — who founded and named Commodore in 1953 as a typewriter company and was running the company when it launched the PET (1977), VIC-20 (1980), and Commodore 64 (1982) — left the company after a dispute with the board in 1984 (a <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/1985/09/19/business/apple-computer-entrepreneur-s-rise-and-fall.html">common</a> industry occurrence in those days, seemingly), founded a new company briefly named Tramel Technology (not “Tramiel”, for ease of spelling), which bought the then-failing consumer business of Atari from Warner Communications and took the Atari name for its own. In 1985 Tramiel <a href="https://www.goto10retro.com/p/atari-st-40th-anniversary">launched the Atari ST line at CES</a>. To me the 16-bit Atari ST barely registers in my memory — I don’t think I ever encountered one anywhere, including in a store. When I think of Atari personal computers I think of the <a href="https://www.goto10retro.com/p/atari-st-40th-anniversary">8-bit Atari 800</a> (pretty cool!) and 400 (horrible — perhaps <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7CnYI0E_6mk">the worst keyboard ever shipped</a>) from 1979.</p>

<p>(Anyway, neither of those aforecited adages are really true, though. Some cameras are much better than others. And the best computers back then were the Apple II’s.)</p>

<p><small>* Just me or was <a href="https://duckduckgo.com/?t=h_&amp;q=jack+tramiel&amp;ia=images&amp;iax=images">Tramiel a dead ringer</a> for character actor <a href="https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0432410/">Gordon Jump</a>, of <em>WKRP in Cincinnati</em> fame?</small></p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Don’t Forget About Atari’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/20/dont-forget-atari">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The WSJ on Late Night TV’s Ad Revenue Decline, and CBS’s Decision to Cancel The Late Show</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.wsj.com/business/media/stephen-colbert-late-show-canceled-profit-3dcc48a2?st=TT3iun" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgw" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/20/wsj-late-night-ad-revenue" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42080</id>
	<published>2025-07-20T20:59:37Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-21T00:36:35Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Joe Flint and John Jurgensen, reporting for The Wall Street Journal (gift link):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>But digital advertising revenue hasn’t made up for the fall in ad
dollars going to traditional broadcast programming. Spending on
linear advertising for the late-night segment on ABC, CBS and NBC
fell from $439 million in 2018 to $221 million in 2024, according
to Guideline, an ad-tracking platform.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That’s a precipitous decline, if accurate. But still, given that Colbert’s <em>The Late Show</em> has consistently been the highest-rated overall and tied with ABC’s <em>Jimmy Kimmel Live</em> for the 18–49 year-old demographic, it feels very safe to presume that it generated at least a full third — say, $75–80 million — of that $221 million total. It’s reported that Colbert’s salary is $20 million per year, and Colbert himself said the other night the show employs 200 staff.</p>

<p>If, as anonymous CBS sources are claiming to multiple outlets, the show lost $40 million last year, that means it costs something on the order of $120 million per year to produce, or $100 million after Colbert’s salary. With a staff of 200 people, that’s an <em>average</em> salary of $500,000. I know it costs money to heat and cool the Ed Sullivan theater, and I’m sure there are other costs. But there is no way the average salary of a staff member on the show is half a million per year.</p>

<p>And, even if somehow <em>The Late Show</em> <em>did</em> lose money last year, it seems implausible that CBS wouldn’t first ask for budget cuts — staff reductions, a salary cut for Colbert, whatever else might possibly be running up a $120 million/year budget — before just shutting the whole thing down. NBC’s <em>Late Night With Seth Meyers</em> <a href="https://variety.com/2024/tv/news/seth-meyers-late-night-8g-band-budget-cuts-1236034409/">sadly cut the live studio band last year</a>, for example. $75 million per year in ad revenue is way down from its <a href="https://nypost.com/2015/08/23/colberts-late-show-ready-to-challenge-fallons-ad-revenue/">Letterman era heyday</a>, but that’s surely more than enough to produce a talk show. Also, all of this back-of-the-napkin budget analysis neglects to assign any promotional value to the show. CBS gets to promote everything else on the network to over 2 million people per night with house ads during commercial breaks and guests on the show from other CBS programs.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The WSJ on Late Night TV’s Ad Revenue Decline, and CBS’s Decision to Cancel The Late Show’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/20/wsj-late-night-ad-revenue">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Myke Hurley Interviews Yours Truly for the Cortex ‘State of the Workflow’ Series</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theenthusiast.net/john-gruber-state-of-the-workflow/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgt" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/19/cortex-hurley-interview-with-yours-truly" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42077</id>
	<published>2025-07-19T16:25:18Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-19T16:25:18Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Myke Hurley:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>For this episode, I took a slightly different approach for the
main section, following step-by-step how John writes and publishes
an article. I think this is a template I want to follow with
future guests, taking a detailed look at what they do from
beginning to end.</p>

<p>I’m so pleased with how this interview turned out — I actually
think it may be one of the best of my career. I’ve never had the
chance to have a one-on-one podcast with John before, and I’m
happy we waited until now to make it happen.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We spoke for a long time, and at some point like halfway through, it really hit me that Hurley was asking <em>really</em> good questions. If you’re interested in how I work and the tools I use, you should enjoy listening to this interview as much as I enjoyed participating in it.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Myke Hurley Interviews Yours Truly for the Cortex ‘State of the Workflow’ Series’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/19/cortex-hurley-interview-with-yours-truly">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Puck: ‘Was Colbert’s Cancellation Really “Economic” for CBS?’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://puck.news/was-colberts-cancellation-really-economic-for-cbs/?sharer=167184&amp;token=9a8ea7a6fea9e13d6d23eaf8102f68d3" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgs" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/19/belloni-colbert-economic" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42076</id>
	<published>2025-07-19T16:17:18Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-21T00:37:19Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Matthew Belloni, writing at Puck (paywall-busting gift link) regarding the claim from anonymous CBS sources that <em>The Late Show</em> lost $40 million last year:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Nobody can know for sure. All I can tell you is what I’m hearing.
Several sources at both CBS and Skydance insist the decision was
based on economics, not politics. After all, if this was about
appeasing Trump, they argue, Cheeks would have pulled Colbert off
the air ASAP rather than giving him 10 more months in the chair.
“Trust me, there’s no conspiracy,” a very good source close to
Colbert told me tonight. Still, two other people with deep ties to
CBS and <em>Late Show</em> suspect otherwise. After all, when a network
decides that a show is too expensive, executives typically go to
the key talent and ask them to take pay cuts, fire people, or
otherwise slash costs. That didn’t happen here — though with
Colbert said to be making between $15 million and $20 million per
year, a pay cut wouldn’t have solved the problem on its own. And
given the company’s willingness to fold to Trump, there’s no
reason for you or me to think they would stand up to any political
pressure, or resist any specific demand (which, of course, is the
reason to not settle frivolous litigation…). If Chris McCarthy,
Cheeks’s counterpart on the cable TV side, cancels <em>The Daily
Show</em> in the next couple weeks, I think we’ll have a good idea
what’s going on. But for now, I cautiously (and skeptically)
believe that this was mostly an economic decision.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Puck: ‘Was Colbert’s Cancellation Really “Economic” for CBS?’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/19/belloni-colbert-economic">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>ChatGPT Agent</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://openai.com/index/introducing-chatgpt-agent/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgr" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/18/chatgpt-agent" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42075</id>
	<published>2025-07-19T01:03:34Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-19T01:03:34Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>OpenAI:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You can now ask ChatGPT to handle requests like “look at my
calendar and brief me on upcoming client meetings based on recent
news,” “plan and buy ingredients to make Japanese breakfast for
four,” and “analyze three competitors and create a slide deck.”
ChatGPT will intelligently navigate websites, filter results,
prompt you to log in securely when needed, run code, conduct
analysis, and even deliver editable slideshows and spreadsheets
that summarize its findings.</p>

<p>At the core of this new capability is a unified agentic system. It
brings together three strengths of earlier breakthroughs:
<a href="https://openai.com/index/introducing-operator/"><em>Operator’s</em> </a> ability to interact with websites, <a href="https://openai.com/index/introducing-deep-research/"><em>deep
research’s</em> </a> skill in synthesizing information, and ChatGPT’s
intelligence and conversational fluency.</p>

<p>ChatGPT carries out these tasks using its own virtual computer,
fluidly shifting between reasoning and action to handle complex
workflows from start to finish, all based on your instructions.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Impressive examples in the embedded videos in the post.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘ChatGPT Agent’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/18/chatgpt-agent">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Billionaire Jackass Bill Ackman Bought His Way Into Playing in a Legit Professional Tennis Tournament and, Shockingly, He Embarrassed Himself and Everyone Involved With Letting Him Play</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.youtube.com/shorts/L7NqTpnSQWo" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgq" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/18/ackman-tennis-jackass" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42074</id>
	<published>2025-07-18T23:59:11Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-18T23:59:55Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Real athletes get <em>30 For 30</em> documentaries; fake athletes get fake ones. Not sure which are more enjoyable.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Billionaire Jackass Bill Ackman Bought His Way Into Playing in a Legit Professional Tennis Tournament and, Shockingly, He Embarrassed Himself and Everyone Involved With Letting Him Play’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/18/ackman-tennis-jackass">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/07/curse_not_the_king_cbs_colbert_trump" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wgp" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42073</id>
	<published>2025-07-18T23:28:19Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-21T03:06:37Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Why CBS’s cancellation of “The Late Show With Stephen Colbert” stinks to high hell.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<h2>Why CBS’s Cancellation of “The Late Show With Stephen Colbert” Stinks to High Hell</h2>

<p>Even back in the now-comparatively-sane Trump 1.0 administration, it seemed palpably true to me that the best check against Trump’s authoritarian instincts wasn’t legal or Constitutional, but rather cultural. The culture of free speech, of being able to criticize — in no uncertain terms, with no held punches — anyone in authority is fundamental to the American mindset. It’s like the opening of David Foster Wallace’s “This Is Water” 2005 commencement address to Kenyon College:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Greetings parents and congratulations to Kenyon’s graduating class
of 2005. There are these two young fish swimming along and they
happen to meet an older fish swimming the other way, who nods at
them and says “Morning, boys. How’s the water?” And the two young
fish swim on for a bit, and then eventually one of them looks over
at the other and goes “What the hell is water?”</p>

<p>This is a standard requirement of US commencement speeches, the
deployment of didactic little parable-ish stories. The story thing
turns out to be one of the better, less bullshitty conventions of
the genre, but if you’re worried that I plan to present myself
here as the wise, older fish explaining what water is to you
younger fish, please don’t be. I am not the wise old fish. The
point of the fish story is merely that the most obvious, important
realities are often the ones that are hardest to see and talk
about. Stated as an English sentence, of course, this is just a
banal platitude, but the fact is that in the day to day trenches
of adult existence, banal platitudes can have a life or death
importance, or so I wish to suggest to you on this dry and lovely
morning.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In the way that fish take water for granted, Americans take <a href="https://xkcd.com/1357/">true freedom of speech</a> and freedom of the press for granted. It’s the culture we were born into, the air we breathe. And to my mind, the fiercest and most effective form of criticism — especially political — is mockery. Mark Twain, America’s first great (and perhaps still greatest) humorist, said, “Against the assault of laughter, nothing can stand.”</p>

<p>No one in Russian media mocks Vladimir Putin, lest they find themselves falling out one of <a href="https://www.newsweek.com/full-list-russians-fall-windows-putin-ukraine-war-1781790">Russia’s easily-fallen-out-of windows</a>. No one in Chinese media mocks Xi Jinping. Back in 2017 the CCP went as far as to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Censorship_of_Winnie-the-Pooh_in_China">censor images of Winnie the Pooh</a>, because Xi resembles Pooh so clearly, and people naturally find that amusing. Trump, clearly, has authoritarian instincts and desires, but US media — print, web, podcasts, YouTube, social, and TV — has been replete with unrelenting mockery aimed at him. There’s no better example of that than late night talk shows: Colbert on CBS, Jimmy Kimmel on ABC, Seth Meyers on NBC, Jon Stewart and his fellow hosts on <em>The Daily Show</em> at Comedy Central, John Oliver and Bill Maher on HBO. Vociferous, unrelenting critics of Trump, all of them. (And it works both ways: Greg Gutfield’s <em>Gutfield!</em> is <a href="https://www.tvinsider.com/1202434/late-night-ratings-2025-gutfeld-kimmel-colbert-fallon/">a ratings success at 10:00pm for Fox News</a>.)</p>

<p>That’s been one of the canaries I’ve been monitoring in the Trump 2.0 drift-into-authoritarianism coal mine. So long as Trump is getting skewered by comedians on major TV channels nightly, in some sense, we’re doing OK.</p>

<p>But while our Constitution and cultural fabric protect our media from <em>government</em> interference, there’s no such protection from <em>ownership</em> interference. Trump can’t dictate what a newspaper prints — proven again, just last night, by The Wall Street Journal, which added significant fuel to the Epstein fire that’s rupturing MAGAland with <a href="https://www.wsj.com/politics/trump-jeffrey-epstein-birthday-letter-we-have-certain-things-in-common-f918d796?mod=hp_lead_pos7">a scoop on a dirty birthday letter Trump wrote to his friend Epstein in 2003</a>, despite Trump trying to quash the story by <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2025/07/17/media/trump-rupert-murdoch-wsj-epstein-story-lawsuit-threat">directly calling Journal owner Rupert Murdoch</a>. Trump can’t dictate who hosts late-night TV shows or censor the jokes they tell, and we still seem far from a world where Jimmy Kimmel might mysteriously “fall” from a high window.</p>

<p>But the owners, they can do what they want. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2024/10/profiles_in_cowardice_bezos_lewis_washington_post">Jeff Bezos kiboshed The Washington Post’s already-written endorsement of Kamala Harris</a> — on the cusp of the election — and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2024/12/journalism_requires_owners_committed_to_the_cause">torched the paper’s previously sterling reputation</a> of independence and journalistic integrity. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2024/12/13/soon-shiong-la-times">Patrick Soon-Shiong has done similar</a> to the LA Times.</p>

<p>CBS is owned by Paramount, and Paramount is controlled by Shari Redstone. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Proposed_merger_of_Skydance_Media_and_Paramount_Global">Redstone has a deal to sell Paramount to Skydance</a>, a company controlled by David Ellison (son of Oracle gazillionaire Larry Ellison) for $8 billion, but the deal needs approval from the FCC, and the FCC answers to Trump. That’s why CBS settled a bullshit lawsuit by Trump against <em>60 Minutes</em> for $16 million. As former <em>60 Minutes</em> correspondent <a href="https://www.tvinsider.com/1201084/trump-cbs-news-60-minutes-steve-kroft-jon-stewart-daily-show/">Steve Kroft told Jon Stewart</a> (righteously, on Paramount-owned Comedy Central) regarding the “settlement”: “They never said, ‘We screwed up.’ They just paid the money. It was a shakedown, that’s what I call it. Some people call it extortion, that’s a legal term.”</p>

<p><a href="https://nypost.com/2025/07/02/media/how-secret-side-deal-helped-seal-paramounts-16m-settlement-with-trump/">The New York Post reported two weeks ago</a> that the official settlement is only half the deal, however:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Shari Redstone’s Paramount received an unusual assist to settle
its controversial lawsuit with President Trump, which should now
clear the way for its long-awaited sale to independent studio
Skydance, On The Money has learned.</p>

<p>Skydance boss David Ellison, the son of Trump friend and
billionaire Oracle co-founder Larry Ellison, stepped up and agreed
that once he takes control of the Tiffany Network, currently part
of Redstone’s flailing media empire, it will run between $15
million and $20 million of public service ads to promote causes
supported by the president, a source with knowledge of the
negotiations said.</p>

<p>“There is an anticipation of a mid-eight-figure sum that will be
allocated by the network to PSA advertisements and other broadcast
transmissions that support conservative causes supported by
President Trump,” the source said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It made no sense journalistically or financially for CBS to settle Trump’s lawsuit. <em>60 Minutes</em> clearly did nothing ethically wrong, let alone illegal, with its editing of Kamala Harris’s interview.<sup id="fnr1-2025-07-18"><a href="#fn1-2025-07-18">1</a></sup> It only makes sense as a de facto payoff to Trump to help secure approval of Skydance’s acquisition of Paramount. Likewise with CBS’s decision not just to part ways with Colbert as host, but to cease production of <em>The Late Show</em> entirely. It makes no TV sense. <em>The Late Show</em> isn’t just doing OK in the ratings, it’s the top show in the 11:30 timeslot. Here’s Jed Rosenzweig, <a href="https://latenighter.com/news/ratings/late-night-tv-ratings-q2-2025/">writing for LateNighter just four days ago</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>As the second quarter of 2025 wrapped, late-night’s pecking order
held mostly steady — with The Late Show with Stephen Colbert
topping the 11:35 PM hour in total viewers, and Late Night with
Seth Meyers leading at 12:37 AM across both key ratings metrics.</p>

<p>CBS’s <em>Late Show</em> was the only show among the nine tracked by
LateNighter to draw more total viewers in Q2 than it had in the
first quarter of 2025 — although just barely, with the show
growing its audience by 1% quarter over quarter. All told, the
Stephen Colbert-hosted show averaged 2.42 million viewers across
41 first-run episodes, comfortably outpacing ABC’s <em>Jimmy Kimmel
Live</em> (1.77 million) and NBC’s <em>The Tonight Show Starring Jimmy
Fallon</em> (1.19 million). In the advertiser-coveted 18–49 demo,
however, Kimmel surged ahead with 220,000 viewers — his strongest
performance in a year — edging out Colbert (219,000) and leaving
Fallon (at 157,000) in a distant third.</p>

<p>At 12:37 AM, <em>Late Night With Seth Meyers</em> continued its quiet
reign. The NBC mainstay averaged 900,000 total viewers and
111,000 in the demo across 35 episodes — easily topping both
metrics in the late-late slot. ABC’s <em>Nightline</em> held second
place with 810,000 total viewers and 108,000 in the demo, putting
it ahead of CBS’s <em>After Midnight</em>, which ended its two-year run
in early June with an average of 591,000 total viewers and 89,000
in the 18–49 demo.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So Colbert’s <em>Late Show</em> is the highest-rated overall, and effectively tied with Kimmel in the advertiser-coveted 18–49 demo.<sup id="fnr2-2025-07-18"><a href="#fn2-2025-07-18">2</a></sup> Like all of traditional TV, late night viewership — and thus revenue — isn’t what it used to be. (For context, through the end of the 1990s and into the 2000s, Letterman and Leno <a href="https://www.deseret.com/2000/1/23/19487374/late-show-scores-ratings-victory-vs-leno/">each drew around 4–6 million viewers per night</a>. Johnny Carson averaged over 10 million viewers per night in the 1970s and 80s.) CBS declaring in its announcement that “This is purely a financial decision against a challenging backdrop in late night” is obvious bullshit — and, <a href="https://politicalwire.com/2025/07/18/trump-gets-a-win-in-the-culture-wars/">in light of its timing</a>, extra stinky bullshit at that. Surely the top-rated show in late night isn’t just at least profitable, but almost certainly more profitable than whatever CBS might replace it with in that time slot. (CBS sources suddenly claim <em>The Late Show</em> <a href="https://puck.news/was-colberts-cancellation-really-economic-for-cbs/">lost $40 million last year</a>; <a href="https://latenighter.com/features/cbs-cites-costs-in-colbert-cancellation-the-timing-tells-a-different-story/">Bill Carter isn’t buying that</a> and neither should you.)</p>

<p>The TV industry has always been obsessed with ratings and obsessed with advertising revenue. I can’t recall the top-rated show in any category being cancelled. Again, it makes no TV sense. It doesn’t pass the sniff test. Back in December, regarding the Bezos-driven upheaval at The Washington Post, I wrote a piece titled “<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2024/12/journalism_requires_owners_committed_to_the_cause">Journalism Requires Owners Committed to the Cause</a>”, which title sort of says it all. The only proper way to run a serious newspaper is for the work and reputation of the newspaper itself to be the topmost priority of everyone in leadership, right up to the owner. That’s just clearly not true for Bezos. And part of it too is that the entire business of The Washington Post just doesn’t matter to Bezos. Jeff Bezos has a net worth of around $230 <em>billion</em>. He bought the Post from its longtime owners, the Graham family (who <em>were</em> <a href="https://www.nyhistory.org/blogs/lets-go-lets-publish-katharine-graham-and-the-pentagon-papers">owners committed to the cause</a>) in 2013 for just $250 <em>million</em>. Financially, the entire Washington Post Company represents like one-thousandth of Bezos’s wealth. Trashing the paper’s reputation and the trust of its readers meant less to him than cozying up to Trump for potential trade policy favors for Amazon and <a href="https://www.wsj.com/business/jeff-bezos-trump-blue-origin-9f5ac75b?st=jo2tkC">rocketry deals for Blue Origin</a>.</p>

<p>It’s exactly the same for David Ellison. His father, Larry Ellison, is even wealthier than Bezos, with <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/dereksaul/2025/06/13/larry-ellison-40-billion-richer---surpassing-bezos-and-zuckerberg---as-oracle-stock-mounts-big-rally/">Forbes estimating his worth above $250 billion</a> after recent Oracle stock price gains. In normal times, with a normal US president (that is to say, not crooked), and a normal incoming buyer of a major television network (that is to say, concerned with ratings and ad revenue) it would be insane for the network to cancel the top-rated late night show just before the deal is finalized. But David Ellison doesn’t give a shit how much money CBS makes at 11:30 and doesn’t care about the three-decade legacy of The Late Show or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ed_Sullivan_Theater">the storied history</a> of the theater in which it’s produced each night. Cancelling this particular hit show isn’t poison to the deal for Skydance to buy Paramount — it’s a sweetener. I missed this at the time, but Oliver Darcy, media reporter extraordinaire, called it at Status (paywalled, alas) <a href="https://www.status.news/p/skydance-colbert-stewart-ellison">just over a week ago</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Jon Stewart opened Monday’s episode of <em>The Daily Show</em> not
mincing words, calling Paramount’s settlement with Donald Trump
“shameful.” Just as he was digging in, a fake Arby’s ad suddenly
appeared on screen, as if to cut him off mid-rant for criticizing
Comedy Central’s parent company. “Did they? Son of a bitch!”
Stewart exclaimed, playing along with the bit — yet nodding to a
deeper fear that his commentary might soon be silenced amid all
the corporate upheaval.</p>

<p>Later in the episode, Stewart continued to needle Paramount,
sitting down with former <em>60 Minutes</em> correspondent Steve Kroft
for a candid and unsparing conversation. Kroft described the
settlement in clear terms: “It was a shakedown.” Inside “The Daily
Show,” I’m told staffers have taken pride that Stewart showed once
again he is willing to stand up to powerful interests, even if it
potentially risks his future employment. And while they may not
yet know it, inside certain power circles, there is an open
question: How much longer will Stewart have this platform?</p>

<p>Indeed, the reality is that the ground under not only Stewart, but
also Stephen Colbert, is shifting fast. Skydance, led by Larry and
David Ellison, now believes its merger with Paramount will close
in the next several weeks, I’m told. Much of the attention has
focused on how the Ellisons will reshape <em>60 Minutes</em> and CBS
News. We first reported that David Ellison met with Bari Weiss
about a possible role at CBS News, and it is clear the Ellisons
want to rid the network of what they see as a liberal taint. But
little has been said about the futures of Colbert and Stewart, who
have been two of Trump’s most consistent comedic antagonists,
under the new corporate leadership. [...]</p>

<p>As one media insider put it to me this week, “What better gift
could [the Ellisons] give Trump than to get rid of Colbert and
Stewart?”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The first shoe dropped at CBS last night. TV-wise, it’d be crazy for Paramount to drop Jon Stewart too. But dropping Colbert is even crazier, and they already did that. It’s not tyranny or the threat of state violence that is taking <em>The Late Show With Stephen Colbert</em> off the air, but rather oligarchy and unchecked cronyism and corruption. The breathtaking abdication we’re seeing at CBS — first news with <em>60 Minutes</em>, now commentary and humor with <em>The Late Show</em> — signals a decidedly American descent into <a href="https://www.biblegateway.com/verse/en/Ecclesiastes%2010%3A20">curse-not-the-king</a> mass media acquiescence to Trump’s authoritarian hostility to criticism and dissent.</p>

<h2>Postscript</h2>

<p><a href="https://truthsocial.com/@realDonaldTrump/posts/114874422468516376">Here’s Trump on his blog this morning</a>, heralding the news with his usual grace, equanimity, and factual accuracy:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I absolutely love that Colbert’ [<em>sic</em>] got fired. His talent was even
less than his ratings. I hear Jimmy Kimmel is next. Has even less
talent than Colbert! Greg Gutfeld is better than all of them
combined, including the Moron on NBC who ruined the once great
Tonight Show.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I will admit that it’s kind of funny that he didn’t even deign to address Fallon by name, especially since Fallon is the one who <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kIGcosb22_Y">did the most</a> to normalize Trump’s aberrant candidacy in 2016.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>

<li id="fn1-2025-07-18">
<p>If any interview with a 2024 presidential candidate was edited deceptively to help the candidate in question, it was <a href="https://www.yahoo.com/news/fox-news-trump-interview-resurfaces-164913528.html">this Fox News interview with Trump</a>, which resurfaced this month amidst the Jeffrey Epstein imbroglio. Fox grossly truncated a glaringly evasive answer from Trump regarding whether, if re-elected, he would release all DOJ files related to Epstein.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2025-07-18"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>

<li id="fn2-2025-07-18">
<p>Which hurts slightly to write about, insofar as I’ve aged out of the demo personally. Now I’m a non-coveted TV watcher — but one who’s skipped all the commercials on late night shows for 25 years anyway.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr2-2025-07-18"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
</li>

</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Curse Not the King</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Apple Sues Jon Prosser Over iOS 26 Leaks</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macrumors.com/2025/07/17/apple-sues-jon-prosser-ios-26-leaks/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgo" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/18/apple-sues-prosser" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42072</id>
	<published>2025-07-18T20:36:52Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-18T21:34:15Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Eric Slivka, reporting last night for MacRumors:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>While the Camera app redesign didn’t exactly match what Apple
unveiled for iOS 26, the general idea was correct and much of
what else Prosser showed was pretty close to spot on, and Apple
clearly took notice as the company filed a lawsuit today (<a href="https://www.scribd.com/document/889709146/Apple-v-Ramacciotti-and-Prosser">Scribd
link</a>) against Prosser and Michael Ramacciotti for
misappropriation of trade secrets.</p>

<p>Apple’s complaint outlines what it claims is the series of events
that led to the leaks, which centered around a development iPhone
in the possession of Ramacciotti’s friend and Apple employee Ethan
Lipnik. According to Apple, Prosser and Ramacciotti plotted to
access Lipnik’s phone, acquiring his passcode and then using
location-tracking to determine when he “would be gone for an
extended period.” Prosser reportedly offered financial
compensation to Ramacciotti in return for assisting with accessing
the development iPhone.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Lipnik, the Apple employee, was fired, but isn’t named in the lawsuit because seemingly all he did was improperly secure his device running an early build of iOS 26. That’s against company policy, but not against the law.</p>

<p>Prosser, on X, <a href="https://x.com/jon_prosser/status/1946056858474525097">disputes the description of his involvement in Apple’s lawsuit</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>For the record: This is not how the situation played out on my
end. Luckily have receipts for that.</p>

<p>I did not “plot” to access anyone’s phone. I did not have any
passwords. I was unaware of how the information was obtained.</p>

<p>Looking forward to speaking with Apple on this.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Prosser also shared <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/07/prosser-signal-screenshot.jpeg">one screenshot</a> of his Signal message correspondence with Ramacciotti.</p>

<p>(MacRumors’s copy of Apple’s lawsuit is <a href="https://www.scribd.com/document/889709146/Apple-v-Ramacciotti-and-Prosser">hosted at Scribd</a>, which is free to read in a browser, but requires a paid account to download the original PDF. I’m <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/07/889709146-Apple-v-Ramacciotti-and-Prosser.pdf">hosting a copy of the PDF here</a>.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Sues Jon Prosser Over iOS 26 Leaks’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/18/apple-sues-prosser">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Network Pinheads at CBS Are Ending ‘The Late Show’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.instagram.com/reel/DMOhWKsxT_G/" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgn" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/17/cbs-pinheads-colbert-ending" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42071</id>
	<published>2025-07-18T00:39:15Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-21T00:38:33Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The above links to an Instagram reel with Colbert breaking the news at the start of his show airing tonight. Here’s <a href="https://twitter.com/latenightercom/status/1945993251938549803">the same clip on X</a>, if you prefer. He, apparently, was as surprised as anyone.</p>

<p><a href="https://latenighter.com/news/cbs-cancels-the-late-show-with-stephen-colbert-show-to-end-in-may-2026/">Here’s Jed Rosenzweig’s story at (the excellent) LateNighter</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“<em>The Late Show with Stephen Colbert</em> will end its historic run in
May 2026 at the end of the broadcast season,” the network said in
a statement. “We consider Stephen Colbert irreplaceable and will
retire <em>The Late Show</em> franchise at that time. We are proud that
Stephen called CBS home. He and the broadcast will be remembered
in the pantheon of greats that graced late night television.”</p>

<p>The statement was issued jointly by George Cheeks (Co-CEO of
Paramount Global and President and CEO of CBS), Amy Reisenbach
(President of CBS Entertainment), and David Stapf (President of
CBS Studios).</p>

<p>CBS emphasized that the decision was not related to performance or
content: “This is purely a financial decision against a
challenging backdrop in late night. It is not related in any way
to the show’s performance, content or other matters happening at
Paramount.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This stinks to high hell. Colbert has the best ratings in late night TV.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Network Pinheads at CBS Are Ending ‘The Late Show’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/17/cbs-pinheads-colbert-ending">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Rare Earth Magnet Maker MP Materials Is Having a Big Week</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/07/10/pentagon-to-become-largest-shareholder-in-rare-earth-magnet-maker-mp-materials.html" />
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/wgm" />
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/16/mp-materials-big-week" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025:/linked//6.42070</id>
	<published>2025-07-16T19:14:27Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-16T19:30:42Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Spencer Kimball, reporting for CNBC one week ago:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The Defense Department will become the largest shareholder in rare
earth miner MP Materials after <a href="https://investors.mpmaterials.com/investor-news/news-details/2025/MP-Materials-Announces-Transformational-Public-Private-Partnership-with-the-Department-of-Defense-to-Accelerate-U-S--Rare-Earth-Magnet-Independence/default.aspx">agreeing to buy $400 million of
its preferred stock</a>, the company said Thursday.</p>

<p>MP Materials owns the only operational rare earth mine in the U.S.
at Mountain Pass, California, about 60 miles outside Las Vegas.
Proceeds from the Pentagon investment will be used to expand MP’s
rare earths processing capacity and magnet production, the company
said. Shares of MP Materials soared about 50% to close at $45.23.
Its market capitalization grew to $7.4 billion, an increase of
about $2.5 billion from the previous trading session. [...]</p>

<p>MP Materials CEO James Litinsky described the Pentagon investment
as a public-private partnership that will speed the buildout of an
end-to-end rare earth magnet supply chain in the U.S.</p>

<p>“I want to be very clear, this is not a nationalization,” Litinsky
told CNBC’s “Squawk on the Street” on Thursday. “We remain a
thriving public company. We now have a great new partner in our
economically largest shareholder, DoD, but we still control our
company. We control our destiny. We’re shareholder driven.” U.S.
miners are facing a unique threat from “Chinese mercantilism,”
Litinsky said. The Pentagon investment in MP could serve as a
model for similar deals with other U.S. companies, the CEO said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This news caught my eye when Taegan Goddard <a href="https://politicalwire.com/2025/07/15/pentagon-buys-into-rare-earth-miner/">linked to it from Political Wire</a> yesterday (quipping, “I’m old enough to remember when this was called ‘socialism’”), because yesterday MP Materials landed a $500 million deal from Apple. <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2025/07/apple-expands-us-supply-chain-with-500-million-usd-commitment/">Apple Newsroom</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Today Apple announced a new commitment of $500 million with MP
Materials, the only fully integrated rare earth producer in the
United States. With this multiyear deal, Apple is committed to
buying American-made rare earth magnets developed at MP Materials’
flagship Independence facility in Fort Worth, Texas. The two
companies will also work together to establish a cutting-edge rare
earth recycling line in Mountain Pass, California, and develop
novel magnet materials and innovative processing technologies to
enhance magnet performance. The commitment is part of Apple’s
pledge to spend more than $500 billion in the U.S. over the next
four years, and builds on the company’s long history of investment
in American innovation, advanced manufacturing, and
next-generation recycling technologies. [...]</p>

<p>When complete, the new recycling facility in Mountain Pass,
California will enable MP Materials to take in recycled rare earth
feedstock — including material from used electronics and
post-industrial scrap — and reprocess it for use in Apple
products. For nearly five years, Apple and MP Materials have been
piloting advanced recycling technology that enables recycled rare
earth magnets to be processed into material that meets Apple’s
exacting standards for performance and design. The companies will
continue to innovate together to improve magnet production, as
well as end-of-life recovery.</p>

<p>Apple pioneered the use of recycled rare earth elements in
consumer electronics, first introducing them in the Taptic Engine
of iPhone 11 in 2019. Today, nearly all magnets across Apple
devices are made with 100 percent recycled rare earth elements.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The timing of these two announcements could be purely coincidental, but I can’t help but wonder if both moves were fueled by concerns about China cornering the market on rare earth magnets. Conversely, I wonder if this deal (and promotion of it) from Apple is aimed just to placate the Trump administration. A $500 million commitment is surely a big deal for MP Materials. It’s not that big a deal for Apple. What makes it interesting is that it’s with an American company.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Rare Earth Magnet Maker MP Materials Is Having a Big Week’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/07/16/mp-materials-big-week">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/07/make_me_rich_on_amazon_prime_day" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wg4" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42052</id>
	<published>2025-07-09T19:33:52Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-10T05:14:00Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">You can support Daring Fireball and save yourself a veritable bundle through some Prime Day discounts.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>It’s Amazon’s annual Prime Day sale, and if you <a href="https://www.amazon.com/primeday/?tag=df-amzn-20">click through this link</a>, or any of the ones below, you can show your support for Daring Fireball by throwing the referral revenue from any purchases you make my way. You don’t pay a penny more but I get a few percentage points of your purchases. Prime Day discounts are no joke either — we need an outdoor TV for our sun-drenched deck, and I’d been putting off purchasing one out of indecision, but I pulled the trigger and <a href="https://amzn.to/40wWYZp">saved $500</a> with a Prime Day discount last night. (Sometimes my procrastination pays off.)</p>

<p>Just about everything Amazon sells from Apple is being offered at significant discounts. Just a handful of popular ones:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Apple-11-inch-Intelligence-Display-All-Day/dp/B0DZ76BN5D/?tag=df-amzn-20">11-inch M3 iPad Air for $480</a> (regularly $600).</li>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/4lemIlr">iPad Mini (A17 Pro) for $380</a> (regularly $500).</li>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/44lQIG5">AirPods 4 With Active Noise Cancellation for $120</a> (regularly $180) and the ones without ANC <a href="https://amzn.to/46vrJS4">are just $90</a>. (You should definitely get the ones with ANC, though — I never did write a proper review, but I tested a pair with ANC for <em>months</em> and they’re quite amazing given their price and non-sealed ear fit.)</li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Apple-Cancellation-Transparency-Personalized-High-Fidelity/dp/B0D1XD1ZV3/?tag=df-amzn-20">AirPods Pro 2 are just $150</a> (regularly $250).</li>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/3Gt8EFE">13-inch M4 MacBook Airs starting at just $850</a> (regularly $1,000) and the sweet configuration <a href="https://amzn.to/3TrhB5c">with 24 GB RAM and 512 GB storage for $1,250</a> (regularly $1,400). It seems like you save $150 on any MacBook Amazon sells.</li>
</ul>

<p>Even small items like Apple’s <a href="https://amzn.to/4lPsuKh">woven USB-C cables</a> and wired EarPods (<a href="https://amzn.to/4kw3lD8">USB-C</a> or <a href="https://amzn.to/3U0PvxI">old-school 3.5mm</a>) are a few bucks off. (I keep a pair of the old 3.5mm EarPods in my laptop bag for use with my <a href="https://play.date/">Playdate</a>, along with Apple’s <a href="https://amzn.to/4f00O3f">$9 USB-C headphone jack adapter</a> (one of the few products I saw that’s not discounted for Prime day, but, come on, it’s $9) in case I ever find myself needing wired buds.)</p>

<p>It’s called Prime Day for a reason: you need to be <a href="https://www.amazon.com/amazonprime/?tag=df-amzn-20">a Prime subscriber</a> to get these deals. We’ve been members since forever, and the $140/year fee pays for itself in shipping fees alone. But for some high-priced items like MacBooks and iPads, you can make up the entire annual fee in one purchase today.</p>

<p>I don’t post a ton of affiliate links here on DF, but when I do, they sometimes work out to a nice windfall. As the media industry moves more and more toward subscriptions and memberships — and, alas, paywalled content — I’m still freely publishing the entirety of my work other than <a href="https://dithering.fm/">Dithering</a>. I really do get asked by readers on a regular basis how they can support Daring Fireball directly. I’ll do a new round of t-shirts and maybe some other merch soon. That’s one way. I might someday offer a membership tier with bonus content (<a href="https://daringfireball.net/2004/06/something_daring">again</a>), but that day is not today. But one way you can support DF directly today is by buying anything — anything at all — from Amazon after clicking through any of the above links.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Save Yourself Some Dough on Apple Kit and Make Me Rich on Amazon Prime Day</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/07/jeff_williams_is_retiring_as_coo" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wfz" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42047</id>
	<published>2025-07-08T23:26:53Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-10T19:35:30Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Post-Williams, Apple’s operations will clearly remain under excellent, experienced leadership under Sabih Khan. But the company will be left with its design teams reporting directly to Cook, leaving it less clear whose taste, [ultimately], is steering the work of the company into the future.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2025/07/apple-announces-chief-operating-officer-transition/">Apple Newsroom, this afternoon</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple today announced Jeff Williams will transition his role as
chief operating officer later this month to Sabih Khan, Apple’s
senior vice president of Operations as part of a long-planned
succession. Williams will continue reporting to Apple CEO Tim Cook
and overseeing Apple’s world class design team and Apple Watch
alongside the company’s Heath initiatives. Apple’s design team
will then transition to reporting directly to Cook after Williams
retires late in the year.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Apple’s executive ranks have been so remarkably stable for so long that any change feels surprising. But Williams is 62 years old and has been at Apple for 27 years. Tim Cook is 64, and Khan <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sabih_Khan">is 58</a>. The whole thing seems amicable and orderly, and thus completely in line with everything we know about Williams’s and Cook’s seemingly similar personalities. After a long and successful career, Apple’s COO is retiring and his longtime lieutenant is being promoted to replace him this month. Apple’s operations aren’t just world-class, they’re almost certainly world-best. Even their leadership transitions are operationally smooth. <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2019/06/apple-names-sabih-khan-senior-vice-president-of-operations/">Khan was promoted in 2019</a> to the title of senior vice president of operations. Williams was promoted from that title (SVP of operations) to COO in 2015, four years after Cook took over as CEO from Steve Jobs.</p>

<p>But that’s the operations part. </p>

<p>What’s intriguing about the announcement is the design part — a functional area where, especially on the software side, Apple’s current stature is subject to much debate. While Williams is staying on until “late in the year” to continue his other responsibilities — Watch, Health, and serving as the senior executive Apple’s design teams report to — Khan isn’t taking over those roles when Williams leaves. And so by the end of the year, Apple’s design teams will go from reporting to Williams to reporting directly to Tim Cook. </p>

<p>I’ve long found it curious, if not downright dubious, that Apple’s design leaders have reported to Williams ever since it was announced in 2019 (<a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2019/06/jony-ive-to-form-independent-design-company-with-apple-as-client/">the very same day</a> that <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2019/06/apple-names-sabih-khan-senior-vice-president-of-operations/">Khan was promoted to SVP</a> of operations) that Jony Ive would be stepping down as chief design officer and leaving Apple to found the (as-yet-unnamed) design firm LoveFrom. Williams had no background in design at all. Apple’s design teams reporting to an operations executive makes no more sense than it would for Apple’s operations teams to report to, say, Alan Dye. Well, maybe it made a little more sense than that — having design report to Williams sort of felt like a way to give Williams experience across the breadth of the company in the case that he ever needed to step in to replace Cook as CEO, either temporarily or permanently, as Cook was asked to for Jobs. </p>

<p>But when that was announced in 2019, I expected it to be temporary, while Apple took its time to properly identify a new senior design leader. Someone with, you know, design leadership experience, and strong opinions about and deep knowledge of the craft of design. That was six years ago, and Apple has seemingly made not one move toward naming a new chief design officer or (the more likely title) SVP of design. It seems like time for that now.</p>

<p>I get the impression — from multiple sources — that <em>overseeing</em>, not <em>leading</em>, is in fact exactly the right word for Williams’s role regarding design since 2019. Williams oversaw design the same way Tim Cook, ultimately, oversees everything the company does. It was in no way a token role. Williams was <em>there</em>. He asked insightful questions about product designs and experiences. But he didn’t push back or offer opinions. There’s much to like about Liquid Glass, for example, but there’s also a lot of <a href="https://lmnt.me/blog/ive-got-better-things-to-do-than-this-and-yet.html">shitty UI functionality</a> and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2025/06/24/sorry-macos-tahoe-b2-finder-icon">just plain bad</a> design that makes you wonder how numerous aspects even escaped the drawing board, let alone made their way into the WWDC keynote and various OS 26 betas. Looking back at the last six years of Apple design — hardware, software, packaging, architecture — I detect not one fingerprint of style or taste that belongs to Jeff Williams. Given that Williams is not a designer, that’s not a surprise. But it’s a problem for the company if its products don’t ultimately have a distinctive <em>voice</em>.</p>

<p>I’m of the mind that, in hindsight, it was a mistake for Jony Ive to bring HI (software human interface design) under the same roof as ID (hardware industrial design). That arrangement made sense for Ive’s unique role in the company, and the unique period in the wake of Steve Jobs’s too-young demise. But it might have ultimately made Ive more difficult to replace than Steve Jobs. Williams’s combination of authority, mild-mannered-ness, and equanimity might have made him uniquely suited to either finding another Ive-like design leader whom all sides could have agreed to (even if begrudgingly), or, perhaps, to the task of unwinding the intermingling of HI and ID that occurred during the Jony-as-CDO era. But neither of those things happened.</p>

<p>Post-Williams, Apple’s operations will clearly remain under excellent, experienced leadership under Sabih Khan. But the company will be left with its design teams reporting directly to Cook — who is three years older than Williams. Six years after Jony Ive’s departure, today’s announcements leave it less clear than ever whose taste, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xk3UcgbbmxQ">ultimately</a>, is steering the work of the company into the future. Perhaps, I hope, Williams is staying until the end of the year to help answer that question.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Jeff Williams, 62, Is Retiring as Apple’s COO</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2025/07/full-screen_ad_for_f1_the_movie_in_apples_tv_app_linked_directly_to_the_web" />
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/wfv" />
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2025://1.42043</id>
	<published>2025-07-07T18:26:38Z</published>
	<updated>2025-07-08T00:34:32Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">I can see the argument that Apple’s answer is “Yes, it’s potentially confusing for many users”. But I can’t see the argument that the answer is “Yes, it’s potentially confusing for many users, but only if they’re trying to buy in-app content or subscriptions, but not confusing at all if they’re trying to buy, say, movie tickets.”</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://www.threads.com/@mgsiegler/post/DLdXyO6otsI">MG Siegler, on Threads last week</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We’re already beyond ridiculous with the full-on ad assault from
Apple as everyone is well aware by now. But the wild thing here — in this <em>full screen</em> pop-up in the Apple TV app — is that it’s
not in-app but links out to the web to pay?!</p>
</blockquote>

<p>At least here in the US, if you just opened the TV app on iOS 18 last week, you were presented with <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/06/f1-tv-app-tickets-via-web.jpeg">this full-screen ad</a> (replete with all those dumb ®’s, despite Apple’s <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2025/06/f1-appstore-via-fandango.jpeg">ads for the same thing in the App Store</a> omitting them).</p>

<p>There were two buttons to choose from: “Not Now” and “Buy Tickets ↗︎”. If you tapped the “Buy Tickets ↗︎” button, boom, you just jumped to <a href="https://www.f1themovie.com/">the F1 The Movie website</a> in your default browser. <a href="https://www.threads.com/@kylealden/post/DLdhE1JhpeL">Kyle Alden, on Threads</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>That’s weird, Apple’s new full screen F1 ad in the TV app links
out to the browser to compete the transaction, but for some reason
doesn’t include any full screen interstitials warning of the big
scary web, nor a confirmation dialog that it would open in the
browser? Must be an oversight.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The hypocrisy isn’t that Apple didn’t show a full-screen scare sheet for this link-out to the web. It’s that they require other developers, who are doing it to sell digital content, to show a scare sheet/confirmation.</p>

<p>One of the subtle differences with this particular promotion is that buying movie tickets is not “digital content” — even if they’re just passes in Apple Wallet or saved QR codes in an app like Fandango. You’re purchasing a real-world experience, so it’s not eligible for Apple’s In-App Purchase (IAP) system. This is why when you buy theater tickets in the Fandango app, Fandango charges your credit or debit card directly. Same when you pay for rides in Uber or Lyft. It’s really subtle for something like a movie. Pay for a movie to watch on your TV at home? That’s a digital purchase. Pay for a movie to watch in a theater? <em>Not</em> a digital purchase.</p>

<p>I understand the distinction between digital content (that’s consumed on your Apple device) and real-world goods and experiences (even if you pay for them in apps on your Apple device). But how many iPhone users understand this distinction? Like, if you polled 1,000 U.S. iPhone users who (a) purchase in-game content in games like Candy Crush, and (b) hail rides in Uber or Lyft, what percentage of those iPhone users do you think could give a coherent answer as to why their in-game purchases <em>must</em> use Apple’s IAP system, and why Uber not only <em>doesn’t</em> use IAP to charge for rides, but is not <em>allowed</em> to use IAP for that? I’d bet fewer than 1 percent. (I’d also bet that fewer than 1 percent <em>care</em>, which is why they don’t know.)</p>

<p>Is it inherently confusing to have a button in an app that jumps you out of the app to your default web browser (probably Safari, especially for people who might be confused) to complete a transaction, without a scare sheet or even a confirmation alert? I can see the argument that Apple’s answer is “Yes, it’s potentially confusing for many users”. But I can’t see the argument that the answer is “Yes, it’s potentially confusing for many users, but only if they’re trying to buy in-app content or subscriptions, but not confusing at all if they’re trying to buy, say, movie tickets.”</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Full-Screen Ad for ‘F1 The Movie’ in Apple’s TV App Linked Directly to the Web, and Nothing Bad Seemed to Happen</title></entry></feed><!-- THE END -->
