<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Maggie Appleton</title><description>Essays on programming, design, and anthropology</description><link>https://maggieappleton.com/</link><language>en-us</language><item><title>A Treatise on AI Chatbots Undermining the Enlightenment</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/ai-enlightenment/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/ai-enlightenment/</guid><description>On chatbot sycophancy, passivity, and the case for more intellectually challenging companions</description><pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Treatise on AI Chatbots Undermining the Enlightenment</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/ai-enlightenment/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/ai-enlightenment/</guid><description>On chatbot sycophancy, passivity, and the case for more intellectually challenging companions</description><pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Vibe Code is Legacy Code</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/2025-08-vibe-legacy-code/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/2025-08-vibe-legacy-code/</guid><description>Vibe code is legacy code by Steve Krouse</description><pubDate>Sat, 02 Aug 2025 11:31:48 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.val.town/vibe-code&quot;&gt;Vibe code is legacy code&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lovely little write-up by my friend &lt;a href=&quot;https://stevekrouse.com/&quot;&gt;Steve Krouse&lt;/a&gt; on how vibe code and legacy code are roughly the same thing; “code that nobody understands.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I particularly like this graph which illustrates the relationship between vibe code and understanding:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;img src=&quot;/images/smidgeons/vibe-code.png&quot; alt=&quot;A line chart with vibe on the Y axis and understanding on the X axis with a downwards diagonal line&quot; /&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This type of discussion feels helpful in a moment where the term “vibe coding” is being tossed around in vague and unhelpful ways. It rings true to me that it&apos;s a continuous spectrum, and no professional developers are sitting at the all-vibes end of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As many have &lt;a href=&quot;https://simonwillison.net/2025/Mar/19/vibe-coding/&quot;&gt;pointed out&lt;/a&gt;, not all code written with AI assistance is vibe code. Per the &lt;a href=&quot;https://x.com/karpathy/status/1886192184808149383&quot;&gt;original definition&lt;/a&gt;, it&apos;s code written in contexts where you “forget that the code even exists.” Or as the fairly fleshed-out &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vibe_coding&quot;&gt;Wikipedia article&lt;/a&gt; puts it: ”A key part of the definition of vibe coding is that the user accepts code without full understanding.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like many developers, I&apos;m constantly grappling with how much understanding I&apos;m willing to hand over to Cursor or Claude Code. I sincerely try to keep it minimal, or at least have them walk me through the functionality line-by-line if I feel I&apos;m out of my depth. But it&apos;s always easier and faster to YOLO it – an impulse I have to actively keep in check.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our AI minions are also exceptional tools for learning when you move too far towards the high-vibes-low-understanding end of the spectrum. I particularly like getting Claude to write me targeted exercises to practice new concepts when I get lost in generated functions or fail to implement something correctly sans-AI. Even though doubling-down up on engineering skills sometimes feels like learning to operate a textile loom in 1820.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded></item><item><title>May 2025</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/now-2025-05/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/now-2025-05/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;In a wonderfully dramatic change to my life, I became a mother two months ago. My son was born at the end of March via an unplanned but otherwise uncomplicated c-section. Parenthood has been predictably overwhelming, exhausting, and existentially glorious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My days are now spent holding a sleeping newborn on my chest, timing wake windows, picking up the dropped pacifier for the 19th time, trying to eat with 0.5 hands free, and watching an eternal stream of Gilmore Girls episodes on a precariously balanced iPhone while feeding/burping/soothing/rocking/patting this tiny human. It swings between hard physical labour with high cortisol levels, to extremely chill, serene, and joyful a dozen times throughout the day and night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had doubts about becoming a mother when I was younger. Mostly related to systemic gender inequality, believing I would need to sacrifice my whole career for it, and thinking myself incapable of bearing the responsibility (which, to be fair, I was before age ~28). I spent a solid year in angst and turmoil trying to figure it out. All the parents around me only shared details of how stressful, sleep-deprived, expensive, and burdensome their new lives were. Perhaps because it felt too trite or vulnerable to put into words the love, joy, and purpose that comes with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being on the other side, I now realise there was no calculation or algorithm or pro/con list or financial spreadsheet that could have helped me understand what it would feel like. Nothing that would do justice to the emotional weight of holding your sleeping baby that you made with your own body. Of watching them grin back at you with uncomplicated joy. Of realising you&apos;ll get to watch them grow into a full person; one that is – at least genetically – half you and half the person you love most in the world. Of watching them trip out as they realise they have hands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can now say with certainty I am evolutionarily wired for this. Perhaps not everyone is. But everything in me is designed to feel existential delight at each little fart, squeak, grunt, and sneeze that comes out of this child. Delight that is unrivalled by any successful day at work, fully shipped feature, long cathartic run, or Sunday morning buttery croissant – the banal highlights of my past life. When I think back to my pre-baby self, trying to calculate herself into a clear decision, I wish I could let her feel for one minute what it&apos;s like to hold him. And tell her I can&apos;t believe I ever considered depriving myself of this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other news, I&apos;ve read no books (other than &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.penguin.co.uk/books/391245/your-baby-week-by-week-by-dr-caroline-fertleman/9780091910556&quot;&gt;Your Baby Week by Week&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.co.uk/books/edition/Secrets_Of_The_Baby_Whisperer/ZCWIlXocNowC?hl=en&amp;amp;gbpv=0&quot;&gt;Secrets Of The Baby Whisperer&lt;/a&gt;), had few higher-order thoughts, and binge watched all of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/iplayer/episodes/p05j1jkp/motherland&quot;&gt;Motherland&lt;/a&gt;. As this child learns to sleep in more predictable ways, I&apos;m looking forward to being less of a zombie and engaging with the world again.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded></item><item><title>Statistically, When Will My Baby Be Born?</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/birth-probability/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/birth-probability/</guid><description>A tiny tool to calculate when your baby might arrive</description><pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>ChatGPT Would be a Decent Policy Advisor</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/2025-03-chat-gpt-policy/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/2025-03-chat-gpt-policy/</guid><description>Revealed: How the UK tech secretary uses ChatGPT for policy advice by Chris Stokel-Walker for the New Scientist</description><pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 16:30:58 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.is/i89l9#selection-1037.0-1049.44&quot;&gt;Revealed: How the UK tech secretary uses ChatGPT for policy advice&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The New Scientist used freedom of information laws to get the ChatGPT records of the UK&apos;s technology secretary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The headline hints at a damning exposé, but ends up being a story about a politician making pretty reasonable and sensible use of language models to be more informed and make better policy decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He asked it why small business owners are slow to adopt AI, which popular podcasts he should appear on, and to define terms like &lt;em&gt;antimatter&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;digital inclusion&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This all seems extremely fine to me. Perhaps my standards for politicians are too low, but I assume they don&apos;t actually know much and rely heavily on advisors to define terms for them and decide on policy improvements. And I think ChatGPT connected to some grounded sources would be a decent policy advisor. Better than most human policy advisors. At least when it comes to consistency, rapidly searching and synthesising lots of documents, and avoiding personal bias. Models still carry the bias of their creators, but it all becomes a trade-off between human flaws and model flaws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Claiming language models should have anything to do with national governance feels slightly insane. But we&apos;re also sitting in a moment where Trump and Musk are implementing policies that trigger trade wars and crash the U.S. economy. And I have to think &quot;What if we just put Claude in charge?&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I joke. Kind of.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded></item><item><title>March 2025</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/now-2025-03/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/now-2025-03/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Well, I&apos;ve had a dramatic start to the year.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://normally.com/&quot;&gt;Normally&lt;/a&gt;, the design agency I joined a short eight months ago, unexpectedly &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/posts/normally_ai-leadership-innovation-activity-7290396641226891266-JIYQ&quot;&gt;closed down&lt;/a&gt; in January. Despite running for a decade and working with almost every major tech company, client work slowed down and the founders decided to close up shop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&apos;s been a sad time. Everyone I worked with there was exceptionally talented and kind. I&apos;m thankful I got to build with them for a short while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was already due to start maternity leave in March, so Normally closing just moved that date up a bit sooner. But I managed to fit in a couple of months of work with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.deepmirror.ai/&quot;&gt;Deep Mirror&lt;/a&gt; before taking my baby break. They&apos;re a London-based startup using machine learning to speed up the drug discovery process, specifically by helping medicinal chemists generate ideas for new molecules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I was completely new to the field of drug discovery, many of the design challenges echoed the ones I&apos;d worked on with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.elicit.com/&quot;&gt;Elicit&lt;/a&gt; – complex research workflows, information-dense interfaces, and making the inner workings of models and their reasoning process visible to users. I&apos;ve learned I like this shape of work; AI/ML tools designed to help scientific researchers who have high standards and need to thoroughly understand how models “reason” and how answers are generated. It&apos;s fertile ground for responsible AI interface design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My baby break has now started. Only &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; weeks remain until the new human arrives. A terrifyingly short timeline. Luckily, the excitement of meeting our child and the physical discomfort of late pregnancy outweigh any fears about birth or the impending marathon of sleep deprivation. I&apos;d happily start labour tomorrow if I had any say in the matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that I won&apos;t be in a 9-5 job for the next six months, I&apos;ve stocked up on new books. Though it&apos;s naïve to think I&apos;ll have the mental capacity to read any of them in between baby feedings and waking up a dozen times a night. But one can hope. I&apos;ve added the full pile to my &lt;a href=&quot;/antilibrary&quot;&gt;Antilibrary&lt;/a&gt;, but these are the ones I&apos;m most excited about:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.co.uk/books/edition/Soldiers_and_Kings/EzPBEAAAQBAJ&quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Soldiers and Kings: Survival and Hope in the World of Human Smuggling&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; by Jason De Leon&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This got my attention when it started popping up on all the “best of” ethnography lists in 2024, and then went on to win the national book award for non-fiction. I expect it to be a slightly intense read, but well-researched ethnographies are my favourite genre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.co.uk/books/edition/Cue_the_Sun/GObnEAAAQBAJ&quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Cue the Sun! The Invention of Reality TV&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; by Emily Nussbaum&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like most of us, I have a love/hate/fascination/repulsion relationship with reality TV. I&apos;ve watched my fair share of trash series, but will happily defend (most of) them as time well spent. They&apos;re always insightful windows into our collective value systems and cultural narratives, and I&apos;m keen to read Nussbaum&apos;s critical take on the medium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.co.uk/books/edition/The_Invention_of_Nature/w1WNBQAAQBAJ&quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;The Invention of Nature: The Adventures of Alexander von Humboldt&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; by Andrea Wulf&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given my long &lt;a href=&quot;/growing-a-human#all-natural-organic-granola-earth-mothering&quot;&gt;standing&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/natureculture&quot;&gt;preoccupation&lt;/a&gt; with how we try to define and divide “nature” from “culture”, it&apos;s about time I did a bit more historical reading into the origins of this cultural dichotomy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve been using a bit of my pre-baby time to build as well. I added a new section to this garden called &lt;a href=&quot;/smidgeons&quot;&gt;Smidgeons&lt;/a&gt;. These are teeny tiny posts: links with a bit of commentary, research papers I enjoyed, or one-liners that would otherwise go on Bluesky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m also quite deep into a new research project and set of prototypes I&apos;m calling &lt;strong&gt;Lodestone&lt;/strong&gt;. It&apos;s an exploration of how language models might be able to get us to think more, not less. Specifically, I&apos;m interested in whether models can enable me to be a better critical thinker and rigorous writer. Not by writing for me, but by guiding me through a well-defined process of understanding what claims I&apos;m making, what evidence I have to support it, and how my argument structure fits together. I&apos;m tackling it from a few angles, but here&apos;s some previews from the latest prototype:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The code is all &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MaggieAppleton/lodestone&quot;&gt;open source on Github&lt;/a&gt;, though it&apos;ll evolve a lot from here. I&apos;ll publish more about it soon, but the ideas still feel early and my thesis is unproven. I&apos;ll wait until it all gels together a bit more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should mention that starting this summer I&apos;ll be looking for a new role as a Design Engineer or technically-inclined Product Designer. I&apos;m planning to be on maternity leave until early September, but I&apos;m happy to start talking to companies, teams, and founders now if you think we could be a good fit. Just email hello at maggieappleton.com or DM me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://bsky.app/profile/maggieappleton.com&quot;&gt;Bluesky&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded></item><item><title>Humanity&apos;s Last Exam</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/2025-02-last-exam/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/2025-02-last-exam/</guid><description>Humanity&apos;s Last Exam by Center for AI Safety (CAIS) and Scale AI</description><pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 11:42:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;a href=&quot;https://agi.safe.ai/&quot;&gt;Humanity&apos;s Last Exam&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a new(ish) benchmark, cutely named “Humanity&apos;s Last Exam.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&apos;re not familiar with benchmarks, they&apos;re how we measure the capabilities of particular AI models like o1 or Claude Sonnet 3.5. Each one is a standardised test designed to check a specific skill set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://paperswithcode.com/dataset/mmlu&quot;&gt;MMLU&lt;/a&gt; (Massive Multitask Language Understanding) measures understanding across 57 academic subjects including STEM, social science, and the humanities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2107.03374v2&quot;&gt;HumanEval&lt;/a&gt; measures code generation skills.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2311.12022&quot;&gt;GPQA&lt;/a&gt; (Graduate-Level Google-Proof Q&amp;amp;A Benchmark) measures correctness on a set of questions written by PhD students and domain experts in biology, physics, and chemistry.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you run a model on a benchmark it gets a score, which allows us to create &lt;a href=&quot;https://llm-stats.com/&quot;&gt;leaderboards&lt;/a&gt; showing which model is currently the best for that test. To make scoring easy, the answers are usually formatted as multiple choice, true/false, or unit tests for programming tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the many problems with using benchmarks as a stand-in for “intelligence” (other than the fact they&apos;re multiple choice standardised tests – do you think that&apos;s a reasonable measure of human capabilities in the real world?), is that our current benchmarks aren&apos;t hard enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New models routinely achieve 90%+ on the best ones we have. So there&apos;s a clear need for harder benchmarks to measure model performance against.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence, &lt;a href=&quot;https://lastexam.ai/&quot;&gt;Humanity&apos;s Last Exam&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Made by ScaleAI and the Center for AI Safety, they&apos;ve crowdsourced &quot;the hardest and broadest set of questions ever&quot; by experts across domains. 2,700 questions at the moment, some of which they&apos;re keeping private to prevent future models training on the dataset and memorising answers ahead of time. Questions like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;img src=&quot;/images/smidgeons/last-exam-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Samples of the diverse and challenging questions submitted to Humanity&apos;s Last Exam.&quot; /&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;img src=&quot;/images/smidgeons/last-exam-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Samples of the diverse and challenging questions submitted to Humanity&apos;s Last Exam.&quot; /&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;img src=&quot;/images/smidgeons/last-exam-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Samples of the diverse and challenging questions submitted to Humanity&apos;s Last Exam.&quot; /&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, it&apos;s doing it&apos;s job well – the highest scoring model is OpenAI&apos;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://openai.com/index/introducing-deep-research/&quot;&gt;Deep Research&lt;/a&gt; at 26.6%, with other common models like GPT-4o, Grok, and Claude only getting 3-4% correct. Maybe it&apos;ll last a year before we have to design the next “last exam.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;A quick note on benchmarks and sweeping generalisations&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When people make sweeping statements like “language models are bullshit machines” or “ChatGPT lies,” it usually tells me they&apos;re not seriously engaged in any kind of AI/ML work or productive discourse in this space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, because saying a machine “lies” or “bullshits” implies motivated intent in a social context, which language models don&apos;t have. Models doing statistical pattern matching aren&apos;t purposefully trying to deceive or manipulate their users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And second, broad generalisations about “AI”&apos;s correctness, truthfulness, or usefulness is meaningless outside of a specific context. Or rather, &lt;strong&gt;a specific model measured on a specific benchmark or reproducible test.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, next time you hear someone making grand statements about AI capabilities (both critical and overhyped), ask: which model are they talking about? On what benchmark? With what prompting techniques? With what supporting infrastructure around the model? Everything is in the details, and the only way to be a sensible thinker in this space is to learn about the details.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded></item><item><title>DeepSeek</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/2025-01-deepseek/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/2025-01-deepseek/</guid><description>If you&apos;re not distressingly embedded in the torrent of AI news on Twixxer like I reluctantly am, you might not know what DeepSeek is yet. Bless you.</description><pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2025 10:00:35 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;If you&apos;re not distressingly embedded in the torrent of AI news on Twixxer like I reluctantly am, you might not know what &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DeepSeek&quot;&gt;DeepSeek&lt;/a&gt; is yet. Bless you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From what I&apos;ve gathered:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On January 20th, a Chinese company named DeepSeek released a new reasoning model called R1.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A reasoning model is a large language model told to “think step-by-step” before it gives a final answer. This “&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2201.11903&quot;&gt;chain of thought&lt;/a&gt;” technique dramatically improves the quality of its answers. These models are also fine-tuned to perform well on complex reasoning tasks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;R1 reaches equal or better performance on a number of major benchmarks compared to OpenAI&apos;s o1 (our current state-of-the-art reasoning model) and Anthropic&apos;s Claude Sonnet 3.5 but is significantly cheaper to use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DeepSeek R1 is &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/deepseek-ai/DeepSeek-R1/tree/main&quot;&gt;open-source&lt;/a&gt;, meaning you can download it and run it on your own machine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They offer &lt;a href=&quot;https://api-docs.deepseek.com/&quot;&gt;API access&lt;/a&gt; at a &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; lower cost than OpenAI or Anthropic. But given this is a Chinese model, and the current political climate is “complicated,” and they&apos;re almost certainly training on input data, don&apos;t put any sensitive or personal data through it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can use R1 online through the DeepSeek &lt;a href=&quot;https://chat.deepseek.com/&quot;&gt;chat interface&lt;/a&gt;. You can turn on both reasoning and web search to inform your answers. Reasoning mode shows you the model “thinking out loud” before returning the final answer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;img src=&quot;/images/smidgeons/deepseek1.png&quot; alt=&quot;DeepSeek R1 showing its thinking&quot; /&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can use &lt;a href=&quot;https://ollama.com/&quot;&gt;Ollama&lt;/a&gt; to run R1 on your own machine, but standard personal laptops won&apos;t be able to handle the larger, more capable versions of the model (32B+). You&apos;ll have to run the smaller 8B or 14B version, which will be slightly less capable. I have the 14B version running just fine on a Macbook Pro with an Apple M1 chip. Here&apos;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/selfhosted/comments/1i6ggyh/got_deepseek_r1_running_locally_full_setup_guide/&quot;&gt;a Reddit guide&lt;/a&gt; on getting it running locally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DeepSeek claims it only cost $5.5 million to train the model, compared to an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/katharinabuchholz/2024/08/23/the-extreme-cost-of-training-ai-models/&quot;&gt;estimated $41-78 million&lt;/a&gt; for GPT-4. If true, building state-of-the-art models is no longer just a billionaires game.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The thoughtbois of Twixxer are winding themselves into knots trying to theorise what this means for the U.S.-China AI arms race. A few people have referred to this as a “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.exponentialview.co/p/the-year-end-wake-up-the-chinese&quot;&gt;sputnik moment&lt;/a&gt;.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From my initial, unscientific, unsystematic explorations with it, it&apos;s &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; good. Using it as my default LM going forward (for tasks that don&apos;t involve sensitive data). Quirks include being way too verbose in its reasoning explanations and using lots of Chinese language sources when it searches the web. Makes it challenging to validate whether claims match the source texts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&apos;s the announcement Tweet:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TLDR&lt;/strong&gt; high-quality reasoning models are getting significantly cheaper and more open-source. This means companies like Google, OpenAI, and Anthropic won&apos;t be able to maintain a monopoly on access to fast, cheap, good quality reasoning. This is net good for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded></item><item><title>Common Misconceptions in AI</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/2025-01-common-misconceptions/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/2025-01-common-misconceptions/</guid><description>Common Misconceptions About the Complexity in Robotics vs AI by Dan Ogawa</description><pubDate>Sun, 12 Jan 2025 14:52:12 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;a href=&quot;https://harimus.github.io//2024/05/31/motortask.html&quot;&gt;Common Misconceptions About the Complexity in Robotics vs AI&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A roboticist breaks down common misconceptions about what&apos;s hard and easy in robotics. A response to
everyone asking “can&apos;t we just stick a large language model into its brain to make it more capable?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contrary to the assumptions of many people, making robots perceive and move in the world in the way
humans can turns out to be an extraordinarily hard problem to solve. While seemingly “hard” problems
like scoring well on intelligence tests, winning at chess, and acing the GMAT turn out to be much
easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone thought it would be extremely hard and computationally expensive to teach computers
language, and easy to teach them to identify objects visually. The opposite turned out to be true.
This is known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moravec%27s_paradox&quot;&gt;Moravec&apos;s Paradox&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Especially liked the ending where Dan explores &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; people are so resistant to the idea picking up
a cup is more complex than solving logic puzzles. Partly anthropocentrism; humans are special
because we can do higher order thinking. Any lowly animal can sense the world and move through it.
Partly social class bias; people who work manual labour jobs using their bodies are less valued then
people who sit still using their intellect to solve problems.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded></item><item><title>Undetected AI Exam Answers</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/2025-01-undetected/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/2025-01-undetected/</guid><description>A real-world test of artificial intelligence infiltration of a university examinations system: A “Turing Test” case study by Peter Scarfe, Kelly Watcham, Alasdair Clarke, Etienne Roesch</description><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2025 17:24:34 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0305354&quot;&gt;A real-world test of artificial intelligence infiltration of a university examinations system: A “Turing Test” case study&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researchers submitted entirely AI-generated exam answers to the undergraduate psychology department
of a “reputable” UK university. The vast majority went undetected and the AI answers achieved higher
scores than real students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We report a rigorous, blind study in which we injected 100% AI written submissions into the
examinations system in five undergraduate modules, across all years of study, for a BSc degree in
Psychology at a reputable UK university. We found that &lt;strong&gt;94% of our AI submissions were
undetected&lt;/strong&gt;. The grades awarded to our AI submissions were on average &lt;strong&gt;half a grade boundary
higher than that achieved by real students&lt;/strong&gt;. Across modules there was an 83.4% chance that the AI
submissions on a module would outperform a random selection of the same number of real student
submissions.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to assume educators are swiftly moving to hand-written exams under supervised conditions and
oral exams. Anything else seems to negate the point of exams.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded></item><item><title>Unbaited</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/2025-01-unbaited/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/2025-01-unbaited/</guid><description>Unbaited by Daniel Petho</description><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2025 17:12:34 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;a href=&quot;https://unbaited.danielpetho.com/&quot;&gt;Unbaited&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A browser extension that filters out engagement bait from your feed on Twixxer. Uses Llama 3.3 under
the hood to analyse Tweets in real time and then blurs out sensationalist political content. Or
whatever else you prompt it to blur – the system prompt is editable:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;img src=&quot;/images/smidgeons/unbaited.png&quot; alt=&quot;System settings and a customisable prompt for the Unbaited app&quot; /&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is certainly &lt;em&gt;a way&lt;/em&gt; to try and manage Twixxer&apos;s slow demise into right-wing extremist content.
Though I&apos;m taking this more as a thought experiment and interesting prototype than a sincere
suggestion we should spend precious energy burning GPUs on clickbait filtering. Integrating LLMs
into the browsing experience and using them to selectively curate content for you is the more
interesting move here.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded></item><item><title>Smidgeons</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/2025-01-smidgeons/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/2025-01-smidgeons/</guid><description>Welcome to the smidgeon stream. This is a new kind of content on the Garden. One that was</description><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2025 17:02:34 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the smidgeon stream. This is a new kind of content on the &lt;a href=&quot;/garden&quot;&gt;Garden&lt;/a&gt;. One that was
overdue. They&apos;re called &lt;em&gt;smidgeons&lt;/em&gt;. Teeny, tiny entries. The kinds of things I used to put in
Tweets, before Twitter died a terrible death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most are only a few sentences long. They&apos;re mainly links to notable things – good articles, papers,
and ideas. I&apos;ve been meaning to do this for a while, but a recent migration to
&lt;a href=&quot;https://astro.build/&quot;&gt;Astro&lt;/a&gt; suddenly made it much easier.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded></item><item><title>How to Import Academic Papers from Zotero into Tana</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/tana-zotero/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/tana-zotero/</guid><description>How to use Zotero&apos;s translator and Tana Paste formatting to easily import papers into Tana</description><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 09:58:54 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Growing a Human: The First 30 Weeks</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/growing-a-human/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/growing-a-human/</guid><description>Reflections on the strange experience of growing a human from scratch, without any conscious understanding of how you are doing it</description><pubDate>Sat, 04 Jan 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>December 2024</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/now-2024-12/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/now-2024-12/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;We&apos;re back in that glorious post-Christmas, pre-New-Year&apos;s liminal period when the days blur together and I&apos;m allowed to spend inordinate amounts of time tinkering on side projects and laying on the couch eating handfuls of Twiglets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the last couple weeks I&apos;ve been plodding through an overdue and much needed migration of this website from &lt;a href=&quot;https://nextjs.org/&quot;&gt;Next.js&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://astro.build/&quot;&gt;Astro&lt;/a&gt;. No shade on Next, but it wasn&apos;t the right framework for the job; I found myself constantly battling server-side rendering errors and trying to escape hatch out of React. Astro lets me return to writing plain HTML, CSS, and JavaScript, rather than being trapped in a single front-end framework. It also takes a lighter approach to JavaScript, only including it when needed, and is designed for content-heavy websites like this one. If you&apos;re reading this, the migration is complete! It took a good month but I&apos;m &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; happier working in the new codebase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The past six months have been a bit of a rush. At the end of July I got married, promptly learned we were pregnant, and started a new job two weeks later, right when debilitating “morning sickness” began to kick in. While the timing wasn&apos;t ideal, I&apos;m obviously thrilled about all of it. Living life on warp speed over here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily the company I joined was very understanding! &lt;a href=&quot;https://normally.com/&quot;&gt;Normally&lt;/a&gt; is a small design and research agency focused on the practical and thoughtful application of AI. They&apos;re based here in London and I&apos;m now a Lead &lt;a href=&quot;/design-engineers&quot;&gt;Design Engineer&lt;/a&gt; there. This primarily means designing and building early-stage prototypes for our clients – either completely novel products or developing new services and features for existing systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently reading a sobering but beautifully written history of the Sackler family, Purdue Pharma, and the OxyContin opiod crisis called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.co.uk/books/edition/Empire_of_Pain/tN8OEAAAQBAJ?hl=en&amp;amp;gbpv=0&quot;&gt;Empire of Pain&lt;/a&gt;. I&apos;m usually not very good with horror, thrillers, or anything involving too much human peril and suffering. But Radden Keefe is a brilliant writer and his detailed historical narratives make it worth my discomfort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.co.uk/books/edition/Empire_of_Pain/tN8OEAAAQBAJ?hl=en&amp;amp;gbpv=0&quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Empire of Pain: The Secret History of the Sackler Dynasty&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; by Patrick Radden Keefe&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A slightly horrifying tale of a family with no moral standards and egregious levels of megalomania.{&quot; &quot;}&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded></item><item><title>Aesthetic Command Lines with Hyper, Spaceship, and Oh My Zsh</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/aesthetic-commands/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/aesthetic-commands/</guid><description>My fairly banal, basic, but beautiful command line setup</description><pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Leaving Elicit</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/leaving-elicit/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/leaving-elicit/</guid><description>Reflections on two years of working at Elicit and why it&apos;s time to leave</description><pubDate>Sun, 07 Jul 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>July 2024</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/now-2024-07/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/now-2024-07/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Despite the regular drizzle, this summer is looking splendid. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ghr2M8mh8MA&quot;&gt;tories are out&lt;/a&gt; of power. London is out in force enjoying the warm weather. I&apos;m temporarily funemployed and thoroughly enjoying doing almost nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to &lt;a href=&quot;/leaving-elicit&quot;&gt;leave Elicit&lt;/a&gt; back in April, and worked my last day there in June. The team was lovely, but living a life halfway between San Francisco and London was not. I realised I needed to work somewhere with more in-person collaboration, more senior designers, and on the same time zone as me. Fortuitously, I met some people who run an AI prototyping agency here in London and found our interests aligned. I&apos;ll be joining them at the end of July.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until then I&apos;m touching grass, prototyping new ideas for language model interfaces, writing things, shrinking my bedside book pile, improving this website a bit, and getting married somewhere in the middle. I now have a lot of thoughts on the trad femme world of weddings, but I&apos;ll save it for a proper post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently working through John McPhee&apos;s &lt;em&gt;Annals of the Former World&lt;/em&gt;, which is fat but satisfying. I&apos;m not usually a rock-lover, but McPhee&apos;s storytelling and prose is beautiful enough to make plate tectonics, basins, granite, sediments, and conodonts seem compelling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.co.uk/books/edition/Annals_of_the_Former_World/GS81F0RNxesC?hl=en&amp;amp;gbpv=0&quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;strong&amp;gt;Annals of the Former World&amp;lt;/strong&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; by John McPhee&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Pulitzer Prize-winning history of the geology of North America, across the
fortieth parallel and down through 4.6 billion years. Tales of rock structures
and the geologists trying to figure out what they&apos;re telling us.{&quot; &quot;}&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded></item><item><title>Home-Cooked Software and Barefoot Developers</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/home-cooked-software/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/home-cooked-software/</guid><description>The emerging golden age of home-cooked software, barefoot developers, and why the local-first community should help build it</description><pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Faking William Morris, Generative Forgery, and the Erosion of Art History</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/generative-forgery/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/generative-forgery/</guid><description>Buying fake William Morris prints on Etsy and other early signs of epistemological collapse</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>On Opening Essays, Conference Talks, and Jam Jars</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/openings/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/openings/</guid><description>How to open pieces of narrative non-fiction writing, conference talks, and sticky jars</description><pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Spinning Worlds, Seasickness, and Dealing with Vestibular Neuritis</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/spinning/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/spinning/</guid><description>Gaining a strange disease and losing my ability to see straight</description><pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Collection of Design Engineers</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/design-engineers/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/design-engineers/</guid><description>Collecting people I know who work at the intersection of design and engineering, in an attempt to figure out what a design engineer is</description><pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Gathering Structures</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/gathering-structures/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/gathering-structures/</guid><description>How to gather people and create communities in ways that are low-stress and high-payoff</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Feb 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Speculative Calendar Events</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/speculative-events/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/speculative-events/</guid><description>Designing tentative calendar events to solve complex scheduling problems</description><pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Ambient Co-presence</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/ambient-copresence/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/ambient-copresence/</guid><description>Creating a subtle, peripheral, and synchronous sense of shared space and context on the web</description><pubDate>Wed, 27 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Historical Trails</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/historical-trails/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/historical-trails/</guid><description>Giving people a visible, useful trail of where they&apos;ve been over the course of an exploratory journey</description><pubDate>Mon, 18 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>December 2023</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/now-2023-12/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/now-2023-12/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;The limbo-like lull in-between Christmas and News Years is my favourite period of the year. I never know what to do with myself. I arrive back from chaotic, overstimulating family visits and sit amidst my pile of gifts, half-unpacked bags, and leftover chocolate, wondering what in the world I used to do with my days. I&apos;ve long forgotten what it&apos;s like to have any semblance of life structure. Despite it only being a week since I was on a focused, tight schedule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This weird floaty time is beautiful. I sit around writing long, trite reflections on the year. I look through my calendar week-by-week and count up arbitrary numbers of things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1,140 kilometers run&lt;br /&gt;
89 coffee dates and park walks with friends&lt;br /&gt;
14 published pieces of writing (far less than I&apos;d like)&lt;br /&gt;
6 podcast interviews&lt;br /&gt;
5 conference talks&lt;br /&gt;
5 Future of Coding events&lt;br /&gt;
5 driving lessons&lt;br /&gt;
1 driving test cancelled (I still haven&apos;t booked another)&lt;br /&gt;
2 weddings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m not sure these capture anything, but they give some shape to the past 12 months. For the most part, it was a stressful and sad year. I split up with my wonderful, long-term partner at the start of it. I want children, and he didn&apos;t. It&apos;s the one thing you can&apos;t compromise on. So I spent the following months being a pathetically heartbroken lump. I wallowed in work and distracted myself with travel and conferences and podcasts and excessively long park walks with friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But somehow, miraculously, just like the last 15 minutes of a cheaply made Netflix romcom, everything worked out in the final stretch. In our months apart my partner did a lot of reflection. He changed his mind and realised he does want a family. Knowing that you want to take on that level of stress, responsibility, and sleep deprivation isn&apos;t a small question, and one everyone comes to in their own time. I wasn&apos;t entirely sure I wanted children until my very late twenties. And it certainly would have been helpful to realise earlier...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, we got back together. And it&apos;s been pretty happily ever after since. We even put a ring on it to secure the ever after part 😉&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;{&quot; &quot;}&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded></item><item><title>September 2023</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/now-2023-09/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/now-2023-09/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;London flipped from sweltering summer back to drizzling grey yesterday. Autumn was overdue. Summer was a little too manic for my taste anyway. I spent a bunch of time in Maine, New York, and San Fransisco. A mix of long back porch hangouts with family, collaborator coffees, and in-person problem-solving with the Ought team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the Ought team are no longer the Ought team. We&apos;ve changed names! And whole companies come to think of it. Ought as a legal entity was a non-profit research lab. But we found it difficult to get enough funding from the charitable space to hire people and grow &lt;a href=&quot;https://elicit.com&quot;&gt;Elicit&lt;/a&gt;, our primary product. Our founders decided to pull the same move as &lt;a href=&quot;https://hackernoon.com/how-openai-transitioned-from-a-nonprofit-to-a-$29b-for-profit-company&quot;&gt;OpenAI&lt;/a&gt; and Anthropic and flipped to become a VC-backed startup. The new company is just called Elicit. We raised a seed round and rebuilt the product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&apos;re slowly moving our 200,000 active users over to the new beta version. We shipped it while we&apos;re still deeply embarrassed by it. It has a thousand big and small UX cuts that fill me with sadness. Every morning I get on and hack away at them, trusting at some point it will feel beautiful to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My work on Elicit and explorations of &lt;a href=&quot;/lm-sketchbook&quot;&gt;Language Model interfaces&lt;/a&gt; have compounded into some strong opinions. I gathered some of them into a new talk called &lt;a href=&quot;/squish-structure&quot;&gt;Squish Meets Structure&lt;/a&gt;. I did one round of it for &lt;a href=&quot;https://smashingconf.com/meets-ai&quot;&gt;Smashing Meets AI&lt;/a&gt;, and then drastically improved it for &lt;a href=&quot;https://smashingconf.com/sf-2023/&quot;&gt;Smashing Conference&lt;/a&gt; in Freiburg, Germany a few weeks ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m headed to &lt;a href=&quot;https://webdirections.org/summit/&quot;&gt;Web Directions&lt;/a&gt; in Sydney, Australia and &lt;a href=&quot;https://2023.ffconf.org/&quot;&gt;FFConf&lt;/a&gt; in Brighton later this year to present my slightly more macabre talk on the &lt;a href=&quot;/forest-talk&quot;&gt;Expanding Dark Forest and Generative AI&lt;/a&gt;. Expect to be all talked out after that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently taking in writing advice from men named Ste(v/ph)en. Working through Steven Pinker&apos;s &quot;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.co.uk/books/edition/The_Sense_of_Style/eCNBAwAAQBAJ?hl=en&amp;amp;gbpv=0&quot;&gt;The Sense of Style&lt;/a&gt;&quot; and Stephen King&apos;s &quot;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.co.uk/books/edition/On_Writing/DPg4J_xn3ZEC?hl=en&amp;amp;gbpv=0&quot;&gt;On Writing&lt;/a&gt;&quot; – both excellent. The former for grounded advice on non-fiction communication, the latter for an extraordinary account of persistently writing through double-shift minimum wage jobs and a raging alcohol and drug problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spent the summer discovering how much I love dresses and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jumpsuit&quot;&gt;jumpsuits&lt;/a&gt; with deep pockets. Found some of my favourites from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.boden.co.uk/en-gb/womens-dresses&quot;&gt;Boden&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://roandzo.com/collections/jumpsuits&quot;&gt;Ro&amp;amp;Zo&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.whistles.com/clothing/jumpsuits/&quot;&gt;Whistles&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wearethought.com/collections/womens-sustainable-jumpsuits&quot;&gt;Thought&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve realised I spent the last decade avoiding femme clothing, aesthetics, and mannerisms in an attempt to be taken more seriously in the all-male spaces I hang out in. Spaces where I am routinely treated like a small, insignificant girl, ignored, and spoken over. Feels pretty freeing to give fewer shits and permanently live in dresses. They&apos;ll ignore me either way.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded></item><item><title>Squish Meets Structure</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/squish-structure/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/squish-structure/</guid><description>Designing with Language Models</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Language Model Sketchbook, or Why I Hate Chatbots</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/lm-sketchbook/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/lm-sketchbook/</guid><description>Sketchy ideas for interfaces that play with the novel capabilities of language models</description><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jun 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>June 2023</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/now-2023-06/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/now-2023-06/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;The last six months have felt like a disorientating blur. While bouncing between overseas trips, writing conference talks, organising events, and keeping up with work, I ended a long-term relationship and moved across London. My writing took a hit – I haven&apos;t published much this year. I feel like I&apos;m still trying to figure out what to do when I get up every morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having everything thrown out of whack is pretty useful. You figure out how resilient your systems are. You learn what you have committed to muscle memory and what you rely on cues from your environment to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was also reminded how much I value my extended friend network in London (and the rest of Europe). My social groups here often feel like concentric overlapping circles – I can&apos;t neatly distinguish them. Which feels right; like a small village where everyone knows everyone. My philosophy friends show up at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://lu.ma/foclondon&quot;&gt;Future of Coding&lt;/a&gt; meetups I run. My Twitter friends appear at dinners with my more &lt;em&gt;woo&lt;/em&gt; creative people. It&apos;s difficult to beat the sheer density of curious, friendly, ambitious people in a big city like London. It is more than worth the price of rent IMHO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn&apos;t help that everything in the world of language models and generative AI has been moving at warp speed this year. I&apos;m reading notes I took back in October of 2022 on GPT-3 and truthfulness, and it feels like we&apos;re in a completely different world now. The benchmarks are out of date. The prompting techniques are more sophisticated. The real-world use cases have proliferated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I keep wanting to throw my hat into the discourse ring – I certainly have formed opinions at this point! But there&apos;s so much noise it&apos;s difficult to determine if you&apos;re adding any signal. I&apos;m being cautious about it. Being a careful thinker feels like a rare quality at this point; I still aspire to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some good reads as of late:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bought myself used copies of Christopher Alexander&apos;s classics. Feels much better to hold these in your hands than scroll the PDFs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;{&quot; &quot;}&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded></item><item><title>The Expanding Dark Forest and Generative AI</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/forest-talk/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/forest-talk/</guid><description>An exploration of the problems and possible futures of flooding the web with generative AI content</description><pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Computational Notebooks</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/computational-notebooks/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/computational-notebooks/</guid><description>Shareable, browser-based documents that can compile and run code</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Teenage Skeuomorphic Desktop Designs</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/teenage-desktop/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/teenage-desktop/</guid><description>An archive of my high school desktop designs, circa 2009</description><pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Reverse Outlining with Language Models</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/reverse-outline/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/reverse-outline/</guid><description>Using language models to generate reverse outlines of writing drafts</description><pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Dark Forest and Generative AI</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/ai-dark-forest/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/ai-dark-forest/</guid><description>Proving you&apos;re a human on a web flooded with generative AI content</description><pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Empty Pointers and Constellations of AI</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/ai-empty-pointer/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/ai-empty-pointer/</guid><description>On the fuzziness of calling things “artificial intelligence” and moving the goalposts</description><pubDate>Sat, 17 Dec 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Command K Bars</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/command-bar/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/command-bar/</guid><description>Command line bars you can quickly summon with a keyboard shortcut</description><pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>November 2022</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/now-2022-11/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/now-2022-11/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;It&apos;s a weird week. Twitter is (possibly) entering a slow death march and much of my community is reluctantly slouching over to Mastodon. I&apos;ve started cross-posting there as well: &lt;a href=&quot;https://indieweb.social/@maggie&quot;&gt;indieweb.social/@maggie&lt;/a&gt;. The Elon-escapades only drive home how important it is to own and control the platform you&apos;re publishing to. Which means writing on your own website first and cross-posting to external platforms. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://indieweb.org/&quot;&gt;IndieWeb&lt;/a&gt; community has a catchy acronym for this: &lt;a href=&quot;https://indieweb.org/POSSE&quot;&gt;POSSE&lt;/a&gt;. Publish (on your) Own Site, Syndicate Elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still don&apos;t have a Twitter-like stream setup on this site, but I&apos;m working on it. Tools like &lt;a href=&quot;https://webmention.io/&quot;&gt;WebMentions&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://brid.gy/&quot;&gt;Bridgy&lt;/a&gt; are going to do a lot of the heavy lifting. I&apos;m having trouble finding many tutorials or guides on how to do it though – perhaps another case of writing the piece you want to read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve been working at &lt;a href=&quot;https://ought.org/&quot;&gt;Ought&lt;/a&gt; since late August. The London ↔ SF time difference is a bit crap, but I can&apos;t say enough good things about my fellow Oughters 🦦. It&apos;s rare and special to work alongside such thoughtful and ambitious people. We&apos;re in the middle of designing and prototyping some wildly different interfaces for &lt;a href=&quot;https://elicit.org/&quot;&gt;Elicit&lt;/a&gt;, our AI research assistant and Ought&apos;s main product. Users say they love the current version, but we know it could be so much better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other news, I bought a cheap, used laser printer and it&apos;s drastically improved my reading experience for long articles and PDFs. Can&apos;t recommend it enough. There are plenty going for £30-40 on eBay and you&apos;ll finally read all those 5000-word blog posts you have bookmarked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve finally gotten back into a good writing cadence. I recently published &lt;a href=&quot;/programming-portals&quot;&gt;Programming Portals&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/command-bar&quot;&gt;Command K Bars&lt;/a&gt;. Now I&apos;m slowly chipping away at &lt;a href=&quot;/tools-for-thought&quot;&gt;Tools for Thought&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/tools-for-thought&quot;&gt;as Cultural Practices,&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/tools-for-thought&quot;&gt;Not Computational Objects&lt;/a&gt;. I&apos;ve been writing it forever, but that&apos;s kind of the point of &lt;a href=&quot;/garden-history&quot;&gt;gardening&lt;/a&gt; in public. You post up loose skeletons of ideas and flesh them out over time. Nothing forces you to write like knowing people are reading your half-baked version.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded></item><item><title>Programming Portals</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/programming-portals/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/programming-portals/</guid><description>Small, scoped areas within a graphical interface that allow users to read and write simple programmes</description><pubDate>Sun, 23 Oct 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Folk Interfaces</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/folk-interfaces/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/folk-interfaces/</guid><description>People reappropriating existing software to solve their own unique problems</description><pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Joining Ought</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/joining-ought/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/joining-ought/</guid><description>A new role at an AI research lab working on tools for open-ended reasoning</description><pubDate>Fri, 15 Jul 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>July 2022</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/now-2022-07/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/now-2022-07/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve decided to join &lt;a href=&quot;https://ought.org/&quot;&gt;Ought&lt;/a&gt;, a non-profit research lab. I wrote about the move &lt;a href=&quot;/joining-ought&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, but TLDR:
Ought is exploring how machine learning techniques can support &lt;a href=&quot;https://ought.org/mission&quot;&gt;open-ended reasoning&lt;/a&gt; and research. At the moment their main focus is building &lt;a href=&quot;https://elicit.org/&quot;&gt;Elicit&lt;/a&gt; an AI research assistant that helps automate literature reviews. The long-term vision is to develop tools and techniques that mitigate &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AI_alignment&quot;&gt;AI alignment&lt;/a&gt; risks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They&apos;re based in the Bay Area of California, so I&apos;ll be on flights over the Atlantic more often. London is still my home base for the long-term future. I&apos;ll spare you my gauche love letter to this city, but leaving only makes me realise how deeply I appreciate it. Stepping back onto TFL platforms, Sainsbury&apos;s aisles, and hodge-podge pavements feel like breathing again. Perhaps it&apos;s just a matter of contrasts though; San Fransisco&apos;s grimey vibes are not for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve started hosting a monthly event for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://lu.ma/london-foc&quot;&gt;Future of Code&lt;/a&gt; community here. I&apos;m keeping it low-key for the moment. Meaning it&apos;s just thirty people in a pub talking shop about CRDT&apos;s, spatial canvases, and embodied cognition. My kind of Friday night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&apos;ve got an exceptional class of people coming at the moment. I&apos;m thinking hard about how to preserve this early group energy; keeping it small, not promoting it too much (lest the recruiters and VC&apos;s get wind of the event), and maintaining the “don&apos;t take this too seriously” vibes. Most other tech meetups in London turn out to be overstuffed, impersonal networking evenings. They&apos;re held in some fluorescently lit office where a handful of people give lightweight talks over lukewarm pizza. Everyone wants to escape home as soon as they&apos;ve arrived. Avoiding this vibe is my first priority.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded></item><item><title>The Block-Paved Path to Structured Data</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/block-data/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/block-data/</guid><description>How block-based interfaces can help us create more structured data on the web</description><pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Daily Notes Pages</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/daily-notes/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/daily-notes/</guid><description>Daily notes as a frictionless default input for personal knowledge management systems</description><pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Picture Worth a Thousand Programmes</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/programming-pictures/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/programming-pictures/</guid><description>Bringing visual explanations and embodied knowledge to programming tools</description><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Programmable Notes</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/programmatic-notes/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/programmatic-notes/</guid><description>Agent-based note-taking systems that can prompt and facilitate custom workflows</description><pubDate>Fri, 18 Mar 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Interoperable Personal Libraries and Ad Hoc Reading Groups</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/interoperable-libraries/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/interoperable-libraries/</guid><description>Exploring ways to build social infrastructure around books and reading on the open web</description><pubDate>Sun, 20 Feb 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Spatial Web Browsing</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/spatial-web/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/spatial-web/</guid><description>Adding spatial affordances to the experience of browsing the web</description><pubDate>Fri, 14 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Assumed Audiences</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/assumed-audience/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/assumed-audience/</guid><description>Naming your invisible audiences to free yourself from unspoken obligations</description><pubDate>Sat, 08 Jan 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Finest Narrative Non-Fiction Essays</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/narrative-essays/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/narrative-essays/</guid><description>Narrative essays that I consider ideal models of the medium</description><pubDate>Wed, 22 Dec 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Epistemic Disclosure</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/epistemic-disclosure/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/epistemic-disclosure/</guid><description>Providing clear metadata on the epistemic validity of content</description><pubDate>Wed, 10 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Metaphors We Web By</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/metaphors-web/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/metaphors-web/</guid><description>A history of our metaphorical understanding of the web</description><pubDate>Sun, 24 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Algorithmic Transparency</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/algorithmic-transparency/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/algorithmic-transparency/</guid><description>Algorithms that make their reasoning visible</description><pubDate>Sat, 02 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>October 2021</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/now-2021-10/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/now-2021-10/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;After five years of working with &lt;a href=&quot;https://egghead.io&quot;&gt;egghead&lt;/a&gt;, I decided it was time to move on. I started as an illustrator in early 2016. By 2018 I had moved into an art director and leadership role. By 2020 I&apos;d shifted to focusing on UX and product design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I grew up in this company, but over the last year it&apos;s become clear I need/want to engage more in the rising &quot;tools for thought&quot; ecosystem. I&apos;ve now joined &lt;a href=&quot;https://hash.ai&quot;&gt;HASH&lt;/a&gt; as the design lead. We&apos;re working on building a knowledge management platform (aka. &quot;note-taking app&quot;) backed by schemas and structured data.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded></item><item><title>Plebeian Programming with Keyboard Maestro</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/keyboard-maestro/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/keyboard-maestro/</guid><description>How to write macros without touching the terminal</description><pubDate>Thu, 19 Aug 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Cultural Anthropology of React</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/anthropology-react/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/anthropology-react/</guid><description>An anthropological look at the cultural norms of the React community</description><pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>August 2021</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/now-2021-08/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/now-2021-08/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;With lockdown easing in London I&apos;ve spent most of summer outside throwing tennis balls around in the park, rather than sitting in front of screens writing words. It&apos;s been a good break, but I&apos;ve missed researching. The British winter will descend again soon and I&apos;ll be back inside tending to the digital garden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://overreacted.io/&quot;&gt;Dan Abramov&lt;/a&gt; and I finally launched &lt;a href=&quot;https://justjavascript.com/&quot;&gt;Just JavaScript&lt;/a&gt; after 2 years of work. It&apos;s an interactive book that teaches JavaScript with a specific focus on mental models. I created the diagrams and animations that help communicate the core concepts. We created it with the support of the egghead team who took care of logistics like email promotion, web infrastructure, and customer support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve become enamoured with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Visual_programming_language&quot;&gt;Visual Programming&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/End-user_development&quot;&gt;End-user Programming&lt;/a&gt; over the last 6 months. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://futureofcoding.org/&quot;&gt;Future of Coding&lt;/a&gt; community and &lt;a href=&quot;https://subconscious.substack.com/&quot;&gt;Gordon Brandon&lt;/a&gt;&apos;s newsletter have been particularly valuable hubs of insight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chatted with a few podcast folks;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adam Wiggins and Mark McGranaghan on &lt;a href=&quot;https://museapp.com/podcast/&quot;&gt;Metamuse&lt;/a&gt; about visual programming.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scott Francis and Evan Payne on &lt;a href=&quot;https://frontendheroes.transistor.fm/&quot;&gt;Frontend Heroes&lt;/a&gt; about a little bit of everything&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently preparing a talk for two conferences in October; &lt;a href=&quot;https://reactlive.nl/&quot;&gt;React Live Conference&lt;/a&gt; in Amsterdam and &lt;a href=&quot;https://reactadvanced.com/&quot;&gt;React Advanced&lt;/a&gt; here in London. On various ways to visualise React, why visual representations work so well, the pros / cons / wicked historical problems of adding graphical and spatial affordances to programming interfaces, and why we should keep trying despite the challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded></item><item><title>Tools for Thought as Cultural Practices, not Computational Objects</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/tools-for-thought/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/tools-for-thought/</guid><description>On seeing tools for thought through a historical and anthropological lens</description><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jul 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Paleolithic Nostalgia</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/paleolithic-nostalgia/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/paleolithic-nostalgia/</guid><description>Longing for the paleolithic past in the Anthropocene</description><pubDate>Sun, 20 Jun 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Natureculture, Moral Purity, and Cultural Boundaries</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/natureculture/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/natureculture/</guid><description>Why there is nothing natural about the idea of &apos;nature&apos;</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 May 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Linear Oppression of Note-taking Apps</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/note-oppression/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/note-oppression/</guid><description>What we lose when our digital notes remove the freedom to move</description><pubDate>Fri, 07 May 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Digital Gardening for Non-Technical Folks</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/nontechnical-gardening/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/nontechnical-gardening/</guid><description>How to build a digital garden without touching code</description><pubDate>Mon, 26 Apr 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Echo &amp; Narcissus Writing Club</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/echo-narcissus/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/echo-narcissus/</guid><description>A Hyperlink Academy writing club where we mimic the work of others</description><pubDate>Fri, 09 Apr 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Pink, Soft, Glittering Developers</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/glitter-devs/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/glitter-devs/</guid><description>A collection of observations on the rise of soft, sparkly, baby pink aesthetics among developers</description><pubDate>Sat, 13 Mar 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Fetishism &amp; Mechanical Keyboards</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/keyboard-fetishism/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/keyboard-fetishism/</guid><description>Developer self-expression through coloured switches, keystroke actuation, and LED light displays</description><pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Making Programming Visual, Spatial, and Learnable</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/learnable-programming/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/learnable-programming/</guid><description>What&apos;s wrong with linear, static programming mediums and how might we improve them?</description><pubDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Transclusion and Transcopyright Dreams</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/transcopyright-dreams/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/transcopyright-dreams/</guid><description>The lost permissioning and copyright system of the Web</description><pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Organic, Local, Artisan Data Storage</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/artisan-data/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/artisan-data/</guid><description>Data is currently dislocated – our narratives and metaphors around it try to convince us it is immaterial</description><pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Positioning Elements &amp; Scrollytelling in CSS</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/css-position/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/css-position/</guid><description>Notes on how to use the position property in CSS to make scrollytelling stories</description><pubDate>Sat, 26 Dec 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Painting Roam Research with Custom CSS</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/paintingroam/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/paintingroam/</guid><description>How to customise Roam Research with your own CSS themes</description><pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Digital Anthropology Reading List</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/digital-anth-books/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/digital-anth-books/</guid><description>A few favourite books from the field of digital anthropology</description><pubDate>Wed, 18 Nov 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Eponymous Laws of Programming</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/eponymous-laws/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/eponymous-laws/</guid><description>A collection of laws named for specific people in the field of programming</description><pubDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A History of Cyborgs</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/cyborg-history/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/cyborg-history/</guid><description>Notes on the history of cyborgs and why the idea still holds historical weight in Western narratives</description><pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Neologisms</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/neologisms/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/neologisms/</guid><description>A collection of interesting words that have recently been coined</description><pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Brief Introduction to Digital Anthropology</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/digital-anthropology/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/digital-anthropology/</guid><description>A discipline at the intersection of cultural anthropology and binary logic</description><pubDate>Sat, 03 Oct 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>GreenSock Animations with React Hooks</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/greensock-react/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/greensock-react/</guid><description>How to use the Greensock animation library inside React using React hooks</description><pubDate>Sun, 27 Sep 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Tools for Thought as Cultural Practices, not Computational Objects</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/tools-thought-talk/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/tools-thought-talk/</guid><description>On seeing tools for thought through a historical and anthropological lens</description><pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Bare Essentials of Greensock</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/greensock-essentials/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/greensock-essentials/</guid><description>Notes on the basics of the Greensock animation llibrary</description><pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>September 2020</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/now-2020-09/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/now-2020-09/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Digging into the work of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barbara_Tversky&quot;&gt;Barbara Tversky&lt;/a&gt; and reading the literature around &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Embodied_cognition&quot;&gt;embodied cognition&lt;/a&gt;. I&apos;ve been a long time fan of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Lakoff&quot;&gt;George Lakoff&lt;/a&gt; so much of it us familiar. Tverksy&apos;s new book &lt;a href=&quot;/mind-in-motion&quot;&gt;Mind in Motion&lt;/a&gt; builds off many of the same themes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delaying a part-time Masters degree in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/anthropology/study/graduate-taught/digital-anthropology-msc&quot;&gt;Digital Anthropology&lt;/a&gt; at UCL until next year when we&apos;ll hopefully be less Covid-y&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading &lt;a href=&quot;/working-in-public&quot;&gt;Working in Public&lt;/a&gt; by Nadia Eghbal&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exploring the connections between technology and magic through the writings of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alfred_Gell&quot;&gt;Alfred Gell&lt;/a&gt;. Specifically enjoyed the paper &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.xenopraxis.net/readings/gell_technologyenchantment.pdf&quot;&gt;The Technology of Enchantment and the Enchantment of Technology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Playing &lt;a href=&quot;http://situationlab.org/project/the-thing-from-the-future/&quot;&gt;Thing From the Future&lt;/a&gt; – A game that challenges players to collaboratively and competitively describe objects from a range of alternative futures.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded></item><item><title>Illustrating Gatsby&apos;s Key Concepts</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/illustrated-gatsby/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/illustrated-gatsby/</guid><description>Illustrated notes on the key concepts of how Gatsby.js works</description><pubDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Why You Own an iPad and Still Can&apos;t Draw</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/still-cant-draw/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/still-cant-draw/</guid><description>The failure of drawing materials without mediums and meat</description><pubDate>Tue, 18 Aug 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Problematic Proteins</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/problematic-proteins/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/problematic-proteins/</guid><description>How to offend everyone with boundary-crossing steak and nuggets</description><pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>New Harvest &amp; Illustrating the Cultivated Meat Podcast</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/newharvest-podcast/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/newharvest-podcast/</guid><description>Illustrations made for a set of episodes of the Cultivated Meat podcast</description><pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Gift Economy</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/gift-economy/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/gift-economy/</guid><description>Illustrated notes on the idea of Gift Economies and cultural historys of economic exchange</description><pubDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Synecdoche: Drawing the Part for the Whole</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/synecdoche/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/synecdoche/</guid><description>Notes on the metaphorical varieties of synecdoche and metonymy</description><pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Meta-Tour of This Site</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/metatour/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/metatour/</guid><description>A video tour through how I build the old version of this site</description><pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Douglas, Dirt, and Matter Out of Place</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/dirt/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/dirt/</guid><description>Mary Douglas defined dirt as matter out of place – the crossing of boundaries</description><pubDate>Tue, 21 Jul 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Pattern Language of Project Xanadu</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/xanadu-patterns/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/xanadu-patterns/</guid><description>Project Xanadu as a pattern language, rather than a failed software project</description><pubDate>Fri, 10 Jul 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Growing the Evergreens</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/evergreens/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/evergreens/</guid><description>Illustrated notes on the concept of &apos;Evergreen notes&apos; and how to write them</description><pubDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Knowledge Hydrant</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/knowledge-hydrant/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/knowledge-hydrant/</guid><description>Illustrated notes on the Knowledge Hydrant guide to collaborative learning</description><pubDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Frequently Asked Questions</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/faq/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/faq/</guid><description>Questions I am often asked to answer</description><pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Naïve Exploration of Computer-Supported Collaborative Learning</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/cscl/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/cscl/</guid><description>Notes on the academic field of CSCL and major papers in the discipline</description><pubDate>Fri, 26 Jun 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Silent Synchronous Reading Sessions</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/silentsessions/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/silentsessions/</guid><description>Notes on how to run silent meetings and reading sessions</description><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>What the Fork is React Suspense?</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/reactsuspense/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/reactsuspense/</guid><description>Illustrated notes on how React suspense works</description><pubDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Visually Workshopping the AWS Cloud</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/visual-aws/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/visual-aws/</guid><description>Some insights into how I collaborative with experts to create illustrated notes on technical topics</description><pubDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Are Data Unions the Future of Data?</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/data-unions/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/data-unions/</guid><description>Illustrated notes on how data unions work and what problems they might solve</description><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Brief History &amp; Ethos of the Digital Garden</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/garden-history/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/garden-history/</guid><description>A newly revived philosophy for publishing personal knowledge on the web</description><pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Pattern Languages in Programming and Interface Design</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/pattern-languages/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/pattern-languages/</guid><description>Notes on pattern languages and Christopher Alexander&apos;s legacy on software programming</description><pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Metaphorical Reading Collection</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/metaphor-books/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/metaphor-books/</guid><description>A collection of my favourite books on conceptual metaphor theory</description><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Tending Evergreen Notes in Roam Research</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/roam-garden/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/roam-garden/</guid><description>A walkthrough of how I manage and tend Evergreen notes in Roam</description><pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Fixing Common Git Mistakes</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/git-mistakes/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/git-mistakes/</guid><description>Illustrated notes on common mistakes people make in Git, and how to fix them</description><pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>What App is That?</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/apps/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/apps/</guid><description>A guide to the apps and tools I use to create illustrations</description><pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Tracking Humanity</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/tracking-humanity/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/tracking-humanity/</guid><description>The introduction to my thesis on the Quantified Self movement and the culture of self-tracking</description><pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Short History of Bi-Directional Links</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/bidirectionals/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/bidirectionals/</guid><description>Seventy years ago we dreamed up links that would allow us to create two-way, contextual conversations. Why don&apos;t we use them on the web?</description><pubDate>Mon, 04 May 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Dark Forest and the Cozy Web</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/cozy-web/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/cozy-web/</guid><description>An illustrated diagram exposing the inner layers of the dark and cozy web</description><pubDate>Sat, 02 May 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Drawing the Invisible: React Explained in Five Visual Metaphors</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/reactpotato/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/reactpotato/</guid><description>Explaining React through visual metaphors</description><pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Chat with Henry Zhu on OSS &amp; Gift Economies</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/maintainers/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/maintainers/</guid><description>Notes from my podcast episode Open Source and Gift Economies on Maintainers Anonymous</description><pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Building a Second Brain: The Illustrated Notes</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/basb/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/basb/</guid><description>Illustrated notes on the Building A Second Brain course</description><pubDate>Thu, 16 Apr 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>How to Become a Neo-Cartesian Cyborg</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/neocyborgs/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/neocyborgs/</guid><description>A lightening talk on second brains and cyborg embodiment</description><pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Defend Your Cookies with Essential Web Security Tactics</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/websecurity/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/websecurity/</guid><description>Illustrated notes on the essentials of web security</description><pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>How to Draw Invisible Programming Concepts: Part I</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/drawinginvisibles1/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/drawinginvisibles1/</guid><description>A case study showing how I make illustrations for abstract programming concepts</description><pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>What the Fork is xState?</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/xstate/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/xstate/</guid><description>Illustrated notes on how to build state machines with the xState library</description><pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Journey into Vue-Router</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/vuerouter/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/vuerouter/</guid><description>Illustrated notes on how routing works in Vue.js</description><pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>What the Fork is Rust?</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/wtf-rust/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/wtf-rust/</guid><description>Illustrated notes on the core concepts in Rust</description><pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Art and Craft of Gatsby Themes</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/building-gatsby-themes/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/building-gatsby-themes/</guid><description>Illustrated notes on building Gatsby themes</description><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>JavaScript Bits You Skipped the First Time Around</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/advancedjs/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/advancedjs/</guid><description>Illustrated notes on advanced but fundamental topics in JavaScript</description><pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Meat Planet: The Illustrated Notes</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/meat-planet/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/meat-planet/</guid><description>Visualising the cultural narratives around cultured meat</description><pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Building Custom React Hooks</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/customhooks/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/customhooks/</guid><description>Illustrated notes on building custom React hooks</description><pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Immutable Data with Immer and Personal Assistant Bots</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/immer/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/immer/</guid><description>Illustrated notes on how work with immutable data in the Immer state library</description><pubDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Speaking the GraphQL Query Language</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/graphql/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/graphql/</guid><description>Illustrated notes on the basics of the GraphQL query language</description><pubDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Best Illustration Books and Courses</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/illustration-resources/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/illustration-resources/</guid><description>My favourite resources for learning to draw and developing your visual thinking skills</description><pubDate>Sat, 06 Jul 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Fresh Serving of JavaScript ES2019</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/es2019/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/es2019/</guid><description>Illustrated notes on the new language changes in JavaScript ES2019</description><pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The JAMStack, Gatsby &amp; Contentful</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/contentful-gatsby/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/contentful-gatsby/</guid><description>Illustrated notes on the JAMstack, Gatsby &amp; Contentful</description><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Instachatting with Vue &amp; Socket.io</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/vuesocket/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/vuesocket/</guid><description>Illustrated notes on how to implement web sockets with Vue.js and Socket.io</description><pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Building VR Apps with React360</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/react360/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/react360/</guid><description>Illustrated notes on building VR web apps with React360</description><pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Testing Apps with Cypress</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/cypress/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/cypress/</guid><description>Illustrated notes on how to test web apps with Cypress</description><pubDate>Fri, 10 May 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>How Are Compilers &amp; Transpilers Different?</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/compilers/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/compilers/</guid><description>Illustrated notes on how compilers and transpilers are different</description><pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Meet the Robowaiter APIs Serving Us Data</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/api/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/api/</guid><description>Everything you need to know about what API&apos;s are and how they work</description><pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Shelfish Starter Guide to Databases</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/databases/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/databases/</guid><description>The absolute minimum you need to know about data storage</description><pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Fruitful Guide to JavaScript&apos;s Comparison Operators</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/fruit-comparison/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/fruit-comparison/</guid><description>Illustrated notes on how JavaScript&apos;s comparison operators work</description><pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>What the Fork is Babel?</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/babel/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/babel/</guid><description>Illustrated notes on how Babel works</description><pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>JSX is a Lovechild</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/jsx/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/jsx/</guid><description>Illustrated notes on how JSX in React works</description><pubDate>Sun, 20 Jan 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>What the Fork is the React Virtual DOM</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/react-vdom/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/react-vdom/</guid><description>Illustrated notes on how the React virtual DOM works</description><pubDate>Sun, 20 Jan 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>JavaScript&apos;s ...spread Operator</title><link>https://maggieappleton.com/spread/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://maggieappleton.com/spread/</guid><description>Illustrated notes on how JavaScript&apos;s spread operator works</description><pubDate>Sun, 20 Jan 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>